<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-05-27T16:56:23-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Podabrus sp.</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/Podabrus-sp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Podabrus sp." /><published>2021-05-24T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-24T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/Podabrus-sp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/Podabrus-sp.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Kurt Andreas&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Andreas.Podabrus_sp.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Soldier beetle&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Podabrus&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Podabrus&lt;/i&gt; sp.&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; soldier beetle.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Kurt Andreas. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Podabrus sp. &amp;ndash; soldier beetle.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Biologic Institute Closes</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/biologic-institute-closes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Biologic Institute Closes" /><published>2021-05-23T11:25:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-23T11:25:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/biologic-institute-closes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/biologic-institute-closes.html">&lt;p&gt;The blogger known as the Sensuous Curmudgeon &lt;a href=&quot;https://sensuouscurmudgeon.wordpress.com/2021/05/22/the-cosmic-aardvark-is-smiling/&quot;&gt;reported yesterday&lt;/a&gt; that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biologicinstitute.org/&quot;&gt; Biologic Institute&lt;/a&gt;, supposedly the research arm of the Discovery Institute, is closing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Appears the Biologic Institute [An enterprise of the Discovery Institute] is history, green screen and all. On their 2019 990, Director Axe will no longer draw a salary, but will be a prof at Biola “Univ.” Office space is for rent. Location is listed as “permanently closed.” Their final 990 showed a loss of $133,000. [Emendation in original.] &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I checked Guidestar for their latest IRS Form 990-EZ, which is dated 2019 and covers the fiscal year 2018 (Charity Navigator is a year behind). Sure enough, it contains the following statement on line 28:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;DR. AXE ENTERED INTO AN AGREEMENT WITH BIOLA UNIVERSITY TO SERVE AS THE MAXWELL VISITING PROFESSOR OF MOLECULAR BIOLOGY DURING THE 2018/2019 ACADEMIC YEAR, WITH REGULAR VISITS TO CAMPUS. IN AUGUST 2019, DR. AXE BECAME THE MAXWELL PROFESSOR OF MOLECULAR BIOLOGY AT BIOLA, WORKING FULL TIME ON TEACHING AND WORKING TO HELP BUILD A COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH ENVIRONMENT AT BIOLA THAT INCLUDES ADVANCED UNDERGRADUATE STUDENTS. ALTHOUGH HE NO LONGER DRAWS A SALARY FROM BIOLOGIC INSTITUTE, DR. AXE CONTINUES TO SERVE AS THE DIRECTOR AND IS EXPLORING WAYS IN WHICH BIOLOGIC CAN PARTNER WITH BIOLA. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “Dr. Axe” in question is Douglas Axe, the president of the Biologic Institute. His salary of $133,333 in 2018 was the bulk of the total expenses of $201,873. Revenue was $68,600, leaving a deficit almost exactly equal to Dr. Axe’s salary. Inasmuch as Dr. Axe “no longer draws a salary from Biologic Institute,” it seems safe to say that they are effectively out of business, even though he “is exploring ways in which Biologic can partner with Biola.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not very familiar with Biologic Institute, and reading a 2019 Form 990-EZ seems almost like reading ancient history, or at least medieval history, so I took a look at their website. The home page displays an undated article that was reposted from a 2017 article, followed by another article dated 2018. Medieval history indeed! Undiscouraged, I checked a tab labeled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biologicinstitute.org/research&quot;&gt;Research&lt;/a&gt;. After a long discussion of motivation, “core ideas,” and research areas, they list their publications. I will let other people discuss the content of the publications and will note only that the most recent is from 2014. Thus, unless the web page has simply been ignored, there has been little or no activity at the Biologic Institute since 2013 or 2014 at the latest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the Biologic Institute is not dead, it has surely been moribund for the better part of the last decade. Where, I wonder, is their vaunted research program now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ADDED 6:30 p.m., 05/23/2021:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A colleague sent me &lt;a href=&quot;https://ccfs.sos.wa.gov/#/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, whence I scrolled down to “Charity … Search” and entered “Biologic Institute.” I quickly found the following, which suggests that they ceased operations on 09/30/2019 with a balance of $9285, which precisely matches the amount on the last Form 990_EZ that I could find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Biologic_Institute_Data.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Data Sheet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to “Business Search,” the corporation is “Active” through 10/31/2021, but with Dr. Axe gone, we may assume that they will be about as productive as in the past.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">The blogger known as the Sensuous Curmudgeon reported yesterday that the Biologic Institute, supposedly the research arm of the Discovery Institute, is closing: Appears the Biologic Institute [An enterprise of the Discovery Institute] is history, green screen and all. On their 2019 990, Director Axe will no longer draw a salary, but will be a prof at Biola “Univ.” Office space is for rent. Location is listed as “permanently closed.” Their final 990 showed a loss of $133,000. [Emendation in original.] I checked Guidestar for their latest IRS Form 990-EZ, which is dated 2019 and covers the fiscal year 2018 (Charity Navigator is a year behind). Sure enough, it contains the following statement on line 28:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Canceling Huxley; is Darwin next?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/canceling-huxley.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Canceling Huxley; is Darwin next?" /><published>2021-05-21T12:55:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-21T12:55:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/canceling-huxley</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/canceling-huxley.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Huxley.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Huxley&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Thomas_Henry_Huxley_self_portrait,_ca._1857.jpg &quot;&gt;Autograph portrait of Professor Huxley&lt;/a&gt; before he &quot;returned to the use of his razor.&quot; From a notebook used by him about 1857 and evidently made to amuse his baby. &lt;small&gt;John M. Clarke, &lt;i&gt;James Hall of Albany, Geologist and Palaeontologist&lt;/i&gt; (1921). Public domain.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The evil that men do lives after them;&lt;br /&gt;
  
The good is oft interred with their bones.&lt;br /&gt;

&amp;mdash;Shakespeare, &lt;i&gt;Julius Caesar&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask Thomas Henry Huxley if you do not believe Marc Antony. According to an article in AS Review, &lt;a href=&quot;https://asreview.org/2021/01/22/thomas-huxley-once-respected-now-rejected/&quot;&gt;Thomas Huxley: Once Respected, Now Rejected&lt;/a&gt;, a big brouhaha has erupted over the name of the Huxley College of the Environment at Western Washington University. The issue is important, because if people succeed in “canceling” Huxley, possibly Darwin will be next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huxley’s “sin” is to have held many of the same views regarding race as most of his contemporaries. More specifically, &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/files/2021-04/Rupke%20Huxley%20Legacy.pdf&quot;&gt;according to the historian Nicolaas Rupke&lt;/a&gt;, Huxley&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;formulated what became known as ‘Huxley’s Law’ or ‘Huxley’s Rule,’ which stated that the distance in biological, evolutionary development between the highest and lowest humans is greater than the distance between the lowest humans and the highest apes (chimpanzee, gorilla), thus degrading native peoples across the British Empire.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True, as nearly as I can determine, but the term Huxley’s Law is not in common use and appears to have been coined by Prof. Rupke himself, &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/files/2021-04/Rupke%20-%20Huxley%27s%20Rule.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Indeed, the distinguished philosopher of biology, David Hull, has noted in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/3827456&quot;&gt;book review&lt;/a&gt; that “nothing today goes by the name of Huxley’s Law.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The president’s office at Western Washington University has &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/research-and-resources&quot;&gt;appointed a task force and solicited comments&lt;/a&gt; regarding renaming the College. They asked three questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; What role did Huxley’s beliefs on race occupy in his intellectual works, his public statements, and his life as a whole? Were they remarkable in the context of the time and place in which he lived? 

&lt;br /&gt;Did Huxley’s scientific work contribute, either in support or opposition, to the development of scientific racism and Social Darwinism, both during his lifetime and after? What portion of his total work did these contributions occupy, and how significant are those contributions in supporting or refuting the ideology of scientific racism?

&lt;br /&gt;What harmful institutional practices, policies, or general practical consequences, if any, can be specifically traced to Huxley’s views? &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consistently with the quotation from Shakespeare, above, they did not ask a single question about Huxley’s many accomplishments, which, I take it, are to be interred with his bones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read the submissions by Prof. Rupke, who is a professor of history at Washington and Lee University; &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/files/2021-04/PS%20White%20Huxley%20Legacy.pdf&quot;&gt;Paul White&lt;/a&gt; of the Darwin Correspondence Project of the University of Cambridge; &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/files/2021-04/Lyons%20Huxley%20Legacy.pdf&quot;&gt;Sherrie Lyons&lt;/a&gt; of Empire State College; &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/files/2021-04/Reidy%20Huxley%20Legacy.pdf&quot;&gt;Michael Reidy&lt;/a&gt;, Professor of History, Montana State University; and an article in the Seattle Times, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seattletimes.com/opinion/reconsider-cancel-culture-target-at-wwu/&quot;&gt;Reconsider cancel-culture target at WWU&lt;/a&gt;, by Steve Hollenhorst and Wayne Landis, both professors and administrators at Huxley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The submissions that I read, save that of Prof. Rupke and the AS Review article, seem to me to be generally favorable toward Huxley. If you want to read one piece, read the article by Hollenhorst and Landis. I think they get it about right: Huxley’s main crime was living in the 1800’s and sharing many of the attitudes of his contemporaries. But in fact he was well ahead of his contemporaries in being an abolitionist in a country that largely supported the Confederacy during the American Civil War. Sure, he thought that the British aristocracy was in some way superior to the “primitive” peoples in Africa or Australia; who in 1880 did not? Let us be careful to avoid the fallacy of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Presentism_(literary_and_historical_analysis)&quot;&gt;presentism&lt;/a&gt;. Despite his bias, Huxley opposed slavery and fought against social Darwinism on moral grounds. Even Lincoln, I should add parenthetically, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/1862/08/24/archives/a-letter-from-president-lincoln-reply-to-horace-greeley-slavery-and.html&quot;&gt;wrote in the New York Times&lt;/a&gt;, “If I could save the Union without freeing any slave, I would do it….”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might have been catty of them, but Profs. Hollenhorst and Landis opened their article with the observation that their university, Western Washington University, is named indirectly after a slave owner: George Washington. If I wanted to be catty myself, I would add that Prof. Rupke’s university, Washington and Lee University, is named after both Washington and the famous defender of slavery, Robert E. Lee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cattiness aside, I would like to let Profs. Hollenhorst and Landis get the last word:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The distinguished historians WWU asked to look at the issue overwhelmingly concluded the claims just don’t hold up. Huxley’s early writings did reflect the prevailing bigotry and prejudice of Victorian society, although even then to a lesser degree than his scientific peers. By the 1860s, he became a vocal abolitionist and by the end of his life called for universal equal rights regardless of race or gender. The beautiful irony of his scientific work on human diversity is [that] it ultimately leads him to see the oneness, and equality, of all humanity. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, further,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Huxley later expanded these ideas in his great battles against social Darwinism and religion, which he saw as grounded in the dark forces of authority, bigotry and superstition. He feared they led to social order based on competition, subjugation and inequality. In this he was prescient, for indeed both have been used to justify not only laissez-faire capitalism and political conservatism, but also colonialism, eugenics, racism and eventually fascism. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;It’s telling he didn’t teach at Cambridge or Oxford, but rather working-class institutions, the Royal School of Mines and later Imperial College, where he brought science and industry together to solve societal problems. He gave hundreds of free public lectures to common folk. As an early advocate for public education, he was elected to the London School Board, where he worked to bring a decent education to ordinary people and implemented the first training for science teachers. In other words, he’d make an exemplary WWU faculty member today.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

What would Huxley say about his legacy? First, he’d commend us for interrogating it, especially the brave students, who without power and risking reproach, stood up to raise the issue. But he’d then remind them that “it is not what we believe, but why we believe it. Moral responsibility lies in diligently weighing the evidence.” And to all of us he’d likely say, “learn what is true in order to do what is right.” Now that the question is before us, address it with honesty and integrity. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, finally,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Don’t be fooled. Huxley’s message isn’t privileged. It isn’t elitist. It isn’t racist. It’s timeless. The values he fought for are at the core of public higher education to this day. Far from causing harm, we are in a better place because of Thomas H. Huxley. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shall add, finally, and not entirely parenthetically, that Profs. Hollenhorst and Landis trace the association between Huxley and social Darwinism to a notorious fabricator, Henry Morris, the founder of “scientific” creationism and himself something of a racist. It is partly because of this background that I fear that if Huxley is “cancelled,” then Darwin is next.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Autograph portrait of Professor Huxley before he &quot;returned to the use of his razor.&quot; From a notebook used by him about 1857 and evidently made to amuse his baby. John M. Clarke, James Hall of Albany, Geologist and Palaeontologist (1921). Public domain. The evil that men do lives after them; The good is oft interred with their bones. &amp;mdash;Shakespeare, Julius Caesar Ask Thomas Henry Huxley if you do not believe Marc Antony. According to an article in AS Review, Thomas Huxley: Once Respected, Now Rejected, a big brouhaha has erupted over the name of the Huxley College of the Environment at Western Washington University. The issue is important, because if people succeed in “canceling” Huxley, possibly Darwin will be next. Huxley’s “sin” is to have held many of the same views regarding race as most of his contemporaries. More specifically, according to the historian Nicolaas Rupke, Huxley formulated what became known as ‘Huxley’s Law’ or ‘Huxley’s Rule,’ which stated that the distance in biological, evolutionary development between the highest and lowest humans is greater than the distance between the lowest humans and the highest apes (chimpanzee, gorilla), thus degrading native peoples across the British Empire. True, as nearly as I can determine, but the term Huxley’s Law is not in common use and appears to have been coined by Prof. Rupke himself, here. Indeed, the distinguished philosopher of biology, David Hull, has noted in a book review that “nothing today goes by the name of Huxley’s Law.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">We are the knights who say … evolution</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/We-are-the-knights-who-say-evolution.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We are the knights who say … evolution" /><published>2021-05-15T06:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-15T06:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/We-are-the-knights-who-say-evolution</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/We-are-the-knights-who-say-evolution.html">&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Knightni.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;small&gt;Michael Palin, as the chief of the Knights Who Say &quot;Ni&quot;, from &lt;em&gt;Monty Python and the Holy Grail&lt;/em&gt;. From Wikipedia.&lt;/small&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
 In a famous scene in &lt;em&gt;Monty Python and the Holy Grail&lt;/em&gt;, King Arthur and his knights encounter the menacing figures of The Knights Who Say &quot;Ni&quot; (pronounced &quot;nee&quot;).  The word
 is so unhearable that Arthur and his men fall back in anguish, covering their ears.  Ultimately, they are allowed to pass, but only after providing those Knights with what they want, &quot;a shrubbery&quot;.
  &lt;p&gt;
    If you thought that the scene was farfetched, think again.  At &lt;em&gt;Evolution News and and Science Today&lt;/em&gt; their anonymous commentator (Casey Luskin? David Klinghoffer?), in an article about the giraffe genome, &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2021/05/giraffe-genome-is-not-evolutionary/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;complains about an equally unhearable word&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  After interpreting the evolution of the giraffe as brought about by Design rather than by evolutionary processes, the real complaint comes out:
    &lt;p&gt;
    &lt;!--more--&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
&lt;div bgcolor=&quot;lightblue&quot;&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;[quote from EN&amp;amp;ST]&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Bad “Evolutionary” Habit&lt;/h3&gt;

Throughout these articles, one can see the writers inserting the adjective “evolutionary” in front of everything. 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; “an evolutionary geneticist at the University of Copenhagen” — why not just a geneticist?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; “giraffes are a poster child for evolutionary oddities” — why not just oddities?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; “several phenotypic traits that share evolutionary constraints” — why not just constraints, as in engineering specifications?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; “This [reduction in olfactory sensitivity] may be an evolutionary consequence of enhanced vision” — why not just a consequence, as in a designed trade-off for multiple competing specifications?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; “evolutionary adaptations” — why not just adaptations, or unique traits fit for the giraffe’s ecological niche?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; “evolutionary pleiotropy” — why not just pleiotropy?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; “a suite of traits are changed within a short evolutionary time” — why not a suite of traits that work together?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

Typists could avoid carpal tunnel syndrome by eliminating this unnecessary word in science papers and news stories. 
It seems that the “evolutionary” biologists, who should just call themselves biologists, want to push a narrative
that everything in the living world must pay tribute to Darwin. The repetition of the word hammers it into people’s
heads. Everything in nature, they are taught with this propaganda tactic, is part of a fluid phantasmagoric 
tableau where every creature came from some other creature and is becoming something else. 
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;p&gt;  
&lt;em&gt;[end of quote from EN&amp;amp;ST]&lt;/em&gt;
&amp;lt;/blockquote&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;

&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
And here I had thought that the Discovery Institute was now OK with using the word &quot;evolution&quot;.  After all, they
have often explained, everything changes, and that is all that &quot;evolution&quot; means.  It is only when natural selection is invoked that
they become unable to acknowledge those changes.  And, it turns out, when common descent is inferred.  Their love affair with &quot;change&quot;
seems to always end there.
&lt;p&gt;
So now we seem to be back to an earlier era, when species were assumed to be fixed.  Even Young Earth Creationists seemed lately 
to have invoked extremely rapid evolution so as to turn the limited number of &quot;kinds&quot; that would fit on the Ark into all present-day species in a few hundred years.
But now the Discovery Institute announces that, whatever the amount of change, the word &quot;evolution&quot; is unhearable.
&lt;p&gt;
Well, I am an evolutionary biologist, because that's what I work on -- the processes of evolution and the history of life that results. 
And I guarantee you that evolutionary geneticists, evolutionary genomicists, evolutionary anthropologists, evolutionary physiologists, evolutionary developmental biologists,
and evolutionary molecular biologists are going to keep using that word, no matter how unhearable it is to the Discovery Institute. We will investigate
evolutionary rates, evolutionary correlations, evolutionary tradeoffs, and much more.
And there is no &quot;shrubbery&quot; that will change that.
            
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Michael Palin, as the chief of the Knights Who Say &quot;Ni&quot;, from Monty Python and the Holy Grail. From Wikipedia. In a famous scene in Monty Python and the Holy Grail, King Arthur and his knights encounter the menacing figures of The Knights Who Say &quot;Ni&quot; (pronounced &quot;nee&quot;). The word is so unhearable that Arthur and his men fall back in anguish, covering their ears. Ultimately, they are allowed to pass, but only after providing those Knights with what they want, &quot;a shrubbery&quot;. If you thought that the scene was farfetched, think again. At Evolution News and and Science Today their anonymous commentator (Casey Luskin? David Klinghoffer?), in an article about the giraffe genome, complains about an equally unhearable word. After interpreting the evolution of the giraffe as brought about by Design rather than by evolutionary processes, the real complaint comes out:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Avoid Being Derailed on the Reading Railroad</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/how-to-avoid.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Avoid Being Derailed on the Reading Railroad" /><published>2021-05-14T13:10:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-14T13:10:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/how-to-avoid</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/how-to-avoid.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Cassatt_The_Reader_Crystal_Bridges_Museum_of_American_Art_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cassatt, The Reader&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Mary Cassatt, The Reader. &lt;small&gt;Credit: Crystal Bridges Museum of American Art, public domain.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A high-school English teacher once told our class that “higher education is a process of learning more and more about less and less.” Catchy and memorable, but only true to the extent that most of our careers—academic and otherwise—tend to make us “experts” on a limited number of topics. So it is inevitable that we will confront some information that is outside our expertise, and we will need to make judgments about arguments, actions, or policies based on this information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, journalist Nicholas Wade authored a &lt;a href=&quot;https://thebulletin.org/2021/05/the-origin-of-covid-did-people-or-nature-open-pandoras-box-at-wuhan/&quot;&gt; piece in the Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists&lt;/a&gt; about the origin of SARS-CoV-2—the coronavirus that is responsible for the COVID-19 pandemic—giving credence to the claim that the virus was leaked from a laboratory in Wuhan (China) instead of emerging from a natural reservoir such as local bat populations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who have expertise in the details of laboratory research with viruses can certainly evaluate and critique the claims that Wade presented in support of his argument. But what about the rest of us? How do we evaluate arguments with important consequences without resorting to “dueling experts” who claim equal authority and come down on opposite sides?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a challenge for all of us who deal with claims and evidence outside our own expertise and experience. Even if we don’t know an exon from Exxon, we need a way to evaluate how much credibility to give particular arguments, such as this piece from Nicholas Wade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we teach the basics of reading research literature to students, we expect that, at first, they lack the specific disciplinary expertise necessary to critique the content effectively. So we help them to develop an approach that looks for clues in the source, the format and presentation, the language and appeal, the purpose, and other characteristics of the argument that we can identify without having a deep grasp of the technical details of a specific field of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simplified &lt;a href=&quot;https://writingcenter.tamu.edu/Students/Writing-Speaking-Guides/Alphabetical-List-of-Guides/Citing-Documenting/Evaluating-Scholarly-Sources&quot;&gt;example&lt;/a&gt; provided by the Writing Center at Texas A&amp;amp;M University uses the C.R.A.P. acronym to help students focus on revealing indicators of credibility of persuasion pieces such as the one on the source of the COVID-19 pandemic. These are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
•	Currency: Is the information up to date; has it been supplanted or refuted by newer resources?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•	Reliability: Is the information reviewed or vetted by people with specific expertise in a relevant field? Does it represent the consensus of that field, a commonly acknowledged alternative to the consensus, or a position rarely accepted by those most knowledgeable?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 
•	Authority: Is there a specific author whose qualifications to identify and evaluate relevant evidence and to place it in context can be verified? &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
•	Purpose: Does the author or publication have a particular goal or mission to explore issues in a certain way or from a certain perspective, and is it intended more to persuade or to inform? Most of this information is readily available from the source, whether it is a periodical or a web site. We teach students that sources that do not provide this information are automatically suspect. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember: This is not an approach that attempts to evaluate the technical details of the argument, but one that looks at the context in which the argument is made and the way that it is presented and supported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currency: Wade’s article is recent, but the information used in it goes back up to a decade, and it is not clear whether issues raised and inferences and conclusions reached and reported early in the pandemic are still current. Have they been re-evaluated, modified, or even retracted in the light of newer information?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reliability: The publication’s policy for vetting or reviewing technical information is not clear. It does not classify this article as to content and intent. Is it news? Investigative reporting? Opinion? The article seems intent on persuading us of a position, rather than merely informing us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authority: The author, Nicholas Wade, has a good record as an “explainer” of things scientific. He worked for years at the &lt;i&gt;New York Times&lt;/i&gt; and has some good collections of articles that are useful for high-school and introductory-college level readers and that give a good overview of established science. His credentials as a science journalist are well established, but Wade is not a virologist or a microbiologist or an epidemiologist. He is a journalist, albeit one with a specialty in scientific—particularly biologic—topics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is that Wade has to rely on published reports and interviews of scientists in the relevant fields. This is not a bad thing—one should get one’s information from these sources—but it is difficult to evaluate Twitter feeds, interviews, and other media except via an appeal to the authority of those who are quoted in these sources (see reliability above).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purpose: In this case the mission statement of the &lt;i&gt;Bulletin of Atomic Scientists&lt;/i&gt; tells us that its focus is on threats to existence caused by humans. So its articles are going to emphasize things that humans do that threaten human life on Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thebulletin.org/about-us/&quot;&gt;Our Mission&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 
The Bulletin equips the public, policymakers, and scientists with the information needed to reduce man-made threats to our existence.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the themes of the publication is to highlight threats posed by technologies that we do not or cannot control properly; a major theme of this article is the potential for accidental release of laboratory-engineered viruses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;About Us&lt;br /&gt;
At our core, the Bulletin is a media organization, publishing a free-access website and a bimonthly magazine. But we are much more. The Bulletin’s website, iconic Doomsday Clock, and regular events help advance actionable ideas at a time when technology is outpacing our ability to control it. The Bulletin focuses on three main areas: nuclear risk, climate change, and disruptive technologies. What connects these topics is a driving belief that because humans created them, we can control them. &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the very least, this is a publication that is going to be more sympathetic to explanations about “threats” that are caused by humans (intentional or otherwise). In this case, part of the argument is that laboratory technologies used in the study of viruses are endangering humanity and the world, at least in part because of shortcuts taken by researchers, research laboratories, industry, and governments that increase the likelihood that a virus modified in a research project might accidentally be released. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These issues also form the basis of more detailed evaluations that fall under the rubric of “rhetorical analysis”—another approach that looks at the form and format of the argument, as well as its context and some aspects of the construction of the arguments (see one example &lt;a href=&quot;https://miamioh.edu/hcwe/handouts/rhetorical-analyses/index.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Again, the approach in this article is not to evaluate the specific examples and data, but to look at how those are used to construct the argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One part of this analysis is to examine what is called the “warrant” or the connection between the evidence presented and the conclusion. For example, in this article Wade argues that “CGG is coronavirus’s least popular codon for arginine.” There is, Wade continues, a CGG-CGG pair at a critical site that is essential for infecting human cells, even though this arrangement is unknown in related coronaviruses. The “warrant” in Wade’s argument is that rarity of the sequence in Nature implies that a purposeful insertion is a better explanation for this configuration than natural processes that produce changes in nucleotide sequences. (Readers will recognize that this sort of error—the unwarranted conclusion or inference—is the same one that we see in pseudoscientific explications of “evidences against” evolution.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcomes of the C.R.A.P. profile and the rhetorical analysis do not mean that source is necessarily unreliable, but it places the material in a context that allows readers to compare its features and characteristics directly with other material from other sources. In this case, it suggests that the source publication has a vested interest in a particular perspective on the issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the rhetorical analysis, when we come to this point, we advise students that it is time to look at appropriate disciplinary literature and to compare the data, methods, and conclusions that specialists in the field are applying to the problem, and then to record what questions those specialists are still asking after their own investigation. If there is significant disagreement in the field, it pops up in these comparisons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wade looks at the evidence he has compiled and concludes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Neither the natural emergence nor the lab escape hypothesis can yet be ruled out. There is still no direct evidence for either. So no definitive conclusion can be reached.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

That said, the available evidence leans more strongly in one direction than the other. Readers will form their own opinion. But it seems to me that proponents of lab escape can explain all the available facts about [SARS-Cov-2] considerably more easily than can those who favor natural emergence. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He seems to be hedging his bets here—or pulling his punches—at what seemed like an argument strongly committed to a laboratory origin of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By comparison, the joint investigative team of the World Health Organization came to a different conclusion in its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/docs/default-source/coronaviruse/final-joint-report_origins-studies-6-april-201.pdf?sfvrsn=4f5e5196_1&amp;amp;download=true&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; released just about a month earlier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;In summary, the joint team considered the following ranking of potential introduction pathways, from very likely to extremely unlikely: (1) through an intermediate host; (2) direct zoonotic introduction; (3) introduction through cold/ food chain; and (4) introduction resulting from a laboratory incident. Building from the evidence for the studies conducted so far, follow-up research studies were proposed for the first three options (p. 112)....&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, after a review of existing evidence, the WHO report concluded:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;In view of the above, a laboratory origin of the pandemic was considered to be extremely unlikely.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

What would be needed to increase knowledge?&lt;br /&gt;

Regular administrative and internal review of high-level biosafety laboratories worldwide. Follow-up of new evidence supplied around possible laboratory leaks (p. 120). &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, an account by a virologist specializing in coronaviruses would be the gold standard, if it were as accessible as this article written by a science journalist who knows how to communicate effectively with ordinary people. The main question that people ask is,”How can we tell if a virus has been modified in a lab versus a natural process in the wild, and what evidence do we still need to reach a conclusion?” And that is the crux of the argument. If we could make that clear to the average reader, one hopes it would replace big conspiracy theories with reasoned discussion that could resolve the question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BIO: Andrew Petto is Distinguished Lecturer Emeritus at the University of Wisconsin‒Milwaukee, where he taught anatomy in the Departments of Biological Sciences and Kinesiology. For 8 years he and his students initiated and studied mock epidemics in the summer Research Apprenticeship Program for high-school students at the University of Wisconsin School of Medicine and Public Health in Madison, Wisconsin. The culminating publication from this project was Communic-Able: Writing to learn about emerging infectious diseases. In: Yager R. E., ed. Exemplary Science for Solving Societal Problems. Reston, Virginia: National Science Teaching Association. 2010.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew Petto</name></author><summary type="html">Mary Cassatt, The Reader. Credit: Crystal Bridges Museum of American Art, public domain. A high-school English teacher once told our class that “higher education is a process of learning more and more about less and less.” Catchy and memorable, but only true to the extent that most of our careers—academic and otherwise—tend to make us “experts” on a limited number of topics. So it is inevitable that we will confront some information that is outside our expertise, and we will need to make judgments about arguments, actions, or policies based on this information. Recently, journalist Nicholas Wade authored a piece in the Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists about the origin of SARS-CoV-2—the coronavirus that is responsible for the COVID-19 pandemic—giving credence to the claim that the virus was leaked from a laboratory in Wuhan (China) instead of emerging from a natural reservoir such as local bat populations. Those who have expertise in the details of laboratory research with viruses can certainly evaluate and critique the claims that Wade presented in support of his argument. But what about the rest of us? How do we evaluate arguments with important consequences without resorting to “dueling experts” who claim equal authority and come down on opposite sides?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Daucus carota</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/daucus-carota.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Daucus carota" /><published>2021-05-10T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-10T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/daucus-carota</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/daucus-carota.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/DSC04058_Queen_Annes_Lace_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Queen Anne's Lace&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.americansouthwest.net/plants/wildflowers/daucus-carota.html&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Daucus carota&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Queen Anne's Lace seedling, showing the first true leaf.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Daucus carota &amp;ndash; Queen Anne's Lace seedling, showing the first true leaf.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AIG's Statement of Faith Outdoes Itself</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/aig-s-statement.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AIG's Statement of Faith Outdoes Itself" /><published>2021-05-08T13:45:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-08T13:45:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/aig-s-statement</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/aig-s-statement.html">&lt;p&gt;Dan Phelps, in a guest post on Pharyngula, observed the other day that &lt;a href=&quot;https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2021/05/08/answers-in-genesiss-statement-of-faith-becomes-more-strident/&quot;&gt;Answers in Genesis’s Statement of Faith Becomes More Strident&lt;/a&gt;, and indeed it has. Mr. Phelps has dredged up the old version of the statement of faith from the Wayback Machine and compared it with the new. You may read Mr. Phelps’s article for yourself, but in a nutshell, he notes that the new version argues that
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; No fact may be considered valid if it contradicts the &quot;scriptural record.&quot; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; The only valid marriage is that between a naturally born [sic] man and a naturally born woman.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Social justice, intersectionality, and critical race theory are anti-Biblical. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Gender and sex are the same thing, and attempts to change your &quot;sex (gender)&quot; are sinful. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Death, suffering, and &quot;natural evils&quot; such as hurricanes and earthquakes are a direct consequence of sin. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this matters, in part, because Answers in Genesis operates the Ark Park in Williamstown, Kentucky. As Mr. Phelps notes in his article and as we have reported in PT, the Ark Park on the one hand purports to be an Equal Opportunity Employer, and on the other hand requires prospective employees to sign its increasingly strident Statement of Faith. For more detail, see also &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2014/09/does-aig-lie-ab.html&quot;&gt;Does AIG lie about Affirmative Action?&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2014/09/aigs-ambivalent.html&quot;&gt;AIG’s ambivalent relation to the tax code&lt;/a&gt; (written primarily by Ed Hensley), and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2017/07/when-is-a-for-profit.html&quot;&gt;When is a for-profit corporation not for profit?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Dan Phelps, in a guest post on Pharyngula, observed the other day that Answers in Genesis’s Statement of Faith Becomes More Strident, and indeed it has. Mr. Phelps has dredged up the old version of the statement of faith from the Wayback Machine and compared it with the new. You may read Mr. Phelps’s article for yourself, but in a nutshell, he notes that the new version argues that</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Granville Sewell thinks it’s obvious</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/Granville-Sewell-thinks-its-obvious.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Granville Sewell thinks it’s obvious" /><published>2021-05-04T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-04T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/Granville-Sewell-thinks-its-obvious</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/Granville-Sewell-thinks-its-obvious.html">&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Pure_Quartz.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;By Eva K., from Wikimedia Commons.  Something Granville Sewell may not expect.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granville Sewell is at it again, and he never seems to learn.  In &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2021/04/some-problems-can-be-proved-unsolvable/&quot;&gt;a piece at the Discovery Institute’s site Evolution News &amp;amp; Science Today&lt;/a&gt; 
he argues that it is obvious that one can reject the ordinary processes of physics, chemistry, and evolution as having brought about living organisms. His piece is entitled “Some problems can be proved unsolvable”.
He mentions a mathematical theorem that was finally proven after hundreds of years (Fermat’s Last Theorem), and a task that can easily shown to be unsolvable
(covering with two-square-sized dominos a chessboard that has had two squares in opposite corners removed).  Then he argues that it is obvious that evolving present-day
life that ends up inventing iPhones can easily be seen to be impossible by natural processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
He summarizes his argument in a few sentences:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Well, I have a very simple proof that the biological problem #3 posed above is also impossible to solve, that does fit in the margin of this document. All one needs 
to do is realize that if a solution were found, we would have proved something obviously false, that a few (four, apparently) fundamental, unintelligent 
forces of physics alone could have rearranged the fundamental particles of physics into libraries full of science texts and encyclopedias, 
computers connected to monitors, keyboards, laser printers and the Internet, cars, trucks, airplanes, nuclear power plants and Apple iPhones. 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Is this really a valid proof? It seems perfectly valid to me, as I cannot think of anything in all of science that can be stated with more 
confidence than that a few unintelligent forces of physics alone could not have rearranged the basic particles of physics into Apple iPhones.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Now Sewell is a mathematician, author of a book on solving differential equations.  But he seems to accept proof-by-obviousness, a method most mathematicians
would not accept.  He should listen to them.  Instead he lays the obviousness on a bit too thick ...

&lt;!--more--&gt;

He asks whether elementary particles and the four fundamental forces of physics (there are now only two, actually) could end up with computers, iPhones, libraries,
and so on.  That sounds impossible.  But he's left out a few steps.  For example:
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Elementary particles aggregating to form larger particles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Those particles forming atoms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Atoms becoming connected by bonds to form chemicals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Chemicals interacting to form cosmic dust&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Cosmic dust forming clouds by the attraction of gravity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Gravity in dust clouds leading to clumps that become a solar system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; ... including the formation of a star and planets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Lots of geology (steps omitted)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; An early Earth with interesting organic chemicals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Origin of life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Evolution of protists and single-celled eukaryotes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Evolution of multicellular life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Evolution of people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; People producing tools&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; People producing agriculture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; and civilization,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; and technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
See, it isn't just a direct aggregation of particles.  If we don't know all the details of those steps, few seem to think that the processes of astronomy, 
chemistry, and geology can't explain our planet without the intervention of a cosmic Designer.  Intelligent Design arguments are not very visible in physics, in chemistry, in astronomy, 
and in geology.  Those very active sciences get along fine without ID.  Sewell's proof-by-obviousness needs somewhat more focus.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">By Eva K., from Wikimedia Commons. Something Granville Sewell may not expect. Granville Sewell is at it again, and he never seems to learn. In a piece at the Discovery Institute’s site Evolution News &amp;amp; Science Today he argues that it is obvious that one can reject the ordinary processes of physics, chemistry, and evolution as having brought about living organisms. His piece is entitled “Some problems can be proved unsolvable”. He mentions a mathematical theorem that was finally proven after hundreds of years (Fermat’s Last Theorem), and a task that can easily shown to be unsolvable (covering with two-square-sized dominos a chessboard that has had two squares in opposite corners removed). Then he argues that it is obvious that evolving present-day life that ends up inventing iPhones can easily be seen to be impossible by natural processes. He summarizes his argument in a few sentences: Well, I have a very simple proof that the biological problem #3 posed above is also impossible to solve, that does fit in the margin of this document. All one needs to do is realize that if a solution were found, we would have proved something obviously false, that a few (four, apparently) fundamental, unintelligent forces of physics alone could have rearranged the fundamental particles of physics into libraries full of science texts and encyclopedias, computers connected to monitors, keyboards, laser printers and the Internet, cars, trucks, airplanes, nuclear power plants and Apple iPhones. Is this really a valid proof? It seems perfectly valid to me, as I cannot think of anything in all of science that can be stated with more confidence than that a few unintelligent forces of physics alone could not have rearranged the basic particles of physics into Apple iPhones. Now Sewell is a mathematician, author of a book on solving differential equations. But he seems to accept proof-by-obviousness, a method most mathematicians would not accept. He should listen to them. Instead he lays the obviousness on a bit too thick ...</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Crepuscular rays</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/crepuscular-rays.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Crepuscular rays" /><published>2021-04-26T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-26T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/crepuscular-rays</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/crepuscular-rays.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Sarah Wise&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Wise_Crepuscular_3_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Crepuscular rays&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://optics.kulgun.net/Rays/&quot;&gt;Crepuscular rays&lt;/a&gt;, by Sarah Wise, taken from her home near Louisville, Colo., mid-April, 2021.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We chose this splendid picture from among several equally splendid shots in part because it shows clearly the origin of crepuscular rays – just look at the mountain peaks and valleys, especially on the right. The rays are the result of light scattering by the atmosphere. On the left, you can clearly see atmospheric scattering where one of the rays roughly bisects a cloud. And finally, you can see how every cloud has a silver lining.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, I assume that crepuscular rays are the reason Moses has horns in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moses_(Michelangelo)&quot;&gt;Michelangelo’s sculpture of Moses&lt;/a&gt;: ray and horn are the same word in Biblical Hebrew, probably because the ancients simply called crepuscular rays “horns.” It seems likely to me that they envisioned Moses as having had (crepuscular) &lt;i&gt;rays&lt;/i&gt; coming out of his head.  Again incidentally, you may find other depictions of Moses with horns &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/lessons-from-history/the-intriguing-interpretation-of-horns-in-michelangelos-sculpture-moses-a1044179408b&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. There is nothing new in the author’s premise that the word was mistranslated into Greek.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Sarah Wise. Crepuscular rays, by Sarah Wise, taken from her home near Louisville, Colo., mid-April, 2021. We chose this splendid picture from among several equally splendid shots in part because it shows clearly the origin of crepuscular rays – just look at the mountain peaks and valleys, especially on the right. The rays are the result of light scattering by the atmosphere. On the left, you can clearly see atmospheric scattering where one of the rays roughly bisects a cloud. And finally, you can see how every cloud has a silver lining. Incidentally, I assume that crepuscular rays are the reason Moses has horns in Michelangelo’s sculpture of Moses: ray and horn are the same word in Biblical Hebrew, probably because the ancients simply called crepuscular rays “horns.” It seems likely to me that they envisioned Moses as having had (crepuscular) rays coming out of his head. Again incidentally, you may find other depictions of Moses with horns here. There is nothing new in the author’s premise that the word was mistranslated into Greek.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Meditation on a review of a book by Stephen Meyer</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/meditation-on-review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meditation on a review of a book by Stephen Meyer" /><published>2021-04-16T19:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-16T19:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/meditation-on-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/meditation-on-review.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Meyer_Book_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Return-God-Hypothesis-Compelling-Scientific/dp/0062071505&quot;&gt;Return of the God Hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;: Three Scientific Discoveries that Reveal the Mind Behind the Universe&lt;/i&gt;, by Stephen Meyer. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Darrel Falk, a past president of BioLogos, recently reviewed Stephen Meyer’s latest book, &lt;i&gt;Return of the God Hypothesis&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://biologos.org/articles/return-of-the-god-hypothesis-a-biologists-reflections&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Professor Falk is sympathetic with Dr. Meyer and indeed avers that their “perspective[s] on the role of God in creation” are not “much different.” The review is nevertheless negative and led to an interesting exchange on a Google Group devoted in part to The Panda’s Thumb. I should stress that as far as I know none of us on PT has read the book, but by now we have probably all read the review. At any rate, the exchange is reprinted, with permission, below the fold:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Braterman, an honorary chemistry researcher at the University of Glasgow, noticed the following quotation that Prof. Falk singled out in his review:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;To make their case for the adequacy of a strictly materialistic approach to explanation in science and philosophy, defenders of this approach must first show that “gaps” in our knowledge of the materialistic causes of key events in the history of life and the universe can be filled with knowledge of an actual materialistic process capable of producing the events in question. (p. 613).&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He inquired,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;I am not sure what a non-materialistic process would look like, but here Meyer appears to be claiming the right to invoke God of the gaps as the default explanation, placing the onus on the scientific community to prove that no gaps exist. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Am I being unfair?&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Petto, Distinguished Lecturer in BioSciences at the University of Wisconsin – Milwaukee, responded,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;In essence, yes. This is the venerable creationist tactic that claims that if we do not (yet) have an explanation of some event or phenomenon based on naturalistic (so-called &quot;materialistic&quot;) processes, then, by default, the divine intervention &lt;i&gt;has&lt;/i&gt; to be accepted as the only alternative (though ID advocates tried to muddy their embrace of the Deity, they use the same logic). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

This fallacy of dualistic thinking has strong cultural resonance, especially in the USA, where we tout the value of hearing from &quot;both sides&quot; of a controversy (as though there were only two), and it was reinforced, I think, by the fact that lawyers were among some of the more prominent voices in the movement that emerged through the 1960s. For lawyers, of course, the adversarial environment in court works almost always this way: if I can poke enough holes in your argument and conclusions, then my argument and conclusions prevail. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

And this, I think, is why so much of the creationist (and now ID) literature is about problems with or &quot;evidences&quot; against evolution without any significant demonstration that the cre/ID position has any factual or experimental support. In their minds (and in the dualistic framework that they impose on the argument), there doesn't need to be any affirmative evidence. It is enough to show that your opponent's position is untenable or unsupported or somehow defective, and you win by default. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

It may work culturally, but it fails the chief claim made by ID and earlier &quot;creation scientists&quot;: that theirs is a scientific alternative. It is, in fact, not an alternative at all, but a vague cultural default position that is not defensible on its scientific merits&amp;mdash;or lack thereof.&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Return of the God Hypothesis: Three Scientific Discoveries that Reveal the Mind Behind the Universe, by Stephen Meyer. Darrel Falk, a past president of BioLogos, recently reviewed Stephen Meyer’s latest book, Return of the God Hypothesis, here. Professor Falk is sympathetic with Dr. Meyer and indeed avers that their “perspective[s] on the role of God in creation” are not “much different.” The review is nevertheless negative and led to an interesting exchange on a Google Group devoted in part to The Panda’s Thumb. I should stress that as far as I know none of us on PT has read the book, but by now we have probably all read the review. At any rate, the exchange is reprinted, with permission, below the fold:</summary></entry></feed>