<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-12-31T05:57:34-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Take the science and religion quiz</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/science-and-religion-quiz.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Take the science and religion quiz" /><published>2022-12-29T11:55:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-29T11:55:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/science-and-religion-quiz</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/science-and-religion-quiz.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Faraday_Institute_Results_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Survey results&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jerry Coyne on his blog today advises us to &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2022/12/29/take-the-faraday-institutes-science-vs-religion-quiz/&quot;&gt;Take the Faraday Institute’s Science vs. Religion quiz!&lt;/a&gt; So I did! &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencereligioncompass.org/&quot;&gt;(Here.)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may see my result to the left. I ended up in the fourth quadrant, relatively close to the y-axis. The axis labels are to some extent jargon: Functional means that religion is best at social activities, what Dr. Coyne and I would call “tikkun olam,” or “repairing the world.” Substantive, by contrast, means that religion has meaning or content. The terms on the x-axis are reasonably clear, but I consider scientism to be pejorative and wish they had found a better term. (I have more than once been accused of scientism and am somewhat gratified that I did not land farther to the right.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is what the quiz makers said about me, and it is fairly accurate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Science is true, but religion has some value”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For you, science is the only (or main) way to the truth and religion is only really a cultural phenomenon, so the two can get on just fine. But you’re likely to add an important caveat to this: the two can get on just as long as religion doesn’t try and make any truth claims and sticks to what it does best – building community and helping others. When it comes to the job of understanding reality, it has nothing important to contribute. If you’re here, your temperature is probably a bit cool.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s pretty good, and they are certainly correct that I think religion gets into hot water when it makes truth claims. I have no objection to religious beliefs that do not tread on scientific fact, though I do not hold such religious beliefs myself. I came out a little lower on the thermometer than I expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Faraday Institute also provided an estimate of where the great scientists of history may end up on their graph, shown below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Faraday_Institute_Great_Scientists_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Graph&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suppose you could quibble with some of the placements, but it was interesting that I find myself below Darwin, Heisenberg, and Huxley. Dr. Coyne is a more militant atheist than I am, and he ended up in the first quadrant, about where Bohr appears, and farther than I would have expected from the “New Atheists.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you decide to take the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencereligioncompass.org/&quot;&gt; quiz&lt;/a&gt;, feel free to discuss your results in the Comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Jerry Coyne on his blog today advises us to Take the Faraday Institute’s Science vs. Religion quiz! So I did! (Here.) You may see my result to the left. I ended up in the fourth quadrant, relatively close to the y-axis. The axis labels are to some extent jargon: Functional means that religion is best at social activities, what Dr. Coyne and I would call “tikkun olam,” or “repairing the world.” Substantive, by contrast, means that religion has meaning or content. The terms on the x-axis are reasonably clear, but I consider scientism to be pejorative and wish they had found a better term. (I have more than once been accused of scientism and am somewhat gratified that I did not land farther to the right.) Here is what the quiz makers said about me, and it is fairly accurate:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Miracles: William Dembski gets it (mostly) right; NY Times does not</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/miracles-william-dembski.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Miracles: William Dembski gets it (mostly) right; NY Times does not" /><published>2022-12-27T09:06:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-27T09:06:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/miracles-william-dembski</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/miracles-william-dembski.html">&lt;p&gt;The New York Times on Sunday ran what I consider a very credulous article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2022/12/24/opinion/miracles-neuroscience-proof.html&quot;&gt;How Would You Prove That God Performed a Miracle?&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/column/molly-worthen&quot;&gt;Molly Worthen&lt;/a&gt;, an historian who, I thought, had not the foggiest idea how you would do so. You may read Jerry Coyne’s takedown of her article &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2022/12/26/nyt-touts-religious-miracles-as-proof-of-god/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Worthen lets William Dembski get the last word. We have criticized Dr. Dembski seemingly endlessly on this blog, but here I think he’s got it essentially right:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I believe in miracles, but I think they require scrutiny,” Dr. Dembski told me [Dr. Worthen]. “I don’t tend to see things as flamboyant as in the New Testament.” He published a moving &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.baptistpress.com/resource-library/news/first-person-faith-healing-wheres-the-evidence/&quot;&gt;account&lt;/a&gt; of his family’s disappointment at a healing revival, where he sought prayer for his autistic son. “There can be quite a bit of self-delusion on the part of people looking for miracles, and it troubles me,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Dembski’s family has learned to look for the miraculous in everyday loving encounters, like when a teacher’s aide made it her mission to help his son learn to use the bathroom on his own. “His life is so much better because of this person who wouldn’t give up on him,” he said. “It was no miracle, in terms of a magic wand that touched him and everything was fine. It was people who were willing to love him and do the hard work.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Dembski says he believes in miracles. Or perhaps gives lip service to a belief in miracles. What happened when it got down to brass tacks, as when he took his autistic child to the so-called faith healer? The supposed healer refused to see the child because he did not “look the part”; Dr. Dembski saw right through faith healing and indeed recognized it as “self-delusion.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consider a miracle to be a figure of speech for when, say, that teacher takes his son under her wing, does the very best she can with him, and, against the odds, succeeds. Dr. Dembski professes a belief in literal miracles, but seems more impressed with practical, figure-of-speech–type miracles. On that, we can agree.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">The New York Times on Sunday ran what I consider a very credulous article, How Would You Prove That God Performed a Miracle? by Molly Worthen, an historian who, I thought, had not the foggiest idea how you would do so. You may read Jerry Coyne’s takedown of her article here. Dr. Worthen lets William Dembski get the last word. We have criticized Dr. Dembski seemingly endlessly on this blog, but here I think he’s got it essentially right: “I believe in miracles, but I think they require scrutiny,” Dr. Dembski told me [Dr. Worthen]. “I don’t tend to see things as flamboyant as in the New Testament.” He published a moving account of his family’s disappointment at a healing revival, where he sought prayer for his autistic son. “There can be quite a bit of self-delusion on the part of people looking for miracles, and it troubles me,” he said. Dr. Dembski’s family has learned to look for the miraculous in everyday loving encounters, like when a teacher’s aide made it her mission to help his son learn to use the bathroom on his own. “His life is so much better because of this person who wouldn’t give up on him,” he said. “It was no miracle, in terms of a magic wand that touched him and everything was fine. It was people who were willing to love him and do the hard work.” Dr. Dembski says he believes in miracles. Or perhaps gives lip service to a belief in miracles. What happened when it got down to brass tacks, as when he took his autistic child to the so-called faith healer? The supposed healer refused to see the child because he did not “look the part”; Dr. Dembski saw right through faith healing and indeed recognized it as “self-delusion.” I consider a miracle to be a figure of speech for when, say, that teacher takes his son under her wing, does the very best she can with him, and, against the odds, succeeds. Dr. Dembski professes a belief in literal miracles, but seems more impressed with practical, figure-of-speech–type miracles. On that, we can agree.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breakthrough for Intelligent Design? (Part 7)</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/erkell7.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breakthrough for Intelligent Design? (Part 7)" /><published>2022-12-21T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-21T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/erkell7</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/erkell7.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Biologg_Banner_900.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Biolog(g) banner&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The text is a pun in Swedish: &quot;Logg&quot; means something like a ship´s log or a logbook.&lt;br /&gt; A blog is &quot;blogg&quot;. 
 So &quot;Biolog(g)&quot; is a biologist´s log or blog.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is part 7 of a series of 7 posts by Lars Johan Erkell, with comments on each by Ola Hössjer and a reply by Erkell.  Part 1 will be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PandasThumb/pandasthumb.github.io/edit/source/_posts/2022/2022-11-09-erkell1.md&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  They are translations of &lt;a href=&quot;https://biologg.wordpress.com/2020/11/13/genombrott-for-intelligent-design-del-3/&quot;&gt;2020 posts in Swedish&lt;/a&gt; from the Biolog(g) blog of the Department of Biology of Gothenburg University, responding to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519320302071?via%3Dihub&quot;&gt;an article by Steiner Thorvaldsen and Ola Hössjer&lt;/a&gt; titled “Using statistical methods to model the fine-tuning
of molecular machines and systems” in Journal of Theoretical Biology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;breakthrough-for-intelligent-design-part-7&quot;&gt;Breakthrough for Intelligent design? (part 7)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;November 13, 2020&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Lars Jon Erkell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why was the article published?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The publication of Thorvaldsen and Hössjer’s article is embarrassing for the Journal of Theoretical Biology. One could expect the journal to take drastic measures to try to restore its damaged reputation. Like withdrawing the article, firing the responsible editor and blacklisting the reviewers responsible for the scientific review. But they didn’t do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, they let the article stand and published a disclaimer from the journal’s management. It reads:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Journal of Theoretical Biology and its co-Chief Editors do not endorse in any way the ideology of nor reasoning behind the concept of intelligent design. Since the publication of the paper it has now become evident that the authors are connected to a creationist group (although their addresses are given on the paper as departments in bona fide universities). We were unaware of this fact while the paper was being reviewed. Moreover, the keywords “intelligent design” were added by the authors after the review process during the proofing stage and we were unaware of this action by the authors. We have removed these from the online version of this paper. We believe that intelligent design is not in any way a suitable topic for the Journal of Theoretical Biology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the editors distance themselves from ID as such, and say that they did not understand that it was about ID because the keyword “intelligent design” was added by the authors only after the article had been reviewed. That is a strange statement. Firstly, because the editors would not have understood that it was about ID. It is enough to glance quickly through the text to recognize familiar ID themes such as irreducible complexity, specified complexity or Dembski’s explanatory filter. If you happen not to recognize such markers, you should ask yourself what in the world this is all about, and check it out. Failure to understand that this is about creationism/ID shows ignorance and carelessness on a level that is inexcusable for a scientific journal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I believe that it is wrong to reject an article solely for the reason that it deals with ID. It could (theoretically) happen that someone actually managed to find good scientific arguments for ID, and then they should of course be published. That would be a sensation. But, as we saw in the previous post, Thorvaldsen and Hössjer have not managed to show anything at all. The statistical method they want to introduce is useless, and consequently they have no results. The article should not have been accepted for publication for the reason that it has no scientific interest. Added to this is all the pseudoscience the article contains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why didn’t the journal retract the article, and why did they write this strange disclaimer? &lt;!--more--&gt; One reason may be that the publisher that owns the Journal of Theoretical Biology, Elsevier, has had bad experiences with retracting articles related to ID. A well-known ID proponent, the mathematician Granville Sewell, had an article in 2011 titled “A second look at the second law” accepted by Applied Mathematical Letters, also owned by Elsevier. When the editor realized that the work was pseudoscientific, it was retracted. Sewell sued the journal, and the dispute ended with the publisher being forced to pay $10,000 and to publish an apology. They probably don’t want to do this again.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;But how did Thorvaldsen and Hössjer’s article even get through the review process? One possibility is, as I said, ignorance and carelessness on a level that is unforgivable for a scientific journal. Another could be that the authors may have taken advantage of the opportunity that some journals offer, to suggest suitable reviewers themselves. If they then suggested ID-friendly people, and the editor didn’t bother to read the work, the article may have gone under the radar. Then the editor may have been ID-friendly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the reason for this handling may be, it is sad that such a highly ranked journal as the Journal of Theoretical Biology is unable to live up to basic requirements of scientific integrity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;update-for-pandas-thumb&quot;&gt;Update for Panda’s Thumb&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the publication of this post in 2020, new
information about the review procedure has surfaced. In
the article “Creation-based research advances the
positions” &lt;a href=&quot;https://genesis.nu/i/artiklar/skapelsebaserad-forskning-flyttar-fram-positionerna/&quot;&gt;(Skapelsebaserad forskning flyttar fram positionerna)&lt;/a&gt;, 
published on the website of
the Swedish creationist association Genesis on the 9th
of July 2021, we can read this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;During the review process, the journal’s editors and
reviewer advised the authors to tone down the references
to Intelligent Design (ID) and replace it with the term
“fine-tuning”, including in the title of the article, which was
done. On the other hand, they had no objection to a
discussion of ID, as well as criticism of neo-Darwinism,
provided that Thorvaldsen and Hössjer also referred to
sources critical of ID. For this reason, the authors judged
in connection with the final proofreading that it would be
relevant to have “intelligent design” as one of the key
words for the article. The word “intelligent” was then
deleted by the responsible editor (see below); still the
word “intelligent” is considered too sensitive in contexts
like this&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, in the talk “Creation-based research in a
secular research world” &lt;a href=&quot;https://genesis.nu/video/skapelsebaserad-forskning-i-en-sekular-forskarvarld-ola-hossjer/&quot;&gt;(Skapelsebaserad forskning i en sekulär forskarvärld)&lt;/a&gt; given at the annual
meeting of the Swedish creationist association Genesis
in 2021, Ola Hössjer confirms this picture at 27:37:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When we first submitted the article, we included
“Intelligent Design” in the title as well. The editor and
reviewers were positive but they said replace ID with
fine tuning in the title and abstract but you can keep
evolution criticism later in the article and mention ID,
and the article was, to my own surprise, published,
but there were many people who contacted and
wanted the article retracted. The editors were under
a lot of pressure, so they were forced to write a
disclaimer saying we disavow all research in ID, and
it has come to our attention that the researchers are
associated with creationist groups. But they did not
remove the article and that was the most important
thing for me, so it remains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that the editors and the reviewers were
complicit in smuggling the article through the review
process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is more. A post titled “Editors say they won’t
retract intelligent design paper despite subject being
‘not in any way a suitable topic’ for their journal” &lt;a href=&quot;https://retractionwatch.com/2020/10/15/editors-say-they-wont-retract-intelligent-design-paper-despite-subject-being-not-in-any-way-a-suitable-topic-for-their-journal/&quot;&gt;(here)&lt;/a&gt; at the website Retraction Watch points out that
Steinar Thorvaldsen failed to disclose a conflict of
interest when he did not disclose that he was the
chairman of the board in the ID-promoting foundation
BioCosmos. A foundation that had recently received a
$1.6 million grant. According to the guidelines of J.
Theor. Biol., this would have been a cause for
retraction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;end-of-update&quot;&gt;End of update&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, what will be the answer to the question if Thorvaldsen and Hössjer’s article is a breakthrough for Intelligent Design? It depends on who you ask. For the Discovery Institute and the ID movement, it is a success to have an ID-friendly article published in a high-ranking scientific journal. The publication makes it easier to present ID as a scientifically legitimate theory, something that is valuable in public opinion work. At the same time, the journal’s disclaimer provides an opportunity to present the ID movement as a victim and to complain that they are being discriminated against by the “Darwinists”. They go so far as to compare the journal’s treatment of the article to the Nazis’ treatment of the Jews. The Swedish association Genesis sees the critique as a serious attack on academic freedom and illustrates their article with a photo that appears to come from a concentration camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a scientific point of view, the article does not represent any scientific breakthrough for the simple reason that it contains no results. Just a useless statistical model. And that makes perfect sense; ID is not a scientific project, and it cannot produce any scientific knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comment by Ola Hössjer&lt;/strong&gt; June 29, 2021 4:12 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 7: Why was the fine-tuning article published?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last and concluding part of his series of articles, Erkell asks
himself how our article could be accepted by a reputable journal. I find
no reason to comment on Erkell's speculations about the reasons why
TH2020 was published. I am content with the fact that the article was
evaluated according to the usual peer review procedure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After pondering the reasons why TH2020 was published, Erkell arrives at the following conclusion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Whatever the reason for this handling may be, it is sad that such a highly ranked journal as the Journal of Theoretical Biology is unable to live up to basic requirements for scientific integrity.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this context one may ask – which are the basic requirements for
scientific integrity are? Based on Erkell’s first six articles, it is not
difficult to guess that scientific integrity for him means that science
must follow the principle of methodological naturalism. In other words,
Erkell demands that all science should be conducted on a secular basis.
On the contrary, for my part I believe that the editors showed a great
deal of integrity when, despite a storm of criticism from evolutionary
biologists, they held on to their decision to publish the article. This,
as I see it, is a healthy sign that gives good hope for the future of
science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions from parts 1-7&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, I welcome examination and scrutiny of the research articles I
wrote, both constructive criticism and appreciation. In this context, I
would like to take the opportunity to mention that not all scientists
seem to have the same attitude as Erkell towards the article that I wrote
with Thorvaldsen. After TH2020 was published, I co-authored a follow-up
article on the time it would take for evolution to bring about major
genetic changes. This paper has recently been published and I have been
invited to give a talk on its findings at an international conference
with many well-known participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I wrote in the introduction, I want to thank Lars Johan Erkell for
actually taking the time to read, not only the article on fine-tuning
that I coauthored with Steinar, but also several of the articles we refer
to. If time permits, I am happy to continue this exchange of ideas,
through articles or debates. However, I believe that much of Erkell’s
criticism misses the point. First, Erkell has misunderstood what
Intelligent Design or creationism means by assuming that such research is
governed by non-falsifiable criteria. Secondly, Erkell makes a feather
out of a chicken when he criticizes us for using the word &quot;non-physical
information&quot;, because he did not understand what we meant by this term.
Third, Erkell does not seem to realize that his methodological naturalism
is not an objective and agnostic point of view, but on the contrary it is
based on a materialist starting point. By using methodological
naturalism, Erkell thus wants to force all research to be guided by
secular assumptions. For my part, I advocate a scientific environment
where secular, design-based, creationist and other hypotheses are allowed
to participate and be tested on equal terms. I leave it to the reader to
judge whether my approach or Erkell's is the more democratic one and the
one that best matches the purpose of science to seek the truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reply by Lars Johan Erkell&lt;/strong&gt;
September 8, 2021 7:24 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, to the question of how TH2020 came to be published in J. Theor.
Biol. I, and many with me, have been surprised by the matter. You write
above that the article has been reviewed &quot;according to the usual peer
review procedure&quot;. The picture you get of the process in the article
&quot;Creation-based research moves the positions forward&quot;, which the
association Genesis published on its website on July 9, is a completely
different one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;During the review process, the journal’s editors and reviewer advised the authors to tone down the references to Intelligent Design (ID) and replace it with the term ‘fine-tuning’, including in the title of the article, which was done. On the other hand, there were no objections to a discussion of ID, as well as criticism of neo-Darwinism, on the condition that Thorvaldsen and Hössjer also referred to ID-critical sources. For that reason, the authors judged in connection with the final revision that it would be relevant to have “intelligent design” as one of the keywords for the article. The word “Intelligent” was then deleted by the responsible editor (see below); the word ‘intelligent’ is still considered too sensitive in contexts like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we have the explanation why the article could be published: ID-
friendly editors. That the journal's editors and reviewers advise the
authors to avoid sensitive phrases in order to go under the radar and
thus be able to violate the journal's policy is not a &quot;customary&quot;
procedure. It is also confirmed by the disclaimer that was published.
Your claim that this was a &quot;customary peer review procedure&quot; is therefore
not true, if the article on the website of the association Genesis is to
be believed. I am inclined to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to my regret that the journal does not live up to basic requirements for scientific integrity. You write “Based on Erkell’s first six articles, it is not difficult to guess that for him scientific integrity means that science must follow methodological naturalism as a principle”. No, this has nothing to do with naturalism. It is about the fact that a scientific journal should not publish material that does not meet reasonable requirements for scientific rigor, thereby giving it legitimacy. For me, this means in this case that you don’t publish material where you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;claim that you have shown something when you have not actually done it. The reader who is not attentive (or knowledgeable enough) is deceived.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;present an unusable method as if it were useful. Again, you can fool the reader.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;give the impression that concepts that are not established and well defined, such as “specificity” and “non-physical information” would actually be solid and defined. This means that the reasoning can give the impression of being rigorous when in fact the concepts are so blurred that they do not make sense.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;do not discuss weaknesses in your own model. The most glaring weakness in this case is the enormous (and by all accounts insurmountable) difficulties in calculating the probability that a structure would be designed by a non-material designer, something that is not mentioned.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have manipulated quotations in the text.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, you suggest that much of my criticism misses the mark for three reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Firstly, Erkell has misunderstood what Intelligent Design or creationism means, in that he assumes that such research is governed by non-falsifiable criteria”. To that I answer both yes and no. I make an attempt to clarify the problem in the post “Science, hypotheses and Intelligent design”.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Secondly, Erkell makes a chicken out of a feather when he criticizes us for using the word “non-physical information”, because he did not understand what we mean by this concept”. It is quite true that I do not understand what you mean by “non-physical information”. And that is because you yourselves do not seem to understand what you mean - you do not even attempt a definition. The only thing you come up with is a vague reference to “semantic information”.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thirdly, Erkell does not seem to realize that his methodological naturalism is not an objective and agnostic point of view, but on the contrary is based on a materialist belief. By using methodological naturalism, Erkell wants to force all research to be guided by secular assumptions”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an echo of Phillip Johnson’s argument that methodological naturalism is in fact philosophical naturalism in disguise. It’s not.  Methodological naturalism is literally methodological, it is about how to work in a practical way to obtain reliable research results. But ID research (to the extent that it exists at all) has not produced a single concrete result in more than 20 years (please correct me if I’m wrong). This is because there are no practically working methods for “design detection” - all there is, is reasoning about how one might do it. TH2020 is another example of thais.  And because ID research does not work in practice, it is not seen as scientifically interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to democracy. You and Steinar Thorvaldsen have published an article
here that openly argues for ID in J. Theor. Biol., an established
scientific journal. You obviously have full freedom to devote yourself to
ID within the framework of your professorships. The same goes for your
fellow professors Michael Behe, Stuart Burgess and Scott Minnich, to
mention three names that come to mind at the moment. So obviously you are
allowed to work with ID, and you can publish in the scientific press. But
of course you have difficulty getting research grants, and that's not so
strange - a completely ordinary, secular, research program that hasn't
produced any results for more than 20 years wouldn't get a penny either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You write that you are happy to continue our exchange of ideas through
articles or debates. That was nice, I do too, but I’m not particularly
interested in debates. A written exchange with judicious arguments, like
the one we have now, gives much more. And these are important questions
we have to address: what is legitimate science, and where are the limits
of science?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lars Johan Erkell (with comment by Ola Hössjer)</name></author><summary type="html">The text is a pun in Swedish: &quot;Logg&quot; means something like a ship´s log or a logbook. A blog is &quot;blogg&quot;. So &quot;Biolog(g)&quot; is a biologist´s log or blog. This is part 7 of a series of 7 posts by Lars Johan Erkell, with comments on each by Ola Hössjer and a reply by Erkell. Part 1 will be found here. They are translations of 2020 posts in Swedish from the Biolog(g) blog of the Department of Biology of Gothenburg University, responding to an article by Steiner Thorvaldsen and Ola Hössjer titled “Using statistical methods to model the fine-tuning of molecular machines and systems” in Journal of Theoretical Biology Breakthrough for Intelligent design? (part 7) November 13, 2020 by Lars Jon Erkell Why was the article published? The publication of Thorvaldsen and Hössjer’s article is embarrassing for the Journal of Theoretical Biology. One could expect the journal to take drastic measures to try to restore its damaged reputation. Like withdrawing the article, firing the responsible editor and blacklisting the reviewers responsible for the scientific review. But they didn’t do that. Instead, they let the article stand and published a disclaimer from the journal’s management. It reads: The Journal of Theoretical Biology and its co-Chief Editors do not endorse in any way the ideology of nor reasoning behind the concept of intelligent design. Since the publication of the paper it has now become evident that the authors are connected to a creationist group (although their addresses are given on the paper as departments in bona fide universities). We were unaware of this fact while the paper was being reviewed. Moreover, the keywords “intelligent design” were added by the authors after the review process during the proofing stage and we were unaware of this action by the authors. We have removed these from the online version of this paper. We believe that intelligent design is not in any way a suitable topic for the Journal of Theoretical Biology. Here the editors distance themselves from ID as such, and say that they did not understand that it was about ID because the keyword “intelligent design” was added by the authors only after the article had been reviewed. That is a strange statement. Firstly, because the editors would not have understood that it was about ID. It is enough to glance quickly through the text to recognize familiar ID themes such as irreducible complexity, specified complexity or Dembski’s explanatory filter. If you happen not to recognize such markers, you should ask yourself what in the world this is all about, and check it out. Failure to understand that this is about creationism/ID shows ignorance and carelessness on a level that is inexcusable for a scientific journal. Secondly, I believe that it is wrong to reject an article solely for the reason that it deals with ID. It could (theoretically) happen that someone actually managed to find good scientific arguments for ID, and then they should of course be published. That would be a sensation. But, as we saw in the previous post, Thorvaldsen and Hössjer have not managed to show anything at all. The statistical method they want to introduce is useless, and consequently they have no results. The article should not have been accepted for publication for the reason that it has no scientific interest. Added to this is all the pseudoscience the article contains. So why didn’t the journal retract the article, and why did they write this strange disclaimer?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Martian meteorite</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/martian-meteorite.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Martian meteorite" /><published>2022-12-19T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-19T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/martian-meteorite</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/martian-meteorite.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph supplied by &lt;strong&gt;Dan Phelps&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Phelps_Meteorite_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Meteorite&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martian_meteorite&quot;&gt;Martian meteorite&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Mr. Phelps tells us, &quot;I bought a small Mars meteorite: northwest Africa 12269 0.395 grams. About a centimeter wide and slightly more long. Very thin.&quot; The meteorite was discovered in 2018 in an unknown location in northwest Africa. The photograph is from the documentation that came with the meteorite.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph supplied by Dan Phelps. Martian meteorite &amp;ndash; Mr. Phelps tells us, &quot;I bought a small Mars meteorite: northwest Africa 12269 0.395 grams. About a centimeter wide and slightly more long. Very thin.&quot; The meteorite was discovered in 2018 in an unknown location in northwest Africa. The photograph is from the documentation that came with the meteorite.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breakthrough for Intelligent Design? (Part 6)</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/erkell6.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breakthrough for Intelligent Design? (Part 6)" /><published>2022-12-14T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-14T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/erkell6</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/erkell6.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Biologg_Banner_900.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Biolog(g) banner&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The text is a pun in Swedish: &quot;Logg&quot; means something like a ship´s log or a logbook.&lt;br /&gt; A blog is &quot;blogg&quot;. 
 So &quot;Biolog(g)&quot; is a biologist´s log or blog.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is part 6 of a series of 7 posts by Lars Johan Erkell, with comments on each by Ola Hössjer and a reply by Erkell.  Part 1 will be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PandasThumb/pandasthumb.github.io/edit/source/_posts/2022/2022-11-09-erkell1.md&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  They are translations of &lt;a href=&quot;https://biologg.wordpress.com/2020/11/13/genombrott-for-intelligent-design-del-3/&quot;&gt;2020 posts in Swedish&lt;/a&gt; from the Biolog(g) blog of the Department of Biology of Gothenburg University.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;breakthrough-for-intelligent-design-part-6&quot;&gt;Breakthrough for Intelligent design? (part 6)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;November 13, 2020&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Lars Johan Erkell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why was this article written?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I hope has become clear, Thorvaldsen and Hössjer’s article does not
meet the requirements that one reasonably could expect from a scientific
publication. It pretends to have results that do not exist. The article
relies entirely on a statistical method to demonstrate designs that is
useless. It contains references to an indeterminate supernatural designer
that is resorted to &lt;em&gt;ad hoc&lt;/em&gt; to achieve desired results. It introduces the
completely revolutionary concept of &quot;non-physical information&quot; without
definition or discussion. It contains a grossly garbled quote. In
addition, well-known pseudoscientific concepts such as &quot;irreducible
complexity&quot; and &quot;specified complexity&quot; are referred to as if they were
established science. This cannot be called science. It can only be called
pseudoscience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, Thorvaldsen and Hössjer have received criticism. Three biologists write in a comment to the Journal of Theoretical Biology, among other things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… The central claim of this paper is that because biological systems are complex then they must be fine-tuned. This inference is flawed and is not supported by the evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor is the mathematician Jason Rosenhouse gracious in &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/biology-journal-gets-conned.html&quot;&gt;his criticism&lt;/a&gt;. He concludes thus:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… The authors claim to have used probability theory to establish a scientifically rigorous and useful notion of “fine-tuning,” but they have failed because we have nothing like the information we would need to carry out meaningful probability calculations. Done.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;But I don’t think I’ve adequately communicated just how bad this paper is. The authors are constantly tossing out bits of mathematical jargon and notation, but then they do nothing with them. There is a frustrating lack of precision, as when they variously describe fine-tuning as an object, an entity, a method, and an attribute of a system, all on the first page of the paper. They constantly cite creationist references, with only the most glancing mention that any of this work has been strongly and cogently criticized. They say we should give fair consideration to a “design model” for the origin of complex structures, but they do not give the beginning of a clue as to what such a model entails.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;In short, it’s hard to believe this paper could have gotten through an honest peer-review process (as opposed to one in which ideology played a big role). Whatever happened behind the scenes, it’s a huge black eye for the journal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review is worth reading in its entirety. It also covers things I didn’t cover here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steinar Thorvaldsen is Professor of Information Science at Norway's
Arctic University in Tromsø and Ola Hössjer is Professor of Mathematical
Statistics at Stockholm University. They are both established professors
at reputable universities. I find it hard to imagine that they would
write papers of this poor quality in their own fields (I also doubt they
would get away with it). So why have they written this article? As
experienced and competent researchers, they must reasonably be aware of
the article's devastating scientific flaws. Why are they willing to risk
name and reputation to write an article that makes me and many colleagues
facepalm and wonder what has gotten into the authors? This is not
something you expect from a professor at a respected university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My guess is that they see it as their task to spearhead a new kind of science that includes a designer, and that they feel is not limited by the materialism that characterizes established natural science. The idea of “Intelligent Design” as an alternative, non-materialistic science was launched in the USA in the 1990s by the conservative Christian think tank Discovery Institute. The institute’s agenda was revealed in 1999 when the policy document The Wedge Document was leaked and posted on the Internet. It appears that they see “materialism” and moral relativism as the cause of all evil in society. Materialism must therefore be crushed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Discovery Institute’s Center for the Renewal of Science and Culture seeks nothing less than the overthrow of materialism and its cultural legacies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important part of materialism is today’s natural science, and therefore is an overarching goal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To replace materialistic explanations with the theistic understanding that nature and human beings are created by God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design theory has been created to replace materialistic science:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Design theory promises to reverse the stifling dominance of the materialist worldview, and to replace it with a science consonant with Christian and theistic convictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The document shows very clearly that the ID project is a
political/religious project; it is about working for a society that is
completely imbued with a Christian religiosity. A theocracy, in other
words. Natural science is &quot;materialistic&quot; and therefore stands in the
way. Therefore, it must be replaced by a religiously based design
science.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; In case any reader should think that I am presenting conspiracy
theories, I would recommend a careful reading of the document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This explains why ID continues to be pursued as a science even though the
project is completely sterile - in more than 20 years it has failed to
produce a single solid result that concretely demonstrates design in
nature. On the other hand, mountains of material have been produced that
criticize established natural science in general and the theory of
evolution in particular. The goal of the activity is not primarily to
convince the researchers; it is to convince the public and decision-
makers at various levels that design theory is better science than the
established, materialistic, natural science. The document shows that the
strategy is to defeat science in the political arena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does all this have to do with Steinar Thorvaldsen and Ola
Hössjer? It turns out that they are both connected to the Norwegian
foundation BioCosmos, Thorvaldsen as chairman of the board and Hössjer as
&quot;ambassador&quot;. BioCosmos aims to spread Intelligent Design, primarily to
youth and young adults, and is Norwegian partner of the Discovery
Institute. This article falls into the same pattern as countless other
pro-ID articles: it is clearly written to give the impression that ID is
a legitimate scientific theory, it contains no results, but many
arguments against the theory of evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are Thorvaldsen and Hössjer aware that they are participating in a
crusade against natural science? They should, as professional scientists,
be aware that ID is a pseudo-scientific, indeed anti-scientific, project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the case may be, it is sad that two such competent and meritorious researchers are unable to live up to the scientific integrity one has the right to expect from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;English Wikipedia has a comprehensive and informative series on ID. See also:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara Forrest: Understanding the Intelligent Design Creationist Movement: Its True Nature and Goal. Center for Inquiry (2007)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lenny Flank: Deception by Design: The Intelligent Design Movement in America. Red and Black Publishers (2009)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comment by Ola Hössjer&lt;/strong&gt;
June 29, 2021 4:05 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 6: Why was the fine-tuning article written?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In part 6, Erkell continues and asks what prompted me and Thorvaldsen to
write the article on fine-tuning. I quote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Steinar Thorvaldsen is Professor of Information Science at Norway's
Arctic University in Tromsø and Ola Hössjer is Professor of Mathematical
Statistics at Stockholm University. They are both established professors
at reputable universities. I find it hard to imagine that they would
write papers of this poor quality in their own fields (I also doubt they
would get away with it). So why have they written this article? As
experienced and competent researchers, they must reasonably be aware of
the article's devastating scientific flaws. Why are they willing to risk
name and reputation to write an article that makes me and many colleagues
facepalm and wonder what has gotten into the authors? This is not
something you expect from a professor at a respected university. My guess
is that they see it as their task to spearhead a new kind of science that
includes a designer, and that they feel is not limited by the materialism
that characterizes established natural science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In parts 1-5 I responded to Erkell’s claims that TH2020 is a
pseudoscientific article of poor quality. Let me therefore answer
Erkell's question why I have been involved in writing this and other
articles with an ID-based or creationist focus. There are two main
reasons. Firstly, I have been part of the academic community since I
started studying university mathematics at the age of 15. This long
period taught me a lot about how (empirical) science should be conducted.
I advocate academic freedom, where all relevant theories are allowed to
take part and compete on equal footing in terms of providing the best
explanations of data, in the search for the truth. For more than 20
years, I have studied genetics and evolutionary biology, and found that
Darwin's theory of evolution contains crucial flaws that are rarely
mentioned, neither in school nor at universities. It is my duty as a
scientist (part of the third task) to engage in the public sphere and
spread the experiences that I have acquired, both from my own research
and by learning from the research of others. My conscience therefore
urges me to enter the evolution-design debate, and this is more important
than political correctness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, all empirical science is based on faith assumptions. All attempts
to let only empirical data guide natural science (such as logical
positivism) have failed. These beliefs are especially important for
questions of origin, because we cannot replicate through repeated
experiments how life arose, or how the diversity of life between
different species came about. Therefore, every researcher who engages in
origin issues will be more or less guided by their starting assumptions
and beliefs. So am I. I accepted Jesus Christ as my personal Savior and
Lord, at the age of 23-24, and over the years I have realized more and
more how trustworthy and reliable the Bible is. I am therefore convinced
that design-inspired or biblically inspired (and falsifiable) models
provide the best explanation for genetic, geological and morphological
data. But I don't want to force these explanations on others, but let the
ID and creationist models compete with secular models on equal terms.
With sadness in my heart I notice how methodological naturalism has
gradually narrowed (and forced) science into a secular direction ever
since the 18th century. This has to a large extent, driven development of
society in a materialistic direction. And the theory of evolution has had
a decisive role in this process, because it is the creation story of
naturalism, and thus influences many other sciences. If neither God nor
anything else supernatural exists, then everything must have arisen by
itself, just as the theory of evolution claims. This is precisely why it
is so sensitive to criticize the theory of evolution, of which Erkell's
article series is a typical example. To criticize the theory of evolution
is simply to question the foundations of a worldview that dominates a
secular culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Erkell’s opening question about what prompted me and Thorvaldsen to
write the fine-tuning article, he goes on to discuss an American ID think
tank, the Discovery Institute, and its efforts to influence societal
development away from materialism. The reason is that both Thorvaldsen
and myself have been involved in a Norwegian think tank that is positive
about ID:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But what does all this have to do with Steinar Thorvaldsen and Ola
Hössjer? It turns out that they are both connected to the Norwegian
foundation BioCosmos, Thorvaldsen as chairman of the board and Hössjer as
&quot;ambassador&quot;. BioCosmos aims to spread Intelligent Design, primarily to
youth and young adults, and is Norwegian partner of the Discovery
Institute. This article falls into the same pattern as countless other
pro-ID articles: it is clearly written to give the impression that ID is
a legitimate scientific theory, it contains no results, but many
arguments against the theory of evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Are Thorvaldsen and Hössjer aware that they are participating in a
crusade against natural science? They should, as professional scientists,
be aware that ID is a pseudo-scientific, indeed anti-scientific,
project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already argued (in Parts 1-5) that ID and creationism are science, and
I will therefore not repeat my arguments in parts 1-5. I will content
myself by saying that I neither consider TH2020 to be an example of
pseudo-science or anti-science. But Erkell;s claims are not
surprising, since he very strongly advocates methodological naturalism,
that is, secular science. From Erkell's point of view, a crusade against
natural science is the same as a crusade against secular natural science.
As I have stressed in this series of articles, I believe that biblically
inspired models and design-inspired models very often have much better
explanatory power than the corresponding secular models. But since I
don’t want to force others to take this approach, it’s hardly a
crusade. One can rather ask the question whether Erkell is waging a
crusade against all science that does not start from methodological
naturalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reply by Lars Johan Erkell&lt;/strong&gt;
September 8, 2021 7:21 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I discuss the possible motivations of the article authors.
In your reply, you write: &quot;For more than 20 years, I have studied
genetics and evolutionary biology, and found that Darwin's theory of
development contains crucial flaws that are rarely mentioned, neither in
school nor at university.&quot; From what you write, I suspect that you have
drawn your knowledge from creationist sources rather than from university
courses. The formulation of &quot;crucial flaws rarely mentioned&quot; is a classic
creationist theme. But there is no science that is complete or perfect;
there are gaps and &quot;critical deficiencies&quot; in all fields of science.
However, creationists are most interested in the flaws they see in
evolutionary biology. This fact that the flaws are &quot;rarely mentioned&quot; and
your talk of &quot;political correctness&quot; also connects to a well-known
creationist theme: the atheist scientists who completely dominate science
and try to stifle all opposition to the theory of evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe you have misunderstood your duties as a scientist when it comes
to engagement in the public sphere. The university pays you to present 
the science and scientific view that the university stands for, not for
you to present a scientific view (and a view of evolutionary biology)
that the university does not stand for. As a researcher, you certainly
have a lot of freedom to choose different perspectives, but I think you
are probably crossing the line here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You write that &quot;It is with sadness in my heart that I see how
methodological naturalism has gradually narrowed (and forced) science
into a secular direction since the 18th century&quot;, and here I think we
have come to the heart of the matter. You see an ideological struggle
between two cultures, one secular and the other spiritual. I, on the
other hand, see a successful, secular, research program replacing a
sterile, spiritual, program. Materialistic research has gradually
replaced research on a non-materialistic basis because it actually works
and produces results. I have never seen any example of successful natural
science on a spiritual/religious basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as I write in the seventh post in the series, I could imagine an ID-inspired 
research if it produced concrete results. But we are not there.
All you can offer are assurances that an ID-inspired research will open
up to new advances by freeing science from materialistic lock-ins.
However, I can't see any signs that this could be the case. I discuss
this further in the post &lt;a href=&quot;2016-11-16-erkell8.md&quot;&gt;&quot;Science, hypotheses and Intelligent Design&quot;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You avoid perhaps the most serious part of my criticism, namely that the
ID project is fundamentally not about science but is a
political/religious project aimed at building a society completely imbued
with Christian religiosity - a theocracy. Do you have any comment on
that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lars Johan Erkell (with comment by Ola Hössjer)</name></author><summary type="html">The text is a pun in Swedish: &quot;Logg&quot; means something like a ship´s log or a logbook. A blog is &quot;blogg&quot;. So &quot;Biolog(g)&quot; is a biologist´s log or blog. &amp;nbsp; This is part 6 of a series of 7 posts by Lars Johan Erkell, with comments on each by Ola Hössjer and a reply by Erkell. Part 1 will be found here. They are translations of 2020 posts in Swedish from the Biolog(g) blog of the Department of Biology of Gothenburg University. &amp;nbsp; Breakthrough for Intelligent design? (part 6) November 13, 2020 by Lars Johan Erkell Why was this article written? As I hope has become clear, Thorvaldsen and Hössjer’s article does not meet the requirements that one reasonably could expect from a scientific publication. It pretends to have results that do not exist. The article relies entirely on a statistical method to demonstrate designs that is useless. It contains references to an indeterminate supernatural designer that is resorted to ad hoc to achieve desired results. It introduces the completely revolutionary concept of &quot;non-physical information&quot; without definition or discussion. It contains a grossly garbled quote. In addition, well-known pseudoscientific concepts such as &quot;irreducible complexity&quot; and &quot;specified complexity&quot; are referred to as if they were established science. This cannot be called science. It can only be called pseudoscience.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Inaugural address of creationist biology professor</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/inagural-address-creationist.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inaugural address of creationist biology professor" /><published>2022-12-07T18:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T18:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/inagural-address-creationist</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/inagural-address-creationist.html">&lt;p&gt;I have just watched the “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=coJY7emvclY&quot;&gt;inaugural address&lt;/a&gt;” of Richard Buggs, a biology professor at Queen Mary University of London. According to Jerry Coyne, Prof. Buggs is “&lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2021/03/08/a-creationist-professor-of-evolutionary-biology-in-england/&quot;&gt;A creationist professor of evolutionary biology in England&lt;/a&gt;.” Professor Buggs’s lecture was entitled “Trees of life: Do they exist?” The trees in question are those tall, leafy things that we like to lie under, the Darwinian tree of life, and the Biblical tree of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Buggs is amiable, and the lecture was very clear and easy to follow. He uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-022-28312-w&quot;&gt;this figure&lt;/a&gt; by Andre S. Chanderbali and colleagues to suggest that evolutionary trees do not really exist:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Buggs_Chandervali_Fig_2b_1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cloudogram&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Superposition of phylogenetic trees, or cloudogram, Figure 2(b) of paper by Chandervali and colleagues.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my untutored eye, the figure, called a &lt;i&gt;cloudogram&lt;/i&gt;, looks like an evolutionary tree with a great deal of noise, but that is probably no more than an artifact of my background in error analysis. The paper in which it appears is largely unintelligible to me, but it is clear that the authors were not aghast when they saw the figure and did not think that it posed any problems for evolution. A pen pal informs me that the figure combines nonoverlapping trees from a number of species representing groups with different histories, so presumably no conclusion about evolution may be drawn. Indeed, my pen pal adds, “actually some very good phylogenetic trees of chromosomes are in the same paper, and those are the important ones the authors refer to,” for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Buggs_Chandervali_Fig_3b_1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Phylogenetic tree&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Single, unambiguous phylogenetic tree, detail of Figure 3(b) of paper by Chandervali and colleagues.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twenty-odd minutes in, Prof. Buggs comes very close to suggesting that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flowering_plant&quot;&gt;angiosperms&lt;/a&gt; – flowering plants – have no common ancestor, from which we are left to infer that they were created &lt;i&gt;de novo&lt;/i&gt;. According to Wikipedia, the origin of angiosperms is “contentious,” but that is no reason to hint at a God-of-the-gaps argument. With apologies to &lt;a href=&quot;https://quotepark.com/quotes/1891929/history/&quot;&gt;whoever wrote the original&lt;/a&gt;, I immediately thought&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;How odd&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of God&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To tease&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With trees. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Late in the lecture, around 53 min, Prof. Buggs notes some miracles supposedly performed by Jesus of Nazareth and catalogued in the Book of Revelation. He argues that the miracles must be veridical, or Christianity would not have spread so wildly. Such a claim, if not disingenuous, is at least wholly inconsistent with the wild spreading of disinformation in our era or of “heresies” in earlier eras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will not go into detail, but Prof. Buggs suggests that the Christians on the western Turkish coast must have verified the miracles by talking to witnesses. I do not mean to be catty, but I am afraid they could not exactly have hopped on their donkeys and flown to Jerusalem to search for witnesses. In an earlier article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2009/07/francis-collins-3.html&quot;&gt;Francis Collins and the god of the gaps&lt;/a&gt;, I noted that Dr. Collins seemed very credulous when it came to his religious beliefs. Professor Buggs is in good company and comes across as at least equally credulous and perhaps less than critical in his thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But watch the video for yourself and let us know your opinion in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I have just watched the “inaugural address” of Richard Buggs, a biology professor at Queen Mary University of London. According to Jerry Coyne, Prof. Buggs is “A creationist professor of evolutionary biology in England.” Professor Buggs’s lecture was entitled “Trees of life: Do they exist?” The trees in question are those tall, leafy things that we like to lie under, the Darwinian tree of life, and the Biblical tree of life. Professor Buggs is amiable, and the lecture was very clear and easy to follow. He uses this figure by Andre S. Chanderbali and colleagues to suggest that evolutionary trees do not really exist:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breakthrough for Intelligent Design? (Part 5)</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/erkell5.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breakthrough for Intelligent Design? (Part 5)" /><published>2022-12-07T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/erkell5</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/erkell5.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Biologg_Banner_900.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Biolog(g) banner&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The text is a pun in Swedish: &quot;Logg&quot; means something like a ship´s log or a logbook.&lt;br /&gt; A blog is &quot;blogg&quot;. 
 So &quot;Biolog(g)&quot; is a biologist´s log or blog.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is part 5 of a series of 7 posts by Lars Johan Erkell, with comments on each by Ola Hössjer and a reply by Erkell.  Part 1 will be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PandasThumb/pandasthumb.github.io/edit/source/_posts/2022/2022-11-09-erkell1.md&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  They are translations of &lt;a href=&quot;https://biologg.wordpress.com/2020/11/13/genombrott-for-intelligent-design-del-3/&quot;&gt;2020 posts in Swedish&lt;/a&gt; from the Biolog(g) blog of the Department of Biology of Gothenburg University.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;breakthrough-for-intelligent-design-part-5&quot;&gt;Breakthrough for Intelligent design? (part 5)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;November 13, 2020&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Lars Johan Erkell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why is ID not seen as science?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this series of blog posts, I have repeatedly criticized Thorvaldsen and Hössjer for not working scientifically, and I have said that ID does not meet the requirements of science. ID proponents, by contrast, often and readily claim that they are victims of a rigid atheistic scientific (Darwinian) orthodoxy that refuses to recognize intelligent Design as legitimate science. There may therefore be reason to very briefly review what actually characterizes established science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Natural science strives to &lt;em&gt;describe&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;explain&lt;/em&gt; physical reality. Explanations are limited to physical reality because that is the only reality we have the tools to investigate. So there may well be a spiritual reality beyond our explanations; We cannot know anything about that. Many scientists are believers and do not experience a conflict between science and their faith in God. Natural science is thus &lt;em&gt;agnostic&lt;/em&gt; and not atheistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scientific way of working is usually called &lt;em&gt;methodological naturalism&lt;/em&gt;, meaning that only so-called natural explanations are used because that is the only thing that is practically possible, but not commenting on what goes on beyond the method. There is another position called &lt;em&gt;philosophical naturalism&lt;/em&gt;. It involves the a priori exclusion of all kinds of supernatural or spiritual forces, thus an atheistic position. But that is a logically untenable position – it is impossible to know that there cannot be things one does not know. I have never met a colleague who is a philosophical naturalist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This distinction is rarely made among creationists and ID advocates, even though it should be obvious. Scientists are accused again and again of being “materialists” or “naturalists”, by which is meant philosophical naturalists, i.e., atheists. But this is not true; science is, again, agnostic and not atheistic. There are believing scientists and there are atheist scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even though it is untrue that science would be hostile to religion, this is a cornerstone of the ID project. More on this in the next post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientific work is based on explaining phenomena with the help of knowledge. The tides, for example, are explained by the gravitational force of the moon (and also the sun) affecting the sea water. We can measure, we can count, and we can confirm that the explanation matches reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is population genetics. It is based on knowledge of genetic and molecular processes. With the help of population genetics, we can set up models of human evolution. Here, too, we can measure and count and evaluate our models. As we saw in the third post, Ola Hössjer and co-authors in their discussion of possible causes of genetic variation address five known factors: mutations, genetic drift, natural selection, recombination and colonization/isolation/migration. All of these are mechanisms that we know exist, and that we can measure and count on. We can have a fact-based discussion about how important the various factors are and how they work together. And we can get an idea of ​​how reasonable the conclusions are. This is science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the authors add an unknown designer as a sixth mechanism. Then all opportunities to conduct a fact-based discussion disappear; we have no idea when or how such a designer would intervene. Hössjer and his colleagues seem to assume that the designer would create just enough genetic variation that their model fits. How can they know that? How can they test their model? It’s not possible. They have simply invented a designer with the characteristics they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as we stick to tangible and measurable factors, we know what we’re talking about. If, on the other hand, we invoke an unknown designer, we do not know what we are talking about. This is precisely why ID does not work as science. A designer explains everything and nothing&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientific theories tell us something about the world. Gravitational theory, again, says that the planets must move in elliptical orbits around the Sun and that they must not move in hexagonal orbits. This means that if someone comes up with a new physical theory that has as a consequence that the planets would move in hexagonal orbits, we can reject that theory. It does not match reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intelligent Design, however, says nothing about reality. Since we know nothing about the designer, anything is possible and nothing is off limits. There is no design theory or design model that says anything concrete about the world, so there is nothing to compare with reality. It cannot do that because such a model must be based on knowledge of the designer. And we don’t have that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intelligent Design has never been formulated as a concrete theory. The only thing ID can offer is a “theory” that says that since science cannot fully 
explain the world, there must be a designer who created it. The idea is old and well known. It is called the teleological proof of God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this does not mean that one can reject the idea of a designer behind everything - there could be one. Science does not comment on what is beyond the scientific method. But the project to make ID a working science is stillborn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dawes, G.W. (2007): What is Wrong with Intelligent Design? International Journal for Philosophy of Religion, vol. 61, pp. 69–81 https://ourarchive.otago.ac.nz/handle/10523/565&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nichols, R. (2003): Scientific Content, Testability, and the Vacuity of Intelligent Design Theory. The American Catholic Philosophical Quarterly, vol. 77, pp. 591 – 611. https://www.pdcnet.org/acpq/content/acpq_2003_0077_0004_0591_0611&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comment by Ola Hössjer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 5: Intelligent Design and Science&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the fifth part of his series of articles, Erkell turns to a discussion of scientific theories. This is welcome, because the major dividing line between me and Erkell concerns the philosophical starting point of science. Erkell writes the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Natural science strives to &lt;em&gt;describe&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;explain&lt;/em&gt; physical reality. Explanations are limited to physical reality because that is the only reality we have the tools to investigate. So there may well be a spiritual reality beyond our explanations; We cannot know anything about that. Many scientists are believers and do not experience a conflict between science and their faith in God. Natural science is thus &lt;em&gt;agnostic&lt;/em&gt; and not atheistic.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The scientific way of working is usually called &lt;em&gt;methodological naturalism&lt;/em&gt;, meaning that only so-called natural explanations because that is the only thing that is practically possible, but one does not comment on what goes on beyond the method. There is another position called &lt;em&gt;philosophical naturalism&lt;/em&gt;. It involves the a priori exclusion of all kinds of supernatural or spiritual forces, thus an atheistic position. But that is a logically untenable position – it is impossible to know that there cannot be things one does not know. I have never met a colleague who is a philosophical naturalist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fully agree with the distinction between methodological naturalism (allowing only natural explanations in natural science) and philosophical naturalism (excluding the existence of the supernatural), which I also discuss in my book “Becoming a Christian”&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;. Furthermore, I agree with Erkell that natural science strives to describe and explain physical reality. But then Erkell claims that natural explanations are the only explanations that are practically possible. How did he arrive at that? It is simply a secular belief that underlies Erkell’s entire reasoning. Therefore, I believe that his claim that methodological naturalism is agnostic (implied objective) is completely wrong, because naturalism is also a belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make it clear that methodological naturalism is based on a belief assumption, we can summarize this scientific method in the context of the hypothetico-deductive method. We then get the following three steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Propose a falsifiable hypothesis that contains only natural explanations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evaluate and see if the hypothesis in (1) is consistent with the data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the agreement in (2) is not good, go back to (1) and propose a better hypothesis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, therefore, in step (1) one starts from the premise that only natural explanations are allowed, it is obvious that science will only deliver such explanations. As you shout in the forest, your answer will be. I therefore believe that methodological naturalism constitutes a completely unnecessary limitation of science, since it does not allow a number of falsifiable hypotheses (which are chosen based on criteria such as simplicity, ability to explain, relevance, etc.) with different philosophical starting points to be allowed to be tested and compete on equal terms, so that the best possible model can be selected. Since science is all about searching for the truth, this is a very serious limitation of methodological naturalism. I treat this topic more extensively in two articles on secular science in the Scandinavian apologetics journal Theofilos.&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt; Furthermore, in parts 2 and 3 of this article series, I have shown that it is perfectly possible to combine the hypothetico-deductive method with a design perspective or a creationist perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After his initial discussion on methodological and philosophical naturalism, Erkell goes on to criticize creationists and ID proponents for not making this distinction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This distinction is rarely made among creationists and ID advocates, even though it should be obvious. Scientists are accused again and again of being “materialists” or “naturalists”, by which is meant philosophical naturalists, i.e., atheists. But this is not true; science is, aagain, agnostic and not atheistic. There are believing scientists and there are atheistic scientists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is another completely false claim, which makes me wonder how much ID and creationist literature Erkell actually read. Philip Johnson’s book “Darwin on Trial” formed an important part of the birth of the ID movement in the late 1980s. In this book, Johnson devotes an entire chapter to discussing the philosophical underpinnings of Darwinism. He then makes a distinction between naturalism and scientific naturalism, where the latter concept corresponds to methodological naturalism.&lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt; Stephen Meyer and other well-known ID advocates regularly touch upon the philosophical starting points of the theory of evolution in their books and lectures, without claiming that evolutionary biologists must be atheists. More recently, the ID-inspired anthology “Theistic Evolution, A Scientific, Philosophical, and Theological Critique” was published, where I contributed with two articles myself. As many as nine of its 31 chapters deal with the philosophical starting points of the theory of evolution, with methodological naturalism as a central concept. Since the book is primarily written as a polemic against, and addressed to, Christians who have chosen to embrace both the theory of evolution and methodological naturalism, it is clear that the authors make a distinction between methodological and philosophical naturalism.&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt; In Sweden, almost every issue of the creationist magazine Genesis deals with the secular starting points of the theory of evolution, without assuming that all of those that hold on to this theory are naturalists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erkell concludes Part 5 of his article series by commenting on why Intelligent Design is not science:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Intelligent Design, however, says nothing about reality. Since we know nothing about the designer, anything is possible and nothing is off limits. There is no design theory or design model that says anything concrete about the world, so there is nothing to compare with reality. It cannot do that because such a model must be based on knowledge about the designer. And we don’t have that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have already argued in Parts 2 and 3 that this reasoning is incorrect, because I believe that it is perfectly possible to formulate falsifiable hypotheses that are inspired by the Bible or by a design perspective. But interestingly enough, evolutionary theory itself faces the risk of getting into the trap that everything is conceivable and nothing is forbidden (except that one must not violate the principle of methodological naturalism). For example, it is well known that the Darwinian explanation of genetic similarities between the organs of two species looks different depending on how closely related the species are assumed to be in the postulated tree of life. If the species are assumed to be closely related, the organ is believed to have originated in a common ancestor, which was then passed it on to both species, so-called homologous or orthologous organs. If, on the other hand, the species are not assumed to be closely related, the organs are believed to have evolved independently of each other through convergent evolution, so-called analogous organs. In other words, the theory of evolution always has an explanation for observed similarity, which makes it difficult for it to fulfill one of the basic requirements of empirical science â€“ falsifiability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See chapters 2 and 11 in Hössjer, O. (2018).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hössjer, O. (2014). Is secular science unconditional? Theophilos 6(3), 489-496. Hössjer, O. (2016). Review of the secular science. Theofilos 8(2), 256-&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Johnson, P. (1991). Darwin on Trial. InterVarsity Press, Downers Grove, Illinois.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Moreland, J.P., Meyer, S., Shaw, C., Gauger, A. and Grudem. W. (eds.) (2017). Theistic Evolution. A Scientific, Philosophical, and Theological Critique. Crossway, Wheaton, Illinois.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reply by Lars Johan Erkell&lt;/strong&gt;
September 8, 2021 6:28 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We fully agree on the distinction between methodological naturalism and philosophical naturalism, and that is excellent. But then you write:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But then Erkell claims that natural explanations are the only explanations that are practically possible. How did he arrive at that? It is simply a secular belief that underlies Erkell’s entire reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, how have I come to the conclusion that the so-called natural explanations are the only ones that are practically possible to work with? For two reasons: the first is that natural science can only work with factors that can be clearly observed and that can be measured. It excludes supernatural powers that are not visible or measurable. The second reason is that, to my knowledge, no successful research program based on supernatural powers exists (correct me if I’m wrong - it would be interesting to be wrong on this point). So it is not some “secular assumption of faith” that is the basis of my reasoning. That is the reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also write&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Therefore, I believe that his claim that methodological naturalism is agnostic (implied objective) is completely wrong, because naturalism is also a belief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two comments: to claim that agnostic naturalism would implicitly see itself as objective is completely backwards. Agnosticism is a position which means that one does not think one can make objectively correct judgments in matters of faith, and therefore abstains. Then I want to point out that (methodological) naturalism is not a belief, it is an epistemic position that does not exclude non-material explanations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you’re wondering how much ID and creationist literature I’ve actually read. Far too much, is the answer. As for Phillip Johnson, I have published two posts about his book “Darwin on Trial” here on Biologg (https://biologg.wordpress.com/2011/12/08/fallet-darwin/ and https://biologg.wordpress. com/2011/12/14/creationism-and-naturalism/). However, he has a more detailed discussion of naturalism in the book “Reason in the Balance” from 1995. Here he derails already on the first page of the introduction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In our greatest universities, naturalism - the doctrine that nature is “all there is” - is the virtually unquestioned assumption that underlies not only natural science but intellectual work of all kinds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next page reads:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For professional purposes, atheistic and theistic biologists alike must assume that nature is all that is. Natural science is therefore based on naturalism. What a science based on naturalism tells us, not surprisingly, is that naturalism is true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not true. As I said, natural science is based on methodological naturalism, not on the philosophical naturalism Johnson writes about (“nature is all that is”). It is not assumed that nature is the only thing that exists, but that it is only practically possible to work with matter in its various forms. Of course, Johnson knows the difference, but in book after book he pushes the line that scientists make no difference between the two concepts, so really it’s the same thing. Natural science would thus be governed by an atheistic ideology, which would exclude ID explanations in advance. This delusion is a fundamental element of the ID movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have some difficulty understanding why intelligent and well-educated ID advocates constantly confuse methodological naturalism with philosophical naturalism, but I can think of two reasons. The first would be rooted in the fact that in practical research work it does not matter whether one is a methodological or a philosophical naturalist. Since there are no methods to study supernatural phenomena, those kinds of explanations are disregarded. A person of faith can then get the false impression supernatural forces are completely denied, and that the two positions are actually the same - one would just use different pretexts to deny the reality of God. The second reason could be tactics in the debate around ID. By calling both positions “naturalism”, even methodological naturalists can be made to appear as atheists who refuse to accept any form of supernatural forces and thus rule out ID from the start. This makes them appear rigid and intolerant, which is a rhetorical gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you write that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;it is perfectly possible to formulate falsifiable hypotheses that are inspired by the Bible or by a design perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course it is possible, but what can you test with your hypotheses? I address that in the post &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell8.html&quot;&gt;“Science, hypotheses and Intelligent Design”&lt;/a&gt;
Finally, you bring up the idea that the theory of evolution would not be falsifiable, since it contains two different mechanisms that can lead to life forms being similar. They may either be closely related to each other or they may have lived under similar selection pressures, which may cause them to evolve into similar forms. This was a problem for systematics for a long time. Today, however, it is possible to establish kinship with genetic methods, which means that the mechanisms can be separated. If you now want to claim that a certain mechanism is the explanation for observed similarities, you have to provide convincing evidence that it is the correct one. And that reasoning must be falsifiable. You can’t just go with one or the other, as you seem to think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lars Johan Erkell (with comment by Ola Hössjer)</name></author><summary type="html">The text is a pun in Swedish: &quot;Logg&quot; means something like a ship´s log or a logbook. A blog is &quot;blogg&quot;. So &quot;Biolog(g)&quot; is a biologist´s log or blog. &amp;nbsp; This is part 5 of a series of 7 posts by Lars Johan Erkell, with comments on each by Ola Hössjer and a reply by Erkell. Part 1 will be found here. They are translations of 2020 posts in Swedish from the Biolog(g) blog of the Department of Biology of Gothenburg University. &amp;nbsp; Breakthrough for Intelligent design? (part 5) November 13, 2020 by Lars Johan Erkell Why is ID not seen as science? In this series of blog posts, I have repeatedly criticized Thorvaldsen and Hössjer for not working scientifically, and I have said that ID does not meet the requirements of science. ID proponents, by contrast, often and readily claim that they are victims of a rigid atheistic scientific (Darwinian) orthodoxy that refuses to recognize intelligent Design as legitimate science. There may therefore be reason to very briefly review what actually characterizes established science.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AIG to hand out counterfeit money during Coronation</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/aig-counterfeit-money.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AIG to hand out counterfeit money during Coronation" /><published>2022-12-06T17:05:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-06T17:05:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/aig-counterfeit-money</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/aig-counterfeit-money.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Phelps_Funny_Money_900.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Counterfeit notes&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The obverse side of some million-pound notes that AIG plans to hand out at the Coronation. The reverse side will display religious tracts.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ken Ham and his fellow creationist grifters plan to disrupt King Charles’s Coronation by handing out &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/eIUY2oi20Fc&quot;&gt;religious tracts disguised as money&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is hilarious. They are raising money to print and distribute 3 million counterfeit “1 Million Pound” notes that will display fundamentalist/creationist tracts on the reverse side. They are shamelessly raising money to do this. I wonder if the British Secret Service will also be amused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To see this post together with comments on it, click on the title of the post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">The obverse side of some million-pound notes that AIG plans to hand out at the Coronation. The reverse side will display religious tracts. Ken Ham and his fellow creationist grifters plan to disrupt King Charles’s Coronation by handing out religious tracts disguised as money. This is hilarious. They are raising money to print and distribute 3 million counterfeit “1 Million Pound” notes that will display fundamentalist/creationist tracts on the reverse side. They are shamelessly raising money to do this. I wonder if the British Secret Service will also be amused. To see this post together with comments on it, click on the title of the post.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Panthera leo</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/panthera-leo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Panthera leo" /><published>2022-12-05T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-05T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/panthera-leo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/panthera-leo.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Marilyn Susek&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Susek.Lions.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lions&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lion&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Panthera leo&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; African lion, Yorkshire Wildlife Park, 16 July 2017. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Marilyn Susek. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Panthera leo &amp;ndash; African lion, Yorkshire Wildlife Park, 16 July 2017.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A tale of two papers</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/a-tale-of-two-papers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A tale of two papers" /><published>2022-12-02T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-02T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/a-tale-of-two-papers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/a-tale-of-two-papers.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gerdien de Jong was until her retirement Associate Professor in the Department of Biology at Utrecht University&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Red_Panda_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Puzzled Red Panda&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Red Panda, &lt;em&gt;Ailurus fulgens&lt;/em&gt;, wondering what part of the tree it's on.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-tale-of-two-papers&quot;&gt;A tale of two papers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2021, dr Matthew / Matyas Cserhati published two parallel articles on the affinities of the red panda &lt;em&gt;Ailurus fulgens&lt;/em&gt;, one in BMC Genomics and one in Creation Research Society Quarterly. The two articles are mostly based on the same data and have similar and sometimes identical content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bmcgenomics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12864-021-07531-3&quot;&gt;The BMC Genomics article&lt;/a&gt; has the title: “A tail of two pandas – whole genome k-mer signature analysis of the red panda (&lt;em&gt;Ailurus fulgens&lt;/em&gt;) and the Giant panda (&lt;em&gt;Ailuropoda melanoleuca&lt;/em&gt;)”. This paper concludes that on a whole genome level the red panda possibly belongs to the mustelid (marten) clade. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.creationresearch.org/classification-of-the-enigmatic-red-panda-ailurus-fulgens-based-on-molecular-baraminology-based-analysis&quot;&gt;The CRSQ article&lt;/a&gt; has the title: “Classification of the enigmatic red panda (&lt;em&gt;Ailurus fulgens&lt;/em&gt;) based on molecular baraminology-based analysis”. This paper deems it likely that the red panda belongs to the mustelid holobaramin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-bmc-genomics-paper&quot;&gt;The BMC Genomics paper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cserhati uses two types of data for the phylogenetic placement of the red panda: Whole Genome K-mer Signature (WGKS) and sequence analysis on mtDNA.  Cserhati establishes the frequency spectrum of all possible 8-mer base sequences over the whole genome of a species for 28 species. For each species pair a correlation coefficient over 8-mer frequencies can be computed, leading to a correlation matrix of genomic patterning over the species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cserhati uses the correlation matrix to find 4 clusters: the eleven cats, the five bears, the skunk, and a cluster containing the martens and the red panda. But then Cserhati writes: “Based on this evidence, (the red panda) would belong to (the marten family) as a monophyletic group.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the article derails. &lt;!--more--&gt; The clustering can be regarded as evidence that the red panda and the marten family are monophyletic sister groups, but not that the red panda belongs to the marten family. The red panda has a lower mean correlation with the marten species than the mean correlation of the marten species amongst each other, showing a clear distance between panda and martens. This difference is significant (P &amp;lt; 1.4 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-6&lt;/sup&gt;) but Cserhati writes “This difference is not too significant”, and he decides to ignore it. In his heat map of the correlation matrix the difference between red panda and marten species is clearly visible: left figure on top, lighter is higher correlation, and the red panda gives the top right ‘Finnish flag’ pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mtDNA sequences of 52 species/subspecies of bears, skunks, raccoons, martens, and both subspecies of the red panda are aligned and clustered. Cserhati finds 5 clusters: the 15 bears, the 30 martens, the two panda sequences, the two skunks and the 3 raccoons, clearly finding the traditional families. The mtDNA sequences are subjected to phylogenetic analysis by UPGMA, Maximum Likelihood and Neighbour Joining. No outgroup is mentioned, and no outgroup seems to have been specified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three phylogenetic trees on mtDNA differ in the placement of the families. The mess seems the result of the lack of outgroup. When plotting an unrooted tree in a square format, the program picks the plot. The pandas do not appear within the marten family in any of the three phylogenetic trees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cserhati gives his preferred conclusion: “The main conclusion … is that on a whole genome level (the red panda) possibly belongs to the (marten) clade”. Nowhere in his analyses does the red panda appear within the marten group. At most we see a monophyletic group of the marten and panda families. Cserhati conflates monophyly and belonging to the same family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One problem: how did a paper as bad as this ever get through review and published?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/wgks_heat_maps_4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;wgks heat map graphic&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The whole genome k-mers signature heat map used in the two papers.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;creation-research-society-quarterly-paper&quot;&gt;Creation Research Society Quarterly paper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cserhati bases the search for the baraminological placement of the red panda on three types of data: Whole Genome K-mer Signature (WGKS), sequence analysis on mtDNA and sequence analysis on cytochrome-b.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WGKS part is the article is almost identical to the WGKS paragraph in the BMC Genomics paper. The same heat map of the WGKS correlation matrix is presented, but the coloring is reversed: right top figure, darker is higher correlation, and the red panda gives the top right ‘Danish flag’ pattern. Again it is visible that the correlation between red panda and martens is lower than the correlations amongst the martens, and again the significant difference is dismissed. The red panda is held to belong to the marten holobaramin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mtDNA sequences of the same 52 species as in the BMC genomics paper were aligned and the resulting identity matrix showing global sequence similarity was visualized in a heat map. This heat map clearly shows five main groups representing the traditional families: two red panda subspecies, bears, marten family, the three skunks and the two raccoons. The two red panda subspecies form an independent cluster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cytochrome-b sequences of a total of 51 cat, bear, marten, raccoon and skunk species were aligned. The heat map of the similarity matrix shows a clear split between the cat species and all other species, in line with classical systematics. The red panda does not cluster with the marten family according to the heat map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again the data do not support including the red panda in the marten family. Yet, Cserhati judges that the panda belongs to the marten holobaramin. Of course, Cserhati might define a holobaramin containing two families, the marten family and the red panda family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As in all baraminological literature, statistical clustering to different clusters is assumed to indicate unbridgeable biological discontinuity. The reasoning obscures the discontinuity between biology and statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;strategy&quot;&gt;Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://oorsprong.info/wetenschapper-lost-creationistisch-biosystematisch-raadsel-van-de-rode-panda-ailurus-fulgens-op/&quot;&gt;A Dutch creationist website&lt;/a&gt; that recommends Cserhati’s work on the red panda wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cserhati’s work can stand as a model for how to do creation research. First, find funding for a detailed study within the creation paradigm (here, Creation Research Society Grant #62). Second, publish the results in a standard naturalistic science journal. Then, provide a more detailed study in a creation science journal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, play the system, aiming for respectability for creationist writing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gerdien de Jong</name></author><summary type="html">Gerdien de Jong was until her retirement Associate Professor in the Department of Biology at Utrecht University A Red Panda, Ailurus fulgens, wondering what part of the tree it's on. A tale of two papers In 2021, dr Matthew / Matyas Cserhati published two parallel articles on the affinities of the red panda Ailurus fulgens, one in BMC Genomics and one in Creation Research Society Quarterly. The two articles are mostly based on the same data and have similar and sometimes identical content. The BMC Genomics article has the title: “A tail of two pandas – whole genome k-mer signature analysis of the red panda (Ailurus fulgens) and the Giant panda (Ailuropoda melanoleuca)”. This paper concludes that on a whole genome level the red panda possibly belongs to the mustelid (marten) clade. The CRSQ article has the title: “Classification of the enigmatic red panda (Ailurus fulgens) based on molecular baraminology-based analysis”. This paper deems it likely that the red panda belongs to the mustelid holobaramin. The BMC Genomics paper Cserhati uses two types of data for the phylogenetic placement of the red panda: Whole Genome K-mer Signature (WGKS) and sequence analysis on mtDNA. Cserhati establishes the frequency spectrum of all possible 8-mer base sequences over the whole genome of a species for 28 species. For each species pair a correlation coefficient over 8-mer frequencies can be computed, leading to a correlation matrix of genomic patterning over the species. Cserhati uses the correlation matrix to find 4 clusters: the eleven cats, the five bears, the skunk, and a cluster containing the martens and the red panda. But then Cserhati writes: “Based on this evidence, (the red panda) would belong to (the marten family) as a monophyletic group.” Here the article derails.</summary></entry></feed>