<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-07-09T09:58:30-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Anhinga melanogaster</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/anhinga-melanogaster.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Anhinga melanogaster" /><published>2025-07-07T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-07T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/anhinga-melanogaster</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/anhinga-melanogaster.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;John Harshman&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Winner&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Harshman_Anhinga.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Anhinga (bird)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oriental_darter&quot;&gt;Anhinga melanogaster&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; oriental darter, Keoladeo National Park, Rajasthan, India. Mr. Harshman writes, &quot;Immature bird sunning and preening with a background of duckweed. There are four species in the family Anhingidae, and they are all nearly identical. I particularly like the way the curved neck shows the cervical vertebrae so clearly.&quot; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by John Harshman. Photography Contest, Winner. Anhinga melanogaster &amp;ndash; oriental darter, Keoladeo National Park, Rajasthan, India. Mr. Harshman writes, &quot;Immature bird sunning and preening with a background of duckweed. There are four species in the family Anhingidae, and they are all nearly identical. I particularly like the way the curved neck shows the cervical vertebrae so clearly.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Polyxenida sp.</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/polyxenida.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Polyxenida sp." /><published>2025-07-06T10:45:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-06T10:45:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/polyxenida</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/polyxenida.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/DSC06036_Millipede_Polyxenida_Crop.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bristly millipede.&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyxenida&quot;&gt;Polyxenida&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; sp. – bristly millipede, Boulder, Colorado, July, 2025. This fearsome creature is about 3&amp;nbsp;mm long. I managed to get one lucky shot and then could not find it again.&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;header&gt;&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/Photography-Contest-XVI-Finalists.html&quot;&gt;Photography Contest XVI: Finalists&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/header&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voting ends in 15 min, at noon, MDT (UTC - 6).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Polyxenida sp. – bristly millipede, Boulder, Colorado, July, 2025. This fearsome creature is about 3&amp;nbsp;mm long. I managed to get one lucky shot and then could not find it again. Photography Contest XVI: Finalists Voting ends in 15 min, at noon, MDT (UTC - 6).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nature SelectingA children's book explaining evolution</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/nature-selecting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nature SelectingA children's book explaining evolution" /><published>2025-07-05T12:29:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-05T12:29:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/nature-selecting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/nature-selecting.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Nature_Selecting_Cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book Cover&quot; /&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is an unashamed plug for the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lsu.edu/mns/news-and-publications/chakrabarty_evolution.pdf&quot;&gt;Nature Selecting&lt;/a&gt;, subtitled “A children’s book explaining evolution,” by Prosanta Chakrabarty, professor of biology and curator of fish at Louisiana State University, and illustrated by Anjai Noël, who just graduated from Sherwood Middle School in Baton Rouge, Louisiana, and is Prof. Chakrabarty’s 14-year-old daughter. The book cover, left, shows one of Ms. Noël’s delightful illustrations. Prof. Chakrabarty is also the author of the 2023 book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Explaining-through-Evolution-Prosanta-Chakrabarty/dp/0262546256/&quot;&gt;Explaining Life through Evolution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, the present work, Nature Selecting, is available only as a PDF and at no cost. It is worth much more than that, and I hope they will eventually print it on paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Michael Zimmerman and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theclergyletterproject.org/&quot;&gt;Clergy Letter Project&lt;/a&gt; for alerting us to this publication.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">This post is an unashamed plug for the book Nature Selecting, subtitled “A children’s book explaining evolution,” by Prosanta Chakrabarty, professor of biology and curator of fish at Louisiana State University, and illustrated by Anjai Noël, who just graduated from Sherwood Middle School in Baton Rouge, Louisiana, and is Prof. Chakrabarty’s 14-year-old daughter. The book cover, left, shows one of Ms. Noël’s delightful illustrations. Prof. Chakrabarty is also the author of the 2023 book Explaining Life through Evolution. As far as I can tell, the present work, Nature Selecting, is available only as a PDF and at no cost. It is worth much more than that, and I hope they will eventually print it on paper. Thanks to Michael Zimmerman and the Clergy Letter Project for alerting us to this publication.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">1 in 4 Americans Reject Evolution</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/1-in-4-americans-reject.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="1 in 4 Americans Reject Evolution" /><published>2025-07-03T14:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-03T14:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/1-in-4-americans-reject</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/1-in-4-americans-reject.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Scopes_Trial_Darrow_Bryan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Darrow and Brian at the trial&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Clarence Darrow (left) and William Jennings Bryan (right) during the Scopes trial in 1925. &lt;small&gt;Public domain. Brown Brothers, via &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Scopes_trial.jpg&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;. Photographer unknown.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full title of this article by William Trollinger and Susan Trollinger is &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/1-in-4-americans-reject-evolution-a-century-after-the-scopes-monkey-trial-spotlighted-the-clash-between-science-and-religion/&quot;&gt;1 in 4 Americans Reject Evolution, A Century after the Scopes Monkey Trial Spotlighted the Clash between Science and Religion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trollinger and Trollinger give a brief outline of the trial and some of its antecedents; what happened at the trial is comparatively well known, and you can read it for yourself. They point out, in particular, that Clarence Darrow’s famed (or perhaps notorious) “interrogation” of William Jennings Bryan made it obvious that a literal reading of the six-day creation myth in Genesis 1-2 was incompatible with modern science. Additionally, news stories, particularly by H.L. Mencken, portrayed religious fundamentalists as ignorant fools and led many to believe that such biblical literalism would soon disappear. It did not, though I think you could say it went underground for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fundamentalists, note Trollinger and Trollinger, needed scientific evidence to support their belief in a young earth. In 1961, they found it in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.prpbooks.com/book/genesis-flood-the&quot;&gt;The Genesis Flood: The Biblical Record and its Scientific Implications&lt;/a&gt; (the link is to a 50th anniversary edition published by P&amp;amp;R [Presbyterian and Reformed] Publishing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trollinger and Trollinger note that today approximately one-quarter of all Americans are young-earth creationists and reject much of modern biology and modern geology, not to mention modern cosmology. Answers in Genesis, which is strictly YEC, is now the world’s largest creationist organization. We report occasionally on AIG’s Ark Park, most recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/state-police-proselytized.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, so I will not dwell on it. Trollinger and Trollinger note that the Ark Park and other museums such as the Creation Museum attract millions of visitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse, though, they point to “an ever-expanding network of fundamentalist schools and homeschools that present young Earth creationism as true science.” Yet more worse, they say that at least 15 states have school choice programs which use tax money to pay for private and home schools. I would add only that these private schools take scarce funds from public schools that need them badly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young-earth creationism is not dead; it is not even sick (OK, it &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; sick, but it is not at death’s door). With a little help from old-earth creationisms, not least intelligent-design creationism, creationism writ large may be &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/01/is-intelligent-design.html&quot;&gt;making a comeback&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Clarence Darrow (left) and William Jennings Bryan (right) during the Scopes trial in 1925. Public domain. Brown Brothers, via Wikimedia Commons. Photographer unknown. The full title of this article by William Trollinger and Susan Trollinger is 1 in 4 Americans Reject Evolution, A Century after the Scopes Monkey Trial Spotlighted the Clash between Science and Religion. Trollinger and Trollinger give a brief outline of the trial and some of its antecedents; what happened at the trial is comparatively well known, and you can read it for yourself. They point out, in particular, that Clarence Darrow’s famed (or perhaps notorious) “interrogation” of William Jennings Bryan made it obvious that a literal reading of the six-day creation myth in Genesis 1-2 was incompatible with modern science. Additionally, news stories, particularly by H.L. Mencken, portrayed religious fundamentalists as ignorant fools and led many to believe that such biblical literalism would soon disappear. It did not, though I think you could say it went underground for some time. The fundamentalists, note Trollinger and Trollinger, needed scientific evidence to support their belief in a young earth. In 1961, they found it in The Genesis Flood: The Biblical Record and its Scientific Implications (the link is to a 50th anniversary edition published by P&amp;amp;R [Presbyterian and Reformed] Publishing). Trollinger and Trollinger note that today approximately one-quarter of all Americans are young-earth creationists and reject much of modern biology and modern geology, not to mention modern cosmology. Answers in Genesis, which is strictly YEC, is now the world’s largest creationist organization. We report occasionally on AIG’s Ark Park, most recently here, so I will not dwell on it. Trollinger and Trollinger note that the Ark Park and other museums such as the Creation Museum attract millions of visitors. Worse, though, they point to “an ever-expanding network of fundamentalist schools and homeschools that present young Earth creationism as true science.” Yet more worse, they say that at least 15 states have school choice programs which use tax money to pay for private and home schools. I would add only that these private schools take scarce funds from public schools that need them badly. Young-earth creationism is not dead; it is not even sick (OK, it is sick, but it is not at death’s door). With a little help from old-earth creationisms, not least intelligent-design creationism, creationism writ large may be making a comeback.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How the Scopes Trial Was Almost Scooped</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/scopes-trial-almost-scooped.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How the Scopes Trial Was Almost Scooped" /><published>2025-07-01T11:55:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-01T11:55:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/scopes-trial-almost-scooped</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/scopes-trial-almost-scooped.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Billy_The_Kid_Museum.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Billy the Kid Museum&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Billy the Kid Museum in Fort Sumner, New Mexico, where a &quot;monkey trial&quot; could have taken place in 1922. &lt;small&gt;Photograph by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/8638651@N07/&quot;&gt;Kevin Standlee&lt;/a&gt;. CC BY-NC-SA 2.0.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt; Glenn Branch is deputy director of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/&quot;&gt;National Center for Science Education&lt;/a&gt;, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as &lt;/i&gt;Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher, &lt;i&gt;and the &lt;/i&gt;Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics; &lt;i&gt;and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of &lt;/i&gt;Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools (2006). &lt;i&gt;He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1925, a young teacher in Dayton, Tennessee, was convicted of violating a state law that forbade the state’s educators “to teach any theory that denies the story of the Divine Creation of man as taught in the Bible, and to teach instead that man has descended from a lower order of animals.” Especially now, as its centennial year is being commemorated in various ways across the nation, the Scopes “monkey” trial is widely known. But the details of a similar controversy in New Mexico three years earlier deserve to be remembered as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Famously, the antievolution crusade of the 1920s was launched by William Jennings Bryan, a politician of national stature, who began to encourage the passage of bans on the teaching of evolution at both the state and the local level early in the decade. Probably as a result, in the summer of 1922, the school board in Fort Sumner, New Mexico — perhaps most famous as the site where the outlaw &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Billy_the_Kid&quot;&gt;Billy the Kid&lt;/a&gt; was shot and killed — adopted a resolution forbidding the teaching of evolution in the town’s schools, and calling for the resignation of any offending teacher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fort Sumner’s superintendent of schools, F. E. (for Finis Ewing: he was evidently named after the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finis_Ewing&quot;&gt;founder&lt;/a&gt; of the Cumberland Presbyterian Church) Dean, was summering in his home state of Missouri when he received a copy of the resolution. He decided that it would not be useful to argue about the resolution at a distance, planning instead on his return to Fort Sumner to argue in person to the board that “I had not been teaching the…doctrine of evolution in the form attributed to me” and moreover to explain that the antievolution resolution was unworkable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A good many of the texts used in every high school teach evolution,” Dean later explained in the local newspaper, the &lt;i&gt;Fort Sumner Leader&lt;/i&gt;. “In fact, all modern science, even in elementary texts …, is written from the evolutionary point of view. It is even true[,] as LeConte says, that evolution is more than half of modern thought.” (Not quite: in his &lt;a href=&quot;https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044106203474&amp;amp;seq=7&quot;&gt;Evolution and its Relation to Religious Thought&lt;/a&gt; (1889), Joseph LeConte wrote that evolution “is literally one half of all science.”) Dean added, “[T]here is no entering even the vestibule of modern thought except thru [sic] a knowledge of evolution.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While still in Missouri, Dean wrote to the New Mexico superintendent of schools to ask whether the board could legally insist on the resignation of any teacher who taught evolution. The superintendent referred the question to the state attorney general’s office, which answered that it could not. But the board got wind of Dean’s inquiry, and demanded his immediate resignation “on the ground of my manifest insincerity in agreeing to the resolution and then going over their heads to the Attorney General,” as Dean later explained in the &lt;i&gt;Fort Sumner Leader&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Dean, certain members of the board sent him letters “assuring me of the friendly feeling of the Board for me” and blaming the resolution on “public sentiment.” Yet, he was told, “my usefulness was at an end in Fort Sumner and that if I insisted on holding to my contract and returning the school would be torn to pieces.” Unable to return immediately to defend himself, Dean decided to acquiesce, explaining, “I have pioneered long enough. … If the community wants this sort of injustice done to itself, or will even stand for it, it is none of my affairs.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The front page of the next issue of the &lt;i&gt;Fort Sumner Leader&lt;/i&gt;, published August 18, 1922, was almost entirely consumed with reactions to Dean’s resignation. The Alumni Association of the Fort Sumner High School expressed its “love and appreciation” for Dean, and reassured him, and the public, that “we HAVE NOT learned from your teachings that the ‘Mottled ape is our grand-father.’ [Emphasis in original. I don’t recognize the allusion seemingly indicated by the quotation marks.] Neither has it shattered our faith in the bible and made infidels of us.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not everybody was supportive. Someone, possibly a minister, with the surname of Smith — the initials are unclear: possibly P. L. S. — wrote in opposition to evolution, invoking various authorities, including “Dr. [Robert] Etheridge, Fossiologist [a word sadly no longer in vogue!] of the British Museum,” “Prof. [Lionel Smith] Beale, of King’s College, London,” and the British biologist William Bateson, who supposedly rejected evolution. Smith added, “Woodrow Wilson does not believe that man came from the beast. So I suppose he is a back number [i.e, out of date].”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Smith’s contribution, a vestige of the Fort Sumner controversy would later appear in the Scopes trial. Dean apparently asked his former teacher Winterton C. Curtis, a professor of zoology at the University of Missouri, to investigate Smith’s authorities. Etheridge and Beale were both dead, but Curtis duly wrote not only to his fellow scientist Bateson but also to the former president Wilson, who replied, “Of course, like every other man of intelligence and education, I do believe in organic evolution. It surprises me that at this late date such questions should be raised.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three years later, when Curtis was among the expert witnesses for the defense in the Scopes trial, he included the reply from Wilson (who died in 1924) in his affidavit, prefaced by the explanation “Evolution has been generally accepted by the intellectually competent who have taken the trouble to inform themselves with an open mind. The following letter was written in response to a request to state his position, it having been alleged that he was not a believer in organic evolution.” But because the judge decided to exclude expert witness testimony, Wilson’s reply played no role in the Scopes trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only scholar to have taken note of Dean, A. G. Cock (in his “&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/jhered/article-abstract/80/2/96/902887?redirectedFrom=PDF&quot;&gt;Bateson’s Two Toronto Addresses, 1921: 2. Evolutionary Faith&lt;/a&gt;,” published in the &lt;i&gt;Journal of Heredity&lt;/i&gt; in 1989), suggests, “Dean deserves to be remembered, along with John T. Scopes, as an early hero of the continuing fight for the right to teach evolution in U.S. schools.” But Cock wasn’t able to follow Dean’s career further: after Curtis told Bateson in November 1922 that Dean hadn’t secured a new position yet, “at least as far as the sources available to me disclose, he disappears from the record.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was luckier, having found Dean’s obituary in the &lt;i&gt;Arizona Independent Republic&lt;/i&gt; for April 11, 1941. Apparently Dean moved to Arizona in late 1922 or 1923, where he taught in St. David for two years, served as a principal in Benson for seven years, and served as a superintendent of schools in Williams for seven years. After he was discharged from the latter position, he left the education field, engaging in the real estate business and operating a bookstore. He died on April 9, 1941, at the age of 64, owing to complications after a fall in which he broke a left thigh bone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It isn’t clear why Dean decided to resign from his position in Fort Sumner. He thought that the majority of townsfolk were on his side, and he seems to have been right: the local parent-teacher association adopted resolutions protesting his treatment and urging the board to revoke its resolution and refuse his resignation. His health may have played a role: although he was only 47, he complained that he was “worn out” by the controversy. But if he had fought the board, the resulting trial might have scooped the Scopes trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, it is perfectly reasonable to imagine that in 2022 we might have devoted great attention to the centenary of the Dean “monkey” trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Reposted from “&lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/how-the-scopes-trial-was-almost-scooped/&quot;&gt;How the Scopes Trial Was Almost Scooped&lt;/a&gt;,” by Glenn Branch, with permission of the author and of William Trollinger of the Righting America blog.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Glenn Branch</name></author><summary type="html">The Billy the Kid Museum in Fort Sumner, New Mexico, where a &quot;monkey trial&quot; could have taken place in 1922. Photograph by Kevin Standlee. CC BY-NC-SA 2.0. Glenn Branch is deputy director of the National Center for Science Education, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher, and the Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics; and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools (2006). He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers. In 1925, a young teacher in Dayton, Tennessee, was convicted of violating a state law that forbade the state’s educators “to teach any theory that denies the story of the Divine Creation of man as taught in the Bible, and to teach instead that man has descended from a lower order of animals.” Especially now, as its centennial year is being commemorated in various ways across the nation, the Scopes “monkey” trial is widely known. But the details of a similar controversy in New Mexico three years earlier deserve to be remembered as well. Famously, the antievolution crusade of the 1920s was launched by William Jennings Bryan, a politician of national stature, who began to encourage the passage of bans on the teaching of evolution at both the state and the local level early in the decade. Probably as a result, in the summer of 1922, the school board in Fort Sumner, New Mexico — perhaps most famous as the site where the outlaw Billy the Kid was shot and killed — adopted a resolution forbidding the teaching of evolution in the town’s schools, and calling for the resignation of any offending teacher. Fort Sumner’s superintendent of schools, F. E. (for Finis Ewing: he was evidently named after the founder of the Cumberland Presbyterian Church) Dean, was summering in his home state of Missouri when he received a copy of the resolution. He decided that it would not be useful to argue about the resolution at a distance, planning instead on his return to Fort Sumner to argue in person to the board that “I had not been teaching the…doctrine of evolution in the form attributed to me” and moreover to explain that the antievolution resolution was unworkable.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ichneumonid sp.</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/ichneumonid-sp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ichneumonid sp." /><published>2025-06-30T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-30T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/ichneumonid-sp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/ichneumonid-sp.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/DSC06009_Ichneumonid_Wasp_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ichneumonid wasp&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ichneumonidae&quot;&gt;Ichneumonidae&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; ichneumon wasp, fairly frisky, wandering around the house, Boulder, Colorado, June, 2025.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Please do not forget to vote:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;header&gt;&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/Photography-Contest-XVI-Finalists.html&quot;&gt;Photography Contest XVI: Finalists&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/header&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voting continues through Sunday, July 6, at noon, MDT (UTC - 7).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Ichneumonidae &amp;ndash; ichneumon wasp, fairly frisky, wandering around the house, Boulder, Colorado, June, 2025. Please do not forget to vote: Photography Contest XVI: Finalists Voting continues through Sunday, July 6, at noon, MDT (UTC - 7).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest XVI: Finalists</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/Photography-Contest-XVI-Finalists.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest XVI: Finalists" /><published>2025-06-23T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-23T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/Photography%20Contest-XVI-Finalists</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/Photography-Contest-XVI-Finalists.html">&lt;p&gt;Here are the finalists of the 2025 photography contest. It was nice to see some old friends, though new names would have been welcome. With assistance from Our Wife and Harshest Critic, we chose 7, which we display below the Figurative Fold. We chose the photographs more on the basis of their pictorial quality than on their scientific interest. Any text submitted by the photographers has been omitted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The finalists are presented in alphabetical order of last name. Please look through their photographs before voting for your favorite. Polling will close Sunday, July 6 (the 4th being a holiday in the US), at approximately noon MDT, and we will display the winner at noon Monday, July 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please remember that this is a photography contest, not a popularity contest, and discourage your friends from enlisting others specifically to vote for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Philip Abrams&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Abrams_Eurasian_Jay_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Eurasian jay&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wildlondon.org.uk/wildlife-explorer/birds/crows-and-shrikes/jay&quot;&gt;Garrulus glandarius&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; Eurasian jay, Chelsea, London, iPhone 15.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Denelsbeck_Ginkgo_biloba.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ginkgo leaf&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ginkgo_biloba&quot;&gt;Ginkgo biloba&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; ginkgo leaf after a heavy rain, Canon 7D.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Joel Eissenberg&lt;/strong&gt;.

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Eissenberg_Archilestes grandis.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Damselfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_spreadwing&quot;&gt;Archilestes grandis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; damselfly spotted at the Denver zoo.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;John Harshman&lt;/strong&gt;.
  
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Harshman_Anhinga.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Anhinga (bird)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oriental_darter&quot;&gt;Anhinga melanogaster&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; Oriental darter, Keoladeo National Park, Rajasthan, India.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;C. Joseph Long&lt;/strong&gt;.

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Long_Antigone_canadensis.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sandhill crane&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandhill_crane&quot;&gt;Antigone (formerly Grus) canadensis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; sandhill crane, Bernardo State Wildlife Refuge, Rio Grande Valley, New Mexico.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Malcolm Schongalla&lt;/strong&gt;.

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Schongalla_Rangifer_tarandus_skull.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Caribou skull&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barren-ground_caribou&quot;&gt;Rangifer tarandus groenlandicus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; barren-ground caribou, Russell Glacier on the West Coast of Greenland, June, 2022.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;John Trawick&lt;/strong&gt;.

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Trawick_Apis_mellifera_Echium_candicans.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;ldquo;Pride of Madeira&amp;rdquo; (flower)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smgrowers.com/products/plants/plantdisplay.asp?plant_id=543&quot;&gt;Echium candicans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; &quot;Pride of Madeira,&quot; with &lt;i&gt;Apis mellifera&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; European honeybee.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLScYL25zz4LVzQz7di3g-UIJI1vtyLfr93nZFXbC36fO59v_HA/viewform?embedded=true&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;650&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot;&gt;Loading…&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Here are the finalists of the 2025 photography contest. It was nice to see some old friends, though new names would have been welcome. With assistance from Our Wife and Harshest Critic, we chose 7, which we display below the Figurative Fold. We chose the photographs more on the basis of their pictorial quality than on their scientific interest. Any text submitted by the photographers has been omitted. The finalists are presented in alphabetical order of last name. Please look through their photographs before voting for your favorite. Polling will close Sunday, July 6 (the 4th being a holiday in the US), at approximately noon MDT, and we will display the winner at noon Monday, July 7. Please remember that this is a photography contest, not a popularity contest, and discourage your friends from enlisting others specifically to vote for you.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pipilo maculatus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/pipilo-maculatus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pipilo maculatus" /><published>2025-06-16T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-16T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/pipilo-maculatus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/pipilo-maculatus.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/P1031649_Towhee_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spotted towhee&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spotted_towhee&quot;&gt;Pipilo maculatus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; spotted towhee, not exactly in his natural environment.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Please do not forget &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;header&gt;&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/photography-contest-xvi.html&quot;&gt;Photography Contest XVI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/header&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contest remains open for entries through &lt;i&gt;this coming Friday&lt;/i&gt;, June 20.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Pipilo maculatus &amp;ndash; spotted towhee, not exactly in his natural environment. Please do not forget Photography Contest XVI The contest remains open for entries through this coming Friday, June 20.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Agave neomexicana</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/agave-neomexicana.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Agave neomexicana" /><published>2025-06-09T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-09T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/agave-neomexicana</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/agave-neomexicana.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/P1031638_Yucca_Agave_neomexicana_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;New Mexico century plant&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agave_americana&quot;&gt;Agave neomexicana&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; New Mexico century plant (also known as &lt;i&gt;Agave parryi&lt;/i&gt; ssp. &lt;i&gt;neomexicana&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; Parry's agave. The &lt;i&gt;H. sapiens&lt;/i&gt; in the picture, Ron Wittmann, tells us that some botanists recognize it as a distinct species, whereas others do not). The plant has not bloomed in at least 25 years. The pointy, gray-green leaves at the bottom of the stalk are the agave leaves.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Please do not forget &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;header&gt;&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/photography-contest-xvi.html&quot;&gt;Photography Contest XVI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/header&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contest remains open for entries through Friday, June 20.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Agave neomexicana &amp;ndash; New Mexico century plant (also known as Agave parryi ssp. neomexicana &amp;ndash; Parry's agave. The H. sapiens in the picture, Ron Wittmann, tells us that some botanists recognize it as a distinct species, whereas others do not). The plant has not bloomed in at least 25 years. The pointy, gray-green leaves at the bottom of the stalk are the agave leaves. Please do not forget Photography Contest XVI The contest remains open for entries through Friday, June 20.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest XVI</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/photography-contest-xvi.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest XVI" /><published>2025-06-02T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-02T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/photography-contest-xvi</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/photography-contest-xvi.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/DSC05994_OM1_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Olympus OM-1, with assorted paraphernalia&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olympus_OM-1&quot;&gt;Olympus OM-1&lt;/a&gt; – as far as I know the first smallish 35-mm SLR. I used mine from 1976 till 2003, when I bought a digital camera. I have had my present digital camera since 2015, so it has a long way to go. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 16th annual Panda’s Thumb Photography Contest begins now, Monday, June 2, at 12:00 p.m., MDT (MDT = UTC(GMT) – 6 h). Entries will be accepted between now and Friday, June 20, at 12:00 p.m., MDT. The rules are precisely the same as previous years’, except, obviously, that the dates have been updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We encourage entries in a single, general category, which includes pictures of just about anything of scientific interest: any object of experimentation or observation, from single-celled organisms, through nematodes, fruit flies, rats, chimpanzees, and college sophomores to volcanoes, stars, and galaxies. In order not to omit theoreticians, we will consider computer-generated pictures and also photographs of equipment. Photomicrographs and electron micrographs are likewise welcomed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since rumor has it that the pandemic encouraged macro photography, we may, if we receive enough entries, establish a “macro” category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winner will receive a choice between &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/stores/Matt-Young/author/B001HPILDU/&quot;&gt;Why Intelligent Design Fails, A Scientific Critique of the New Creationism&lt;/a&gt;, edited by Taner Edis and me; and Mark Isaak’s 2007 classic &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ucpress.edu/books/the-counter-creationism-handbook/paper&quot;&gt;The Counter-Creationism Handbook&lt;/a&gt;, generously contributed once again by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/&quot;&gt;NCSE&lt;/a&gt;. The runner-up will receive the remaining book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we get enough entries, consistently with Rules 11 and 12, we may add categories and award additional prizes, presuming, of course, that we can find more prizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rules of the contest are simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;We will consider any photograph that displays scientific interest – biological, paleontological, geological, or astronomical, for example.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Submit photographs in JPEG format. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Reduce photographs to an information content of 600 pixels horizontally. If creationists require a definition of information, they may apply in writing to the management. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Photographs may be enhanced but may not be montages. High dynamic range photographs and focus-stacked photographs are, however, accepted. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Submit a maximum of 3 photographs (or 5 photographs per family) to ProfessorSteveSteve@gmail.com. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Submit the photographs as attachments to an e-mail (not embedded in the body of the e-mail). The subject line to the e-mail must have the form YourLastName_PhotographyContest. The filenames for the photographs must have the form YourLastName_Descriptor as, for example, Young_Oxytropis_sericea or Young_Table_Mountain, as appropriate. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;In your e-mail, identify the subject of the photograph: common and biological name, mineral type, or geological formation, for example. Provide a link that will allow a reader to learn more about the subject. You may add descriptive text in the body of the e-mail if you like. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Depending on the number of photographs submitted, we may post the best submissions and ask our readers to vote for the best photograph. Likewise, we may establish several categories with separate entries and separate ballots. In particular, students 16 and under should so identify themselves; if we receive enough entries, we will establish a student category. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;By submitting a photograph, you stipulate that you are the owner of the copyright and grant The Panda’s Thumb a nonexclusive license to publish the photograph on its blog. The photograph will be subject to a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-No Derivatives license. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Regular contributors to The Panda’s Thumb are not eligible to enter the contest. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;The decision of the judges is irrevocable. The judges remain irrepressibly and irreducibly irascible, irreverent, and irredeemable, irregardless and irrespective, but not, we hope, irrational or irritable. So do not be irresolute; irradiate your sensors. We hope for a veritable irruption of entries this year. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Even though we are getting fairly good at running contests, we reserve the right to change any of the rules, or add or subtract rules at any time at our discretion. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will choose a number of finalists (or a winner) and open voting for the winner at 12:00 p.m. MDT, Monday, June 23.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Olympus OM-1 – as far as I know the first smallish 35-mm SLR. I used mine from 1976 till 2003, when I bought a digital camera. I have had my present digital camera since 2015, so it has a long way to go. The 16th annual Panda’s Thumb Photography Contest begins now, Monday, June 2, at 12:00 p.m., MDT (MDT = UTC(GMT) – 6 h). Entries will be accepted between now and Friday, June 20, at 12:00 p.m., MDT. The rules are precisely the same as previous years’, except, obviously, that the dates have been updated. We encourage entries in a single, general category, which includes pictures of just about anything of scientific interest: any object of experimentation or observation, from single-celled organisms, through nematodes, fruit flies, rats, chimpanzees, and college sophomores to volcanoes, stars, and galaxies. In order not to omit theoreticians, we will consider computer-generated pictures and also photographs of equipment. Photomicrographs and electron micrographs are likewise welcomed. Since rumor has it that the pandemic encouraged macro photography, we may, if we receive enough entries, establish a “macro” category. The winner will receive a choice between Why Intelligent Design Fails, A Scientific Critique of the New Creationism, edited by Taner Edis and me; and Mark Isaak’s 2007 classic The Counter-Creationism Handbook, generously contributed once again by NCSE. The runner-up will receive the remaining book.</summary></entry></feed>