<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-08-07T14:46:35-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Belostoma flumineum</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Belostoma-flumineum.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Belostoma flumineum" /><published>2021-08-02T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-02T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Belostoma-flumineum</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Belostoma-flumineum.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Runner-Up&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Denelsbeck_Belostoma_flumineum_Notonecta_kirbyi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Giant water bug&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://bugguide.net/node/view/368937&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Belostoma flumineum&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – Giant water bug – and &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugguide.net/node/view/17932&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Notonecta kirbyi &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – backswimmer prey: The photographer writes, &quot;I'm not &lt;i&gt;absolutely&lt;/i&gt; sure of the prey species, but we'll pretend that I'm confident/competent. I had collected some aquatic arthropods from a glorified ditch for some detailed aquarium shots, when the water bug cooperatively snagged the backswimmer for a meal – not exactly rare, because they're notoriously rapacious. The macro aquarium allowed both good lighting and a decent angle to fit within the short depth of field, and I cannot recommend one enough. The $5 'breeder' aquarium had one plastic side removed and replaced with a pane of glass from a photo frame for better clarity, allowing for desktop aquatic photos.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Al Denelsbeck. Photography contest, Runner-Up. Belostoma flumineum – Giant water bug – and Notonecta kirbyi – backswimmer prey: The photographer writes, &quot;I'm not absolutely sure of the prey species, but we'll pretend that I'm confident/competent. I had collected some aquatic arthropods from a glorified ditch for some detailed aquarium shots, when the water bug cooperatively snagged the backswimmer for a meal – not exactly rare, because they're notoriously rapacious. The macro aquarium allowed both good lighting and a decent angle to fit within the short depth of field, and I cannot recommend one enough. The $5 'breeder' aquarium had one plastic side removed and replaced with a pane of glass from a photo frame for better clarity, allowing for desktop aquatic photos.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy 277th birthday, Jean-Baptiste!</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/happy-birthday-lamarck.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy 277th birthday, Jean-Baptiste!" /><published>2021-08-01T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-01T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/happy-birthday-lamarck</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/happy-birthday-lamarck.html">&lt;p&gt;It has been customary for me to write a post every 1st of August celebrating
the anniversary of the scientist who was, as far as I can see, the first
evolutionary biologist.  No, not Charles Darwin, but Jean-Baptiste Pierre 
Antoine de Monet, the Chevalier de Lamarck.  Born in 1744 to an impoverished
branch of the French nobility, he wrote books on botany, coming to the
attention of the Comte de Buffon, who employed him in the royal botanical
garden in Paris.  After Buffon’s death and the French Revolution, he was
appointed to the least important curatorship in the new Museum of Natural
History, as curator of “worms”, i.e., invertebrates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although originally a botanist, he became fascinated by the structure of
invertebrates,
and from 1801 on he argued that they had evolved in a treelike genealogy. His
theory was propounded in his 1809 book “Philosophie zoologique”.  Although
it never convinced most zoologists, it
influenced many thinkers in the early 1800s, including Charles Darwin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lamarck was not a crackpot but an important pioneer of invertebrate
biology (he coined the words “invertebrate” and “biology”). He also
put forward the first proposal for a mechanism explaining adaptation. No,
not natural selection, but use and disuse.  This is widely misunderstood,
In what follows I want to briefly explain how it is that people who
think of themselves as Lamarckians get it wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lamarck had two processes.  One was a rather mysterious inherent
complexifying force, which he thought was a basic physical principle
of some sort.  It does not really explain why a species getting more complex
would also be adaptive.  And of course even by as soon as 100 years later, when
physics and chemistry were much better understood, no one thought that
there was any such principle.  So the Lamarckians of the late 1800s
quietly forgot about that part of Lamarck’s theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other process was use and disuse. Organisms used their various
organs, such as eyes, limbs, leaves, etc. to try to cope with their
environments, and these strivings were inherited by their offspring
in ways that resulted in those organs growing a bit in ways that increased
adaptation.  As I explain here every year, everyone in Lamarck’s day
thought that there were such inherited effects.  Lamarck did not
invent inheritance of acquired characters, because it was already
widely accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here is where modern Lamarckians go badly wrong.  They think that
it is enough to show that an environmental effect is inherited, such
as by epigenetic mechanisms.  And they think that this vindicates
Lamarck.  But to Lamarck it was the organism’s strivings to cope with
its surroundings that brought about the inherited effect.  That was what
brought about the directionality of the change, in the direction of
adaptation.  A fish tried to swim, and as it used its fins they grew
larger and stronger in its descendants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just showing an environmental effect would not give this directionality.
If your grandfather experienced a famine, and epigenetic inheritance
resulted in some effect on you, why should we think that these would
make you more resistant to famine?  Rather than, say, increasing your
susceptibility to cancer or heart disease?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern Lamarckians have not only thrown out Lamarck’s inherent complexifying
force, they misunderstand him as merely invoking inheritance of environmental
effects.  By doing that they also abandon any attempt to explain
why change is biased toward adaptation.  Lamarck would not recognize
their theory.  His was wrong, but it at least addressed the big issue,
Modern Lamarckians don’t even try to do that.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">It has been customary for me to write a post every 1st of August celebrating the anniversary of the scientist who was, as far as I can see, the first evolutionary biologist. No, not Charles Darwin, but Jean-Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet, the Chevalier de Lamarck. Born in 1744 to an impoverished branch of the French nobility, he wrote books on botany, coming to the attention of the Comte de Buffon, who employed him in the royal botanical garden in Paris. After Buffon’s death and the French Revolution, he was appointed to the least important curatorship in the new Museum of Natural History, as curator of “worms”, i.e., invertebrates. Although originally a botanist, he became fascinated by the structure of invertebrates, and from 1801 on he argued that they had evolved in a treelike genealogy. His theory was propounded in his 1809 book “Philosophie zoologique”. Although it never convinced most zoologists, it influenced many thinkers in the early 1800s, including Charles Darwin. Lamarck was not a crackpot but an important pioneer of invertebrate biology (he coined the words “invertebrate” and “biology”). He also put forward the first proposal for a mechanism explaining adaptation. No, not natural selection, but use and disuse. This is widely misunderstood, In what follows I want to briefly explain how it is that people who think of themselves as Lamarckians get it wrong.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Malacosoma californicum</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/Malacosoma-californicum.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Malacosoma californicum" /><published>2021-07-26T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-26T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/Malacosoma-californicum</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/Malacosoma-californicum.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Ken Phelps&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Winner&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Phelps_Malacosoma_californicum.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tent caterpillar&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malacosoma_californicum&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt; Malacosoma californicum&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – tent caterpillar, photographed on Thetis Island, B.C.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Ken Phelps. Photography contest, Winner. Malacosoma californicum – tent caterpillar, photographed on Thetis Island, B.C.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest XIII: Voting Ends Sunday</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/photography-contest-xiii-voting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest XIII: Voting Ends Sunday" /><published>2021-07-22T13:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-22T13:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/photography-contest-xiii-voting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/photography-contest-xiii-voting.html">&lt;p&gt;1000 apologies, but I will be having a bit of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/tsuris&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;tsuris&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; next Thursday, so I plan to cut off voting on Sunday, July 25, at noon, MDT. I will post the winner on Monday, July 26, at noon, MDT. Voting has slowed considerably in the last day or two; if you want to vote, you have the next 3 days to do so.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">1000 apologies, but I will be having a bit of tsuris next Thursday, so I plan to cut off voting on Sunday, July 25, at noon, MDT. I will post the winner on Monday, July 26, at noon, MDT. Voting has slowed considerably in the last day or two; if you want to vote, you have the next 3 days to do so.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest XIII: Finalists</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/finalists-xiii.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest XIII: Finalists" /><published>2021-07-19T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-19T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/finalists-xiii</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/finalists-xiii.html">&lt;p&gt;Here are the finalists of the 2021 photography contest. It was nice to see some new names as well as old friends. With assistance from Our Wife and Harshest Critic, we chose 8, which we display below the Figurative Fold. We chose the photographs more on the basis of their pictorial quality than on their scientific interest. The text, if any, was written by the photographers and lightly edited for consistency. The majority of finalists are either macros or close-ups, so we did not define a macro category, as we had suggested in the “RFP.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The finalists are presented in alphabetical order of last name. Please look through their photographs before voting for your favorite. Polling will close Friday, July 30, at approximately noon MDT, and we will display the winner at noon Monday, August 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please remember that this is a photography contest, not a popularity contest, and discourage your friends from enlisting others specifically to vote for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ring necked parakeet, by &lt;strong&gt;Philip Abrams&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Abrams_Psittacula_krameri.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Parakeet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rspb.org.uk/birds-and-wildlife/wildlife-guides/bird-a-z/ring-necked-parakeet&quot;&gt; &lt;i&gt;Psittacula krameria&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, ring necked parakeet, photographed 27 June 2021, at the Royal Hospital, Chelsea, London SW3, United Kingdom. The photographer writes, &quot;Although they are not indigenous, there are estimated to be some 8600 breeding pairs in the UK, mostly in and around London. They are very noisy, and, often, quite tame and trusting! More info from the Royal Society for Protection of Birds (link, above).&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giant water bug predating backswimmer, by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Denelsbeck_Belostoma_flumineum_Notonecta_kirbyi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Giant water bug&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://bugguide.net/node/view/368937&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Belostoma flumineum&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – Giant water bug – and &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugguide.net/node/view/17932&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Notonecta kirbyi &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – backswimmer prey: The photographer writes, I'm not &lt;i&gt;absolutely&lt;/i&gt; sure of the prey species, but we'll pretend that I'm confident/competent. I had collected some aquatic arthropods from a glorified ditch for some detailed aquarium shots, when the water bug cooperatively snagged the backswimmer for a meal – not exactly rare, because they're notoriously rapacious. The macro aquarium allowed both good lighting and a decent angle to fit within the short depth of field, and I cannot recommend one enough. The $5 'breeder' aquarium had one plastic side removed and replaced with a pane of glass from a photo frame for better clarity, allowing for desktop aquatic photos.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whistling ducks, by &lt;strong&gt;John Harshman&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Harshman_whistling_duck.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Whistling duck&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whistling_duck&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Dendrocygna viduata&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – white-faced whistling ducks, Botswana. The photographer writes, &quot;Here is a trio of white-faced whistling ducks. It’s not a particularly scientifically informative shot, but it’s one of my all-time favorite photos. Whistling ducks, on the other hand, are interesting from a number of perspectives. They’re the sister group of all other Anatidae, and they’re a very old genus: genetic divergence within &lt;i&gt;Dendrocygna&lt;/i&gt; is approximately equal to that within the rest of Anatidae. And yet they all look pretty much alike, so we have a fine example of morphological stasis. That may also be the reason that white-faced whistling ducks, with fairly sedentary habits, are nevertheless found in both Africa and South America with no recognized subspecific variation. (Fulvous whistling ducks &lt;i&gt;D. bicolor&lt;/i&gt; are worse: they’re found in North and South America, Africa, and India, still with no subspecies.)&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pitcher plant, by &lt;strong&gt;C. Joseph Long&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Long_pitcher_plant.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pitcher plant&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarracenia&quot;&gt; &lt;i&gt;Sarracenia&lt;/i&gt; sp. &lt;/a&gt; – pitcher plant, Green Swamp, west of Wilmington, N. C. (not the Green Swamp west of Orlando).  The photographer writes, &quot;This is a Nature Conservancy site which is typical nitrogen-poor lowland where plants that can find their own protein are favored.  There are also Venus flytraps in the near vicinity and, reportedly, sundews.  Recommended as an easily accessible example of this type of environment.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tent caterpillar, by &lt;strong&gt;Ken Phelps&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Phelps_Malacosoma_californicum.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tent caterpillar&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malacosoma_californicum&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt; Malacosoma californicum&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – tent caterpillar, photographed on Thetis Island, B.C.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snowberry checkerspot butterfly, by &lt;strong&gt;Malcom Schongalla&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Schongalla_Euphydryas_colon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Snowberry checkerspot butterfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.butterfliesoforegon.com/euphydryas-colon&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt; Euphydryas colon&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – snowberry checkerspot butterfly, Hillscreek, Oregon, June, 2021.  The photographer writes, &quot;Some references list this as a subspecies of &lt;i&gt;Euphydryas chalcedona&lt;/i&gt; (chalcedon or variable checkerspot).  I am not a butterfly expert and this is my best attempt at identification.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tawny crescent butterfly, by &lt;strong&gt;Seanna Watson&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Watson_Seanna_Phyciodes_batesii.jpg&quot; alt=&quot; Tawny crescent butterfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbif.gc.ca/eng/species-bank/butterflies-of-canada/tawny-crescent/?id=1370403265789&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Phyciodes batesii&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – tawny crescent, Neys Provincial Park, Ontario.
&lt;/figcaption&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atlantis fritillary, by &lt;strong&gt;Steve Watson&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Watson_Steve_Speyeria_atlantis.jpg&quot; alt=&quot; &quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbif.gc.ca/eng/species-bank/butterflies-of-canada/atlantis-fritillary/?id=1370403265542&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Speyeria atlantis&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – Atlantis fritillary on goldenrod (&lt;i&gt;Solidago&lt;/i&gt; sp.?), Neys Provincial Park, Ontario.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1Aru1WDbMAec3rsC0Rd4L14XRRd7dcGAUD7zA9pFK_b4/viewform?embedded=true&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;618&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot;&gt;Loading…&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Here are the finalists of the 2021 photography contest. It was nice to see some new names as well as old friends. With assistance from Our Wife and Harshest Critic, we chose 8, which we display below the Figurative Fold. We chose the photographs more on the basis of their pictorial quality than on their scientific interest. The text, if any, was written by the photographers and lightly edited for consistency. The majority of finalists are either macros or close-ups, so we did not define a macro category, as we had suggested in the “RFP.” The finalists are presented in alphabetical order of last name. Please look through their photographs before voting for your favorite. Polling will close Friday, July 30, at approximately noon MDT, and we will display the winner at noon Monday, August 2. Please remember that this is a photography contest, not a popularity contest, and discourage your friends from enlisting others specifically to vote for you.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Double Rainbow</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/double-rainbow.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Double Rainbow" /><published>2021-07-12T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-12T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/double-rainbow</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/double-rainbow.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Ivy Turner&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/IMG_9791_Ivy_Double_Rainbow_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Double Rainbow&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;Double &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rainbow&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;rainbow&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Wilmington, Vermont, June 30, 2021, 7:40 p.m.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s nice about this picture, besides that it is a nice picture, is that it shows a bright sky inside the &lt;i&gt;primary rainbow&lt;/i&gt; and outside the &lt;i&gt;secondary rainbow&lt;/i&gt;. These occur because (for the primary bow) droplets of water reflect light at all angles inside the primary bow, but the rays bunch up at the angle of the bow and give a bright dividing line between inside and outside; you may see a nice, if complicated, drawing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikiversity.org/wiki/File:Raindrop_wave.jpg&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Rays are likewise reflected at all angles outside the secondary bow but bunch up at the angle of the bow. The bows are colored because the index of refraction of the water droplets varies with color, but that is another subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. Don’t forget the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/photography-contest-xiii.html&quot;&gt;Photography Contest&lt;/a&gt;; entries close on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Ivy Turner. Double rainbow &amp;ndash; Wilmington, Vermont, June 30, 2021, 7:40 p.m. What’s nice about this picture, besides that it is a nice picture, is that it shows a bright sky inside the primary rainbow and outside the secondary rainbow. These occur because (for the primary bow) droplets of water reflect light at all angles inside the primary bow, but the rays bunch up at the angle of the bow and give a bright dividing line between inside and outside; you may see a nice, if complicated, drawing here. Rays are likewise reflected at all angles outside the secondary bow but bunch up at the angle of the bow. The bows are colored because the index of refraction of the water droplets varies with color, but that is another subject. P.S. Don’t forget the Photography Contest; entries close on Wednesday.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest (really) ends in &amp;lt;4 days</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/photography-contest-xiii-really-ends.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest (really) ends in &amp;lt;4 days" /><published>2021-07-10T13:55:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-10T13:55:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/photography-contest-xiii-really-ends</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/photography-contest-xiii-really-ends.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/DSC04366_Agelenidae_Spider_Eyes_600_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spider&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agelenopsis&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Agelenopsis&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; sp. &amp;ndash; funnel weaver, showing at least four of his or her &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugguide.net/node/view/84423#Agelenidae&quot;&gt;eight eyes&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a reminder that &lt;big&gt;Photography Contest XIII has been extended, and entries close Wednesday, July 14, at noon MDT&lt;/big&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Agelenopsis sp. &amp;ndash; funnel weaver, showing at least four of his or her eight eyes. Just a reminder that Photography Contest XIII has been extended, and entries close Wednesday, July 14, at noon MDT.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Daniel Phelps wins Paleontological Society award</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/daniel-phelps-paleontological-society-award.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Daniel Phelps wins Paleontological Society award" /><published>2021-07-07T14:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-07T14:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/daniel-phelps-paleontological-society-award</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/daniel-phelps-paleontological-society-award.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Dan_Phelps_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Daniel Phelps&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniel Phelps of Lexington, Kentucky, is the recipient if the 2021 Strimple Award of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.paleosoc.org/who-we-are&quot;&gt;Paleontological Society&lt;/a&gt;, an international nonprofit organization devoted exclusively to the advancement of the science of paleontology. The Strimple Award recognizes outstanding achievement in paleontology by someone who does not make a living full-time from paleontology. Contributions may be an outstanding record of research and publication, making outstanding collections, safeguarding unique paleontological materials through public service, teaching activities in the area of paleontology, and collaborations with others working in paleontology. The award will be given online as part of the Geological Society of America annual meeting in Portland, Oregon on October 12.*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Paleontological Society is the world’s leading scientific organization for studying invertebrate and vertebrate paleontology, micropaleontology, and paleobotany. The Society has membership in 40 countries and consists of professional paleontologists, academicians, science editors, earth-science teachers, museum specialists, and undergraduate and graduate students and postdoctoral scholars, as well as avocational paleontologists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniel Phelps is well known to readers of PT. He is President and founder of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.uky.edu/OtherOrgs/KPS/&quot;&gt;Kentucky Paleontological Society&lt;/a&gt;. He is a retired environmental geologist for the Commonwealth of Kentucky. He has also taught geology part-time in Kentucky’s Community College system and once worked for a major petroleum company’s Plano, Texas, research center. Dan is also Vice-President of Kentuckians for Science Education. He was a major participant in the documentary “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webelieveindinosaurs.net&quot;&gt;We Believe in Dinosaurs&lt;/a&gt;,” which aired on PBS’s series Independent Lens in February, 2020 (see, for example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2016/12/we-believe-in-dinosaurs.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/04/reviews-of-documentary.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* Full disclosure: based almost entirely on a press release.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Daniel Phelps of Lexington, Kentucky, is the recipient if the 2021 Strimple Award of the Paleontological Society, an international nonprofit organization devoted exclusively to the advancement of the science of paleontology. The Strimple Award recognizes outstanding achievement in paleontology by someone who does not make a living full-time from paleontology. Contributions may be an outstanding record of research and publication, making outstanding collections, safeguarding unique paleontological materials through public service, teaching activities in the area of paleontology, and collaborations with others working in paleontology. The award will be given online as part of the Geological Society of America annual meeting in Portland, Oregon on October 12.* The Paleontological Society is the world’s leading scientific organization for studying invertebrate and vertebrate paleontology, micropaleontology, and paleobotany. The Society has membership in 40 countries and consists of professional paleontologists, academicians, science editors, earth-science teachers, museum specialists, and undergraduate and graduate students and postdoctoral scholars, as well as avocational paleontologists. Daniel Phelps is well known to readers of PT. He is President and founder of the Kentucky Paleontological Society. He is a retired environmental geologist for the Commonwealth of Kentucky. He has also taught geology part-time in Kentucky’s Community College system and once worked for a major petroleum company’s Plano, Texas, research center. Dan is also Vice-President of Kentuckians for Science Education. He was a major participant in the documentary “We Believe in Dinosaurs,” which aired on PBS’s series Independent Lens in February, 2020 (see, for example, here and here). * Full disclosure: based almost entirely on a press release.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest ends in &amp;lt;2 days</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/photography-contest-xiii-ends-2-days.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest ends in &amp;lt;2 days" /><published>2021-07-05T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-05T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/photography-contest-xiii-ends-2-days</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/photography-contest-xiii-ends-2-days.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/DSC03625_Wasp_Xoridinae_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wasp&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;Ichneumonid wasp, subfamily &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xoridinae&quot;&gt;Xorinidae&lt;/a&gt;, female with ovipositor, September, 2020, Boulder, Colorado.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;Reminder: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/photography-contest-xiii.html&quot;&gt;Photography Contest XIII&lt;/a&gt; ends in &amp;lt;2 days, on Wednesday, July 7, at noon, UTC – 6 h.&lt;/big&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, unless we decide to extend it for a week because of the July 4 holiday in the US. Stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Ichneumonid wasp, subfamily Xorinidae, female with ovipositor, September, 2020, Boulder, Colorado. Reminder: Photography Contest XIII ends in &amp;lt;2 days, on Wednesday, July 7, at noon, UTC – 6 h. Well, unless we decide to extend it for a week because of the July 4 holiday in the US. Stay tuned.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest Ends in 5 Days</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/photography-contest-xiii-ends-5-days.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest Ends in 5 Days" /><published>2021-07-02T16:32:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-02T16:32:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/photography-contest-xiii-ends-5-days</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/photography-contest-xiii-ends-5-days.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/DSC03820_Wasp_Mischocyttarus_flavitarsis_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wasp&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mischocyttarus_flavitarsis&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt; Mischocyttarus_flavitarsis&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; paper wasp, November, 2020, Boulder, Colorado.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;Reminder: Photography Contest XIII ends in 5 days, on Wednesday, July 7, at noon, UTC – 6 h.&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Mischocyttarus_flavitarsis &amp;ndash; paper wasp, November, 2020, Boulder, Colorado. Reminder: Photography Contest XIII ends in 5 days, on Wednesday, July 7, at noon, UTC – 6 h.</summary></entry></feed>