<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-10-14T12:16:53-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Interview with Anthony Edwards on RA Fisher</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/edwards-fisher.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interview with Anthony Edwards on RA Fisher" /><published>2023-10-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/edwards-fisher</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/edwards-fisher.html">&lt;p&gt;Image by &lt;strong&gt;Axel Zeitler&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/fisherTitle2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Edwards Interview on Fisher&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt; I’ve been meaning for ages to publicize this &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/kqLB5a8op5c&quot;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt; with Anthony Edwards, I think the last student of RA Fisher before he moved to Australia in the late 1950s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this relates to the Fisher-window &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economist.com/britain/2022/04/23/a-cambridge-college-reflects-on-the-controversy-over-ronald-fisher&quot;&gt;controversy&lt;/a&gt; you may recall from summer 2020. His &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cai.cam.ac.uk/&quot;&gt;college&lt;/a&gt; kindly agreed to host the interview via their youtube page. As of this writing, they even show this interview as a &quot;featured link&quot; from their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cai.cam.ac.uk/discover/fisher-21st-century&quot;&gt;2022 symposium page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interview was produced by me &amp;amp; Axel Zeitler largely because we felt that Anthony (arguably the most qualified living person to say anything about Fisher's legacy) had been marginalized during the 2020 process. Until now, his voice was notably absent from from the 2022 symposium as well. Anyway, we're pleased that the college agreed (in Aug 2023) to add this interview to the record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click here:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert Asher</name></author><summary type="html">Image by Axel Zeitler. I’ve been meaning for ages to publicize this interview with Anthony Edwards, I think the last student of RA Fisher before he moved to Australia in the late 1950s. All this relates to the Fisher-window controversy you may recall from summer 2020. His college kindly agreed to host the interview via their youtube page. As of this writing, they even show this interview as a &quot;featured link&quot; from their 2022 symposium page The interview was produced by me &amp;amp; Axel Zeitler largely because we felt that Anthony (arguably the most qualified living person to say anything about Fisher's legacy) had been marginalized during the 2020 process. Until now, his voice was notably absent from from the 2022 symposium as well. Anyway, we're pleased that the college agreed (in Aug 2023) to add this interview to the record. To see comments on this post click here:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Halictidae</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/halictidae.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Halictidae" /><published>2023-10-02T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-02T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/halictidae</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/halictidae.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Mark Sturtevant&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Sturtevant.2.Halictid_Bee.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Halictid bee&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halictidae&quot;&gt;Halictid bee&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; commonly called sweat bees.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click here:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Mark Sturtevant. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Halictid bee &amp;ndash; commonly called sweat bees. To see comments on this post click here:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breaking news&amp;amp;colon; Ken Ham apologizes to Williamstown&amp;amp;excl;</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/09/ken-ham-apologizes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breaking news&amp;amp;colon; Ken Ham apologizes to Williamstown&amp;amp;excl;" /><published>2023-09-26T13:57:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-09-26T13:57:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/09/ken-ham-apologizes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/09/ken-ham-apologizes.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Downtown_Williamstown_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Downtown Williamstown&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Downtown Williamstown, its parking area bursting with a single parked car, 13:50, 25 February 2023. &lt;small&gt;w_lemay on &lt;a href=&quot;https://flickr.com/photos/59081381@N03/53035558718&quot;&gt;Flickr&lt;/a&gt;, Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 2.0 Generic license.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;No, he did not really, but William Trollinger on his blog, Righting America, has ghost-written a &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/dear-williamstown-sorry-for-misleading-you-about-ark-encounter-my-bad/&quot;&gt;letter&lt;/a&gt; (which we doubt Mr. Ham will send) on this 10th anniversary of the time that Williamstown, Kentucky, not only underwrote $62.5 million worth of junk bonds but also diverted property tax toward paying off those junk bonds. No good deed goes unpunished, and Williamstown was severely punished, as attendance at Mr. Ham’s Ark Park never reached the projections in the original proposal and Williamstown, alas, found itself on the wrong side of the highway. For more, we suggest you read Prof. Trollinger’s letter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click here:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Downtown Williamstown, its parking area bursting with a single parked car, 13:50, 25 February 2023. w_lemay on Flickr, Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 2.0 Generic license. No, he did not really, but William Trollinger on his blog, Righting America, has ghost-written a letter (which we doubt Mr. Ham will send) on this 10th anniversary of the time that Williamstown, Kentucky, not only underwrote $62.5 million worth of junk bonds but also diverted property tax toward paying off those junk bonds. No good deed goes unpunished, and Williamstown was severely punished, as attendance at Mr. Ham’s Ark Park never reached the projections in the original proposal and Williamstown, alas, found itself on the wrong side of the highway. For more, we suggest you read Prof. Trollinger’s letter. To see comments on this post click here:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chauliognathus basalis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/09/chauliognathus-basalis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chauliognathus basalis" /><published>2023-09-18T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-09-18T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/09/chauliognathus-basalis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/09/chauliognathus-basalis.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/P1010760_Colorado_Soldier_Beetle_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Colorado soldier beetle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chauliognathus_basalis&quot;&gt;Chauliognathus basalis&lt;/a&gt; – Colorado soldier beetle, Wonderland Lake, Boulder, Colorado, August 31, 2023.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post go here:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Chauliognathus basalis – Colorado soldier beetle, Wonderland Lake, Boulder, Colorado, August 31, 2023. To see comments on this post go here:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why do we know that birds are living dinosaurs? Evaluation of reasoning in anti-evolutionist treatise</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/09/why-do-we-know.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why do we know that birds are living dinosaurs? Evaluation of reasoning in anti-evolutionist treatise" /><published>2023-09-12T14:25:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-09-12T14:25:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/09/why-do-we-know</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/09/why-do-we-know.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Neukamm_Summary_Figure_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Birdlike dinosaur&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;What follows is a summary of a longer article &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ag-evolutionsbiologie.net/pdf/2023/evolution-why-birds-are-living-dinosaurs.pdf&quot;&gt;Why do we know that birds are living dinosaurs?&lt;/a&gt; published (in English) by AG Evolutionsbiologie, a German scientific association that deals with evolutionary biology and creationism.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The finding that birds are descendants of certain dinosaurs has been a scientific consensus for over 20 years. Only a very few experts still question it. In the publications of those who deny macroevolution and want to have it replaced by an “intelligent” origin (that is, creationists of various stripes), such criticism is clearly overrepresented. However, unlike the scientists they cite, creationists do not primarily cast doubt on the membership of birds in particular archosaur taxa. Rather, they want to see the evolutionary development as such questioned. They achieve this only by mixing the criticism of individual scientists with antiquated and factually incorrect ideas on evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the creationists who is concerned with criticizing avian evolution is Reinhard Junker, former managing director of the German evangelical association Wort-und-Wissen. His argumentation is typical of creationist criticism. Since such criticism relies on antiquated views of evolution, numerous findings look like serious anomalies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this review, we explain why birds' ancestry from Mesozoic dinosaurs is a scientifically well-established fact. Afterwards, we discuss popular objections against this thesis presented by creationists like Reinhard Junker and by scientists like Alan Feduccia as well. We show that creationist criticism is working under a misunderstanding or misrepresentation of evolutionary theory. This line of reasoning is influential worldwide. It is representative of the whole creationist spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ten main theses of our analysis are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The statement &lt;i&gt;that&lt;/i&gt; birds are the product of a long, evolutionary-historical process is logically independent of the question of &lt;i&gt;how&lt;/i&gt; this evolution proceeded in detail. The evolution of birds and birds' ancestry from Mesozoic dinosaurs is essentially supported by the fact that we can put theropod fossils into a sequence in which their shape gradually takes on the appearance of modern birds. Given that descent, heritable variability, and speciation are &lt;i&gt;observed facts&lt;/i&gt;, bird evolution (or evolution in general) would remain untouched even if we knew nothing about its mechanisms.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creationists allege a &lt;i&gt;waiting time problem&lt;/i&gt; causing a very slow pace of evolution. Hence, in their eyes, evolutionary mechanisms are overstrained by producing the great diversity of avian forms “abruptly” in geologically short periods. However, their reasoning is quite wrong. First, creationists do not seem to have understood how novelties arise in evolution. For instance, evolution never faced the task of waiting until a “fixed and pre-specified target” was reached. Second, the evolvability of novelties, even of &lt;i&gt;irreducibly complex systems&lt;/i&gt;, within short time periods is a well-corroborated and no longer reasonably disputable fact (see, for instance, HUNT 2007b; TONKIN et al. 2008; DE KRAKER &amp;amp; GERSHENZON 2011; SAUTER et al. 2012; TROTTER et al. 2014; YONA et al. 2018; RAWCLIFFE 2019; BEYER et al. 2022; NEUKAMM 2022).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When it comes to the &lt;i&gt;“abrupt” appearance of characters&lt;/i&gt; in the fossil record, the explanation of &lt;i&gt;punctuated equilibria&lt;/i&gt; must be considered as well as the ambiguity of the term “abrupt”. When a paleontologist speaks of the “abrupt” appearance of a feature, he may still think of periods of millions of years. Here, the biased and fragmentary sedimentary record, both in time and in space, must be taken into account. Abrupt appearance may hence be a &lt;i&gt;geological artifact&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creationists ignore the progress of &lt;i&gt;evolutionary developmental biology&lt;/i&gt; (Evo-Devo) in solving specific problems. This includes, for example, the question of how the supposedly contradictory counting of fingers in some theropods (apparently, I-II-III) and birds (II-III-IV) fits together. Evo-Devo can also explain the capability for comparatively rapid convergent evolution of quite a few avian features.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evolution deniers portray the &lt;i&gt;convergence problem&lt;/i&gt; as much more serious than it is. Despite widespread convergence and uncertainty about the position of some taxa, there is a remarkable consensus on the backbone structure of the family tree of the ancestors of birds and the relative hierarchical placement of almost all major clades that constitute this tree. Birds still lie in a deeply nested position within Theropoda (RAUHUT &amp;amp; FOTH 2020, p. 37).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contrary to creationists' reasoning, &lt;i&gt;widespread convergences are not anomalies&lt;/i&gt; but rather a clear expectation of evolutionary theory when &lt;i&gt;developmental biological background knowledge is considered&lt;/i&gt; (MCGHEE 2011, p. 7).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For at least half a century, the idea that evolution must run &lt;i&gt;continuously and linearly&lt;/i&gt; has not been compatible with contemporary knowledge of the processes of speciation and differentiation of species (MAHNER 1986, p. 68). Creationists do not seem to know that just these processes are accompanied by discontinuities, incongruities, and a zigzag course (such as reversions of traits in different lineages).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creationists place antiquated expectations on the nature of evolutionary &lt;i&gt;transitional forms&lt;/i&gt; and claim to have recognized “contradictory” trait mosaics. Hence, they ignore that mosaic evolution is the result of genetic burdens (RIEDL 2003, p. 209) and lineage-splitting events (MAYR 1967, p. 465 f.).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The claim that the features of the avian body plan could not have evolved isolated from each other is false. The theropod fossils can be placed in a sequence in which the “irreducibly complex overall organization” of birds resolves into a &lt;i&gt;series of consecutive feature addition steps&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creationists seem not to understand &lt;i&gt;cladogenesis&lt;/i&gt;; otherwise, they would not problematize the &lt;i&gt;phylogenetic-stratigraphic discrepancy&lt;/i&gt;, i.e., the &lt;i&gt;chronologically later appearance of some species with more primitive features &lt;/i&gt; in the fossil record. (For the attempt to compress the geological time scale by six orders of magnitude, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ag-evolutionsbiologie.net/html/2014/kreationismus-und-radiometrische-datierung.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgement&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would particularly like to thank John HARSHMAN, a specialist in dinosaur evolution, who reviewed this paper and contributed to its accomplishment with his critical comments. Thanks also go to Matt YOUNG for editorial review. Furthermore, we give thanks to Prof. Oliver RAUHUT for his statements, which he allowed us to reproduce in section C.11. We would also like to thank Dandan WU from the Peking Natural Science Organization (PNSO) and Stefan PROCHASKA from SchuBu Systems GmbH for their permission to reproduce their images. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About the authors.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Prof. Dr. Andreas Beyer studied biology at the Ruhr University in Bochum (Germany) with a focus on biochemistry, physiology, cytology and microbiology. Doctorate on the topic “molecular biological characterization of the AAA gene family, a new group of putative ATPases.” Research on the phosphorylation of phosphorylase kinase at the Institute for Physiological Chemistry at the Ruhr University. Applied research in various industrial projects. Lecturer at the Westfälische Hochschule Gelsenkirchen, Bocholt, Recklinghausen (Germany) as Professor of Molecular Biology. Chairman of the working group “AG Evolutionsbiologie” which is associated with the German Association of Biologists (VBio).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin Neukamm is a German chemist and managing editor of the &lt;a href=&quot;www.ag-evolutionsbiologie.de&quot;&gt;AG Evolutionsbiologie&lt;/a&gt;, a German scientific association that deals with evolutionary biology and creationism. He has published various articles and books on evolution and creationism in the German language.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Neukamm and Andreas Beyer</name></author><summary type="html">What follows is a summary of a longer article Why do we know that birds are living dinosaurs? published (in English) by AG Evolutionsbiologie, a German scientific association that deals with evolutionary biology and creationism. Summary The finding that birds are descendants of certain dinosaurs has been a scientific consensus for over 20 years. Only a very few experts still question it. In the publications of those who deny macroevolution and want to have it replaced by an “intelligent” origin (that is, creationists of various stripes), such criticism is clearly overrepresented. However, unlike the scientists they cite, creationists do not primarily cast doubt on the membership of birds in particular archosaur taxa. Rather, they want to see the evolutionary development as such questioned. They achieve this only by mixing the criticism of individual scientists with antiquated and factually incorrect ideas on evolution. One of the creationists who is concerned with criticizing avian evolution is Reinhard Junker, former managing director of the German evangelical association Wort-und-Wissen. His argumentation is typical of creationist criticism. Since such criticism relies on antiquated views of evolution, numerous findings look like serious anomalies. In this review, we explain why birds' ancestry from Mesozoic dinosaurs is a scientifically well-established fact. Afterwards, we discuss popular objections against this thesis presented by creationists like Reinhard Junker and by scientists like Alan Feduccia as well. We show that creationist criticism is working under a misunderstanding or misrepresentation of evolutionary theory. This line of reasoning is influential worldwide. It is representative of the whole creationist spectrum. The ten main theses of our analysis are as follows:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dan Phelps interviewed on the “Oh No, Ross and Carrie!” podcast</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/09/dan-phelps-interviewed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dan Phelps interviewed on the “Oh No, Ross and Carrie!” podcast" /><published>2023-09-11T19:45:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-09-11T19:45:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/09/dan-phelps-interviewed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/09/dan-phelps-interviewed.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Phelps_Ham_Podcast.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dan Phelps, with Ken Ham&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Dan Phelps, r., with Ken Ham at the Ark Park.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you thought that you knew all about the Ark Park, &lt;a href=&quot;https://maximumfun.org/episodes/oh-no-ross-and-carrie/ross-and-dan-phelps-and-the-genesis-of-the-ark-encounter/&quot;&gt;this interview with Dan Phelps&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://maximumfun.org/podcasts/oh-no-ross-and-carrie/&quot;&gt;Oh No, Ross and Carrie!&lt;/a&gt; podcast will disabuse you of that illusion. In a brisk hour and a quarter or so,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Ross talks with Dan Phelps, president of the Kentucky Paleontological Society and persistent thorn in the side of creationist Ken Ham. Learn why Answers in Genesis only paid $1 for 98 acres of land and how their parking lot pays for the corporate jet.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And more!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Dan Phelps, r., with Ken Ham at the Ark Park. In case you thought that you knew all about the Ark Park, this interview with Dan Phelps on the Oh No, Ross and Carrie! podcast will disabuse you of that illusion. In a brisk hour and a quarter or so, &quot;Ross talks with Dan Phelps, president of the Kentucky Paleontological Society and persistent thorn in the side of creationist Ken Ham. Learn why Answers in Genesis only paid $1 for 98 acres of land and how their parking lot pays for the corporate jet.&quot; And more!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nathan Lents interviewed on our poorly designed bodies</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/09/Nathan-Lents-interviewed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nathan Lents interviewed on our poorly designed bodies" /><published>2023-09-09T09:10:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-09-09T09:10:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/09/Nathan-Lents-interviewed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/09/Nathan-Lents-interviewed.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Lents_Interview.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Why the human eye is a disaster&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our colleague Nathan Lents has just posted a series of videos, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehumanevolutionblog.com/2023/09/09/some-interviews-on-our-poorly-designed-bodies/&quot;&gt;Some interviews on our poorly designed bodies&lt;/a&gt;. Lents, a biology professor at John Jay College, is the author of the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehumanevolutionblog.com/book-human-errors/&quot;&gt;Human Errors&lt;/a&gt; and is an expert on poor design. So far, I have watched only the video on “Why the Human Eye Is a Design Disaster” and noted the comparison with the cephalopod eye. All I can add is that, in addition, cephalopods cannot get dry eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To see comments on this post go here:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Our colleague Nathan Lents has just posted a series of videos, Some interviews on our poorly designed bodies. Lents, a biology professor at John Jay College, is the author of the book Human Errors and is an expert on poor design. So far, I have watched only the video on “Why the Human Eye Is a Design Disaster” and noted the comparison with the cephalopod eye. All I can add is that, in addition, cephalopods cannot get dry eyes. To see comments on this post go here:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sympetrum semicinctum</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/09/Sympetrum-semicinctum.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sympetrum semicinctum" /><published>2023-09-04T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-09-04T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/09/Sympetrum-semicinctum</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/09/Sympetrum-semicinctum.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/P1010708_Band_Winged_Meadowhawk_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dragonfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Band-winged_meadowhawk&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Sympetrum semicinctum&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – band-winged meadowhawk, Wonderland Lake, Boulder, Colorado, August, 2023.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saw these dragonflies on the trail in the vicinity of Wonderland Lake, just begging to be photographed. The picture above is the band-winged meadowhawk, as demonstrated by the brown bands on the wings. When I examined the photographs, I found that not all meadowhawks are alike. Below the fold, a dragonfly that to my eye looks identical, except that its wings do not display the brown, translucent bands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/P1010718_White_Faced_Meadowhawk_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dragonfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White-faced_meadowhawk&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Sympetrum obtrusum&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – white-faced meadowhawk, Wonderland Lake, Boulder, Colorado, August, 2023.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Thanks to the experts at &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugguide.net/&quot;&gt;BugGuide&lt;/a&gt; for verifying the identity of &lt;i&gt;S. obtrusum&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Sympetrum semicinctum – band-winged meadowhawk, Wonderland Lake, Boulder, Colorado, August, 2023. I saw these dragonflies on the trail in the vicinity of Wonderland Lake, just begging to be photographed. The picture above is the band-winged meadowhawk, as demonstrated by the brown bands on the wings. When I examined the photographs, I found that not all meadowhawks are alike. Below the fold, a dragonfly that to my eye looks identical, except that its wings do not display the brown, translucent bands.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Double Rainbow</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/08/double-rainbow.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Double Rainbow" /><published>2023-08-21T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-08-21T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/08/double-rainbow</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/08/double-rainbow.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Marilyn Susek&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest XIV, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Marilyn_Susek_Rainbow_5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rainbow&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rainbow&quot;&gt;Double Rainbow&lt;/a&gt;, Meadowhall Shopping Complex, Sheffield, England, UK, July 3, 2023, 8:17 pm. Ms. Susek notes, &quot;When I came out to the car park  there was a lovely double rainbow that appeared to end just over my car.&quot; The photograph shows that the sky is brighter inside the primary arc and, less clearly, outside the secondary arc.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Marilyn Susek. Photography Contest XIV, Honorable Mention. Double Rainbow, Meadowhall Shopping Complex, Sheffield, England, UK, July 3, 2023, 8:17 pm. Ms. Susek notes, &quot;When I came out to the car park there was a lovely double rainbow that appeared to end just over my car.&quot; The photograph shows that the sky is brighter inside the primary arc and, less clearly, outside the secondary arc.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Eric Hedin isn’t sure what natural selection does</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/08/Hedin-information-principle.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Eric Hedin isn’t sure what natural selection does" /><published>2023-08-20T21:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-08-20T21:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/08/Hedin-information-principle</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/08/Hedin-information-principle.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/480px-Ratchet_Gear_and_Pawl.gif&quot; alt=&quot;[Ratchet Gif]&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;By Arglin Kampling. From Wikimedia, CCA 4.0.&lt;br /&gt;  Is this the first GIF we have used?&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ID advocacy site &lt;em&gt;Evolution News&lt;/em&gt; has had a series of posts by the physicist 
Eric Hedin.  The theme has been that adaptive information in biological organisms info
cannot have been produced by natural processes, because these always degrade information. 
Hedin is a well-trained physicist.  He is currently the Professor of Physics and Astronomy 
and the Chair of the Department of Chemistry, Physics, and Engineering at Biola University, 
and he trained in plasma physics at my own university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that strong background in physics, we should be able to rely on his statements about 
the increase of the amount of biological information which is possible 
owing to ordinary physical and biological processes.  Here’s what his says 
at one point in &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2023/05/is-life-an-information-ratchet/&quot;&gt;this recent post at Evolution News&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Could a natural information ratchet exist? Since our goal is to understand whether life is an information ratchet, we first need to examine what kind of mechanism might be required to cause a living system to ratchet up its information content over time. To increase information means to select outcomes that correspond to a greater level of functional or meaningful complexity. The only way for this to happen is if the selection mechanism (in other words, the ratchet) is designed to produce the target outcome, and this means that the mechanism must already contain the information specifying the target. A physical mechanism cannot produce any information beyond what it already contains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have complained &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/22/09/badinformation.html&quot;&gt;in a previous post&lt;/a&gt; about 
his statements about conservation of information and about there being no 
natural process that can account for the information accumulated in 
living things.  Here it is again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can it be that Professor Hedin has got his basic science wrong?  Say it ain’t so!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, it ain’t so in one case.   If we have a population that consists of 
only one individual, and that individual reproduces exclusively clonally, by budding off 
a single offspring identical to itself, then Hedin is right.  There is never
any other individual in the population than that offspring, and no opportunity 
for natural selection to act.  If a mutation occurs, the altered genotype is 
immediately 100% of the population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mutation-accumulation-lines&quot;&gt;Mutation accumulation lines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geneticists actually use such situations as an experimental design, when 
they want to see as many as possible of the mutations that occur, both 
advantageous and deleterious.  These one-individual populations are 
called “mutation accumulation lines”.  Of course many species cannot 
reproduce with only one parent, and cannot reproduce by budding.  The 
closest we can come to a clone in, say, mice, is to have a population 
of two individuals, who are brother and sister, and mate those every
generation.  But that allows natural selection to occur for one or 
two generations for the average mutation.  So the spectrum of mutations 
accumulated in the population is partly biased against deleterious 
mutants.  Which suggests that in all cases other than a clonally-reproducing 
population of one single individual, there will be some natural 
selection occurring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-professor-hedin-gets-it-wrong&quot;&gt;Why Professor Hedin gets it wrong&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when there is, not a single individual, but a population of 
individuals, then Eric Hedin’s analysis has to ask what the effect 
of natural selection is, not just what the effect of accumulated 
mutation is.  He sounds as if he is only taking mutation into account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his next paragraph, he deals with natural selection:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Darwin’s Proposed “Ratchet”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;What about Darwin’s proposed “ratchet” mechanism of natural selection based on survival of the fittest? The mechanism invoked here already contains a high degree of functional complexity (all the complexity residing in a living organism). But what can this “ratchet” do? No more than it was designed to do — namely to reproduce daughter organisms according to its inherent mechanism of reproduction. Variations in the organism’s genome, by any unguided process, may lead to an increase in fitness and therefore survivability. But natural processes cannot produce unnatural results. Selection based on the ratchet mechanism of increased fitness cannot of itself produce novel complex functionality if each successive small change does not give some increased advantage towards survival and reproduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(We should note that Darwin never used the word “ratchet”.  Daniel Dennett did, in his writings on natural selection.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Hedin returns to the role of natural selection in the paragraph following that in his 
post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The allure of Darwinism is that it suggests a process by which a population of organisms can ratchet up information and increase organismal functionality. A common misunderstanding of evolution is to assume that it can do more than steadily lock in natural variations that increase survivability. The error is in ascribing to this process the ability to ratchet up the information content of a simple common ancestor until all the complex, functionally coherent species of life on Earth have formed. But as shown in our examination of the functionality of any ratchet mechanism, it cannot produce an outcome beyond what it was designed to achieve. With information as the outcome, the mechanism can only reproduce the level of information it already contains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;does-hedin-think-natural-selection-can-increase-information&quot;&gt;Does Hedin think natural selection &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; increase information?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this is puzzling.  In the preceding paragraph it was clearly stated that natural processes could not add meaningful biological information to the organism, unless the process already contains the information.  That seems to say that natural processes, including natural selection, cannot possibly increase the specified (adaptive) information.  The natural processes can at best transfer information that they already have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; acknowledge that natural selection in a population &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; “steadily lock in natural variations that increase survivability”.  That would involve increasing the specified information in the population.  This would seem to completely contradict his own earlier statements. He says that “selection based on the ratchet mechanism of 
increased fitness cannot of itself produce novel complex functionality if each successive small change does not give some increased advantage towards survival and reproduction”. The later statements say, in effect, that actually natural selection &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; increase the content of 
adaptive (specified) information.  The implication is that selection &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; produce increased 
information content in the genome if each small change on the way &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; give some 
increase in fitness.  The previous impossibility has turned into a possibility.  It is just that natural selection and mutation (and other 
ordinary evolutionary processes) cannot produce “unnatural” results, really big increases in “complexity”.  Hedin continues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Another Process at Work&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Given the obvious, that the complexity of organisms on Earth has increased through time from single-cell archaea to functional multicellular creatures, some process other than a supposed evolutionary information ratchet must have been at work. The genomic information content of the prokaryotic cells descriptive of the earliest life on Earth falls far short of the greater information content and complexity of advanced life. An intelligent mind is the only known source for the necessary input of complex specified information throughout biological history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hedins-actual-conclusions&quot;&gt;Hedin’s actual conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Professor Hedin has argued, in effect, that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Natural evolutionary processes cannot increase the adaptive 
information of a population of organisms, because there is a 
conservation law preventing that.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;… except that they &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; increase the adaptive 
information in the population, they just cannot increase 
it to an “unnatural” extent.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And it is his (unsupported) opionion that the increases 
of “complexity” in living things involve those kinds of 
“unnatural” increases.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;… and therefore those require Design Intervention.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A promised conservation law that prevents information from being increased by natural selection is described.  Then it evaporates and is 
replaced by Professor Hedin’s personal incredulity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would add that the information in the genome does not come from 
nowhere – the process of natural selection is part of the flow 
of energy through the biosphere, and is accompanied by an 
increase of entropy in the whole system, with adaptation 
capturing energy and slowing the increase of entropy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;your-opinion&quot;&gt;Your opinion?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have I got this wrong?  I hope that someone, perhaps Dr. 
Hedin himself, will let us know.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">By Arglin Kampling. From Wikimedia, CCA 4.0. Is this the first GIF we have used? &amp;nbsp; The ID advocacy site Evolution News has had a series of posts by the physicist Eric Hedin. The theme has been that adaptive information in biological organisms info cannot have been produced by natural processes, because these always degrade information. Hedin is a well-trained physicist. He is currently the Professor of Physics and Astronomy and the Chair of the Department of Chemistry, Physics, and Engineering at Biola University, and he trained in plasma physics at my own university. With that strong background in physics, we should be able to rely on his statements about the increase of the amount of biological information which is possible owing to ordinary physical and biological processes. Here’s what his says at one point in this recent post at Evolution News): Could a natural information ratchet exist? Since our goal is to understand whether life is an information ratchet, we first need to examine what kind of mechanism might be required to cause a living system to ratchet up its information content over time. To increase information means to select outcomes that correspond to a greater level of functional or meaningful complexity. The only way for this to happen is if the selection mechanism (in other words, the ratchet) is designed to produce the target outcome, and this means that the mechanism must already contain the information specifying the target. A physical mechanism cannot produce any information beyond what it already contains. I have complained in a previous post about his statements about conservation of information and about there being no natural process that can account for the information accumulated in living things. Here it is again. Can it be that Professor Hedin has got his basic science wrong? Say it ain’t so!</summary></entry></feed>