<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-08-04T15:26:38-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Aphantasia and me</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/aphantasia-and-me.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aphantasia and me" /><published>2024-08-03T08:50:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-08-03T08:50:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/aphantasia-and-me</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/aphantasia-and-me.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Dingfelder_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who knew? I have &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aphantasia&quot;&gt;aphantasia&lt;/a&gt;, the inability to visualize things. Well, probably not fully fledged aphantasia, but certainly &lt;i&gt;dys&lt;/i&gt;phantasia. Aphantasia is a word I first learned on listening to an NPR program with a somewhat lengthy title, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2024/06/26/1198910315/face-blindness-prosopagnosia-memory-aphantasia-sight-imagination&quot;&gt;The human brain is hardwired to recognize faces. But what if you can’t?&lt;/a&gt; It turns out that Sadie  Dingfelder, the author of the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/0316545147/&quot;&gt;Do I Know You? A Faceblind Reporter’s Journey into the Science of Sight, Memory, and Imagination&lt;/a&gt;, can’t. Recognize faces, that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms. Dingfelder is not only face blind; she is also &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stereoblindness&quot;&gt;stereo blind&lt;/a&gt; and aphantasic. Now, I understand that freshman psychology students think they suffer from every affliction they study, but I was surprised to find that I have some degree of all of those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was stereo blind until a dozen or two years ago. Indeed, I remember commenting to the eminent lens designer Rudolf Kingslake that I saw no difference between one eye and two. He was astonished and told me everything popped into life with two eyes open. I in turn was baffled. (I must have had some stereopsis, because I found that, when I looked at a painting or photograph with one eye, I saw more depth than with two eyes, presumably because the clue that the painting was flat was missing without the stereopsis afforded by two eyes. This technique, which was taught to me by a photogrammetrist at the University of Guelph, is very useful when walking around art galleries.) Many years later, while engaging in eye exercises for something else, I suddenly developed what I think may be fairly good stereo vision, and it has never gone away, even after I quit the exercises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that I first learned of face blindness, or &lt;i&gt;prosopagnosia&lt;/i&gt;, from Oliver Sacks’s book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/man-who-mistook-his-wife-hat&quot;&gt;The Man Who Mistook His Wife for a Hat&lt;/a&gt;. According to the NPR report, Ms. Dingfelder is almost completely face blind, more so than almost anyone else. After reading Sacks’s book, I realized that I too have a degree of face blindness – I suppose I could say prosop&lt;i&gt;dys&lt;/i&gt;gnosia, but that would be a dreadful word. At any rate, although I have never accused anyone else’s spouse of buying junk food, as did Ms. Dingfelder, I have a lot of trouble recognizing people I have just met or know only slightly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for aphantasia, I can visualize things but not well. Possibly that is one reason I do not like fiction that is heavy with description. The apple I am visualizing right now is merely a hollow, transparent shell. I can see the stem, the black sepals at the blossom end, and the core, but the skin has no color, and the flesh has no texture, if it exists at all. I think probably this inability to visualize is why I cannot draw objects with curves very well, and faces are out of the question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kirkusreviews.com/book-reviews/sadie-dingfelder/do-i-know-you/&quot;&gt;Kirkus Reviews&lt;/a&gt;, Ms. Dingfelder has amblyopia, or lazy eye, which I presume is the origin of her stereo blindness (unless, of course, it is the other way around). Kirkus says that as a result of her stereo blindness she cannot get around easily, walk on uneven surfaces, or drive a car. Either Ms. Dingfelder or Kirkus partly misunderstands depth perception. We have depth perception even with one eye; it is just not as good as stereo vision. In Colorado, for example, you may drive as long as your vision in one eye is 20/40 or better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sounds as if the book is part memoir and part science, rather like this essay. I have not yet read it, but I intend to do so as soon as I can manage it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 1.&lt;/strong&gt; An appendix is a vestigial part of a document and has no known function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 2.&lt;/strong&gt; While writing this essay, I was reminded of an anecdote told to our class by my philosophy professor, Murray Turbayne. Professor Turbayne relates asking his mother-in-law to visualize an apple. I forget the exact order, but, roughly, he asks her to imagine that it has no color. OK, no color. No smell or taste. OK. No weight. OK. No texture. A little harder, but OK. What is left? The apple! We then had a discussion, which I only dimly remember, about whether the apple was more than the sum of its attributes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Who knew? I have aphantasia, the inability to visualize things. Well, probably not fully fledged aphantasia, but certainly dysphantasia. Aphantasia is a word I first learned on listening to an NPR program with a somewhat lengthy title, The human brain is hardwired to recognize faces. But what if you can’t? It turns out that Sadie Dingfelder, the author of the book Do I Know You? A Faceblind Reporter’s Journey into the Science of Sight, Memory, and Imagination, can’t. Recognize faces, that is. Ms. Dingfelder is not only face blind; she is also stereo blind and aphantasic. Now, I understand that freshman psychology students think they suffer from every affliction they study, but I was surprised to find that I have some degree of all of those.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy 280th birthday to Jean-Baptiste Lamarck</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/happy-280th-birthday-lamarck.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy 280th birthday to Jean-Baptiste Lamarck" /><published>2024-08-02T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-08-02T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/happy-280th-birthday-lamarck</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/happy-280th-birthday-lamarck.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/2022-04-12-Metro_Lamarck_-_Caulaincourt-8402.jpg&quot; width=&quot;640px&quot; alt=&quot;[Lamarck-Coulaincourt metro station]&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Entrance to the Lamarck-Coulaincourt metro station, Paris.© Superbass / CC-BY-SA-4.0 (via Wikimedia Commons)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, the 1st of August, is the 280th anniversary of the birth of Jean-Baptiste Pierre Antoine 
de Monet, who was the Chevalier de Lamarck.  As I have noted each year here, he was, 
as far as I am concerned, the first evolutionary biologist.  He had a (wrong) mechanism 
that would explain adaptation, and was the major pioneer in drawing evolutionary 
trees.  He was also a pioneer of invertebrate biology.  (Although he made use of 
inheritance of acquired characters in his mechanisms, he did not invent that idea, 
as most folks already believed that).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I want to note the way Lamarck is comemmorated in the name of a street 
in Paris, the Rue de Lamarck.  His name is also on streets in some other French cities. 
The explanation that I have heard of why that particular street was named after him 
is that it was being built about the time that Darwin was becoming famous, and the 
French found a then-almost-forgotten French biologist to commemmorate, to compete with 
Darwin.  So they named a street for him in an area where new streets were being built and named.  I don’t know whether this is really an accurate explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rue de Lamarck is famous in Paris today as it gives its name to a major Metro 
stop, Lamarck-Coulaincourt.  Above you will see the very dramatic entrance to 
that Metro station, photographed from the Rue de Lamarck.  The entrance is between 
two stairways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy 280th, Jean-Baptiste!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;to-read-or-post-comments-first-click-on-the-title-of-this-post&quot;&gt;To read or post comments, first click on the title of this post.&lt;/h5&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Entrance to the Lamarck-Coulaincourt metro station, Paris.© Superbass / CC-BY-SA-4.0 (via Wikimedia Commons) &amp;nbsp; Yesterday, the 1st of August, is the 280th anniversary of the birth of Jean-Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet, who was the Chevalier de Lamarck. As I have noted each year here, he was, as far as I am concerned, the first evolutionary biologist. He had a (wrong) mechanism that would explain adaptation, and was the major pioneer in drawing evolutionary trees. He was also a pioneer of invertebrate biology. (Although he made use of inheritance of acquired characters in his mechanisms, he did not invent that idea, as most folks already believed that). This time I want to note the way Lamarck is comemmorated in the name of a street in Paris, the Rue de Lamarck. His name is also on streets in some other French cities. The explanation that I have heard of why that particular street was named after him is that it was being built about the time that Darwin was becoming famous, and the French found a then-almost-forgotten French biologist to commemmorate, to compete with Darwin. So they named a street for him in an area where new streets were being built and named. I don’t know whether this is really an accurate explanation. The Rue de Lamarck is famous in Paris today as it gives its name to a major Metro stop, Lamarck-Coulaincourt. Above you will see the very dramatic entrance to that Metro station, photographed from the Rue de Lamarck. The entrance is between two stairways. Happy 280th, Jean-Baptiste! To read or post comments, first click on the title of this post.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Institutional (and departmental) neutrality</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/institutional-and-departmental.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Institutional (and departmental) neutrality" /><published>2024-07-27T12:58:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-07-27T12:58:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/institutional-and-departmental</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/institutional-and-departmental.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Science_Cover_7_27_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Science magazine cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Cover of this week's issue of &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; magazine. &lt;small&gt;The photo is by David Dee Delgado/Getty Images.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;H. Holden Thorpe, the editor of &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; magazine, ran an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.adr8867&quot;&gt;editorial&lt;/a&gt; this week on institutional neutrality, the idea, as he put it, “that universities in the United States—and especially their presidents—should be politically neutral….” I would add to that the idea that departments and especially their heads should be politically neutral. The editorial is short  and open access, so I think you can read it for yourselves, but he invokes the &lt;a href=&quot;https://provost.uchicago.edu/sites/default/files/documents/reports/KalvenRprt_0.pdf&quot;&gt; Kalven Report&lt;/a&gt;, a mercifully equally short document from the University of Chicago, which declared a “heavy presumption” against universities expressing opinions on political issues or modifying their investments in order to “foster social or political values, however compelling and appealing they may be.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hardly any universities have adopted the Kalven Report as policy, though I gather that a few have adopted the less-stringent &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chicago_principles&quot;&gt;Chicago principles&lt;/a&gt;. Since the war in Gaza, there has been pressure to adopt the Kalven principles, according to Thorpe. For a crash course in the latest activity regarding Kalven or the Chicago principles, see Jerry Coyne’s blog, Why Evolution Is True, &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/category/kalven-report/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thorpe is less of an absolutist regarding Kalven than is Coyne, though he agrees that universities need to be neutral regarding matters of opinion. He draws a distinction, however, between matters of opinion and matters of fact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; But what about matters of science, especially when a finding has powerful political implications such as studies on climate or vaccines? Where should universities draw the line?&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or evolution. Several people told Thorpe that universities must keep strictly away from commenting on any research whatsoever, except to support the right of the researcher to publish that research. Another, Eric Topol, told him that such a stance is “spineless” and appears to dissociate the university from its faculty and their published science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thorpe himself seems somewhat conflicted, and I can understand why, but he expresses concern that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; Stanford University just shut down its disinformation research program after it was hit by lawsuits from conservative groups.… [T]here is a danger that universities will shirk their responsibility to stand up not for any particular finding but for a more overriding principle—the importance of independent scholarship. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Cover of this week's issue of Science magazine. The photo is by David Dee Delgado/Getty Images. H. Holden Thorpe, the editor of Science magazine, ran an editorial this week on institutional neutrality, the idea, as he put it, “that universities in the United States—and especially their presidents—should be politically neutral….” I would add to that the idea that departments and especially their heads should be politically neutral. The editorial is short and open access, so I think you can read it for yourselves, but he invokes the Kalven Report, a mercifully equally short document from the University of Chicago, which declared a “heavy presumption” against universities expressing opinions on political issues or modifying their investments in order to “foster social or political values, however compelling and appealing they may be.” Hardly any universities have adopted the Kalven Report as policy, though I gather that a few have adopted the less-stringent Chicago principles. Since the war in Gaza, there has been pressure to adopt the Kalven principles, according to Thorpe. For a crash course in the latest activity regarding Kalven or the Chicago principles, see Jerry Coyne’s blog, Why Evolution Is True, here. Thorpe is less of an absolutist regarding Kalven than is Coyne, though he agrees that universities need to be neutral regarding matters of opinion. He draws a distinction, however, between matters of opinion and matters of fact: But what about matters of science, especially when a finding has powerful political implications such as studies on climate or vaccines? Where should universities draw the line? Or evolution. Several people told Thorpe that universities must keep strictly away from commenting on any research whatsoever, except to support the right of the researcher to publish that research. Another, Eric Topol, told him that such a stance is “spineless” and appears to dissociate the university from its faculty and their published science. Thorpe himself seems somewhat conflicted, and I can understand why, but he expresses concern that Stanford University just shut down its disinformation research program after it was hit by lawsuits from conservative groups.… [T]here is a danger that universities will shirk their responsibility to stand up not for any particular finding but for a more overriding principle—the importance of independent scholarship. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cheap fossils for only $55!</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/cheap-fossils.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cheap fossils for only $55!" /><published>2024-07-24T11:58:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-07-24T11:58:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/cheap-fossils</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/cheap-fossils.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Duff_Fossils_Under_Ark_Title_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Title slide showing fossils under Ark&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our colleague Dan Phelps, vigilant as usual, has just sent us&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;[a] nice video by Dr. &lt;a href=&quot;https://joelduff.org/&quot;&gt;Joel Duff&lt;/a&gt; about collecting fossils at outcrops adjacent to the Ark Park. I was at these outcrops several years ago and found mostly &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryozoa&quot;&gt;bryozoa&lt;/a&gt; from the Upper Ordovician Kope Formation. The creationist “scientists” at the Ark seem oblivious to the existence of these fossils that don’t jibe with creationist Flood geology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Duff also discusses the grift AiG does of selling bags of fossils in dirt for exorbitant prices (up to $55 a bag for kids to wash out in a fake mining sluice!). This method is obviously not how fossils are typically unearthed, but the kids and parents buying this product wouldn’t be likely to know better. The Ark apparently purchases their fossils from other parts of the world, while not taking advantage of their local abundant fossils.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Duff_Mining_Sluice_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mining sluice&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Sluice for sorting fossils. The prices for these cheap fossils encased in mud range from $8 to $55.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Phelps expresses the hope that Dr. Duff does not give the Ark Park any ideas. Well, he does:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Duff estimates that there may be 1 trillion (yes, not a typo) fossils buried within the Ark’s property. They are encased in layers of limestone and shale, not buried in dirt. Dr. Duff, therefore, recommends that the Ark Park employ a backhoe and dig a trench a few meters deep, so that children can walk into it and see for themselves how real fossils are discovered. He further recommends that children be allowed to sort through the tailings and perhaps take home a small bag full of fossils in return for a modest payment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing they will find is that their small bag of fossils contains a very limited variety, no diatoms, no fish, no reptiles. How come, if the fossils were deposited by a worldwide flood, do we see so little variety over a very large area? Because there was no worldwide flood, and that is why the Ark Park cannot dig the trench and cannot allow the children to pick at the tailings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joel Duff is a professor of biology at the University of Akron. He describes himself &lt;a href=&quot;https://joelduff.org/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; as a Christian who believes, as I understand it, that science is one way of learning about God’s natural world. He blogs as &lt;a href=&quot;https://thenaturalhistorian.com/author/naturalhistorian/&quot;&gt;Naturalis Historia&lt;/a&gt; and is listed as an &lt;a href=&quot;https://biologos.org/people/joel-duff&quot;&gt;author&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://biologos.org/&quot;&gt;BioLogos&lt;/a&gt;. It is regrettable that the Ark Park and other creationists will not listen to him.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Our colleague Dan Phelps, vigilant as usual, has just sent us [a] nice video by Dr. Joel Duff about collecting fossils at outcrops adjacent to the Ark Park. I was at these outcrops several years ago and found mostly bryozoa from the Upper Ordovician Kope Formation. The creationist “scientists” at the Ark seem oblivious to the existence of these fossils that don’t jibe with creationist Flood geology. Dr. Duff also discusses the grift AiG does of selling bags of fossils in dirt for exorbitant prices (up to $55 a bag for kids to wash out in a fake mining sluice!). This method is obviously not how fossils are typically unearthed, but the kids and parents buying this product wouldn’t be likely to know better. The Ark apparently purchases their fossils from other parts of the world, while not taking advantage of their local abundant fossils. Sluice for sorting fossils. The prices for these cheap fossils encased in mud range from $8 to $55. Mr. Phelps expresses the hope that Dr. Duff does not give the Ark Park any ideas. Well, he does:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Holbrookia approximans</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/holbrookia-approximans.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Holbrookia approximans" /><published>2024-07-22T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-07-22T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/holbrookia-approximans</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/holbrookia-approximans.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Joseph Long&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Third Place&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Long_Holbrookia_approximans.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Western earless lizard&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holbrookia_approximans&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Holbrookia approximans&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – Western (or speckled) earless lizard, Pawnee National Grassland, Weld County, Colorado, June 1, 2024. Mr. Long writes, &quot;Note that the subject has apparently escaped an attempt by something else to eat it.  Technical: Olympus OM-D EM-1 Mark III, Olympus 300 mm f/4.0 lens on 2.0x teleconverter, 1/1250 s, f/16, ISO 1000, handheld.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Joseph Long. Photography Contest, Third Place. Holbrookia approximans – Western (or speckled) earless lizard, Pawnee National Grassland, Weld County, Colorado, June 1, 2024. Mr. Long writes, &quot;Note that the subject has apparently escaped an attempt by something else to eat it. Technical: Olympus OM-D EM-1 Mark III, Olympus 300 mm f/4.0 lens on 2.0x teleconverter, 1/1250 s, f/16, ISO 1000, handheld.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Looking for Mr. Goodlink? Re-examining the “Standing” of Sahelanthropus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/looking-for-mr-goodlink.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Looking for Mr. Goodlink? Re-examining the “Standing” of Sahelanthropus" /><published>2024-07-19T13:05:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-07-19T13:05:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/looking-for-mr-goodlink</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/looking-for-mr-goodlink.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Petto_0_Sahelanth_outline_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sahelanthropus&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Andrew J Petto is Distinguished Lecturer Emeritus in the Department of Biological Sciences at the University of Wisconsin–Milwaukee, where he taught anatomy and physiology, human gross anatomy, and kinesiology courses. He is a bioanthropologist with a concentration on primate functional morphology. His latest book, as a co-author with Alice Beck Kehoe, is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.taylorfrancis.com/books/mono/10.4324/9781003226819/humans-alice-beck-kehoe-andrew-petto&quot;&gt;Humans: An Introduction to Four-Field Anthropology&lt;/a&gt;, 2nd ed. New York: Routledge. 2022 (Dec).&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus tchadensis&lt;/i&gt; is the story of the emergence of the human evolutionary branch from the last common ancestor of the African ape clades (evolutionary branches): humans, chimpanzees, and gorillas. It is a story of transitions. To understand the importance of &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; in reconstructing human evolutionary history, we could paraphrase Dobzhansky’s famous quotation: “Nothing in &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; biology makes sense except in the light of evolutionary transition” (Dobzhansky 1973).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since its discovery in 2001, &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus tchadensis&lt;/i&gt;  has intrigued scientists (Brunet et al. 2002). Nicknamed “Toumai” which means “hope of life” in the local language, it is (so far) the oldest fossil on our human evolutionary branch, and it is very close to the time when this evolutionary branch separated from the last common ancestor with the other African great apes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Petto_1_Human_evolution_timeline_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Timeline&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Figure 1: Timeline of Human Evolution. Arrangement of hominin species by their time span in the fossil record.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; is located at the bottom left of the chart in Figure 1, living between 7 and 6 million years before present. (A quick overview of the major findings about this species is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://humanorigins.si.edu/evidence/human-fossils/species/Sahelanthropus-tchadensis&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of the fossil remains reflect what we might expect for a human ancestor at this very early stage of human emergence: a mixture of features that are common to all the African apes, some that are modified from the ancestral form that appear differently from their appearances both in the human and great-ape branches, and several specific modifications of ancestral features that we have never found outside of the human branch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is still very little fossil material from this species, and we have a lot of questions that we cannot answer based on the material we have. Answers to some of these questions—when they finally come—will tell us important things about how early humans made the transition to the peculiar ape descendant that we are today. Others will tell us more about evolution as a process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why there is a lot of debate within the scientific community about this species. The scientific debate is not about whether &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; is an early member of the human evolutionary branch, but about what these remains can tell us about the evolutionary journey from the last common ancestor between humans and our closest ape relatives to our own species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key questions for human paleontology is when our ancestors first became committed to walking upright on two legs. The most recent discussion of &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; is about what the available fossil material can tell us about this important human adaptation (Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology 2024).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ongoing field work and excavation have added a few more remains to the original finds, but the entire collection attributable to &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; remains quite limited. Some questions can be answered by continuing study of the available remains, but for others we can only find final answers if and when we discover more preserved material from more individuals (and maybe from more locations).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; What is a human?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of what we need to know to answer our questions about &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; is “What, exactly, is a human?” (for example, Smithsonian Institution 2024; LeMaître et al 2022). And another important question for understanding the early stage of the emergence of the human evolutionary branch is “How many of all the features that are unique to modern humans does an organism need to have in order to be considered human?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For any hominin so soon after (or maybe still in the process of) branching off from the African great apes, we would look for a number of features that appear only in the human branch of the family modified in a way that is different from how it appears in the other branches. The organism doesn’t need to show &lt;i&gt;everything&lt;/i&gt; that separates humans from other apes, only things that are undisputedly found only in humans and not in our closest ape relatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brunet and his team describe a list of these features in the skull, jaws, and teeth that they excavated (Brunet et al 2002). Guy et al (2005) provide data tables and graphics to show the mosaic of features that tend to be different between humans and African great ape species. It should not be surprising that Guy et al (2005) demonstrate that &lt;i&gt;some&lt;/i&gt; of these features in &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; are more similar to those of humans (living and fossil), some of them are more similar to African great apes, and the rest are somewhere in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few particulars stand out. One major change in almost all the members of the human branch is in the canine teeth in the upper jaw and how they work with the canine and first premolar in the lower jaw. In hominins, the crowns and roots of the upper canines are smaller than in African great apes, and the upper and lower teeth tend to meet their opposites crown-to-crown. The earlier members of the hominin branch will show the &lt;i&gt;tendency&lt;/i&gt; for this change, but the process will not be complete for a few million years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional materials from teeth and lower jaws (Brunet et al 2005) confirmed the analysis in the original reports (Brunet et al 2002) that the upper canine was reduced compared to African great apes (though still somewhat longer than the adjacent teeth), and the arrangements of teeth in the lower jaw were consistent with the pattern in later hominins, rather than in the great ape evolutionary branches most closely related to humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important dental changes was a reduction in the gap (diastema) in the upper jaw between the canine and the lateral incisor where the lower canine would fit when the jaw is closed. In the other primates, the upper canine then slides between the lower canine and first premolar and meets in an interlocking arrangement. This arrangement allows a shearing action when the jaw is closed. These species also show a “honing” surface when the upper canine slides past the lower first premolar to help maintain an edge on the canine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The diastema in the upper jaw and the honing surfaces in the lower jaw are both reduced in all fossil hominins and absent in living hominins (Guy et al, 2005), as shown in Figure 2. In addition, Figure 2 shows the change in shape of the first lower premolar (labeled as P&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;). The surface where the upper teeth make contact with P&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; changes from the part of the tooth oriented toward the front of the jaw to the crown facing the upper jaw. The overall shape of the crown in P&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; in hominins resembles molars more than it does the canines and incisors that perform cutting, slicing, and piercing actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Petto_2_Dentition_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dentition&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Figure 2: Comparison of jaws and teeth of a great ape (chimpanzee), an Australopith, and a modern human. Note the sizes of the diastemata, the sizes and shapes of the canine and premolar teeth, and the change in the shape of the jaw from parallel to arched. Labels translated and rewritten by the author.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key issues in recent exchanges on Toumai concerns changes in human anatomy and behavior related to the way that we walk: standing upright and striding on two legs—technically known as obligate bipedal orthogrady. This means that we walk on two feet and carry our spines perpendicular to the ground, and that no other way of walking is a practical option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Toumai, the parts of the skeleton that give us direct evidence for this behavior are scant, but a recent analysis of thigh bones has been the focus of a mild dispute (see Daver et al 2020; Meyer et al 2023; Cazenave et al 2024). The dispute is over whether there is strong evidence of skeletal adaptations for bearing all the body’s weight only on the legs. Furthermore, a recent analysis of an ulna from the forearm suggests that &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; was bearing weight on the arms at least a significant part of the time (Karoui Canedo et al 2023).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though there are very few specimens involved, the evidence that these studies present is that &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; had not transitioned to standing upright and striding on two legs. Nevertheless, the base of the skull shows an important change associated with an upright posture (Guy et al 2005). The opening in the skull to allow the spinal cord to enter the brain case—the foramen magnum—is shifted forward. In humans, we usually associate this change with upright walking (for example, Neaux et al 2017), because when the spinal column is held perpendicular to the ground, placing the joint between the base of the skull and topmost vertebra under the middle of the skull instead of toward the back allows us to balance our heads with our eyes forward when we stand upright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several other changes in the base of the skull that go along with bipedalism (see for example, Kimbel and Rak 2010). These researchers report that even in &lt;i&gt;Australopithecus afarensis&lt;/i&gt; at 3.7 million years ago—though the foramen magnum and the joint surfaces that allow the skull to work with the first of the vertebrae have moved forward into a position typical of fully bipedal modern humans—a number of other important changes in the base of the skull have not yet been made (and, of course, &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; lacks these modern touches, as well).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Petto_3_Undersides_of_Homo_Pan_Toumai_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Skulls&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Figure 3: Skulls with relative location of the foramen magnum in modern humans, &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt;, and Pan (chimpanzee). Skulls are drawn to same scale for easier comparison.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The position of the foramen magnum in &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; is moved forward compared to its location in the African great apes, but not as far forward as we see in later hominins (Guy et al 2005). Although it is common to say that the more forward position of the foramen magnum is indicative of upright &lt;i&gt;walking&lt;/i&gt; (for example, &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; SI 2024), the evidence from comparative anatomy of the primates indicates that it is rather more indicative of an upright &lt;i&gt;posture&lt;/i&gt;, as we see in several prosimian primate species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These primates do not “walk” upright—they may climb vertical trunks, leap vertically from one tree to another, or clamber holding onto branches above and below as they move— but their preferred &lt;i&gt;posture&lt;/i&gt; is to hold the spinal column perpendicular to the ground, and the result is that the foramen magnum is shifted closer to the front of the skull (Russo and Kirk 2013).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we can conclude from the relative position of the foramen magnum is that &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; was accustomed to a more upright posture, even if further evidence from the limbs, wrists, hips, knees, ankles, and feet may someday tell us that bipedal striding was not the preferred way of getting around. &lt;i&gt;Could&lt;/i&gt; they walk upright? Perhaps, but the available materials from the limbs suggest that they would probably find it difficult. Of course, that does not mean that they could not do it at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For modern humans, we know that walking on two legs is our most efficient way of moving. However, we &lt;i&gt;can&lt;/i&gt; swim, brachiate like gibbons, climb trees like monkeys, hop like sifakas, leap like bush babies, and move in a lot of different ways on the ground, in the trees, and in the water. It is just that we aren’t particularly good at these ways of moving compared with other animals for whom any of these is their primary mode of locomotion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So maybe what later hominins inherited from ancestors like &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt;—or more accurately from the populations of early hominins that were pioneering the anatomic changes that are underway in &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt;— was not a particular style of locomotion, but a preference for a particular posture, and that preference led to adjustments in ways of walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An intriguing possibility for this preferred posture is a behavioral pattern called “extended limb clambering” in Miocene apes—walking on top of a limb while holding onto the limb or branch above oneself (Zhang et al 2024; Böhme et al 2019). Like the illustration at the beginning of this article, Böhme et al (2019) inferred from skeletal anatomy that the Miocene ape species &lt;i&gt;Danuvius guggenmosi&lt;/i&gt; moved through the trees supporting the upper body using its arms to grasp limbs and branches overhead and supporting its lower body using its legs on branches below. This type of locomotion would preserve the preference for an upright posture, but not require the skeletal specializations necessary to stride along the ground on two legs. Those could come later if moving on the ground became an integral part of life in the descendants of at least some Miocene apes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent work on the balance organs of the inner ear gives us another way to assess the transition to bipedalism. Studying the anatomy of the inner ears of fossil and extant primates suggests that the semicircular canals of the inner ear show changes associated with “agility” in movement—that is, carrying out complex movements in multiple dimensions as one might have to do moving among tree trunks, limbs, and branches that do not form a continuous flat surface (Zhang et al 2024; Silcox et al 2009; Spoor et al 2007).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three semicircular canals detect changes in speed and direction of movement relative to the three dimensions of space.  Movements through complex environments like trees require changing the relative positions, speeds, and directions of arms, legs, trunks, heads, and necks during locomotion and produce a lot of changes that the inner ear monitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The information from detecting the movement of fluids in these canals is transmitted to various reflexes and to integrating centers in the brain. The brain then coordinates senses and movements so that the individual can continue to focus on the intended direction of movement and on specific features for navigating through the environment, even as the body changes its orientation and direction frequently. To succeed in their environments, arboreal primates have longer and wider canals than terrestrial ones (relative to body size). Smaller semicircular canals indicate more commitment to simpler locomotor behaviors, for example, walking in a single direction in a plane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we might expect, modern humans tend to have smaller and thinner canals than other primates, when adjusted for body size, suggesting less adaptive pressure for “agility” from complex environments. In the modeling reported by Zhang et al (2024) the rate of change in the size and shape of the semicircular canals increased significantly in hominins about 3.6 million years ago—at about the time when we have undisputed evidence—both anatomic and from footprints—that Australopiths were fully bipedal and at the foundation of a series of anatomic specializations that would make this way of walking more efficient over the next few million years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The form of the semicircular canals in &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; is not yet known. The imaging of this structure is complex, and when skulls are distorted by post-burial pressure it is even more difficult to assess their size, shape, and proportions. However, since skulls are common in the fossil record, the ability to detail the anatomy of the semicircular canals would be useful in determining whether &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; engaged in the more complex array of behaviors seen in arboreal apes or in the more limited set that are typical of bipedal hominins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is Toumai a “missing link”?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most persistent misconceptions about evolutionary change is the concept of “missing links”—organisms that appear as some sort of half-finished transition between ancestors and descendants. The inference is that there should be an uninterrupted series of transitional organisms from one species to another. The more serious error is the failure to see species bearing a mix of transitional features as unique living organisms in their own right, with a suite of biologic and behavioral features that embody an environmental role in relationship to other contemporary species, rather than just as stepping stones on the way to some projected end point: in this case, modern humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This misconception is based on two fundamental misunderstandings of modern evolutionary biology. The first misconception is that evolution is a process in which individuals in one species “turn into” another species, and therefore we ought to see an infinite array of “links” illustrating each of the steps in that process. This leads to the expectation of a “smooth” series of stepwise changes. Any apparent gaps in the expected steps are conceived of as “missing” links in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second misconception is a typologic view of species in which all members of a species are defined by the characteristics of the type specimen—an idealized concept of the defining features of the species. This leads to the unrealistic expectation that that there will be clear boundaries distinguishing one species from another in an evolutionary series. In this case, the “gaps” among species appear when examining the “types” but may be quite a bit less impressive when we consider all the variation among the known members of a species—especially those that deviate the most from the type specimen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biologic variation among individuals in populations (and in species) is one of the most fundamental properties of all life on Earth. How much anatomic variation can we accept within a single species? How different from each other must two specimens be before we can agree that they are different species? We know from DNA analysis that modern &lt;i&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/i&gt;, Neanderthals, and Denisovans mated with each other when the populations encountered each other. Apparently these people did not see themselves as separate species even though some in the scientific community may disagree!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the differences in these misconceptions, when a specimen shows affinities for more than one branch in the tree of life, the reaction is to demand that we come up with the specific features that tell us on which one of the branches (and where on that branch) such specimens lie. People want to know the ancestry that links a particular species to its relatives in the past and the future (and this means identifying the intermediates). As in the case of &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus tchadensis&lt;/i&gt;, answering this question is especially a problem when there is only a very small sample of skeletal remains and when the closest relative in the family tree—in this case, &lt;i&gt;Orrorin tugensis&lt;/i&gt; — is located close to 1 million years and 2700 km away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have only a very limited sample of all the ways that important features can vary among members of this species. The analysis of Macchiarelli et al (2020) shows us how putting this specimen in the context of the range of variability in hominin species allows us to be confident that &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; is an early hominin whether or not it was fully committed to upright walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a very early member of the hominin clade, this species—as one should expect—shows overall anatomic features that strongly resemble those of the African great ape species in this geologic epoch (&lt;a href=&quot;https://ucmp.berkeley.edu/tertiary/miocene.php&quot;&gt;the Miocene&lt;/a&gt;, Polly et al 1994). &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; clearly shows that some anatomic changes that separate humans from the other African great apes have begun to appear in these late Miocene populations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time that &lt;i&gt;Orrorin tugensis&lt;/i&gt; appears, &lt;a href=&quot;https://humanorigins.si.edu/evidence/human-fossils/species/orrorin-tugenensis&quot;&gt; anatomic changes in the neck and the shaft of the femur&lt;/a&gt; show that this bone is responding to the stresses of habitual upright walking (Pickford et al 2002; Richmond and Jungers 2008). This means of locomotion has become common enough in at least one evolutionary branch of humans to show that the bone is responding to the mechanical stresses from bearing the whole weight of the body only on the two legs. These bones were reinforced and thickened in a characteristic pattern shared by bipedal animals, even though many aspects of the bones themselves show a mixture of physical features that resemble those of both Miocene apes who lived earlier and Australopiths who came later (Almécija et al 2013).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Walking Points?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The takeaways from the arguments on bipedalism in &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; are these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, whether &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; walked bipedally or not is an interesting question that needs more indisputable evidence. For now, there are strong hints of habitual upright &lt;i&gt;posture&lt;/i&gt; in this species. Even so—however far along the trajectory of bipedalism &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; has progressed—we should expect the anatomic features to be mixed at this early stage of the transition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is important is that &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; is a species showing some features unique to hominins or intermediate between humans and African great apes mixed with features that are common in all the African great-ape branches. In other words, it is a species in transition. Toumai shows us that this transition was underway at least a million years before we have the first direct anatomic evidence of adaptations to upright walking—so far. What Salehanthropus does is to give us a glimpse into some of the anatomic and behavioral changes that shaped the emergence of the human evolutionary branch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with any evolutionary branch in transition, membership in the human branch of the evolutionary family does not depend on possessing any one anatomic feature or complex—even one as distinctive as bipedalism. Even if &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; did not walk fully upright, it is still a valuable example of biologic variation and evolutionary change near the time of emergence of early humans from their last common ancestor with the African great apes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgment.&lt;/strong&gt; Thanks to Prof Benjamin Campbell in the Department of Anthropology at the University of Wisconsin–Milwaukee for comments, questions, and suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almécija S, Tallman M, Alba DM, Pina M, Moyà-Solà S, Jungers WL. The femur of Orrorin tugenensis exhibits morphometric affinities with both Miocene apes and later hominins. Nature Communications. 2013:4(1):2888. https://doi.org/10.1038/ncomms3888&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Böhme M, Spassov N, Fuss J, Tröscher A, Deane AS, Prieto J, Kirscher U, Lechner T, Begun DR. A new Miocene ape and locomotion in the ancestor of great apes and humans. Nature (London). 2019;575(7783):489–493. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-019-1731-0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brunet M, Guy F, Pilbeam D, et al. A new hominid from the Upper Miocene of Chad, Central Africa. Nature (London). 2002; 418(6894):145–151. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature00879&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brunet M, Guy F, Pilbeam D, Lieberman DE, Likius A, Mackaye HT, Ponce de León MS, Zollikofer CPE, Vignaud P. New material of the earliest hominid from the Upper Miocene of Chad. Nature. 2005; 434(7034):752–755. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature03392&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cazenave M, Pina M, Hammond AS, Böhme M, Begun DR, Spassov N, Gazabón AV, Zanolli C, Bergeret-Medina A, Marchi D, Macchiarelli R, Wood B. Postcranial evidence does not support habitual bipedalism in &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt; tchadensis: A reply to Daver et al. (2020). [Commentary]. Journal of Human Evolution. 2024 (in press); 103557. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhevol.2024.103557.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daver G, Guy F, Mackaye HT, Likius A, Boisserie J-R, Moussa A, Pallas L, Vignaud P, Clarisse ND. Postcranial evidence of late Miocene hominin bipedalism in Chad. Nature (London). 2022; 609(7925):94–100. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-022-04901-z&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dobzhansky T. Nothing in biology makes sense except in the light of evolution. American Biology Teacher. 1973;35(3):125–129. doi:10.2307/4444260.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guy F, Lieberman DE, Pilbeam D, de León MP, Likius A, Mackaye HT, Vignaud P, Zollikofer C, Brunet M. Morphological affinities of the &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus tchadensis&lt;/i&gt; (late Miocene hominid from Chad) cranium. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences – PNAS. 2005;102(52):18836–18841. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0509564102&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karoui Canedo J, Daver G, Blasi-Toccacceli A, Clarisse ND, Likius A, Mackaye HT, Moussa A, Mahamat A, Pallas L, Surault J, Guy F. Ulnar morphology in &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus tchadensis&lt;/i&gt;, what it tells us on the locomotor repertoire of the last common ancestor of humans and chimpanzees (LCA). Bulletins et Mémoires de La Société d’Anthropologie de Paris. 2024;36(suppl). https://doi.org/10.4000/bmsap.12956&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kimbel WH, Rak Y. The cranial base of Australopithecus afarensis: New insights from the female skull. Phil Trans R Soc B. 2010;365:3365–3376. https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2010.0070.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Le Maître A, Daver G, Mounier A, Prat S, Villotte S, Noûs C. Peut-on définir l’humanité? Une perspective théorique et empirique. Bulletins et mémoires de la Société d’Anthropologie de Paris. 2022; 34(2). https://doi.org/10.4000/bmsap.10434&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Macchiarelli R, Bergeret-Medina A, Marchi D, Wood B. Nature and relationships of &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus tchadensis&lt;/i&gt;. Journal of Human Evolution. 2020;149:102898. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhevol.2020.102898&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology. What about bipedalism in &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt;? Accessed 5 July 2024. https://www.mpg.de/22183908/what-about-bipedalism-in-&lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meyer MR, Jung JP, Spear JK, Araiza IF, Galway-Witham J, Williams SA. Knuckle-walking in &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus&lt;/i&gt;? Locomotor inferences from the ulnae of fossil hominins and other hominoids. Journal of Human Evolution. 2023;179:103355. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhevol.2023.103355.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neaux D, Bienvenu T, Guy F, Daver G, Sansalone G, Ledogar JA, Rae TC, Wroe S, Brunet M. Relationship between foramen magnum position and locomotion in extant and extinct hominoids. Journal of Human Evolution. 2017;113:1–9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhevol.2017.07.009&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pickford M, Senut B, Gommery D, Treil J. Bipedalism in &lt;i&gt;Orrorin tugenensi &lt;/i&gt; revealed by its femora. Comptes Rendus Palevol. 2002;1(4):191–203. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1631-0683(02)00028-3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polly D, Speer B, Smith D, et al. The Miocene Epoch. Understanding Evolution. Berkeley: University of California Museum of Paleontology. April 1994. Updated June 2011. Accessed 9 July 2024. https://ucmp.berkeley.edu/tertiary/miocene.php.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richmond BG, Jungers WL. &lt;i&gt;Orrorin tugenensis&lt;/i&gt; Femoral morphology and the evolution of hominin bipedalism. Science. 2008;319:1662-1665(2008). https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1154197&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russo GA, Kirk EC. Foramen magnum position in bipedal mammals. Journal of Human Evolution. 2013;65(5):656–670. http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jhevol.2013.07.007&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silcox MT, Bloch JI, Boyer DM, Godinot M, Ryan TM, Spoor F, Walker A. Semicircular canal system in early primates. Journal of Human Evolution. 2009;56(3):315–327. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhevol.2008.10.007&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spoor F, Garland Jr T, Krovitz G, Ryan TM, Silcox MT, Walker A. The primate semicircular canal system and locomotion. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences – PNAS. 2007;104(26):10808–10812. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0704250104&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smithsonian Institution (SI). What does it mean to be human? Human Characteristics. Washington (DC): Smithsonian Institution. Updated 3 Jan 2024. Accessed 15 July 2024. https://humanorigins.si.edu/human-characteristics&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smithsonian Institution (SI). What does it mean to be human? &lt;i&gt;Sahelanthropus tchadensis&lt;/i&gt;. Washington (DC): Smithsonian Institution. Updated 3 Jan 2024. Accessed 9 July 2024. https://humanorigins.si.edu/evidence/human-fossils/species/Sahelanthropus-tchadensis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smithsonian Institution (SI). What does it mean to be human? &lt;i&gt;Orrorin tugensis&lt;/i&gt;. Washington (DC): Smithsonian Institution. Updated 3 Jan 2024. Accessed 9 July 2024. https://humanorigins.si.edu/evidence/human-fossils/species/orrorin-tugenensis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zhang Y, Ni X, Li Q, Stidham T, Lu D, Gao F, Zhang C, Harrison T. (2024). &lt;i&gt;Lufengpithecus&lt;/i&gt; inner ear provides evidence of a common locomotor repertoire ancestral to human bipedalism. Innovation (New York). 2024;5(2):100580–100580. H 8&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew J Petto</name></author><summary type="html">Andrew J Petto is Distinguished Lecturer Emeritus in the Department of Biological Sciences at the University of Wisconsin–Milwaukee, where he taught anatomy and physiology, human gross anatomy, and kinesiology courses. He is a bioanthropologist with a concentration on primate functional morphology. His latest book, as a co-author with Alice Beck Kehoe, is Humans: An Introduction to Four-Field Anthropology, 2nd ed. New York: Routledge. 2022 (Dec). The story of Sahelanthropus tchadensis is the story of the emergence of the human evolutionary branch from the last common ancestor of the African ape clades (evolutionary branches): humans, chimpanzees, and gorillas. It is a story of transitions. To understand the importance of Sahelanthropus in reconstructing human evolutionary history, we could paraphrase Dobzhansky’s famous quotation: “Nothing in Sahelanthropus biology makes sense except in the light of evolutionary transition” (Dobzhansky 1973). Since its discovery in 2001, Sahelanthropus tchadensis has intrigued scientists (Brunet et al. 2002). Nicknamed “Toumai” which means “hope of life” in the local language, it is (so far) the oldest fossil on our human evolutionary branch, and it is very close to the time when this evolutionary branch separated from the last common ancestor with the other African great apes. Figure 1: Timeline of Human Evolution. Arrangement of hominin species by their time span in the fossil record. Sahelanthropus is located at the bottom left of the chart in Figure 1, living between 7 and 6 million years before present. (A quick overview of the major findings about this species is available here.)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Book: The Kingdom, the Power, and the Glory</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/book-the-kingdom.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book: The Kingdom, the Power, and the Glory" /><published>2024-07-18T12:20:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-07-18T12:20:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/book-the-kingdom</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/book-the-kingdom.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Alberta_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A relative of mine is a practicing psychologist. Among other things, she favors trans women participating in women’s sports and affirmative care for transgender teenagers. Quite innocently, I asked her whether she had ever read the book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Irreversible-Damage-Transgender-Seducing-Daughters-ebook/dp/B07YL6XK55/&quot;&gt;Irreversible Damage: The Transgender Craze Seducing Our Daughters&lt;/a&gt;, by Abigail Shrier. She responded by making what is conventionally called “a face.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think she should read the book, if only to find out firsthand what her adversaries think. As for me, I have long since tired of Dembski, Behe, Schroeder, and their ilk, not to mention Ken Ham, so I turned to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Kingdom-Power-Glory-Evangelicals-Extremism-ebook/dp/B0BTYWH2YP&quot;&gt;The Kingdom, the Power, and the Glory&lt;/a&gt;, subtitled American Evangelicals in an Age of Extremism, by the veteran journalist Tim Alberta. And a splendid book it is, despite your probably justified suspicion that Alberta and I would agree on very little, theologically and possibly politically (according to his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bytimalberta.com&quot;&gt;home page&lt;/a&gt;, Alberta worked for the &lt;i&gt;National Review&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;Politico&lt;/i&gt;, and now &lt;i&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/i&gt;, so we may be observing some evolution in action, but I could not find anything specifically concerning his political affiliation, if any).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book concerns Christian nationalism, and how so many American evangelicals, in my reading, at least, learned to idolatrize the United States and conflate their conservative religious beliefs with conservative, even reactionary politics. Alberta gets his material by traveling around the country for approximately 4 years and interviewing countless evangelical pastors and their parishioners. Though I found the book a little long at times, I thought it worked well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is written in three parts, besides a prologue and an epilogue. The three parts, not surprisingly, are The Kingdom, The Power, and The Glory. You could get almost everything you needed to know about the book from reading the epilogue, but I think you would miss a lot. The identity of The Kingdom was a little obscure to me, but probably refers to the United States, which many evangelicals have convinced themselves was founded as a Christian nation. The Power shows how many evangelical churches were taken over by a tacit conspiracy of Christian nationalists and hucksters. And the chapter on The Glory details the stories of those who have resisted or are fighting back. The biggest villain in the book, I think, was probably Jerry Falwell, Jr. Among several heroes were Chris Winans, the pastor who succeeded Alberta’s father and was practically drummed out of his own church, and Rachael Denhollander, a layperson who fought against strong opposition to expose sexual predators in the church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book has been out for 7 or 8 months now, and I do not want to go into detail. You may find excellent reviews in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2023/12/02/books/review/the-kingdom-the-power-and-the-glory-tim-alberta.html&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Times&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/books/2023/12/07/kingdom-power-glory-evangelicals-extremism-tim-alberta-review/&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Post&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/books/2023/dec/02/kingdom-power-glory-review-tim-alberta-trump-evangelical&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Guardian&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.christianitytoday.com/ct/2024/january-web-only/tim-alberta-kingdom-power-glory-american-evangelicals.html&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Christianity Today&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the blog &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/the-kingdom-the-power-and-the-glory-american-evangelicals-in-an-age-of-extremism-a-review/&quot;&gt;Righting America&lt;/a&gt;, and elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Readers of PT may be disappointed to find that Ken Ham is not mentioned once. Rather than worry about creationists, Alberta shows how people can be swept up by a sort of herd mentality, abandon churches that preach conservative Christianity, and instead flock to churches that preach Christian nationalism, that is, conservative or evangelical Christianity married to very right-wing politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you watch the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/newshour/show/tim-alberta-discusses-his-new-book-exploring-american-evangelicals-and-political-extremism&quot;&gt;PBS News Hour interview with Tim Alberta&lt;/a&gt;, you will discover how white Americans, who used to be in the majority, find that they are losing status and feel under siege, even though to my mind they are on the verge of a takeover even more clearly now than when the book was issued. Indeed, they are more than willing to demolish the wall between church and state, and make Christianity at least implicitly a state religion. As noted in the News Hour, they may not accept the outcome of a democratic election that they have lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By “Christianity,” of course, they mean “evangelical Christianity,” and I am sorry to note that throughout the book Alberta also conflates Christianity with evangelical Christianity. I was also a little bit put off by what I thought was his implicit assumption that the religion of Jesus was the Only Right One, but that could be me reading something unwarranted into the text.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">A relative of mine is a practicing psychologist. Among other things, she favors trans women participating in women’s sports and affirmative care for transgender teenagers. Quite innocently, I asked her whether she had ever read the book, Irreversible Damage: The Transgender Craze Seducing Our Daughters, by Abigail Shrier. She responded by making what is conventionally called “a face.” I think she should read the book, if only to find out firsthand what her adversaries think. As for me, I have long since tired of Dembski, Behe, Schroeder, and their ilk, not to mention Ken Ham, so I turned to The Kingdom, the Power, and the Glory, subtitled American Evangelicals in an Age of Extremism, by the veteran journalist Tim Alberta. And a splendid book it is, despite your probably justified suspicion that Alberta and I would agree on very little, theologically and possibly politically (according to his home page, Alberta worked for the National Review, Politico, and now The Atlantic, so we may be observing some evolution in action, but I could not find anything specifically concerning his political affiliation, if any). The book concerns Christian nationalism, and how so many American evangelicals, in my reading, at least, learned to idolatrize the United States and conflate their conservative religious beliefs with conservative, even reactionary politics. Alberta gets his material by traveling around the country for approximately 4 years and interviewing countless evangelical pastors and their parishioners. Though I found the book a little long at times, I thought it worked well.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cotinis mutabilis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/cotinis-mutabilis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cotinis mutabilis" /><published>2024-07-15T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-07-15T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/cotinis-mutabilis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/cotinis-mutabilis.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;John Trawick&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Second Place&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Trawick_Cotinis_mutabilis_on_PonytailPalm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Figeater beetle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ipm.ucanr.edu/PMG/GARDEN/FRUIT/PESTS/grfruitbeetle.html&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Cotinis mutabilis&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – figeater beetle (green fruit beetle) feeding on the flower stalk of a ponytail palm (&lt;i&gt;Beaucarnea recurvata&lt;/i&gt;). Mr. Trawick writes, &quot;&lt;i&gt;C. mutabilis&lt;/i&gt; eats tomatoes and other fruits, so can be kind of a pest, though the brilliant green color is beautiful. Ponytail palms are not true palms, being more closely related to agave and yucca plants.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by John Trawick. Photography Contest, Second Place. Cotinis mutabilis – figeater beetle (green fruit beetle) feeding on the flower stalk of a ponytail palm (Beaucarnea recurvata). Mr. Trawick writes, &quot;C. mutabilis eats tomatoes and other fruits, so can be kind of a pest, though the brilliant green color is beautiful. Ponytail palms are not true palms, being more closely related to agave and yucca plants.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Vitalism in New Zealand science education (in Science Magazine)</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/vitalism-NZ-science_education2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vitalism in New Zealand science education (in Science Magazine)" /><published>2024-07-12T01:24:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-07-12T01:24:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/vitalism-NZ-science_education2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/vitalism-NZ-science_education2.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Science_2024-07-12_letters.png&quot; alt=&quot;[Screenshots of Science 2024 letters on Mātauranga Māori]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Screenshots of Science 2024 letters on Mātauranga Māori&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Panda’s Thumb readers may recall &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/2024-07-12-vitalism-NZ-science_education.html&quot;&gt;my 2022 post&lt;/a&gt; on the controversy in New Zealand about the the NZ Ministry of Education sticking the concept of “mauri” into the high school Chemistry/Biology curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said at the time, this content was a big problem scientifically, as it was inserting vitalism into basic chemistry. I also made a prediction which some were skeptical of, that it would eventually have to be taken out. In October 2022, Paul Kilmartin, the chemistry professor whose talk I quoted, published a detailed analysis of the issue in &lt;a href=&quot;https://nzic.org.nz/unsecure_files/cinz/2022-86-4.pdf&quot;&gt;the journal &lt;i&gt;Chemistry in New Zealand&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spectator.co.uk/article/why-im-sticking-up-for-science/&quot;&gt;Richard Dawkins&lt;/a&gt; and others eventually commented.  In early 2024, &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; published a Policy Forum article, by Black and Tyliankankis, “&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Teach Indigenous knowledge alongside science&lt;/a&gt;,” which cited Dawkins’s critique and rebutted it by proclaiming the virtues of the Ministry of Education’s policy of “Mana ōrite: equal status for mātauranga Māori.” However, Black and Tyliankankis left out any discussion of Dawkins’s mention of vitalism, or indeed any discussion of the controversy over the mauri/vitalism issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I viewed this as pretty misleading, especially because, in late 2022, the Ministry of Education’s mana ōrite policy began to come crashing down, at least for science education. Mauri and a variety of other material was stripped out, the schedule for the rollout of the NCEA Level 1 science curriculum (15-16 year olds) was pushed back by years (it looks like the whole approach may be being scrapped by the new government, elected in late 2023; NCEA Levels 2 and 3 have been pushed back by several more years), and several other scandals involving the science curriculum reform &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.google.com/search?q=science%20education%20nz&amp;amp;hl=en-NZ&amp;amp;gl=NZ&amp;amp;ceid=NZ%3Aen&quot;&gt;hit the news in 2023-2024&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To inform &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;’s readership about some of the problems, I wrote a response letter which has just been published. Another response was also published by a group of New Zealand scientists and academics (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ado6679&quot;&gt;Adhar et al. 2024&lt;/a&gt;), along with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ado9278&quot;&gt;a reply from Black and Tylianakis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I paste the final text of my letter below. Here is a link to free access to my and other letters: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/stoken/author-tokens/ST-1981/full&quot;&gt;https://www.science.org/stoken/author-tokens/ST-1981/full&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;(Asides: (1) Unfortunately, some copyediting misadventure occurred after my last look at the proof; I clarify after the main text. (2) I have added the full references for google-ability. (3) If it had been up to me, I would not have italicized “mauri” except for the first non-quoted instance. I follow my preference below.)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Vitalism in New Zealand science education&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
NICHOLAS J. MATZKE&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;SCIENCE&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
11 Jul 2024&lt;br /&gt;
Vol 385, Issue 6705&lt;br /&gt;
p. 152&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
DOI: &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.ado6728&quot;&gt;10.1126/science.ado6728&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A. Black and J. M. Tylianakis (&quot;Teach Indigenous knowledge alongside science,&quot; Policy Forum, 9 February, p. 592) give an overly rosy picture of New Zealand's policy of &quot;mana ōrite,&quot; or equal status for mātauranga Māori, in science education, which they say teaches Indigenous knowledge &quot;alongside&quot; science rather than &quot;as&quot; science. They suggest that this policy avoids problems such as teaching creationist myths in science class. However, the New Zealand Ministry of Education placed supernatural content directly into science and math curricula with no clarification that it was nonscientific material.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
The chemistry curriculum required students to &quot;recognise that mauri is present in all matter which exists as particles held together by attractive forces&quot; (1), with a glossary that defined &lt;i&gt;mauri&lt;/i&gt; as &quot;[t]he vital essence, life force of everything.&quot; This concept, known as vitalism, has long been debunked (2). Teaching concepts that directly conflict with empirical evidence undermines the goals of science education. Dozens of science teachers opposed the inclusion of mauri in the chemistry curriculum, but the Ministry steamrolled their objections, citing &quot;the requirement for mana ōrite&quot; (1). The objective was only removed after 18 months of controversy, at a time when the 2023 election was looming. The Ministry, ignoring vitalism's evidentiary flaws, claimed the reversal occurred because inserting concepts such as mauri into science curricula ran the &quot;risk of recolonisation&quot; (3), despite the fact that mana ōrite's entire rationale was decolonization.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Problems remain in 2024. Despite its removal from exam objectives, mauri remains in the chemistry curriculum, in which students are told, &quot;Revisit the concept of mauri (&lt;a href=&quot;http://giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&quot;&gt;giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&lt;/a&gt; [in the publication, ref. 4 was substituted for the link]). This learning can sit beside learnings in atomic theory&quot; (5), and the Gulf Innovation Fund Together website (4) says that mauri is &quot;the force that interpenetrates all things to bind and knit them together.&quot; A math qualification on practical problems of &quot;life in...the Pacific&quot; asks trigonometry students to calculate how much flaxen rope the demigod Maui made to lasso the Sun, slowing it to lengthen the day (6). The text of the exercise is studiously agnostic about the literal truth of this story, describing it as a &quot;narrative.&quot; Black and Tylianakis might categorize this as teaching Indigenous knowledge alongside math, but teachers face the prospect of strife among students over whether it is appropriate to call it knowledge or myth and if students of various backgrounds are expected to defend or disclaim its verity.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Black and Tylianakis provide some examples of cases in which Indigenous knowledge can unproblematically sit alongside science, such as uses of a particular plant. However, the Ministry's failure to avoid supernatural content indicates that the mana ōrite policy operated with a postmodern relativist philosophy that gave equal status to poorly evidenced ideas. If the policy goal is cross-cultural understanding and appreciation of Māori interests, values, philosophy, and worldview, then the curriculum should include a nonscience class or unit that provides an overview of the traditional worldview as an integrated belief system and also gives due attention to the diversity of beliefs among Māori today.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;References&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
1. Paul Kilmartin (2022). Mātauranga Māori and chemistry teaching: 'mauri is present in all matter.' &lt;i&gt;Chemistry in New Zealand&lt;/i&gt;. 86, 157 (2022). &lt;a href=&quot;https://nzic.org.nz/unsecure_files/cinz/2022-86-4.pdf&quot;&gt;https://nzic.org.nz/unsecure_files/cinz/2022-86-4.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
2. Peter J. Ramberg (2000). The Death of Vitalism and The Birth of Organic Chemistry: Wohler's Urea Synthesis and the Disciplinary Identity of Organic Chemistry. &lt;i&gt;Ambix&lt;/i&gt; 47, 170 (2000). &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1179/amb.2000.47.3.170&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1179/amb.2000.47.3.170&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
3. Sara Tolbert, Rosemary Hipkins, Bronwen Cowie, Pauline Waiti (2024). Epistemic agency, Indigenous knowledge, and the school science curriculum: reflections from Aotearoa New Zealand. &lt;i&gt;International Journal of Science Education&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/09500693.2024.2356229&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/09500693.2024.2356229&lt;/a&gt; (2024).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
4. Gulf Innovation Fund Together (GIFT), &quot;What is Mauri?&quot; (2020); &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&quot;&gt;https://www.giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
5. New Zealand Ministry of Education (2024); &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/chemistry-and-biology?view=teaching&quot;&gt;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/chemistry-and-biology?view=teaching&lt;/a&gt; . Download &quot;CB Level 1 Course Outline 3&quot; and see page 3.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
6. New Zealand Ministry of Education (2024); Mathematics and Statistics / Assessment / 1.2 / Activities / Activity A / Ko Māui me te Rā: Ākonga will use mathematics to explore the pūrākau of how Māui and his brothers slowed down Tama-nui-te-rā. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/mathematics-and-statistics/mathematics-and-statistics/1/2?view=activities&quot;&gt;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/mathematics-and-statistics/mathematics-and-statistics/1/2?view=activities&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;


&lt;b&gt;RELATED LETTERS&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Black, Amanda; Tylianakis, Jason M. (2024). Teach Indigenous knowledge alongside science. &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;, 383(6683), 592-594. February 9, 2024.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.adi9606&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.adi9606&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.adi9606&quot;&gt;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.adi9606&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Ahdar, Rex; Boyd, Brian; Chaudhuri, Ananish; Clements, Kendall D.; Cooper, Garth; Elliffe, 
Douglas; Gill, Brian; Gray, Russell D.; Hamilton-Hart,  Natasha; Lillis, David; Matthews, Michael; Raine, John; Rata, Elizabeth; Schwerdtfeger, Peter (2024). World science and Indigenous knowledge. &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;, 385(6705), 151-152. July 12, 2024. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.ado6679&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.ado6679&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ado6679&quot;&gt;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ado6679&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Matzke, Nicholas J. (2024). Vitalism in New Zealand science education. &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;, 385(6705), 152. July 12, 2024. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.ado6728&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.ado6728&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ado6728&quot;&gt;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ado6728&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Free link: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/stoken/author-tokens/ST-1981/full&quot;&gt;https://www.science.org/stoken/author-tokens/ST-1981/full&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Black, Amanda; Tylianakis, Jason M. (2024). Vitalism in New Zealand science education -- Response. &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;, 385(6705), 152-3. July 12, 2024. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.ado9278&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.ado9278&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ado9278&quot;&gt;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ado9278&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Typo issue&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published version:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
Problems remain in 2024. Despite its removal from exam objectives, mauri remains in the chemistry curriculum, in which students are told, &quot;Revisit the concept of mauri&quot; (4). This learning can sit beside learnings in atomic theory&quot; (5), and the Gulf Innovation Fund Together website (4) says that mauri is &quot;the force that interpenetrates all things to bind and knit them together.&quot;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Matzke says: This sentence somehow got garbled in a final copyedit, after my last look at the proof.  Presumably this was due to there being a link in the original verbatim quote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original read (using the published citation numbers):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
Despite its removal from exam objectives, mauri remains in the chemistry curriculum, in which students are told, &quot;Revisit the concept of mauri (&lt;a href=&quot;http://giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&quot;&gt;giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&lt;/a&gt;). This learning can sit beside learnings in atomic theory,&quot; (5) and the link (4) says that mauri is &quot;the force that interpenetrates all things to bind and knit them together.&quot;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Brief further comments&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the response by Black and Tylianakis mostly speaks for itself. Critical issues remain unaddressed, including the importance of evidence for the content taught in science classes, the definitions of &lt;i&gt;knowledge&lt;/i&gt; versus &lt;i&gt;belief&lt;/i&gt;, how the problems of postmodern relativism can be avoided, and what the heck actually happened to produce the Ministry of Education’s mauri-in-chemistry curriculum episode of 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If both scientists and Mātauranga Māori experts were actually &lt;i&gt;against&lt;/i&gt; mauri-in-chemistry, how the heck did it get in?  Why were the objections of science teachers – in the end, well-informed and correct objections – &lt;i&gt;overridden&lt;/i&gt; by the Ministry of Education, specifically by referencing the “mana ōrite” policy?  Why did it take 18 months to make the correction?  Why wasn’t the correction actually done thoroughly, instead of some of this material being reintroduced via example materials, still online in 2024?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Education touted an extensive series of expert review committees to advise the NCEA Change Process, including specifically experts on Mātauranga Māori. In addition to the Subject Expert Groups (SEG), which provided the expertise on science content for NCEA, the Ministry of Education quite publicly announced an elaborate feedback system for drafting the new curriculum. It included these formal entities to provide expertise and expert feedback:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
Te Whakaruruhau - Mātauranga Māori experts&lt;br /&gt;
NCEA Māori Panel&lt;br /&gt;
Māori Pathways Advisory Group&lt;br /&gt;
NCEA Mātauranga Māori Expert Reviewers&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The descriptions are online here:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://curriculumtimelines.education.govt.nz/sector-reach-advice-and-input/&quot;&gt;https://curriculumtimelines.education.govt.nz/sector-reach-advice-and-input/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s my guess. I think what &lt;i&gt;actually&lt;/i&gt; happened is that a lot of people at the Ministry of Education &lt;i&gt;thought&lt;/i&gt; that including mauri in chemistry was a great idea and an instance of implementing the mana ōrite policy. Experts were either not consulted, or didn’t realize the embarrassing scientific problems that would result.  Ministry staff who were skeptical either kept quiet, or were overridden, in the highly ideological environment that prevails in many academic and governmental institutions, especially in 2020-2021.  Initial objections from science teachers were overridden as just being objections from colonialist-hangover sticks in the mud, people with objections to be swept aside in the coming decolonialisation revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, once the curriculum was online publicly, scientists objected, the story went international, and it became sufficiently embarrassing that higher-ups at the Ministry of Education, and experts, took another look and re-thought it, resulting in partial corrections in late 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, with the 2023 election looming, the retroactive explanation started, with Rosemary Hipkins (cited above; and, coincidentally, mother of Chris Hipkins, Minister of Education from 2017-2023 and New Zealand’s Prime Minister from January 2023 through to the election loss in October 2023) proffering the “recolonisation” explanation for why mauri-in-chemistry was bad. Rosemary Hipkins first made this claim &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencelearn.org.nz/resources/3228-enduring-competencies-for-designing-science-learning-pathways&quot;&gt;in PLD training sessions for teachers&lt;/a&gt; in early 2023 (PLD sessions – Professional Learning and Development). (The mauri/recolonisation discussion occurs at about minute 19.) In May 2024, the same recolonisation claim is made in the publication of Tolbert, Hipkins et al. 2024, cited above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black and Tylianakis introduce another, different explanation, “The change was made because of inappropriate and inadequate references supporting its use.” But how could this have possibly happened, with all of the expert advice the Ministry of Education had recruited?  It’s not like scientists were begging for mauri to be included in chemistry!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, are Black and Tylianakis saying that &lt;a href=&quot;http://giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&quot;&gt;giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&lt;/a&gt;, cited in several places in NCEA Level 1 materials pertaining to mauri (from 2021-present), is actually an “inappropriate and inadequate reference”? Are they saying the speakers in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&quot;&gt;giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&lt;/a&gt; webpages/videos are making &lt;i&gt;incorrect&lt;/i&gt; statements of mātauranga Māori when they endorse (several times) interpretations of mauri involving molecular forces and vibrations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the legend of Maui and the Sun, this requires a longer post.  Briefly, I agree that the story could have truths and/or value in the sense of its literary, cultural, artistic (etc.) aspects.  But (a) if so, why is none of this mentioned in the cited Maths curriculum as it was posted online? (b) Why would this be useful or important in a trigonometry assignment in a math class? (c) What are the grand nonliteral truths of this story?  It’s a nice story, my daughters have already learned it in New Zealand daycare.  But the purpose of a curriculum is to &lt;i&gt;explain&lt;/i&gt; what the learning objectives are and how the material gets students there, not to leave everyone guessing. (d) Are Black and Tylianakis prepared to say that, yes, parts of Mātauranga Māori are legend and myth, and that is it OK for teachers, students, and scientists to say so, when it really does appear to be the case?  (Cases of legends with some historical truth are a different matter.)  There is tremendous pushback in New Zealand against the phrase “myths and legends”, so speaking the plain truth on these matters seems to often be viewed very negatively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, (e) How does any of this help students learn trigonometry?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Matzke</name></author><summary type="html">Screenshots of Science 2024 letters on Mātauranga Māori Panda’s Thumb readers may recall my 2022 post on the controversy in New Zealand about the the NZ Ministry of Education sticking the concept of “mauri” into the high school Chemistry/Biology curriculum. As I said at the time, this content was a big problem scientifically, as it was inserting vitalism into basic chemistry. I also made a prediction which some were skeptical of, that it would eventually have to be taken out. In October 2022, Paul Kilmartin, the chemistry professor whose talk I quoted, published a detailed analysis of the issue in the journal Chemistry in New Zealand. Richard Dawkins and others eventually commented. In early 2024, Science published a Policy Forum article, by Black and Tyliankankis, “Teach Indigenous knowledge alongside science,” which cited Dawkins’s critique and rebutted it by proclaiming the virtues of the Ministry of Education’s policy of “Mana ōrite: equal status for mātauranga Māori.” However, Black and Tyliankankis left out any discussion of Dawkins’s mention of vitalism, or indeed any discussion of the controversy over the mauri/vitalism issue. I viewed this as pretty misleading, especially because, in late 2022, the Ministry of Education’s mana ōrite policy began to come crashing down, at least for science education. Mauri and a variety of other material was stripped out, the schedule for the rollout of the NCEA Level 1 science curriculum (15-16 year olds) was pushed back by years (it looks like the whole approach may be being scrapped by the new government, elected in late 2023; NCEA Levels 2 and 3 have been pushed back by several more years), and several other scandals involving the science curriculum reform hit the news in 2023-2024. To inform Science’s readership about some of the problems, I wrote a response letter which has just been published. Another response was also published by a group of New Zealand scientists and academics (Adhar et al. 2024), along with a reply from Black and Tylianakis. I paste the final text of my letter below. Here is a link to free access to my and other letters: https://www.science.org/stoken/author-tokens/ST-1981/full (Asides: (1) Unfortunately, some copyediting misadventure occurred after my last look at the proof; I clarify after the main text. (2) I have added the full references for google-ability. (3) If it had been up to me, I would not have italicized “mauri” except for the first non-quoted instance. I follow my preference below.) Vitalism in New Zealand science education NICHOLAS J. MATZKE SCIENCE 11 Jul 2024 Vol 385, Issue 6705 p. 152 DOI: 10.1126/science.ado6728 A. Black and J. M. Tylianakis (&quot;Teach Indigenous knowledge alongside science,&quot; Policy Forum, 9 February, p. 592) give an overly rosy picture of New Zealand's policy of &quot;mana ōrite,&quot; or equal status for mātauranga Māori, in science education, which they say teaches Indigenous knowledge &quot;alongside&quot; science rather than &quot;as&quot; science. They suggest that this policy avoids problems such as teaching creationist myths in science class. However, the New Zealand Ministry of Education placed supernatural content directly into science and math curricula with no clarification that it was nonscientific material.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ardea herodias herodias</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/ardea-herodias.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ardea herodias herodias" /><published>2024-07-08T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-07-08T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/ardea-herodias</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/ardea-herodias.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Winner&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Denelsbeck_Ardea_herodias_herodias.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Great Blue Heron&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Great_Blue_Heron/overview&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Ardea herodias herodias&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – great blue heron with red-bellied watersnake &lt;a href=&quot;https://herpsofnc.org/red-bellied-watersnake&quot;&gt;Nerodia erythrogaster&lt;/a&gt;. Mr. Denelsbeck writes, &quot;Late afternoon on World Migratory Bird Day last year, having little luck all day, my brother spotted this heron and we realized it had a capture. The snake was still writhing as we attempted to get close enough for a clean shot, and managed it just before the heron flew off with its prey. It's challenging enough for a heron to get a large fish in the right position to swallow whole &amp;ndash; I imagine it's quite a bit harder with something as wickedly aggressive as a watersnake, though we missed that action. There are now &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_blue_heron&quot;&gt;four recognized subspecies of great blue herons&lt;/a&gt;, with the possibility of &lt;i&gt;A. h. wardi&lt;/i&gt; creeping into the area, but this is much more likely &lt;i&gt;A. h. herodias&lt;/i&gt;, as noted. Canon 7D, Tamron SP 150-600 at 600mm, handheld, cropped.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We received only around a dozen submissions this year, and all were very good indeed. In the past, we have polled our readers, but participation in the polls has dropped off. We therefore decided, consistently with Rules 8 and 12, to choose the winners ourselves rather than poll our readers. In this endeavor, we enlisted the assistance of our Wife and Harshest Critic, Deanna, and also our Son the Geek, David. Deanna grew up making dye transfers, and David is a formidable photographer himself. The one thing we three agreed upon was to place Al Denelsbeck’s photograph of what David called “sad snake, happy bird” first. We will announce the runner-up and the bronze medalist, so to speak, in subsequent weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Denelsbeck, who blogs &lt;a href=&quot;https://wading-in.net/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, will be offered his choice between Why Intelligent Design Fails, A Scientific Critique of the New Creationism, edited by Taner Edis and me (and autographed by me); and What’s Gotten Into You by Dan Levitt, generously contributed by NCSE. The runner-up will be offered the remaining book.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Al Denelsbeck. Photography Contest, Winner. Ardea herodias herodias – great blue heron with red-bellied watersnake Nerodia erythrogaster. Mr. Denelsbeck writes, &quot;Late afternoon on World Migratory Bird Day last year, having little luck all day, my brother spotted this heron and we realized it had a capture. The snake was still writhing as we attempted to get close enough for a clean shot, and managed it just before the heron flew off with its prey. It's challenging enough for a heron to get a large fish in the right position to swallow whole &amp;ndash; I imagine it's quite a bit harder with something as wickedly aggressive as a watersnake, though we missed that action. There are now four recognized subspecies of great blue herons, with the possibility of A. h. wardi creeping into the area, but this is much more likely A. h. herodias, as noted. Canon 7D, Tamron SP 150-600 at 600mm, handheld, cropped.&quot; We received only around a dozen submissions this year, and all were very good indeed. In the past, we have polled our readers, but participation in the polls has dropped off. We therefore decided, consistently with Rules 8 and 12, to choose the winners ourselves rather than poll our readers. In this endeavor, we enlisted the assistance of our Wife and Harshest Critic, Deanna, and also our Son the Geek, David. Deanna grew up making dye transfers, and David is a formidable photographer himself. The one thing we three agreed upon was to place Al Denelsbeck’s photograph of what David called “sad snake, happy bird” first. We will announce the runner-up and the bronze medalist, so to speak, in subsequent weeks. Mr. Denelsbeck, who blogs here, will be offered his choice between Why Intelligent Design Fails, A Scientific Critique of the New Creationism, edited by Taner Edis and me (and autographed by me); and What’s Gotten Into You by Dan Levitt, generously contributed by NCSE. The runner-up will be offered the remaining book.</summary></entry></feed>