<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-11-23T20:05:35-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Sun dog</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/sun-dog.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sun dog" /><published>2021-11-22T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-11-22T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/sun-dog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/sun-dog.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Nicky Turner&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Nicky_Turner_Sun_Dog_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sun dog&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sun_dog&quot;&gt;Sun dog&lt;/a&gt;. The photographer writes, &quot;The picture was taken on the terrace here at our house, &lt;a href=&quot;https://villasantalucia.net/&quot;&gt;Villa Santa Lucia&lt;/a&gt;, about 15 km south of Livorno on the Etruscan coast of Italy,&quot; October, 2021.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sun dog is formed from refraction by hexagonal ice crystals held with their axes vertical by hydrodynamic forces (drop a small scrap of paper, and you will see how it remains mostly horizontal). If the air is not still and the crystals are not oriented, you may see the full &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/22%C2%B0_halo&quot;&gt;22&amp;deg; halo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Nicky Turner. Sun dog. The photographer writes, &quot;The picture was taken on the terrace here at our house, Villa Santa Lucia, about 15 km south of Livorno on the Etruscan coast of Italy,&quot; October, 2021. The sun dog is formed from refraction by hexagonal ice crystals held with their axes vertical by hydrodynamic forces (drop a small scrap of paper, and you will see how it remains mostly horizontal). If the air is not still and the crystals are not oriented, you may see the full 22&amp;deg; halo.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Your brain as a walnut</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/your-brain-as-walnut.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Your brain as a walnut" /><published>2021-11-19T10:55:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-11-19T10:55:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/your-brain-as-walnut</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/your-brain-as-walnut.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Josh_Axe_Moron_6.53_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Josh Axe in action&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6Swksd9ivRs&quot;&gt;Josh Axe in action&lt;/a&gt;. Here he seems to think that a reduction of 1/4 is 40&amp;nbsp;%. &lt;small&gt;Credit: Addicted Tolgnerance, &quot;Dr. Josh Axe is a Moron,&quot; fair use.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other day, I (MY) received note from the Kentucky paleontologist Dan Phelps. The note was an anguished letter that he had sent to the PBS affiliate Kentucky Educational Television and was headed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;If someone dies, what will KET say?&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What anguished Mr. Phelps was the station’s airing of a program called “Ancient Remedies” by a quack nutritionist (or something) called Josh Axe. It seems that KET is not the only affiliate that runs his “advice”: so do Rhode Island PBS, New Hampshire PBS, Arizona Public Media, Duluth-Superior Area Educational Television, Kansas Public Television, Blue Ridge PBS, Delta College Public Media, PBS Western Reserve, and I suppose more, but I gave up looking. In my own area, it looks like PBS12, Colorado Public Television, carries the program, but Rocky Mountain PBS does not. May we suggest that after you read this post you check your own PBS affiliate and if appropriate complain about their airing this nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had never heard of Josh Axe, so I looked him up and watched – no, endured an hour-long program &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FxIbJEhMrzQ&quot;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;. I did not take notes, but what I came away with was&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Cancer is a psychosomatic disease (my interpretation of what he said)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Certain personality types and get breast cancer on the left side, others on the right, depending on some mumbo jumbo about qi (chi)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The plural of anecdote is data; Chinese medicine is 5000 (?) years old and has accumulated plenty of data (he does not seem to have heard of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confirmation_bias&quot;&gt;confirmation bias&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Western medicine believes in evidence (again, my interpretation; I do not remember his precise wording)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And, finally, like cures like, so walnuts are good for your brain, or something like that, reminiscent of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homeopathy&quot;&gt;homeopathy&lt;/a&gt;, only worse &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now yield the floor to my colleague Dan Phelps, who started this discussion with the following letter to KET:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back in August, during a fundraiser, Kentucky &lt;i&gt;Educational&lt;/i&gt; Television aired an infomercial for “Dr. Josh Axe,” a chiropractor. He touted his version of “ancient remedies.” Every ten seconds or so of his spiel, the camera did a close-up of the grinning/nodding zombies in the audience nodding their heads in total agreement. Some of the things he said concerning diet made sense, but why couldn’t the PBS station get someone reputable to say that? Most of the “ancient remedies” touted seem to be based on symbolism. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Tomatoes have four chambers, just like your heart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mushrooms are the same shape as adrenal glands&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carrots in section look like the eyes' irises&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walnuts look like brains&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celery looks like bones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beets are the color of blood …&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;The color of the food will tell you what part of the body it will heal&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

The website “The Encyclopedia of American Loons” did a &lt;a href=&quot;http://americanloons.blogspot.com/2021/10/2487-josh-axe.html&quot;&gt;nice entry on Axe.&lt;/a&gt;  

Today I was looking at KET’s schedule and found they are showing more of Axe’s infomercials in late November.

Why KET? Why? If someone dies, what will KET say?&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To clarify (MY again), in the interview that I watched, Mr. Axe stated explicitly that walnuts were good for your brain because they looked like your brain. He added that people who accepted the theory of evolution would not understand, because when God created the universe, he set it up that way deliberately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kali Mattheus, a Programming Specialist at KET, blissfully unaware that there’s no degree known as doctor of natural medicine, responded thus:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Thank you for your additional comments. We appreciate your thoughts and concerns. After your initial email we reviewed the program and talked with the distributor. We confirmed [that] Dr. Axe’s credentials as a doctor of natural medicine and certified nutrition specialist more than qualify him to speak on the subject of diet. Also, as mentioned in a previous email there are disclaimers recommending viewers speak with their primary care physicians prior to making any changes to their diets. We will continue to review programs as they are submitted.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Phelps broadcasts a lot of his e-mails; Vincent M. Cassone, Jack and Linda Gill Professor of Biology at the University of Kentucky, which I take to be an endowed chair, was incensed by Mr. Mattheus’s response and wrote,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am stunned by your answer to Mr. Dan Phelps, a highly regarded science educator, expressing his concern about false and probably deliberately misleading statements made by chiropractor Josh Axe on your station, which, based upon your name, presumes to be educational. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, contrary to your statements otherwise, Josh Axe has virtually no credentials in terms of medical advice, including diet. A very quick perusal of Dr. Axe’s websites shows he is a chiropractor, which qualifies him to adjust the spine, and is a practitioner of “naturopathic medicine” in Tennessee, which has proven to be quackery over and over. He even lists a fake university, Exodus Clinic, as the institution where he received his “doctor of natural medicine.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among his “credentials” on his website, he lists his height and weight. I suspect these data are the most accurate of his credentials. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the dietary advice has some support in mainstream diet fields, but adherence to a keto diet is not supported by many registered dieticians, who actually have credentials to prescribe dietary advice. Secondly, many of the statements he has made on his program, as catalogued by Mr. Phelps, are categorically false. Tomatoes do not &lt;i&gt;always&lt;/i&gt; have four chambers. The most common anatomy among tomatoes has 5 seed “chambers.” Mushrooms do &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; look like adrenal glands. Carrots in cross-section do &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; look like irises.  Etc., etc. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These inaccuracies could just be curious, even humorous. &lt;i&gt;However&lt;/i&gt;, statements proposed by Mr. Axe are &lt;i&gt;dangerous&lt;/i&gt;. He video lectures that “cancer is caused by two things: Deficiency and Toxicity.” He actually says that Splenda (sucralose) can break down into chlorine. This is patently untrue. &lt;/p&gt;
 
&lt;p&gt;I am stunned, very disappointed, that your station would promote this ridiculous accumulation of ignorance. I’m outraged. I strongly encourage you to see &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/6Swksd9ivRs&quot;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt; that completely debunks Axe. [Reproduced with permission.] &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I (MY) watched the video, and it does. I usually shy away from invective, but I can only conclude that Mr. Axe has a walnut for a brain. Or else he is a conscious faker.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps and Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Josh Axe in action. Here he seems to think that a reduction of 1/4 is 40&amp;nbsp;%. Credit: Addicted Tolgnerance, &quot;Dr. Josh Axe is a Moron,&quot; fair use. The other day, I (MY) received note from the Kentucky paleontologist Dan Phelps. The note was an anguished letter that he had sent to the PBS affiliate Kentucky Educational Television and was headed If someone dies, what will KET say? What anguished Mr. Phelps was the station’s airing of a program called “Ancient Remedies” by a quack nutritionist (or something) called Josh Axe. It seems that KET is not the only affiliate that runs his “advice”: so do Rhode Island PBS, New Hampshire PBS, Arizona Public Media, Duluth-Superior Area Educational Television, Kansas Public Television, Blue Ridge PBS, Delta College Public Media, PBS Western Reserve, and I suppose more, but I gave up looking. In my own area, it looks like PBS12, Colorado Public Television, carries the program, but Rocky Mountain PBS does not. May we suggest that after you read this post you check your own PBS affiliate and if appropriate complain about their airing this nonsense. I had never heard of Josh Axe, so I looked him up and watched – no, endured an hour-long program here. I did not take notes, but what I came away with was Cancer is a psychosomatic disease (my interpretation of what he said) Certain personality types and get breast cancer on the left side, others on the right, depending on some mumbo jumbo about qi (chi) The plural of anecdote is data; Chinese medicine is 5000 (?) years old and has accumulated plenty of data (he does not seem to have heard of confirmation bias) Western medicine believes in evidence (again, my interpretation; I do not remember his precise wording) And, finally, like cures like, so walnuts are good for your brain, or something like that, reminiscent of homeopathy, only worse I now yield the floor to my colleague Dan Phelps, who started this discussion with the following letter to KET:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fired for endangering others</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/fired-for-endangering.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fired for endangering others" /><published>2021-11-08T12:50:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-11-08T12:50:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/fired-for-endangering</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/fired-for-endangering.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Fired_For_My_Beliefs.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Man holding sign&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An observant reader sent us &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/aigkenham/photos/4898302493533401&quot;&gt;this picture&lt;/a&gt;, which was the subject of a tweet by Ken Ham of AIG, and noted that the caption should have been&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;big&gt;&quot;Fired because my beliefs endangered the health and safety of others.&quot;&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He further commented,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seriously, it doesn't bother AiG to fire or not to hire people because they don't believe what the organization requires (this behavior is legal under the Civil Rights Act, BTW, if carefully structured). SO why do they take such umbrage when someone else does the same thing?&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;And, there certainly is a clear and present danger to acting on these [anti-vaccination] beliefs, whereas I would be hard pressed to find such a danger among, say, other Christian denominations that do not follow the bizarre twists that AiG insists on. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may read about First Liberty Institute (mentioned in the figure) &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_Liberty_Institute&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">An observant reader sent us this picture, which was the subject of a tweet by Ken Ham of AIG, and noted that the caption should have been &quot;Fired because my beliefs endangered the health and safety of others.&quot; He further commented, Seriously, it doesn't bother AiG to fire or not to hire people because they don't believe what the organization requires (this behavior is legal under the Civil Rights Act, BTW, if carefully structured). SO why do they take such umbrage when someone else does the same thing? And, there certainly is a clear and present danger to acting on these [anti-vaccination] beliefs, whereas I would be hard pressed to find such a danger among, say, other Christian denominations that do not follow the bizarre twists that AiG insists on. You may read about First Liberty Institute (mentioned in the figure) here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">White rainbow</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/white-rainbow.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="White rainbow" /><published>2021-11-08T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-11-08T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/white-rainbow</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/white-rainbow.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Paul Strode&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Strode_White_Rainbow_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;White rainbow&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fog_bow&quot;&gt;White rainbow, or fog bow&lt;/a&gt;, overlooking the Flatirons, Boulder Colorado, October, 2021. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This splendid picture by Paul Strode shows a white rainbow, or a fog bow. The white rainbow is seen when the droplets are very small, as in a fog. In that case the angle of diffraction is at least much as the angle of refraction, so the colors overlap, and the rainbow appears white. M. Minnaert, in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Nature-Light-Colour-Dover-Sciences/dp/0486201961/&quot;&gt;The nature of light and color in the open air&lt;/a&gt; (&amp;#167;128), notes that the width of the white rainbow may be as much as twice the width of the ordinary rainbow. Additionally, the colors may be reversed, because red light is diffracted more than blue, whereas it is refracted less. In Dr. Strode's picture, we see a &quot;conventional&quot; rainbow at the left merging into a white arc where, presumably, the droplets are smaller. The arc is about the same width as the colored section, which hints that the droplets are sized so that diffraction barely covers refraction. In consequence, we do not see any color, reversed or otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, contrary to popular descriptions &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.popsci.com/where-do-white-rainbows-come-from/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and (especially) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.realsimple.com/holidays-entertaining/entertaining/seasonal-events/white-rainbow&quot;&gt;there&lt;/a&gt;, the light is always refracted by the droplets, but sometimes diffraction plays a role as well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Paul Strode. White rainbow, or fog bow, overlooking the Flatirons, Boulder Colorado, October, 2021. This splendid picture by Paul Strode shows a white rainbow, or a fog bow. The white rainbow is seen when the droplets are very small, as in a fog. In that case the angle of diffraction is at least much as the angle of refraction, so the colors overlap, and the rainbow appears white. M. Minnaert, in The nature of light and color in the open air (&amp;#167;128), notes that the width of the white rainbow may be as much as twice the width of the ordinary rainbow. Additionally, the colors may be reversed, because red light is diffracted more than blue, whereas it is refracted less. In Dr. Strode's picture, we see a &quot;conventional&quot; rainbow at the left merging into a white arc where, presumably, the droplets are smaller. The arc is about the same width as the colored section, which hints that the droplets are sized so that diffraction barely covers refraction. In consequence, we do not see any color, reversed or otherwise. Incidentally, contrary to popular descriptions here and (especially) there, the light is always refracted by the droplets, but sometimes diffraction plays a role as well.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is common descent untestable?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/is-common-descent-untestable.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is common descent untestable?" /><published>2021-11-06T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-11-06T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/is-common-descent-untestable</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/is-common-descent-untestable.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/300Px-Pay_the_bill.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Paying the bill]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Illustration EN&amp;amp;ST uses for &quot;paying the bill&quot;, from Wikimedia Commons&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ever-astonishing site Evolution News and Science Today has astonished once again.  Finding a paper in the
scientific literature which provides evidence for a horizontal gene transfer event, they declare that
this shows that &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2021/11/case-study-inadvertently-shows-why-universal-common-descent-is-untestable/&quot;&gt;common descent is an untestable
concept&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper is in the journal Molecular Biology and Evolution: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mbe/advance-article/doi/10.1093/molbev/msab317/6420225&quot;&gt;Citrullination was introduced into animals by horizontal gene transfer from
cyanobacteria&lt;/a&gt;  (Disclosure: I have
published in that journal, and served as President of its parent society).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper straightforwardly provides evidence from molecular phylogenies and functional studies that the enzyme
peptidylarginine deaminase has a distribution discordant with the overall phylogeny of life, in that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The animal and cyanobacterial PADI proteins share functionally relevant primary and tertiary synapomorphic sequences
that are distinct from a second PADI type present in fungi and actinobacteria …. The consilience of evidence
indicates that PADIs were introduced from cyanobacteria into animals by horizontal gene transfer (HGT).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aha! exclaims EN&amp;amp;ST. About Universal Common Descent, they note that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;UCD is often held to be testable via the counterfactual of “genes and proteins might have been discovered in
 groups where they should not exist”. In other words, if we observed genes and proteins occurring in the TOL,
 with unequivocal homology to the same sequences found elsewhere in phylogenetically distant or divergent groups, UCD
 would be in trouble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And indeed they think that horizontal gene transfer is an added assumption that needs to be verified, and that if we
invoke it in this way, UCD is in trouble:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;UCD’s big entourage only becomes a problem when its members always pay the fines for UCD’s failed
predictions, pick up UCD’s tab at restaurants and hotels, and generally cover the empirical shortfalls of UCD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and they end with the declaration that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If ever anyone needed evidence of the
untestability of UCD, papers like this provide it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The even-more-astonishing Denyse O’Leary (“News” at Uncommon Descent) also &lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/darwinism/a-friend-says-this-paper-illustrates-that-universal-common-descent-is-untestable/&quot;&gt;made the same point&lt;/a&gt;,
attributing it to “a friend”; one of the two of them also seems to be a friend of EN&amp;amp;ST.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could argue with these dramatic conclusions, but the commenters here at PT might well do a better job.  So let’s hear what
you have to say.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Illustration EN&amp;amp;ST uses for &quot;paying the bill&quot;, from Wikimedia Commons The ever-astonishing site Evolution News and Science Today has astonished once again. Finding a paper in the scientific literature which provides evidence for a horizontal gene transfer event, they declare that this shows that common descent is an untestable concept The paper is in the journal Molecular Biology and Evolution: Citrullination was introduced into animals by horizontal gene transfer from cyanobacteria (Disclosure: I have published in that journal, and served as President of its parent society). The paper straightforwardly provides evidence from molecular phylogenies and functional studies that the enzyme peptidylarginine deaminase has a distribution discordant with the overall phylogeny of life, in that The animal and cyanobacterial PADI proteins share functionally relevant primary and tertiary synapomorphic sequences that are distinct from a second PADI type present in fungi and actinobacteria …. The consilience of evidence indicates that PADIs were introduced from cyanobacteria into animals by horizontal gene transfer (HGT). Aha! exclaims EN&amp;amp;ST. About Universal Common Descent, they note that UCD is often held to be testable via the counterfactual of “genes and proteins might have been discovered in groups where they should not exist”. In other words, if we observed genes and proteins occurring in the TOL, with unequivocal homology to the same sequences found elsewhere in phylogenetically distant or divergent groups, UCD would be in trouble. And indeed they think that horizontal gene transfer is an added assumption that needs to be verified, and that if we invoke it in this way, UCD is in trouble: UCD’s big entourage only becomes a problem when its members always pay the fines for UCD’s failed predictions, pick up UCD’s tab at restaurants and hotels, and generally cover the empirical shortfalls of UCD. and they end with the declaration that If ever anyone needed evidence of the untestability of UCD, papers like this provide it. The even-more-astonishing Denyse O’Leary (“News” at Uncommon Descent) also made the same point, attributing it to “a friend”; one of the two of them also seems to be a friend of EN&amp;amp;ST.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Haldane (1938) on the Biology of Inequality</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/haldane-1938-biology-of-inequality.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Haldane (1938) on the Biology of Inequality" /><published>2021-11-04T18:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-11-04T18:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/haldane-1938-biology-of-inequality</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/haldane-1938-biology-of-inequality.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Haldane_1938_Biology_of_Inequality_p118.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Haldane 1938 on Fisher/Jefferson&quot; class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As noted in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html&quot;&gt;post on the attempts to can T.H. Huxley&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/equality/activities/history-group/&quot;&gt;Imperial College is proposing to also dename&lt;/a&gt; rooms named for R. A. Fisher and J.B.S. Haldane. Fisher has been widely targeted since 2020 (in my view out all proportion of the actual evidence – I agree with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.proquest.com/docview/210620887?accountid=8424&quot;&gt;Stephen Jay Gould&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/11612599/&quot;&gt;1991&lt;/a&gt;) on Fisher, but that is another post). But as a political conservative and eugenicist (although he basically stopped eugenics advocacy in the 1930s, unlike many others), and without a big obvious record of progressive actions, Fisher is a challenge to defend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Targeting J.B.S. Haldane, of all people, is, well, nuts. Everyone seems to have forgotten that he was a vocal critic of the older eugenics, another reform eugenicist like Julian Huxley, but even further left. Haldane was a literal card-carrying communist and inveterate critic of the classist assumptions of the earlier eugenicists. His far-left views got him in trouble when it came to defending Stalin – Haldane probably was on a lot of lists for cancellation by the right in the 1950s. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/07/28/books/review/a-dominant-character-haldane-samanth-subramanian.html&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt; New York Times&lt;/i&gt; review&lt;/a&gt; of the 2020 biography &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Dominant_Character&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;A Dominant Character: The Radical Science and Restless Politics of J. B. S. Haldane&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; says, “British intelligence kept him under surveillance for more than 20 years on the suspicion — probably unfounded — that he was a Soviet spy.”  Haldane’s slowness to criticize Lysenko didn’t make him any friends in the genetics community either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haldane was a remarkable individual and progressive in many ways, for example, as a critic of empire (specifically the Suez Crisis of 1956) he moved to India in his later years, something that the Imperial College tribunal tasked with reviewing colonialist legacies at Imperial somehow does not mention. But, I don’t have the bandwidth for a detailed defense of Haldane at the moment.  But I can help in one way.  For many moderns who make judgements based on what’s put in front of them online, preferably in a Twitter post, sources don’t really exist unless they are online, free, and text-searchable by Google.  Haldane’s famous 1938 essay “The Biology of Inequality,” from his book &lt;i&gt;Heredity and Politics&lt;/i&gt;, does not appear to be online.  But I dare anyone to read these passages and then present an argument that Haldane is really someone who should be cancelled in the name of social justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haldane’s essay begins with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;We will first consider the doctrine of the equality of man. I will quote from a great revolutionary document of the eighteenth century, the American Declaration of Independence, which was published in 1776 and is mainly due to Jeffersion. 'We hold these truths to be self-evident, that all men are created equal, that they are endowed by their Creator with certain unalienable Rights, that among these are Life, Liberty, and the pursuit of Happiness.'&quot;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haldane’s essays considers to proponents of the opposing view – inequality – taking each in turn. Be sure to read the footnotes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;Let us now consider a series of doctrines that are based on the theory of inequality. We will take first the theory that 'the unfit should be sterilized'. I may add at once that the operation of sterilization is not castration. It means an operative interference which prevents the conception or begetting of children. It is a slight operation in men, more serious in women. There have been many statements of this doctrine. For example, Mr Justice Holmes of the United States Supreme Court, in a judgment on appeal, said: 'It is better for all the world if society can prevent those who are manifestly unfit from continuing their kind.' We must ask, however, 'Who are the unfit?' and 'Do they all continue their kind?' We must also ask who is to decide these questions, both the question of the unfitness and that of whether it is handed on; and we must ask a final question -- whether sterilization is the only practicable way of preventing the individual from continuing his kind, if we find that is desirable. There have been, of course, mnay attempts to answer this question, and to put sterilization on a legal basis.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I prefer not to quote the German law on the subject because it is inevitable that to do so would give rise to a certain amount of prejudice either for or against this law. I will quote the American model Sterilization Law, drafted by H. H. Laughlin in a Report of the Psychopathic Laboratory of the Municipal Court of Chicago (1922).&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Haldane1938_footnote1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Here are some sections of this law; [Section 2, subsection &lt;i&gt;(a)&lt;/i&gt;] 'A socially inadequate person is one who by his or her own effort, regardless of etiology or prognosis, fails chronically in comparison with normal persons, to maintain himself or herself as a useful member of the organized social life of the state; provided that the term socially inadequate shall not be applied to any person whose individual or social ineffectiveness is due to the normally expected exigencies of youth, old age, curable injuries, or temporary physical or mental illness, in case such ineffectiveness is adequately taken care of by the particular family in which it occurs.'&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
'&lt;i&gt;(b)&lt;/i&gt; The socially inadequate classes, regardless of etiology or prognosis, are the following: 

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(1) Feeble-minded; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(2) Insane (including the psychopathic); &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(3) Criminalistic (including the delinquent and wayward); &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(4) Epileptic; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(5) Inebriate (included drug habitués); &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(6) Diseased (including the tuberculous, the syphilitic, the leprous, and others with chronic, infectious and legally segregable diseases); &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(7) Blind&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Haldane1938_footnote2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (including those with seriously impaired vision);&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;li&gt;(8) Deaf&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Haldane1938_footnote3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (including those with seriously impaired hearing); &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(9) Deformed (including the crippled); and &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(10) Dependent (including orphans, ne'ev-do-wells, the homeless,&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Haldane1938_footnote4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; tramps,&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Haldane1938_footnote4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and paupers&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Haldane1938_footnote4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;).'&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

[...]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Now you see that goes rather far! [...] I do put it forward, however, that such legislation is considerably more revolutionary than, for example, the more moderate forms of socialism, and would involve considerably more interference with individual liberty.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;Haldane1938_footnote1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Haldane1938_footnote1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; pp. 446-447 of &lt;i&gt;Eugenical Sterilization in the United States&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;Haldane1938_footnote2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Haldane1938_footnote2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; For example Milton.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;Haldane1938_footnote3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Haldane1938_footnote3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; For example Beethoven.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;Haldane1938_footnote4&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Haldane1938_footnote4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; For example Jesus.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
pp. 115-116 of: J.B.S. Haldane (1938). &quot;The Biology of Inequality.&quot; pp. 113-134 of: &lt;i&gt;On Being the Right Size and other essays&lt;/i&gt;, Edited by John Maynard Smith. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1985.  Originally published as Chapter 1 of &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.routledge.com/Heredity-and-Politics/Haldane/p/book/9781138955141&quot;&gt;Heredity and Politics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;.   Derived from Haldane's Muirhead Lectures given at the University of Birmingham in February and March 1937.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another passage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;The third statement which we shall have to consider is that certain classes are congenitally superior to others, and that it is desirable that the superior classes should reproduce more rapidly. As an example of that type of thinking I will quote the &lt;i&gt;Report of the Committee of the Eugenics Society&lt;/i&gt; (1910)&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which commented on the &lt;i&gt;Reports of the Royal Commission on the Poor Laws&lt;/i&gt; published in 1909. &quot;That element in pauperism which represents and transmits original defect, almost completely neglected in the investigation and wholly neglected in the recommendations of the Commission, is the one we wish to take into consideration. The determination of this element is not a matter of opinion but of the application of methods of careful investigation. It is impossible to disregard the fact that the typical dependant who habitually received relief. Yet it is precisely the latter who is primarily the subject of Poor Law relief, and who affords the chief burden on the public purse. He is not the man who responds to a call on manly independence or stands ready to take a place made available through the Labour Exchange. He was born without manly independence&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and is unable to do a normal day's work however frequently it is offered to him.'&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
(ibid, p. 117)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;Haldane1938_footnote5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Haldane1938_footnote5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Quoted by E. J. Lidbetter, Heredity and the Social Problem Group (1933), vol. I, p. 12.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;a name=&quot;Haldane1938_footnote6&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Haldane1938_footnote6&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In my own experience the majority of new-born infants are devoid of this quality.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, he addresses R. A. Fisher’s (1930) book &lt;i&gt;The Genetical Theory of Natural Selection&lt;/i&gt;. I mention in passing that, although Fisher was a conservative and Haldane was a communist, Fisher helped Haldane out in 1940, during the London Blitz of World War 2, by inviting Haldane to share his lab space out of the city.  They did fall out later, during the Cold War, over Haldane’s gentle treatment of Lysenkoism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;It is only fair to remember that was written in 1910, and that since then the problem of unemployment has entirely changed in character. Those people who were regarded as unemployable have been called the 'social problem group' by the investigators of the Eugenics Society. Modern sociologists, however, rarely ascribe the unemployment of 1 1/2 million people to congential abnormalities. We shall later discuss the theory that many of the poor are poor because of hereditary defects.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In the same way many biologists believe in the innate superiority of certain classes and in the extreme importance of the ruling classes. Professor Fisher, for example, in his book, &lt;i&gt;The Genetical Theory of Natural Selection&lt;/i&gt;,&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Haldane1938_footnote7&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; writes:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
'The fact of the decline of past civilizations is the most patent in history, and since brilliant periods have frequently been inaugurated, in the great centres of civilization, by the invasion of alien rulers, it is recognized that the immediate cause of decay must be the degeneration or depletion&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Haldane1938_footnote8&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of the ruling classes.'&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;
We note that Fisher takes for granted the exact opposite of the proposition concerning equality that was obvious to Jefferson. The truth may lie between the two ideas.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;Haldane1938_footnote7&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Haldane1938_footnote7&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; p. 237.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;Haldane1938_footnote8&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Haldane1938_footnote8&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Thus if English culture decayed during the sixteenth century and particularly under Elizabeth, this may be attributed to the depletion of the feudal nobility in the Wars of the Roses. If not, not.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
(ibid, p. 118)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I note that Fisher, according to Haldane a critic of the Jeffersonian ideal; Haldane, critic of Fisher’s criticism; and Jefferson himself, have now all been canned, all for violating Jefferson’s proposition concerning equality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J.B.S. Haldane (1938). “The Biology of Inequality.” pp. 113-134 of: &lt;i&gt;On Being the Right Size and other essays&lt;/i&gt;, Edited by John Maynard Smith. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1985.  Originally published as Chapter 1 of &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.routledge.com/Heredity-and-Politics/Haldane/p/book/9781138955141&quot;&gt;Heredity and Politics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;.   Derived from Haldane’s Muirhead Lectures given at the University of Birmingham in February and March 1937.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jerry Coyne has a good blogpost on Haldane at: https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2020/08/15/the-colorful-and-erudite-j-b-s-haldane-my-take-and-a-new-biography/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coyne on the Imperial College situation:
https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2021/10/27/t-h-huxley-about-to-be-cancelled-at-imperial-college-london/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Images of Haldane 1938 excerpts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Haldane_1938_Biology_of_Inequality_p113.png&quot; alt=&quot;Skadoosh&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Haldane_1938_Biology_of_Inequality_p115.png&quot; alt=&quot;Skadoosh&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Haldane_1938_Biology_of_Inequality_p116.png&quot; alt=&quot;Skadoosh&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Haldane_1938_Biology_of_Inequality_p118.png&quot; alt=&quot;Skadoosh&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Addendum: Haldane story from Joseph Felsenstein&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2021-11-09 update: I am adding in this story that Joe Felsenstein &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/haldane-1938-biology-of-inequality.html#comment-5597331791&quot;&gt;posted in the comments&lt;/a&gt;. Because comments are in a different system (Disqus) they can get lost, and this might as well be preserved for posterity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Joe Felsenstein, Moderator • 4 days ago • edited&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I should just mention that I am possibly the only person reading this post who actually got to see JBS Haldane. In the fall of 1963 he visited the U.S., after years of being prevented from doing so. He was to give a lecture in North Carolina, but the state legislature prevented it. The University of Wisconsin invited him. I was an undergraduate student in James Crow's lab; I got to hear his lecture to a large audience. He talked about mutation, and made it clear that he was following closely the progress of working out the genetic code, which was happening then. I also heard him talk to a smaller audience of about 30 people, one of whom was Sewall Wright. We students of population genetics were looking forward to hearing them say important things. They were quite polite to each other but Haldane was concentrating on making the worst puns possible, while Wright, as usual, mumbled to anyone who would listen about this or that paper he had written. I listened also to Haldane speak with admirers at a reception (again, mostly bad puns). There is a wonderful new biography of Haldane, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Dominant-Character-Radical-Restless-Politics/dp/0393634248&quot;&gt;A Dominant Character&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;, by Samanth Subramanian. I described his bad pun at the reception to Subramanian, who included it. If anyone were tempted to accuse Haldane of racism, they should deal with the fact that he was fascinated by India since recuperating there from wounds in World War I, and in the 1950s he emigrated there and identified himself as an Indian. He also declared that this was owing to his disgust at the French/British/Israeli seizure of the Suez Canal in 1956, but he had been planning the move before that.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
(Felsenstein comment on Nov. 5, 2021)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Matzke</name></author><summary type="html">As noted in the post on the attempts to can T.H. Huxley, Imperial College is proposing to also dename rooms named for R. A. Fisher and J.B.S. Haldane. Fisher has been widely targeted since 2020 (in my view out all proportion of the actual evidence – I agree with Stephen Jay Gould (1991) on Fisher, but that is another post). But as a political conservative and eugenicist (although he basically stopped eugenics advocacy in the 1930s, unlike many others), and without a big obvious record of progressive actions, Fisher is a challenge to defend. Targeting J.B.S. Haldane, of all people, is, well, nuts. Everyone seems to have forgotten that he was a vocal critic of the older eugenics, another reform eugenicist like Julian Huxley, but even further left. Haldane was a literal card-carrying communist and inveterate critic of the classist assumptions of the earlier eugenicists. His far-left views got him in trouble when it came to defending Stalin – Haldane probably was on a lot of lists for cancellation by the right in the 1950s. The New York Times review of the 2020 biography A Dominant Character: The Radical Science and Restless Politics of J. B. S. Haldane says, “British intelligence kept him under surveillance for more than 20 years on the suspicion — probably unfounded — that he was a Soviet spy.” Haldane’s slowness to criticize Lysenko didn’t make him any friends in the genetics community either. Haldane was a remarkable individual and progressive in many ways, for example, as a critic of empire (specifically the Suez Crisis of 1956) he moved to India in his later years, something that the Imperial College tribunal tasked with reviewing colonialist legacies at Imperial somehow does not mention. But, I don’t have the bandwidth for a detailed defense of Haldane at the moment. But I can help in one way. For many moderns who make judgements based on what’s put in front of them online, preferably in a Twitter post, sources don’t really exist unless they are online, free, and text-searchable by Google. Haldane’s famous 1938 essay “The Biology of Inequality,” from his book Heredity and Politics, does not appear to be online. But I dare anyone to read these passages and then present an argument that Haldane is really someone who should be cancelled in the name of social justice.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Updated: Creationists and advocates of social justice unite to take down T.H. Huxley, a leader in educational inclusion</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Updated: Creationists and advocates of social justice unite to take down T.H. Huxley, a leader in educational inclusion" /><published>2021-11-03T23:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-11-03T23:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;WWU’s Huxley College of the Environment may be renamed after a bizarre report uncritically plagiarising far-right creationist &amp;amp; conspiracist materials gets Thomas Henry Huxley exactly backwards on racism.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;From 2004-2007 Dr. Nick Matzke worked at the National Center for Science Education, including the &lt;u&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.talkorigins.org/faqs/dover/kitzmiller_v_dover.html&quot;&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/u&gt; court case that determined that teaching “intelligent design” in public schools was unconstitutional. He obtained his Ph.D. in Integrative Biology from the University of California, Berkeley, in 2013. He is now a Senior Lecturer in the School of Biological Sciences at the University of Auckland. This essay represents his personal scholarly views, not those of current or former employers.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Update, November 2021:&lt;/b&gt; A similar situation has now broken out at Imperial College, London. A “History Group” review of colonialist legacies at Imperial has decided that the important thing to do is to target a Huxley statue and building, as well as room named for J.B.S. Haldane (apparently for discussing cloning; never mind Haldane’s strong socialism, critique of hardline eugenics, and explicit anti-imperialism). The name “Imperial College” appears to be untouched. An outline and list of “Key Links” has been added, along with various corrections/clarifications. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html&quot;&gt;The original post and comments are here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outline&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html#intro&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html#HuxleyAntiRacism&quot;&gt;Huxley’s anti-racist activities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html#HuxleyVsJamesHunt&quot;&gt;T.H. Huxley vs. Leading Scientific Racist James Hunt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html#HuxleyJamaica&quot;&gt;Huxley on the Jamaica Committee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html#Huxley1867&quot;&gt;Huxley’s 1867 Birmingham lecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html#RadicalsRace1865&quot;&gt;Radicals and Race in 1865&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html#OtherWWUerrors&quot;&gt;Other WWU Task Force errors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html#HuxleyDEI&quot;&gt;T.H. Huxley's Advocacy for Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion in Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html#footshooting&quot;&gt;Is WWU shooting its anti-racism goals in the foot?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html#references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html#KeyLinks&quot;&gt;Key Links&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html#WWU_Task_Force&quot;&gt;WWU Legacy Review Task Force (LRTF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html#WWU_Response_to_Task_Force&quot;&gt;Responses to WWU’s LRTF Report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html#Imperial&quot;&gt;Imperial College, London&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html#blogs_media&quot;&gt;Blogs and Media&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
  
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Western Washington University’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://huxley.wwu.edu/&quot;&gt;Huxley College of the Environment&lt;/a&gt; was founded in 1969, the year of the Santa Barbara oil spill, when the Cuyahoga River caught on fire, and when Earth Day was proposed. It is now one of the oldest and most prestigious environmental colleges in the country. It was named for Thomas Henry Huxley (1825-1895), famed not only as Darwin’s defender after the 1859 publication of the &lt;i&gt;Origin of Species&lt;/i&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linnean.org/news/2019/07/01/1st-july-2019-why-there-was-no-darwins-bulldog&quot;&gt;“Darwin’s Bulldog” came into use in 1895&lt;/a&gt;), but also for his remarkable career, rising from a family too poor to pay for school to becoming a leading anatomist (proposing the kinship of humans with the great apes, and birds with dinosaurs), geologist, ethnologist, and philosopher (coiner of the word “agnostic,” foe of Social Darwinism). Above all he was a leading figure in making science a profession (rather than a hobby for priests and the landed gentry), and making a liberal science education available to all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite accomplishing more than most could ever dream for science and public science education, Huxley is now in the dock at WWU. The main charge is racism, with many at WWU calling for Huxley College to be renamed. WWU’s president commissioned a &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/research-and-resources&quot;&gt;Legacy Review Task Force&lt;/a&gt; (LRTF) which issued a &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/files/2021-07/LRTF%20Report%20and%20Recommendations_June%202021.pdf&quot;&gt;Report&lt;/a&gt; making the rather elliptical claim that Huxley’s “ethnological accomplishments were grounded in white supremacist values that dehumanize and harm many members of the Western community.” More directly, the Report indicts him for advocating polygenism (the idea that different human races are separate species) and “many negative generalizations on the basis of race.” Another charge was that “Huxley’s claims about the inexhaustibility of fisheries has contributed to the decline of the salmon runs that are central to Coast Salish cultures.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are the accusations correct? A large debate could be had about the substantial difficulties of fully understanding the views of historical figures, let alone judging them. But clearly universities should not ignore major relevant evidence, nor rely on badly biased and one-sided presentations of the evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://wp.wwu.edu/huxley-legacy/&quot;&gt;Response to the WWU Task Force&lt;/a&gt; from 10 WWU Faculty (followed by a critical &lt;a href=&quot;https://cpb-us-e1.wpmucdn.com/wp.wwu.edu/dist/b/8327/files/2021/09/Response-to-LRTF-report-updated-9-9-2021-2.pdf&quot;&gt;letter endorsed by 20 WWU Environmental Science faculty&lt;/a&gt;) documents many mistakes in the Task Force’s analysis of Huxley, as well as the sourcing of many anti-Huxley claims from the extremist right. The idea that Huxley claimed salmon stocks were inexhaustible – which gets Huxley’s actual view exactly backwards – stems from a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icr.org/article/huxley-error-led-cod-calamity/&quot;&gt;2009 Institute for Creation Research article&lt;/a&gt;. The false idea that Huxley was a polygenist traces to an &lt;a href=&quot;https://larouchepub.com/eiw/public/2015/eirv42n24-20150612/18-29_4224.pdf&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; from the conspiracist &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/national/longterm/cult/larouche/main.htm&quot;&gt;Lyndon LaRouche organization&lt;/a&gt;; the citation is present in the Task Force’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/files/2021-04/TH%20Huxley%20Research%20Document_%20_Why%20is%20TH%20Huxley%20problematic__.pdf&quot;&gt;notes&lt;/a&gt;, but the LaRouche citation was dropped from the Report, while the outrageous claim was kept. The notes and Report also cite &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.troy.edu/index.php/JSAHMS/article/view/256&quot;&gt;anti-Huxley material&lt;/a&gt; from Michael Flannery, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discovery.org/p/flannery/&quot;&gt;Fellow of the Discovery Institute&lt;/a&gt;, the infamous Seattle home of “intelligent design” creationism, also known for advocating &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/41487865&quot;&gt;climate denialism&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2020/05/stephen-meyer-teach-the-coronavirus-controversy/&quot;&gt;Covid denialism&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discovery.org/p/rufo/&quot;&gt;anti-critical race theory&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/news/annals-of-inquiry/how-a-conservative-activist-invented-the-conflict-over-critical-race-theory&quot;&gt;hysteria&lt;/a&gt;. The other major source the Task Force relies on is historian Nicholaas Rupke, himself a former young-earth creationist, and now a lonely apostle for Richard Owen (1804-1892), Huxley’s bitter scientific rival, who tried to keep a place for &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution-outreach.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1007/s12052-010-0230-4&quot;&gt;divine intervention&lt;/a&gt; in evolution. The Task Force essentially ignored the positive &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/research-and-resources&quot;&gt;evaluations&lt;/a&gt; of Huxley provided by three other historians that WWU commissioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about the racism accusation? While admitting Huxley’s anti-slavery position, the Task Force says that “opposition to slavery and belief in the basic humanity of people of African descent was not uncommon, exceptional, or, in the context of Huxley’s many negative generalizations on the basis of race, laudable.” The cited “negative generalizations” come entirely from Huxley’s 1865 essay “&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathcs.clarku.edu/huxley/CE3/B&amp;amp;W.html&quot;&gt;Emancipation—Black and White&lt;/a&gt;,” which has some cringeworthy passages, although made while endorsing “equal natural rights” of Black people and arguing to “give women the same civil and political rights as men,” some 53 years before British women attained the vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;HuxleyAntiRacism&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Huxley’s anti-racist activities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creationists have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icr.org/article/evolution-modern-racism/&quot;&gt;quote-mined this essay for decades&lt;/a&gt;, shorn of context, to portray Huxley as racist. The Legacy Review Task Force does the same. But relying on a single source for Huxley’s views is hazardous. Huxley’s style was “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Politics-literature-modern-Britain-George/dp/0874719879&quot;&gt;vigorously paradoxical&lt;/a&gt;” and he loved to use hyperbole and superficial self-contradiction to make his points, which were often about separating factual claims from value claims. In addition, his public statements on race were actively evolving in the 1860s. A proper historical review would at least consider the major episodes. Three important episodes give a much clearer view on where Huxley stood on race: his battle with the leading scientific racist of the day, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/j.ctt1pprf8.19&quot;&gt;James Hunt&lt;/a&gt;; his participation in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oxforddnb.com/view/10.1093/ref:odnb/9780198614128.001.0001/odnb-9780198614128-e-42293&quot;&gt;Jamaica Committee&lt;/a&gt;; and Huxley’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://mathcs.clarku.edu/huxley/guide18.html&quot;&gt;1867 Birmingham lectures&lt;/a&gt; on race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;HuxleyVsJamesHunt&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;i&gt;T.H. Huxley versus James Hunt, Leader of the Scientific Racists&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to historian &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Colour-Class-Victorians-Attitudes-Mid-Nineteenth-dp-0718511611/dp/0718511611/&quot;&gt;Douglas Lorimer&lt;/a&gt;, in 1863, James Hunt broke away from the older Ethnological Society of London to form the Anthropological Society, in part so that Hunt could promote “the racist speculations of Robert Knox.” Knox was “the outstanding British advocate of…revived polygenesis and of the place of race in determining man’s past […Knox’s 1850] &lt;i&gt;The Races of Man&lt;/i&gt;, [was] the fullest statement of his racist theory.” The Anthropological Society received donations from a Confederate agent who “apparently viewed the Society as a useful outlet for pro-Southern propaganda, for he included his donations to the anthropologists in his Secret Service Accounts for the Richmond Government.” Hunt “became the leading British exponent of scientific racism in the 1860s.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Huxley was a leading critic of Hunt. Lorimer says, “Huxley severely criticized Hunt for his paper, ‘On the Negro’s Place in Nature’”.  (Hunt’s title was a dig at Huxley’s 1863 book &lt;i&gt;Man’s Place in Nature&lt;/i&gt;, which apparently offended Hunt with its monogenism and lack of racist vitriol. Hunt’s paper was largely a collection of quotes of older authorities “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/j.ctt1pprf8.19&quot;&gt;carefully&lt;/a&gt; select[ing] authorities to represent the most negative scientific expressions of racial evaluation available.”) According to Lorimer, Huxley “ridiculed, in particular, the comparison between the Negro and the ape. In Huxley’s view, Hunt’s study of the Negro was ‘the most remarkable result of a modification of anatomical structure I had ever heard of. And the faculty for evolving nonsense displayed by its author…. I forbear to characterize, because the only appropriate phraseology would not be for me to utter or for you to hear.’” Huxley worried the Anthropological Society could do “a good deal of harm if it went wrong,” and advised colleagues to avoid “the quacks who are at the head of the ‘Anthropological Society’.” Huxley was “thoroughly disgusted” with the split-off Anthropological Society, and he resigned his membership, calling the Society a “nest of imposters.” Hunt, for his part, accused Huxley of “negromania” and printed in 1868 that Huxley was “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/4331106&quot;&gt;our most deadly, and sometimes even our most bitter, foe&lt;/a&gt;.” After Hunt died in 1869, Huxley and others in 1871 engineered a merger of the Ethnological and Anthropological societies into the Anthropological Institute of Great Britain and Ireland, fulfilling Hunt’s earlier worry that Huxley would “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/2799027&quot;&gt;crush us&lt;/a&gt;.” In 1873, some of Hunt’s followers again split off so they could “study the laws of race”, forming the London Anthropological Society, which only lasted for two years.  Those who condemn Huxley as a racist should consider what history of science and evolutionary biology would have looked like if someone of Huxley’s talents and prestige had promoted the views of James Hunt, instead of opposing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;HuxleyJamaica&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;i&gt;Huxley on the Jamaica Committee&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huxley not only opposed Britain’s leading scientific racist, he engaged in political activism. In late 1865, in the wake of the Civil War, the British colonial governor of Jamaica, Edward Eyre, killed hundreds of Black protestors who were marching for justice, land reform, and enfranchisement. A massive multiyear controversy broke out in Britain over the carnage. But the government refused to prosecute Eyre, so the Jamaica Committee, led by philosopher, parliamentarian, Radical, and feminist John Stuart Mill, decided to privately prosecute Eyre for murder. Mill was joined by Huxley, himself a Radical, along with most other prominent evolutionists, including Charles Darwin, Alfred Russel Wallace, Charles Lyell, and Herbert Spencer, and about 800 others. It would take rose-coloured glasses to pretend that the Jamaica Committee’s actions were popular. The Eyre Defense Fund was supported by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/43244890&quot;&gt;many leading lights&lt;/a&gt; of British society, including Thomas Carlyle (who was a major intellectual influence on Huxley), Alfred Lord Tennyson, Charles Dickens, John Tyndall, 40 generals, 26 admirals, 400 clergy and 6 bishops, 71 peers and 20 MPs, and 30,000 others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The link between being an evolutionist and having progressive views on race was noticed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/25611713&quot;&gt;racists of the day&lt;/a&gt;, for example when the &lt;i&gt;Pall Mall Gazette&lt;/i&gt; said, “It would be curious also to know how far Sir Charles Lyell’s and Mr. Huxley’s peculiar views on the development of species have influenced them in bestowing on the negro that sympathetic recognition which they are willing to extend even to the ape as ‘a man and a brother’.” James Hunt, for his part, wrote that “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B002RI9S8I/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;btkr=1&quot;&gt;ignorant, prejudiced Stupid&lt;/a&gt; and bigoted Humbugs of the Jamaica Committee who were hunting to the gallows…the brave Heroic Man who had saved Jamaica”, and Governor Eyre was explored as a replacement for Hunt when he resigned as leader of the Anthropological Society. In 1867, Hunt gave a particularly nasty address to his Society, targeting Huxley &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/j.ctt1pprf8.19&quot;&gt;yet again&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(227, 180, 180); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;&quot;&amp;gt;Even scientific men were sometimes afflicted with the disorder [of negromania]. He heard, only on passing through London, that a very eminent anatomist had had another attack, and actually gone and joined the Jamaica committee (laughter). This was Professor Huxley; and it was said that he intended to propose that they should prosecute M. du Chaillu for shooting gorillas (laughter).&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Huxley1867&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;i&gt;Huxley’s 1867 Birmingham lecture&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is true that early in these debates, Huxley sometimes disclaimed support for egalitarianism, although as we have seen above, he had a longstanding &lt;a href=&quot;https://shareok.org/handle/11244/14408&quot;&gt;rhetorical strategy&lt;/a&gt; of separating claimed facts and values. However, his statements seem to shift later in the 1860s, probably because of a combination of his continuing anatomical and evolutionary work, his battles with James Hunt, and the changing political context after slavery was outlawed and radicals moved to obtaining the vote for disenfranchised groups like American Blacks or British working-class Whites (battles fought and won in 1867-1868). In October 1867, Huxley gave a lecture to the Birmingham and Midland Institute. This was a region populated by his people, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.british-history.ac.uk/vch/warks/vol7/pp223-245&quot;&gt;working class&lt;/a&gt; artisans who were not granted the vote until 1868 (for men) and 1918 (women); they saw &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/25611713&quot;&gt;common cause with nonwhites&lt;/a&gt; in the colonies who were also being oppressed by the British ruling classes. In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.gale.com/apps/doc/BA3201120082/BNCN?u=learn&amp;amp;sid=bookmark-BNCN&amp;amp;xid=8e5a703f&quot;&gt;lecture&lt;/a&gt;, Huxley strongly denied polygenism, noting that all races could interbreed successfully, saying, “no sound argument had been brought forward on the side of the distinct origination of the modifications of mankind.” He also denied the idea that any extant races were intermediate with apes, stating “there was no shade of justification for the assertion that any existing modification of mankind now known was to be considered as an intermediate form between man and the animals next below him in the scale of the fauna of the world.” He also states clearly that all existing races (Huxley prefers the word “&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathcs.clarku.edu/huxley/guide18.html&quot;&gt;modifications&lt;/a&gt;”) are closer to each other than any are to the recently-discovered Neanderthal, which itself is vastly more similar to modern humans than it is to apes. This explodes the WWU Legacy Review Task Force’s claim, stemming from Rupke, that there was a “Huxley’s Rule” stating that Africans were intermediate between whites and apes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this lecture, Huxley even challenged the very idea that “so-called higher” and “lower” races were meaningful categories. Undermining the idea that Africans are closer to apes, Huxley notes that “beyond everything”, human hair varies across the races, “[b]ut the apes were all straight-haired, like the respectable assemblage in that lecture theatre, and in that respect the white people were a great deal more like the lower animals than the negro was.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huxley also pillories Hunt’s absurd claim that Black people had projecting heels, a common enough topic for Huxley that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Wentworth_Higginson&quot;&gt;Thomas Wentworth Higginson&lt;/a&gt;, an American militant abolitionist who helped arm John Brown’s slave rebellion and who led the Union’s first Black regiment through 2 years of combat duty, specifically &lt;a href=&quot;https://nla.gov.au/nla.obj-895212518/view&quot;&gt;wrote Huxley&lt;/a&gt; in June 1867 to confirm that his soldiers wore the same boots as White soldiers. And anyway, says Huxley in his lecture, if the absurd claim were true, it would be more evidence that Whites were more apelike, as apes have short heels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turning to cultural attributes, Huxley points out how the technology and organization of societies is historically and culturally contingent, rather than some innate feature of races, noting that the Romans thought Britons and Germans were barbarians, but now these were technological leaders, and the Roman Empire was gone. He concludes by denying that “any of those differences observed among mankind were such as to justify the higher races in dealing with the lower differently from the manner in which the higher races thought themselves justified in dealing with each other.” By an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/3014371&quot;&gt;1870 lecture&lt;/a&gt; on geographic distribution of humans, Huxley abandons the usage of the terms “race,” “higher”, and “lower” (despite these terms still being utterly conventional at the time); by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/018467a0&quot;&gt;1878&lt;/a&gt; he emphasizes “social conditions which exercise an enormous influence” on the economic and political status of races. (Huxley is here commenting on Irish – Celts – towards whom there was a &lt;a href=&quot;https://victorianweb.org/history/race/Racism.html&quot;&gt;tremendous amount of racism in the Victorian era&lt;/a&gt;; Huxley opposed this consistently, again fighting James Hunt, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/3826928&quot;&gt;writing&lt;/a&gt; “the arguments about the differences between Anglo-Saxons and Celts are a mere sham and delusion.”)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;RadicalsRace1865&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Radicals and Race in 1865&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have seen the dangers in considering Huxley’s 1865 essay in isolation from Huxley’s other anti-racist activities. Yet another danger is ignoring historical context. To search for context, we have to consider the political issues of the day; because Huxley was staunchly antislavery and a political Radical, we should look to other antislavery Radicals. The U.S. Civil War was ending in 1865, and the Radicals were striving to solidify the Union’s victory with lawmaking achievements. Huxley’s 1865 statements should be compared to the 1865 comments of Thaddeus Stevens, the U.S. Congressman and Radical Republican. As surprising as it might be to modern readers, in the 1860s the Republicans were the “left-wing” party, insofar as modern categories are meaningful in the 1800s, and the Radical Republicans were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g7spJRHAnUU&amp;amp;t=2234s&quot;&gt;the most extreme&lt;/a&gt;, championing not just the abolition of slavery (13th Amendment) but, after Lincoln’s assassination, giving Black people equal rights and the vote (the 14th and 15th Amendments), impeaching Democrat Andrew Johnson (who opposed all of these measures), and leading the Radical Reconstruction, which included military occupation of the South, suppression of the KKK, the election of hundreds of Black state legislators, and redistribution of land confiscated from secessionists to Black people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thaddeus Stevens was one of the leaders of the Radical Republicans. For his efforts, he was hated by racist Southerners for generations, for example when pilloried as Austin Stoneman in the infamous 1915 movie &lt;i&gt;The Birth of a Nation&lt;/i&gt;, which inspired the second rise of the KKK. Given all of this, we might expect Stevens, of anyone, to have views acceptable to modern ears. But what did Stevens actually say in 1865?  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Final-Freedom-Abolition-Thirteenth-Historical-ebook-dp-B00174LWPA/dp/B00174LWPA/&quot;&gt;He said&lt;/a&gt;, “I never held to that doctrine of negro equality…not equality in all things – simply before the laws, nothing else.” Another historian &lt;a href=&quot;https://housedivided.dickinson.edu/sites/blogdivided/2013/02/22/how-the-lincoln-movie-reconstructed-thaddeus-stevens/&quot;&gt;calls this&lt;/a&gt; “part of a concerted radical strategy during this period to avoid inflammatory questions about racial equality” in order to accomplish the most important goal, passage of amendments and legislation.  (The episode was dramatized, perhaps &lt;a href=&quot;https://housedivided.dickinson.edu/sites/blogdivided/2013/02/22/how-the-lincoln-movie-reconstructed-thaddeus-stevens/&quot;&gt;overly so&lt;/a&gt;, in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/results?search_query=tommy+lee+jones+lincoln&quot;&gt;a famous Tommy Lee Jones scene&lt;/a&gt; in the 2012 Spielberg movie &lt;i&gt;Lincoln&lt;/i&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judging historical figures is therefore not so simple as mining historical material for sentence fragments that sound bad to modern ears, and evaluating them as if they were 2020s posts on Twitter. Returning to Huxley, several points deserve consideration. Throughout his career Huxley made a point to distinguish claims about facts from claims about values, often using his “vigorously paradoxical” style to dramatize the distinction. For example, in &lt;a href=&quot;https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=uc1.b000787429&amp;amp;view=1up&amp;amp;format=plaintext&amp;amp;seq=272&quot;&gt;1854&lt;/a&gt;, Huxley wrote something more “offensive” (out of context) than anything he said in 1865: “Grant that the negro is a distinct species, or even a metamorphosed orang…”  However, Huxley never actually believed either of these positions; his point was that it didn’t matter for the ethical argument. He went on to say “the most complete demonstration of the specific diversity of the types of mankind [i.e. polygenism, the racist position that different human races are different species] will nowise constrain science to spread her ægis over their [slaveholders’] atrocities,” and “Ethnology had better perish as a science than be swamped” by Southern sympathizers arguing for polygenism to support slavery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirty-nine years later, in his famous 1893 essay &lt;a href=&quot;https://mathcs.clarku.edu/huxley/CE9/E-E.html&quot;&gt;Evolution and Ethics&lt;/a&gt;, Huxley, as strong an evolutionist as any, affirmed that humans were subject to Darwin’s process of natural selection. But he departed radically from the “social Darwinism” and eugenics which were increasingly popular in the late 1800s, writing, “what we call goodness or virtue – involves a course of conduct which, in all respects, is &lt;i&gt;opposed&lt;/i&gt; to that which leads to success in the cosmic struggle for existence… the ethical progress of society depends, not on imitating the cosmic process, still less in running away from it, but in &lt;i&gt;combating&lt;/i&gt; it” (emphasis added). Again and again, Huxley makes his ethical points by saying that, even if his opponents’ claimed facts are admitted, they do not support the value judgments made. Modern readers are, of course, free to disagree with Huxley’s rhetorical strategy, but they should at least acknowledge that it exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;OtherWWUerrors&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Other WWU Task Force errors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the above information is easily accessible with a little scholarly due diligence, and these episodes are referenced in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mathcs.clarku.edu/huxley/guide18.html&quot;&gt;online Huxley File&lt;/a&gt;; yet none of it appears in the Task Force Report, despite nearly a year of controversy at WWU. While this shockingly poor form for an official report that is supposed to provide authoritative guidance for university decision making, it is perhaps not surprising, considering that the makeup of the Task Force failed to include any evolutionary biologists or historians of evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other Task Force errors flow from the lack of scientific input. Misunderstandings of the relevant science and history are rife. For example, the Task Force Report says that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;&quot;&amp;gt;“Genetic scientists have since disproved the notions of a ‘Black gene’ or ‘White gene’ and have disproven the idea that intragroup difference exceeds intergroup difference—establishing that race is a social, not biological, system.”&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Report is attempting to make the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2012/02/continuous-geog.html&quot;&gt;accurate statement&lt;/a&gt; that in humans, within-group genetic variance exceeds between-group variance, but the Report text actually states the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another mistake is the assumption that a “Black gene” vs. a “White gene” was a real discussion at any point. The word “gene” was not coined until the early 1900s, and Huxley died in 1895. “Gene” was not part of the conceptual framework of Huxley or any other evolutionists in the 1800s, who had to work with vaguer notions of heredity. The concept of a “Black gene” and “White gene” therefore could not have even been raised in the 1800s, and in fact was probably never a view held by any scientist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, part of the difficulty in accurately understanding Victorian-era comments on “race” is that cultural and biological inheritance &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-1-349-24950-3_7&quot;&gt;were very blurred in this era&lt;/a&gt;. After all, Darwin and others believed in the inheritance of acquired characteristics through use and disuse, and this opens up the possibility that cultural change could rapidly cause biological change. Taking the primarily 20th-century concept of “race” as genetic categorization, and uncritically reading it back into Victorian discussions of race, commits the historian’s fallacy of anachronism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the Task Force sidetracks into an irrelevant attack on Julian Huxley, grandson of T.H. Huxley (another grandson was Aldous Huxley, author of &lt;i&gt;Brave New World&lt;/i&gt;; their brother, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Huxley&quot;&gt;Sir Andrew Huxley&lt;/a&gt;, merely &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/medicine/1963/huxley/facts/&quot;&gt;won a Nobel Prize&lt;/a&gt;, and is the third most famous Huxley grandson). Julian was invited to speak at Huxley College (he declined due to advanced age). The Report notes Julian’s eugenics advocacy, but makes the absurd claim that this “suggests that the racist pseudoscience of ‘better breeding’ was seen as a legitimate aspect of [T.H.] Huxley’s legacy even after eugenics had been widely critiqued as unethical and potentially genocidal.”  This is made up out of whole cloth. Julian Huxley was a famous zoologist and popular science writer in his own right, one of the leaders of the “Modern Synthesis” in twentieth-century evolutionary biology. Julian’s legacy cannot be described as a racist eugenicist. He was actually known as a “reform” eugenicist, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/144521a0&quot;&gt;group known&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.nz/books/edition/Beyond_the_Laboratory/IzGtDwAAQBAJ?hl=en&amp;amp;gbpv=1&amp;amp;dq=%22A+Call+to+Scientists%22+Huxley+Haldane&amp;amp;pg=PA175&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&quot;&gt;strongly&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.nz/books?id=-c8aSO-gnwMC&amp;amp;q=exploitation+race+concept#v=snippet&amp;amp;q=exploitation%20race%20concept&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;and&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/jhered/article-abstract/30/9/371/791396&quot;&gt;publicly&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.nz/books/edition/Beyond_the_Laboratory/IzGtDwAAQBAJ?hl=en&amp;amp;gbpv=1&amp;amp;dq=%22A+Call+to+Scientists%22+Huxley+Haldane&amp;amp;pg=PA175&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&quot;&gt;opposing&lt;/a&gt; the Nazis &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/138988a0&quot;&gt;and their&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/134229a0&quot;&gt;racist&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/137635a0&quot;&gt;eugenics&lt;/a&gt; in the 1930s, well before World War 2. As a result this group did not associate their relatively restrained and anti-racist eugenic views with the Nazis after the war. On anti-racism, Julian Huxley was actually probably the most important anti-racist biologist of the mid-20th century. He coauthored the 1935 &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.nz/books/edition/We_Europeans/_4YYAQAAMAAJ&quot;&gt;We Europeans: A Survey of ‘Racial’ Problems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.nz/books?id=-c8aSO-gnwMC&amp;amp;vq=letter&amp;amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s&quot;&gt;historians&lt;/a&gt; “a popular and influential anti-racist statement,” “[a]mong the most important of this genre which helped undermine the scientific basis for racism.” Julian was also the founding director of UNESCO in 1946, and helped draft UNESCO’s famous anti-racism declarations in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.unesco.org/courier/july-august-1950&quot;&gt;1950&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000073351_eng&quot;&gt;1952&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://search.credoreference.com/content/entry/fofe/huxley_julian_s/0?institutionId=181&quot;&gt;Encyclopedia of Evolution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; says, “largely due to his efforts, the UNESCO statement on race reported that race was a cultural, not a scientific, concept, and that any attempts to find scientific evidence of the superiority of one race over another were invalid.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;HuxleyDEI&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;T.H. Huxley’s Advocacy for Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion in Science&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all the Task Force Report’s scholarly flaws, the most concerning is its claim that “Huxley contributed to upholding values that have made education less inclusive.” The reality is that Huxley promoted &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/621619&quot;&gt;scientific education&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.nz/books?id=hggzbROi9NcC&amp;amp;q=committee+of+ladies#v=snippet&amp;amp;q=committee%20of%20ladies&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;women&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://embryo.asu.edu/pages/thomas-henry-huxley-1825-1895&quot;&gt;working class&lt;/a&gt;. For example, in 1868 Huxley “&lt;a href=&quot;https://embryo.asu.edu/pages/thomas-henry-huxley-1825-1895&quot;&gt;inaugurated and became head&lt;/a&gt; of the South London Working Men’s College, which, along with its educational opportunities for working class men, held evening classes for women and kindergarten classes for the children of working class families.” His famous lectures ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/43410826&quot;&gt;On a piece of chalk&lt;/a&gt;’ and ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.nz/books?id=jJTzDwAAQBAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA16&amp;amp;lpg=PA16&amp;amp;dq=T+H+Huxley,+%22learned+from+a+piece+of+coal%22&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=Zy6l24aXSa&amp;amp;sig=ACfU3U0Q0ZK_v4F6LoClpkGKS0KAXhhN-w&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwj9kN3ksNjyAhXdzjgGHeZvBXYQ6AF6BAgCEAM#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=T%20H%20Huxley%2C%20%22learned%20from%20a%20piece%20of%20coal%22&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;What is to be learned from a piece of coal&lt;/a&gt;’ were designed in this period, serving as the basis for his 1877 book &lt;i&gt;Physiography&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/621619&quot;&gt;which&lt;/a&gt; “defined for a generation the way in which the earth’s physical features were studied in Britain; it defined also the nature of school education”, and “was the first thoroughly scientific presentation of elementary ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.nz/books?id=hggzbROi9NcC&amp;amp;dq=was+the+first+thoroughly+scientific+presentation+of+elementary+%27environmental+studies&amp;amp;q=environmental+studies#v=snippet&amp;amp;q=environmental%20studies&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;environmental studies&lt;/a&gt;‘”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1869, at the request of a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.nz/books?id=hggzbROi9NcC&amp;amp;q=committee+of+ladies#v=snippet&amp;amp;q=committee%20of%20ladies&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;committee of ladies&lt;/a&gt; ” he gave a course of 12 science lectures, with notes, to an audience of 300 women. He supported “Emily Davies in the establishment of Girton College for female university education, as he later did Maria Grey with her Girls’ Public Day School Company and her Bishopsgate Training College for Women,” opened his classes to women, hired a woman as a Physiology demonstrator, and backed the founding of London School of Medicine for Women. He said, “I am at a loss to understand on what grounds of justice or public policy a career which is open to the weakest and most foolish of the male sex should be forcibly closed to women of vigour and capacity”. Huxley was instrumental in addressing “the greatest need of all, a system of schooling for the children of the ordinary people, [which] had always been held up by the conflicting interests of the competing religious sects.” He gave another course of a dozen lectures to schoolchildren to illustrate his approach basing science education on local observation and applied common sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1869 Huxley &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.nz/books?id=hggzbROi9NcC&amp;amp;q=committee+of+ladies#v=snippet&amp;amp;q=committee%20of%20ladies&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;ran for and won&lt;/a&gt; a position on the newly-established London School Board, and chaired the “all-important Scheme of Education Committee,” which established “the pattern of infant, junior and senior schools which spread right across the land and lasted until the Act of 1944”, mandated standards for hygiene, restricted corporal punishment, and protected teachers’ authority from political interference. The inclusion of practical lab exercises in biology and earth science classes can be traced to his influence. This work included 170 committee meetings and extensive travel; in 1871 Huxley suffered “total collapse” and required extensive convalescence. Late in life he wrote, “I am glad to think that, after all these years, I can look back upon that period of my life as perhaps the part of it least wasted.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;footshooting&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Is WWU shooting its anti-racism goals in the foot?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bellinghamherald.com/news/local/news-columns-blogs/article22220466.html&quot;&gt;2014 retrospective&lt;/a&gt; on the key founder of Huxley College of the Environment, Jerry Flora, the &lt;i&gt;Bellingham Herald&lt;/i&gt; explored the origins of the name. Flora chose the name “Huxley” in the 1960s because he feared that the new environmental college “might stress ‘green’ consciousness over tested truth. ‘I wanted science, man,’ he recalled. ‘I wanted hard science.’” T.H. Huxley, as we have seen, was a leader in science and science education, spanning biological and earth sciences, a leader in distinguishing claimed facts and values, an important ethical thinker, a leader in promoting inclusion in science, and a leading opponent of the most prominent scientific racist of his day, the latter because Huxley’s science indicated the unity of the human species, and advocated for the common ancestry of humans with apes without claiming different races were transitional forms. Confronted with Huxley’s actual record, we should all ask ourselves: What have I done lately?  Can any reader say they have accomplished as much as T.H. Huxley? The names put on buildings and institutions are often arbitrary – the product of donor money or historical accidents. There ought to be a little space in the world for naming institutions after inspirational figures who changed the world for the better, even though such figures, as humans, are never perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Legacy Review Task Force, unfortunately, has so far failed to do its due diligence on Huxley’s legacy. The many flaws in the Task Force Report on Huxley show that moral outrage against racism and social injustice, while laudable, does not by itself supply reliable facts upon which to base decisions. The facts need to be determined by careful research, particularly in the case of historical figures with a record of activities and accomplishments so massive that even assembling a decent survey of them is challenging. Racial equality and equity, social justice, and diversity and inclusion are all crucial goals for any modern university, but by relying on badly flawed depictions of Huxley, WWU may end up shooting itself in the foot with respect to these goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does it serve justice to treat T.H. Huxley as if he were James Hunt or Governor Eyre, when he actually was their vehement opponent?  Removing Huxley’s name from the College would in fact be removing the name of a champion for educational inclusion, a key figure in scientifically establishing that all humans are one species, and undermining the concept of biological “race.” Doing so while relying on propaganda deriving from fundamentalist creationists and other right-wing provocateurs would be falling into the exact trap arranged by these provocateurs: namely, to drive a wedge between science and the causes of social and racial justice. Helping to drive this wedge deeper cannot help increase diversity, equity, and inclusion in science. Imagine creationists, for the next several decades, going to legislatures and state school boards with a line like: “Evolution is a racist theory. After all, Western Washington University acknowledged this when they removed the name ‘Huxley’ from their College of the Environment.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, there are wider implications for the credibility of academic institutions if renamings are premised on inaccurate, poorly-researched historical claims. First, far more important than the name of any university entity is the basic purpose of universities, namely, to promote truth and good scholarship. Renaming a building by accepting warmed-over creationist propaganda would only spread the propaganda further. Creationists would surely use a victory at the university level to push their evolution-is-racist material, which is &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/charles-darwin/racism/&quot;&gt;voluminous&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/?s=racism+Huxley&quot;&gt;and&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icr.org/home/submitsearch?f_search_type=icr&amp;amp;f_keyword_all=racism&amp;amp;module=home&amp;amp;action=submitsearch&amp;amp;search=AdvancedSearch&amp;amp;section=0&amp;amp;f_constraint=both&amp;amp;f_context_all=any&amp;amp;f_context_exact=any&amp;amp;f_context_any=any&amp;amp;f_context_without=any&amp;amp;op=&quot;&gt;pre-prepared&lt;/a&gt;, into the public schools. Second, establishing such a precedent could very easily backfire against social justice goals. Consider that the initial demand to the administration &lt;a href=&quot;https://as.wwu.edu/gov/board/&quot;&gt;submitted&lt;/a&gt; by WWU’s Black Student Organizations was to “Rename Huxley College, and rename campus buildings to honor important figures in Black History.” Surely it is worthwhile and important to memorialize important figures in Black History by naming buildings after them. But renaming Huxley College based on sloppy history derived from tendentiously selective portrayals of Huxley, assembled by his worst enemies, would create a precedent that could easily be turned against any other historical figure. All people are complex, and no historical figure who is memorialized for significant achievements that improved society will be unassailable if absolute perfection according to modern lights is the standard. This is particularly so if depictions by those motivated to portray them in an unfavorable light are adopted uncritically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;references&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As most references are online and hyperlinked, I list only a few particularly useful offline references.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorimer, Douglas A. (1978). &lt;i&gt;Colour, Class and the Victorians: English attitudes to the Negro in the mid-nineteenth century&lt;/i&gt;. New York: Holmes &amp;amp; Meier Publishers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watson, George (1977). “Race and the Socialists.” Chapter 8 of &lt;i&gt;Politics and Literature in Modern Britain&lt;/i&gt;. London: The Macmillan Press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Acknowledgements/Updates&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to everyone involved in the WWU/Huxley discussion. Thanks to John Wilkins for pointing out that “Darwin’s Bulldog” was a later moniker for Huxley, it was not used at the time, although &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linnean.org/news/2019/07/01/1st-july-2019-why-there-was-no-darwins-bulldog&quot;&gt;Huxley seems to have described himself that way to Henry Osborn&lt;/a&gt;, who recounted the story just after Huxley’s death. Updates: various minor updates to fix typos/links, add minor clarifications. 2021-10-29&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;KeyLinks&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Key Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;WWU_Task_Force&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;WWU Legacy Review Task Force (LRTF)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WWU Legacy Review Task Force page - links to reports, historian comments, etc.&lt;br /&gt;
https://president.wwu.edu/research-and-resources&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Why is TH Huxley Problematic? - report by WWU student Laura Wagner that uncritically gathered a great many extremist right-wing claims about TH Huxley. She was put on the Legacy Review Task Force (no evolutionary biologists or historians of science were on the Task Force), and much of this material ended up in the LRTF Report.&lt;br /&gt;
https://president.wwu.edu/files/2021-04/TH%20Huxley%20Research%20Document_%20_Why%20is%20TH%20Huxley%20problematic__.pdf&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;WWU Legacy Review Task Force (LRTF) Report&lt;br /&gt;
https://president.wwu.edu/files/2021-07/LRTF%20Report%20and%20Recommendations_June%202021.pdf&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Historian Paul White's report on Huxley, basically ignored by the LRTF&lt;br /&gt;
https://president.wwu.edu/files/2021-04/PS%20White%20Huxley%20Legacy.pdf&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;WWU_Response_to_Task_Force&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Responses to WWU’s LRTF Report&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Response to the Western Washington University Legacy Review Task Force Report by 10 WWU Faculty&lt;br /&gt;
https://huxley.wwu.edu/response-legacy-review-task-force-report&lt;br /&gt;
https://wp.wwu.edu/huxley-legacy/&lt;br /&gt;
https://huxley.wwu.edu/files/2021-08/Response%20to%20LRTF%20report%207-18-2021_1.pdf&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Response to the Western Washington University Legacy Review Task Force Report by 20 WWU Environmental Science Faculty&lt;br /&gt;
https://wp.wwu.edu/responseslegacyreviewtaskforce/files/2021/10/ESCI_Motion_Legacy_Review_Com_Final_Oct6-1.pdf&lt;/li&gt;


&lt;li&gt;Faculty response to Western Washington University’s proposal to cancel the name of T. H. Huxley&lt;br /&gt;
https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2021/08/20/response-to-proposal-to-cancel-t-h-huxley/&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;T. H. Huxley about to be cancelled at Imperial College London&lt;br /&gt;
https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2021/10/27/t-h-huxley-about-to-be-cancelled-at-imperial-college-london/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Imperial&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Imperial College, London&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imperial College 'History Group' that called for the removal of Huxley, Haldane, etc.&lt;br /&gt;
https://www.imperial.ac.uk/equality/activities/history-group/&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Imperial College London urged to remove statue and rename buildings&lt;br /&gt;
https://www.theguardian.com/education/2021/oct/26/imperial-college-london-urged-remove-statue-rename-buildings&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Adrian Desmond comments on Huxley&lt;br /&gt;
https://www.imperial.ac.uk/media/imperial-college/administration-and-support-services/equality/public/history-group/Appendix-10---Huxley-and-Racism-by-Adrian-Desmond.pdf&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Letter from Stephen Warren, astrophysicist at Imperial College&lt;br /&gt;
https://www.thetimes.co.uk/article/times-letters-tax-rises-and-sunaks-expansion-of-the-state-0tgc7lb9w&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;HUXLEY CONTROVERSY AT IMPERIAL&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Sir, The History Group at Imperial College London, my university, has recommended renaming the Huxley Building, among several changes (“Rename science buildings with eugenics links, university is urged”, Oct 27). I am sorry that it has chosen to judge people from the past by the standards of today. I would say that Thomas Henry Huxley is the individual of whom Imperial can be most proud. Rightly, he was and is widely admired. If Huxley is to be cancelled, no one from the past is secure. There are much better approaches. One is summarised in the careful report from Yale University on renaming buildings, which includes the recommendation to judge people by the times in which they lived, and to focus on a person’s principal legacies, because no one is perfect. The Imperial History Group was very aware of the Yale report.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Stephen Warren&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Professor of astrophysics, Imperial College London&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;Haldane (1938) on the Biology of Inequality, by Nick Matzke&lt;br /&gt;
    https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/haldane-1938-biology-of-inequality.html&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;blogs_media&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Blogs and Media&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(TBA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;This article was originally posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://osf.io/4smwv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and is reproduced at the request of the author. Matt Young will be the principal moderator. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Matzke</name></author><summary type="html">WWU’s Huxley College of the Environment may be renamed after a bizarre report uncritically plagiarising far-right creationist &amp;amp; conspiracist materials gets Thomas Henry Huxley exactly backwards on racism. From 2004-2007 Dr. Nick Matzke worked at the National Center for Science Education, including the Kitzmiller v. Dover court case that determined that teaching “intelligent design” in public schools was unconstitutional. He obtained his Ph.D. in Integrative Biology from the University of California, Berkeley, in 2013. He is now a Senior Lecturer in the School of Biological Sciences at the University of Auckland. This essay represents his personal scholarly views, not those of current or former employers. Update, November 2021: A similar situation has now broken out at Imperial College, London. A “History Group” review of colonialist legacies at Imperial has decided that the important thing to do is to target a Huxley statue and building, as well as room named for J.B.S. Haldane (apparently for discussing cloning; never mind Haldane’s strong socialism, critique of hardline eugenics, and explicit anti-imperialism). The name “Imperial College” appears to be untouched. An outline and list of “Key Links” has been added, along with various corrections/clarifications. (The original post and comments are here.) Outline Introduction Huxley’s anti-racist activities T.H. Huxley vs. Leading Scientific Racist James Hunt Huxley on the Jamaica Committee Huxley’s 1867 Birmingham lecture Radicals and Race in 1865 Other WWU Task Force errors T.H. Huxley's Advocacy for Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion in Science Is WWU shooting its anti-racism goals in the foot? References Key Links WWU Legacy Review Task Force (LRTF) Responses to WWU’s LRTF Report Imperial College, London Blogs and Media Introduction Western Washington University’s Huxley College of the Environment was founded in 1969, the year of the Santa Barbara oil spill, when the Cuyahoga River caught on fire, and when Earth Day was proposed. It is now one of the oldest and most prestigious environmental colleges in the country. It was named for Thomas Henry Huxley (1825-1895), famed not only as Darwin’s defender after the 1859 publication of the Origin of Species (“Darwin’s Bulldog” came into use in 1895), but also for his remarkable career, rising from a family too poor to pay for school to becoming a leading anatomist (proposing the kinship of humans with the great apes, and birds with dinosaurs), geologist, ethnologist, and philosopher (coiner of the word “agnostic,” foe of Social Darwinism). Above all he was a leading figure in making science a profession (rather than a hobby for priests and the landed gentry), and making a liberal science education available to all. Despite accomplishing more than most could ever dream for science and public science education, Huxley is now in the dock at WWU. The main charge is racism, with many at WWU calling for Huxley College to be renamed. WWU’s president commissioned a Legacy Review Task Force (LRTF) which issued a Report making the rather elliptical claim that Huxley’s “ethnological accomplishments were grounded in white supremacist values that dehumanize and harm many members of the Western community.” More directly, the Report indicts him for advocating polygenism (the idea that different human races are separate species) and “many negative generalizations on the basis of race.” Another charge was that “Huxley’s claims about the inexhaustibility of fisheries has contributed to the decline of the salmon runs that are central to Coast Salish cultures.” Are the accusations correct? A large debate could be had about the substantial difficulties of fully understanding the views of historical figures, let alone judging them. But clearly universities should not ignore major relevant evidence, nor rely on badly biased and one-sided presentations of the evidence.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ID advocates look forward to discovery of natural genetic engineering</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/discovery-of-natural-engineering.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ID advocates look forward to discovery of natural genetic engineering" /><published>2021-10-31T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-10-31T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/discovery-of-natural-engineering</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/discovery-of-natural-engineering.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Tacoma_Narrows_Bridge.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of the Tacoma Narrows Bridge&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to keep up with the Discovery Institute’s site Evolution News and Science Today’.  It used to
be called ‘Evolution News and Views’ but they presumably wanted to emphasize that all that was
published there is hard factual information, so they changed the name.  I am getting a bit
behind: on the 24th of September there was a remarkable article written by Brian Miller, the Research Coordinator
of the DI’s Center for Science and Culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the title “Nearly All of Evolution Is Best Explained by Engineering” &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2021/09/nearly-all-of-evolution-is-best-explained-by-engineering/&quot;&gt;his
post&lt;/a&gt; notes a
report that, as it describes “Transposable elements modify gene regulation in maize to confer drought tolerance,
alter flowering time, and enable plants to grow in toxic aluminum soils.”  He also mentions a number
of other cases in which organisms adapt rapidly in ways which seem to him to be the result
of their being engineered to do so.  His report is one in a series on a Conference on Engineering in
Living Systems (CELS) given in June and sponsored by the Engineering Research Group (ERG) of
the Center for Science &amp;amp; Culture of the Discovery Institute.  Proceedings of the CELS conference
seem not to be available online at this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To Miller, this seems to be evidence of the correctness of James Shapiro’s hypothesis of
Natural Genetic Engineering (NGE).  Shapiro’s view and many references to his summaries of it
can be found in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_genetic_engineering&quot;&gt;Wikipedia article on NGE&lt;/a&gt;.
He thinks that organisms adapt by containing mechanisms that propose, not random genetic variation, but
the genetic variation that is specifically needed in the current situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among advocates of ID, this has been greeted with enthusiasm.  At Uncommon Descent, their in-house
science reporter “News” (Denyse O’Leary) made a similar comment about a report that reptile teeth
were gained multiple times in evolution, &lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/evolution/reptiles-evolved-de-evolved-re-evolved-teeth/&quot;&gt;on
10/16/21&lt;/a&gt; she noted that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In short, when researchers actually looked at reptile tooth history, it was hardly a simple evolution tale at all. It seems as if there are plans that life forms can access, perhaps within their genomes. But how do they trigger the needed changes, as opposed to just going extinct?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of natural genetic engineering that responds adaptively by making the needed changes in the
genome, rather than by having natural selection pick them out from among available variation, is wildly
popular among ID advocates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are a few questions that need to be raised …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does NGE mean that when an organism is stressed by an environmental change, or by lack of
resources, it has a higher rate of mutation, including genomic changes such as chromosome
rearrangements?  There are numerous reports of this.  Is this an adaptation, or simply
the mechanisms of replication functioning less exactly when the organism is stressed?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are the mutants (including genomic changes) preferentially in an adaptive direction?  Or are
they, as usually happens, mostly neutral or deleterious?&lt;br /&gt;
Note that Brian Miller describes NGE by saying that
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;NGE refers to genetic alterations that are not random. Instead, they result from cells employing highly complex machinery to direct targeted DNA modifications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Where is natural selection in all of this?  If a mutation arises which is adaptive, is its
increase in frequency in the population due to its fitness advantage?  Or does NGE somehow
continually push it up in frequency?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Where in the genome is this mechanism?  And how does it know what the organism needs?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How is it maintained intact in the face of mutation?  If the genetic variations it induces
spread, do they only continue to be present in individuals whose NGE system is intact?  If so
that would be a mechanism maintaining NGE.  But recombination should rapidly break down any such
association.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There also seems to be an interesting contradiction between the NGE view and current advocacy by
young earth creationists.  The YECs are strongly pushing the idea that there are basically no
advantageous mutations.  NGE seems to say that its marvellous mechanisms guarantee mostly
superbly beneficial mutations.  Can these two views be reconciled?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian Miller, in EN&amp;amp;ST, actually goes so far as to declare that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Traditional evolutionary processes do play a part in biological adaptation, but mounting evidence demonstrates that their role is relatively minor in the drama of life …. Instead, engineered adaptive mechanisms that direct targeted modifications perform on center stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We await the answers to these questions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">I try to keep up with the Discovery Institute’s site Evolution News and Science Today’. It used to be called ‘Evolution News and Views’ but they presumably wanted to emphasize that all that was published there is hard factual information, so they changed the name. I am getting a bit behind: on the 24th of September there was a remarkable article written by Brian Miller, the Research Coordinator of the DI’s Center for Science and Culture. Under the title “Nearly All of Evolution Is Best Explained by Engineering” his post notes a report that, as it describes “Transposable elements modify gene regulation in maize to confer drought tolerance, alter flowering time, and enable plants to grow in toxic aluminum soils.” He also mentions a number of other cases in which organisms adapt rapidly in ways which seem to him to be the result of their being engineered to do so. His report is one in a series on a Conference on Engineering in Living Systems (CELS) given in June and sponsored by the Engineering Research Group (ERG) of the Center for Science &amp;amp; Culture of the Discovery Institute. Proceedings of the CELS conference seem not to be available online at this point. To Miller, this seems to be evidence of the correctness of James Shapiro’s hypothesis of Natural Genetic Engineering (NGE). Shapiro’s view and many references to his summaries of it can be found in the Wikipedia article on NGE. He thinks that organisms adapt by containing mechanisms that propose, not random genetic variation, but the genetic variation that is specifically needed in the current situation. Among advocates of ID, this has been greeted with enthusiasm. At Uncommon Descent, their in-house science reporter “News” (Denyse O’Leary) made a similar comment about a report that reptile teeth were gained multiple times in evolution, on 10/16/21 she noted that In short, when researchers actually looked at reptile tooth history, it was hardly a simple evolution tale at all. It seems as if there are plans that life forms can access, perhaps within their genomes. But how do they trigger the needed changes, as opposed to just going extinct? The idea of natural genetic engineering that responds adaptively by making the needed changes in the genome, rather than by having natural selection pick them out from among available variation, is wildly popular among ID advocates. But there are a few questions that need to be raised …</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chrysopa sp.</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/Chrysopa_sp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chrysopa sp." /><published>2021-10-25T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-10-25T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/Chrysopa_sp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/Chrysopa_sp.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Todd Shannon&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Todd_Lacewing_Eggs_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lacewing eggs&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://webdoc.agsci.colostate.edu/hempinsects/PDFs/Green%20Lacewings%20with%20Photos.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Chrysopa&lt;/i&gt; sp.&lt;/a&gt;, possibly &lt;i&gt;C. oculate&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; green lacewing eggs, Boulder, Colorado.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to detract from Mr. Shannon's photograph, but I rummaged around in my old files and found a snapshot I had taken of an adult lacewing, which I shall display below the fold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/IMG_0155_Lacewing_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lacewing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Todd Shannon. Chrysopa sp., possibly C. oculate &amp;ndash; green lacewing eggs, Boulder, Colorado. Not to detract from Mr. Shannon's photograph, but I rummaged around in my old files and found a snapshot I had taken of an adult lacewing, which I shall display below the fold.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interaction between science and religion</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/interaction-between-science-religion.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interaction between science and religion" /><published>2021-10-24T16:15:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-10-24T16:15:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/interaction-between-science-religion</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/interaction-between-science-religion.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Sinai_Synapses_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cover&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;Detail from the cover of the &lt;i&gt;Electronic Journal for Research
in Science &amp;amp; Mathematics Education&lt;/i&gt;, Vol. 25, no. 3, Fall, 2021.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If I had not been familiar with &lt;a href=&quot;https://sinaiandsynapses.org/&quot;&gt;Sinai and Synapses&lt;/a&gt;,* I might have dismissed this &lt;a href=&quot;https://ejrsme.icrsme.com/issue/view/1643/222&quot;&gt;special issue&lt;/a&gt; of an obscure journal as yet another attempt to use science to rationalize religious beliefs. It is nothing of the kind. The entire issue consists of essays by Fellows who have been supported over the years by the Sinai and Synapses organization, about which I have said a few words below, in an Endnote. The Fellows are experts in their fields and mostly faculty at secular universities. All of them, I am certain, know what they are talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The front matter contains helpful synopses of all the papers. Sometimes, I admit, the synopsis was all I wanted. I learned, however, that a second-century CE rabbi, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judah_ha-Nasi&quot;&gt;Judah ha-Nasi&lt;/a&gt;, had noted that “pestilence” often transferred from pigs to humans, so Rabbi Judah recommended fasting whenever pigs suffered pestilence. I wondered why on earth such an influential rabbi would care one whit about pigs, so I naturally turned first to the article, “Zoonotic pandemics and Judaism’s early-modern turn to science,” by Jonathan Crane of Emory University. I was relieved to find that Rabbi Judah did not raise pigs, but he had nevertheless noted the similarity between pigs’ organs and humans’. More strikingly, he recognized that diseases could be contagious and could be transferred from pigs to humans. Rabbi Crane introduces us to later Talmudic scholars who, in addition to citing earlier scholars and relying on their expertise, adduced their own evidence and required confirmation. Specifically, medieval Jewish scholars such as Maimonides accepted the scientific knowledge of their day, and the early modern period found Jews embracing “exogenous knowledge as well as the emerging means to discover and develop it.” Rabbi Crane continues, “To be precise, scientific method and evidence matter when it comes to physical issues like medicine and public health.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do I find this article important? Because if the ultra-Orthodox &lt;i&gt;Charedim&lt;/i&gt;, in both the United States and Israel, can be convinced that the sages accepted and indeed embraced the medical knowledge of their times and even understood zoonotic diseases, then we may have hope of getting them vaccinated and otherwise contributing to the battle against Covid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The need to convince people about scientific realities is not limited to the ultra-Orthodox. I next read the article, “Communicating with skeptical audiences,” by Matthew Groves. Mr. Groves is a high school science teacher and a faith educator who lives in rural Appalachia. His article primarily concerns convincing evangelicals of the reality of climate change. The data, as he says, are clear, “so how can people remain unconvinced?” He learned (slowly, I infer) to employ “the communication skills [he] developed as a teacher and a pastor and have found significant successes with audiences of all ages, denominations, and acceptance levels of climate science.” In short, language matters or, perhaps more precisely, terminology matters, and he has learned to strictly avoid technical terms and scientific jargon. The bottom line, to me, was somewhere in the middle of the article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;To get around [the vocabulary problem], oftentimes I completely avoid using these terms [climate change vs. global warming]. I often finish a full hour Sunday School class without using either, but end up in a place that’s much closer to where I want our conversation to culminate. We spend time talking about humanity’s relationship with God, each other, and nature, and therein I’ve been able to spark much more interesting conversations, which are fundamentally tied to climate change, than if I had started with throwing in those words initially and triggered someone’s sensitivities. If we can arrive at the conversations we want without tripping people up, all the better! This isn’t being dishonest, it’s just smarter communication. In my own work, if I walk into a church and trigger every audience member by leading with the climate-related issues that are sticking points for this community, no one will listen to me. This is true regardless of how central those tangential topics really are to solving the climate crisis – like its intersections with race, economics, gender, etc. When I plan my lessons, I think to myself: “&lt;i&gt;Here are the 8 words that will stop half of the audience from listening to me. How can I cover these concepts without saying those words?&lt;/i&gt;” [Italics in original.]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Mr. Groves notes that people may be “alarmed, concerned, cautious, disengaged,
doubtful, [or] dismissive,” and his job is to move them up the ladder one rung at a time, not all in one jump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I read the articles by Rabbi Crane and Mr. Groves, I began to wonder, in order to get through to religious conservatives, do you have to be one? Perhaps not, but it helps an awful lot to know how to sing the appropriate song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last article I have read, so far, at least, is “Overlapping magisteria: Motivated cognition and the places where science and religion mingle,” by Jonathan Morgan of the University of Colorado, Colorado Springs. Prof. Morgan introduces Stephen Jay Gould’s concept of Non-Overlapping Magisteria, or Noma. Prof. Morgan argues that, if the magisteria do not overlap, then at a minimum they encroach on each other’s properties (a claim that I made myself &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B079332NDB&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). The article is fairly dense and concentrates on areas where science may encroach on religion, as opposed to religion encroaching on science, which he says has been amply covered elsewhere. I will discuss only a very small part of it. The author devotes several paragraphs to free will, mostly demonstrating that a belief in free will may have practical consequences. Studying the consequences of believing in free will is not the same as asking whether we have it or not, but the author criticizes the studies for using science as a sort of default condition. I cannot disagree, though, that those of us who claim that we do or do not actually have free will may be leaving the domain of science and entering religion or philosophy, even as we think we are doing science. Are we engaging in motivated reasoning? Probably. Is it a problem? I will let Dr. Morgan explain:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;…when
science communicators venture onto metaphysical grounds, they risk threatening broad swaths of the
public who hold different theological views. …[W]hen people were presented with a highly credentialed scientist who was advocating for a position with which they disagreed, they were significantly less likely to rank that scientist as an expert. In other words, they did not dismiss the argument, they dismissed the source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When science communicators are representing capital “S” Science while staking out
metaphysical disagreements with religious worldviews, they risk undermining a broader sense of trust
in the expertise of science. This is risky because there are plenty of other issues around which scientists
are making well-founded inferences that people may still dislike–evolution, climate change, and
vaccinations are among the most well studied. We make it more difficult for public buy-in on these
contentious issues when science communicators are also making threatening incursions onto terrain
where they cannot actually stand on solid empirical ground.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I think we can infer that the best people to talk to groups like vaccination, global warming, or evolution deniers are members of those groups or at least people who understand them implicitly. Then, to return to Mr. Groves’s categories, we work them up the ladder one rung at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will eventually read more of the articles and will comment only if I think they are important enough. In the meantime, any readers who want to read one or more of the contributions are invited to discuss them in the Comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*A word about &lt;a href=&quot;https://sinaiandsynapses.org/our-mission-and-methods/ &quot;&gt;Sinai and Synapses&lt;/a&gt;. I think it is fair to say that it is a religious organization that is interested in scientific inquiry. It has been “incubated” by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.clal.org/&quot;&gt;Clal – The National Jewish Center for Learning and Leadership&lt;/a&gt; and provides education and seminars. I have listened to a few interviews presided over by Geoffrey Mitelman and attended two or three sessions of &lt;a href=&quot;http://sinaiandsynapses.org/scientists-in-synagogues/&quot;&gt;Scientists in Synagogues&lt;/a&gt; and found them at least mildly interesting. Scientists in Synagogues is partly funded by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.templeton.org/&quot;&gt;Templeton&lt;/a&gt;. I do not think Sinai and Synapses has any hidden agenda such as trying to mount a scientific defense of religion. And they have an exceedingly clever logo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Sinai_And_Synapses_Logo_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Logo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may find more about them on their website, above.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Detail from the cover of the Electronic Journal for Research in Science &amp;amp; Mathematics Education, Vol. 25, no. 3, Fall, 2021. If I had not been familiar with Sinai and Synapses,* I might have dismissed this special issue of an obscure journal as yet another attempt to use science to rationalize religious beliefs. It is nothing of the kind. The entire issue consists of essays by Fellows who have been supported over the years by the Sinai and Synapses organization, about which I have said a few words below, in an Endnote. The Fellows are experts in their fields and mostly faculty at secular universities. All of them, I am certain, know what they are talking about. The front matter contains helpful synopses of all the papers. Sometimes, I admit, the synopsis was all I wanted. I learned, however, that a second-century CE rabbi, Judah ha-Nasi, had noted that “pestilence” often transferred from pigs to humans, so Rabbi Judah recommended fasting whenever pigs suffered pestilence. I wondered why on earth such an influential rabbi would care one whit about pigs, so I naturally turned first to the article, “Zoonotic pandemics and Judaism’s early-modern turn to science,” by Jonathan Crane of Emory University. I was relieved to find that Rabbi Judah did not raise pigs, but he had nevertheless noted the similarity between pigs’ organs and humans’. More strikingly, he recognized that diseases could be contagious and could be transferred from pigs to humans. Rabbi Crane introduces us to later Talmudic scholars who, in addition to citing earlier scholars and relying on their expertise, adduced their own evidence and required confirmation. Specifically, medieval Jewish scholars such as Maimonides accepted the scientific knowledge of their day, and the early modern period found Jews embracing “exogenous knowledge as well as the emerging means to discover and develop it.” Rabbi Crane continues, “To be precise, scientific method and evidence matter when it comes to physical issues like medicine and public health.”</summary></entry></feed>