<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-07-10T14:36:11-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Does David Klinghoffer really want to have an exchange of ideas?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/07/klinghoffer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does David Klinghoffer really want to have an exchange of ideas?" /><published>2022-07-06T23:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-06T23:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/07/klinghoffer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/07/klinghoffer.html">&lt;p&gt;
UPDATE: July 8, 2022.  David Klinghoffer has now &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2022/07/rosenhouse-roundup/&quot;&gt;posted a link&lt;/a&gt; to my reply to William Dembski's review of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Failures-Mathematical-Anti-Evolutionism-Jason-Rosenhouse/dp/1108820441/ref=sr_1_1?crid=26C2DNOQ4ZV60&amp;amp;keywords=rosenhouse&amp;amp;qid=1657328451&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;sprefix=%2Cstripbooks%2C89&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot;&gt;my book&lt;/a&gt;.  He even encourages people to buy the book.  Thanks!   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On July 5, at 4:09 pm, Eastern time, I received the following email from the Discovery Institute's David Klinghoffer:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Dear Jason,

Your new book caught the attention of my Discovery Institute colleague Bill Dembski. We have been publishing his review of it serially at Evolution News, which I edit. Now that that’s done, as your time permits, I wanted to cordially invite you to respond to his review in the same forum, at whatever length you think is appropriate, without editorial interference. Since Dembski’s work is covered and critiqued extensively in your book, as he notes, I hope you will accept the offer, while giving me a reply to the invitation that I can share with our readers, whom I’ve alerted about this prospect for dialogue.

I look forward to hearing from you.

David
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Normally I would not publish a private email without the sender's permission, but in this case I think it's OK to do so.  You see, Klinghoffer was so pleased with this email that he posted it himself at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2022/07/invitation-to-jason-rosenhouse-respond-to-dembski/&quot;&gt;Discovery Institute's blog.&lt;/a&gt;  The title of the post was: Invitation to Jason Rosenhouse: Respond to Dembski.  He concluded the post with, &quot;Now let's find out what he will say.&quot;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At 4:17 pm, just eight minutes later, I sent the following reply to Klinghoffer:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Hi David.  Thank you for the invitation.  I have recently posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/07/Dembski-response.html&quot;&gt;a reply to Dembski&lt;/a&gt; at the Panda's Thumb.  I intend for that to be my last word on the subject.
  
Jason
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I write this, close to two days have passed, but Klinghoffer has not updated his original post to let his readers know that I had replied to Dembski.  Nor did he post something new indicating that I had done so.  One minute he's looking forward to hearing from me and musing about the prospects for dialogue, but the next it's crickets.
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  It's almost as if he didn't &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; want to have an exchange of ideas, but was instead just preening for his readers. He now knows &quot;what he will say&quot;, but seems afraid to let his readers in on it.  Why do you suppose that is?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;(Click on the title of this PT post to see comments).&lt;/strong&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jason Rosenhouse</name></author><summary type="html">UPDATE: July 8, 2022. David Klinghoffer has now posted a link to my reply to William Dembski's review of my book. He even encourages people to buy the book. Thanks! On July 5, at 4:09 pm, Eastern time, I received the following email from the Discovery Institute's David Klinghoffer: Dear Jason, Your new book caught the attention of my Discovery Institute colleague Bill Dembski. We have been publishing his review of it serially at Evolution News, which I edit. Now that that’s done, as your time permits, I wanted to cordially invite you to respond to his review in the same forum, at whatever length you think is appropriate, without editorial interference. Since Dembski’s work is covered and critiqued extensively in your book, as he notes, I hope you will accept the offer, while giving me a reply to the invitation that I can share with our readers, whom I’ve alerted about this prospect for dialogue. I look forward to hearing from you. David Normally I would not publish a private email without the sender's permission, but in this case I think it's OK to do so. You see, Klinghoffer was so pleased with this email that he posted it himself at the Discovery Institute's blog. The title of the post was: Invitation to Jason Rosenhouse: Respond to Dembski. He concluded the post with, &quot;Now let's find out what he will say.&quot; At 4:17 pm, just eight minutes later, I sent the following reply to Klinghoffer: Hi David. Thank you for the invitation. I have recently posted a reply to Dembski at the Panda's Thumb. I intend for that to be my last word on the subject. Jason As I write this, close to two days have passed, but Klinghoffer has not updated his original post to let his readers know that I had replied to Dembski. Nor did he post something new indicating that I had done so. One minute he's looking forward to hearing from me and musing about the prospects for dialogue, but the next it's crickets. It's almost as if he didn't really want to have an exchange of ideas, but was instead just preening for his readers. He now knows &quot;what he will say&quot;, but seems afraid to let his readers in on it. Why do you suppose that is? (Click on the title of this PT post to see comments).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Uncommon Descent tries to stay on topic</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/07/uncommon-diversion.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Uncommon Descent tries to stay on topic" /><published>2022-07-05T09:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-05T09:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/07/uncommon-diversion</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/07/uncommon-diversion.html">&lt;p&gt;
One can always count on the ID/creationist website Uncommon Descent for oddities.  Yesterday they noticed a post here: Timothy Sandefur's
discussion of the legal issues raised by the rightward move of the U.S. Supreme Court, and the legal theories the court majority used 
to address separation of church and state.  And how the court might now rule on a case like the Dover School Board case.  (Tim's post 
is of course, found &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/religious-conservatism-on-the-Supreme-Court.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
 The UD post &lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/at-pandas-thumb-worry-that-the-u-s-supreme-court-will-rule-for-creationism/&quot;&gt;(here)&lt;/a&gt; is 
 signed by their official reporter &quot;News&quot;, who seems these days to be physicist Eric Hedin. They first quote a paragraph from Sandefur's post 
 about the flaws in the legal theory of &quot;originalism&quot; used by the Supreme Court majority.  Then
they close in for the kill, saying:
&lt;blockquote&gt;For some, tormenting themselves with this stuff probably seems to make more sense than confronting the fact that 
Darwinism (which is generally what they mean by “evolution”) isn’t as widely believed as it used to be within biology. Never 
mind what a judge thinks should be taught to kids in school.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They follow this with a paragraph from the Discovery Institute site &lt;em&gt;Mind Matters&lt;/em&gt; touting a science commentary article from 
&lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt; which advocates the renaming of the Modern Evolutionary Synthesis because it has been incorporating 
too many new phenonmena.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Click on the title of this PT post to see comments)&lt;/strong&gt;.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">One can always count on the ID/creationist website Uncommon Descent for oddities. Yesterday they noticed a post here: Timothy Sandefur's discussion of the legal issues raised by the rightward move of the U.S. Supreme Court, and the legal theories the court majority used to address separation of church and state. And how the court might now rule on a case like the Dover School Board case. (Tim's post is of course, found here). The UD post (here) is signed by their official reporter &quot;News&quot;, who seems these days to be physicist Eric Hedin. They first quote a paragraph from Sandefur's post about the flaws in the legal theory of &quot;originalism&quot; used by the Supreme Court majority. Then they close in for the kill, saying: For some, tormenting themselves with this stuff probably seems to make more sense than confronting the fact that Darwinism (which is generally what they mean by “evolution”) isn’t as widely believed as it used to be within biology. Never mind what a judge thinks should be taught to kids in school. They follow this with a paragraph from the Discovery Institute site Mind Matters touting a science commentary article from The Guardian which advocates the renaming of the Modern Evolutionary Synthesis because it has been incorporating too many new phenonmena. (Click on the title of this PT post to see comments).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ardea herodias</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/07/ardea-herodias.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ardea herodias" /><published>2022-07-04T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-04T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/07/ardea-herodias</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/07/ardea-herodias.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Vivian Dullien&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/DSCN3777_Vivian_Heron_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Crepuscular Rays&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_blue_heron&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Ardea herodias&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; great blue heron, with fish.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Vivian Dullien. Ardea herodias &amp;ndash; great blue heron, with fish.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A reply to Dembski’s review of my book</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/07/Dembski-response.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A reply to Dembski’s review of my book" /><published>2022-07-03T09:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-03T09:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/07/Dembski-response</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/07/Dembski-response.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/RosenhouseCover3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Image of cover of Rosenhouse book]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
William Dembski has now reviewed my new book &lt;em&gt;The Failures of Mathematical Anti-Evolutionism&lt;/em&gt;.  His review comes to roughly 18000 words.  According to at least one standard classification scheme, that makes it a novella.  The full review can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://billdembski.com/intelligent-design/success-of-mathematics-in-advancing-intelligent-design/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  It is also appearing in sections at the Discovery Institute's site Evolution News (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/author/wdembski/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;p&gt;
It is a person of rare talent who can write at such length without getting anything right.  Dembski’s response consists mostly of lengthy, irrelevant digressions that have little to do with anything I actually wrote, out-of-context sentences and sentence fragments from my book that seem specifically intended to mislead his readers about my arguments, and his usual arrogance and self-puffery about his own brilliance.  He obsesses over minor comments I include in a chapter’s endnotes, while ignoring the main argument I made in the chapter itself.  When he does get around to responding to an argument, he seems in most cases not even to understand the point I was making.  Frankly, I could easily have written a more cogent reply to my own book.
&lt;p&gt;
I will only respond to what I regard as the most important points and will simply ignore large swaths of his review.  To anything that I do not specifically address, you can assume my response is to roll my eyes and say, “Whatever.  Let him blather.”
&lt;p&gt;
 &lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
 &lt;strong&gt;PROBABILITY CALCULATIONS&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anti-evolutionists routinely present spurious probability calculations meant to refute evolution.  In a lengthy chapter on probability, I explain that a proper calculation must take place in the context of what mathematicians refer to as a “probability space”.  For our purposes, this means that you must have a good grasp on the range of possible outcomes, as well as an understanding of the probability distribution appropriate to those outcomes.  In the context of the evolution of complex adaptations, we never have what we need to do this.  As Harvard biologist Martin Nowak put it, “You cannot calculate the probability that an eye came about.  We don’t have the information to make this calculation.”
&lt;p&gt;
I then considered several anti-evolutionist probability arguments, including the notorious flagellum calculation Dembski presented in his book &lt;em&gt;No Free Lunch&lt;/em&gt;.  I argued that his calculation was worthless for two main reasons: It was based on the false assumption that an “irreducibly complex” system could not evolve gradually, and it assumed a completely unrealistic model of how such structures arise.
&lt;p&gt;
How does Dembski respond to all this?  Mostly by complaining that I described his work as an attempt at “mathematical proof” that the flagellum is the result of intelligent design:
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Rosenhouse, as a mathematician, must at some level realize that he’s prevaricating.  It’s one thing to use mathematics in an argument.  It’s quite another to say that one is offering a mathematical proof.  The latter is much much stronger than the former, and Rosenhouse knows the difference.  I’ve never said that I’m offering a mathematical proof that systems like the flagellum are designed.  Mathematical proofs leave no room for fallibility or error.  Intelligent design arguments use mathematics, but like all empirical arguments they fall short of the deductive certainty of mathematical proof.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This appears in Section 9 of Dembski’s review.  This section is more than 1500 words, and it consists of little else than variations on this complaint.
&lt;p&gt;
If Dembski really wants to cavil over the difference between “mathematical proof” and “a mathematical argument so powerful it should convince any reasonable person” then he is welcome to do so.  None of my arguments are affected in the slightest by this sort of asinine rhetorical nitpicking.  My criticism of Dembski’s flagellum calculation was not that it falls short of deductive certainty.  Rather, my criticism was that the calculation was based on so many biologically ludicrous assumptions that it is completely worthless. 
&lt;p&gt;
The relevant paragraph from &lt;em&gt;No Free Lunch&lt;/em&gt; is this:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
An irreducibly complex system is a discrete combinatorial object.  Probabilities therefore naturally arise and attach to such objects.  Such objects are invariably composed of building blocks.  Moreover, these building blocks need to be [&lt;em&gt;sic&lt;/em&gt;] converge on some location.  Finally, once at this location the building blocks need to be configured to form the object.  It follows that the probability of obtaining an irreducibly complex system is the probability of originating the building blocks required for the system, multiplied times the probability of locating them in one place once the building blocks are given, multiplied times the probability of configuring them once the building blocks are given and located in one place.  (&lt;em&gt;No Free Lunch&lt;/em&gt; pp. 290-291)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I replied that this model for understanding the evolution of the flagellum is flatly ridiculous.  An irreducibly complex system cannot be treated as a discrete combinatorial object.  Nor can we model the construction of the flagellum by multiplying three independent probabilities related to origination, localization, and configuration.  All of this is discussed at length in my book.
&lt;p&gt;
In his review, Dembski makes no attempt to defend the biological legitimacy of his model.  Instead, he says things like this (still in Section 9):
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Thus, I’m supposed to be presupposing that irreducible complexity makes it impossible for a system to evolve by Darwinian means.  . . .  But that’s not what I’m doing.  Instead, I’m using irreducible complexity as a signpost of where to look for biological improbability.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That is a pretty strange thing to write, considering that in &lt;em&gt;No Free Lunch&lt;/em&gt; he wrote this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Richard Dawkins has memorably described this gradualistic approach to achieving biological complexity as “climbing Mount Improbable.”  . . .  For irreducibly complex systems that have numerous diverse parts and that exhibit the minimal level of complexity needed to retain a minimal level of function, such a gradual ascent up Mount Improbable is no longer possible. (&lt;em&gt;No Free Lunch&lt;/em&gt; p. 290)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
“A gradual ascent up Mount Improbable is no longer possible.”  Sure sounds like he is assuming that an irreducibly complex system cannot evolve gradually.  Moreover, irreducible complexity is only a signpost of where to look for biological improbability if you accept the premise that such a system cannot evolve gradually.  Since that premise is false, irreducible complexity is not a signpost for anything.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think what is going on here is that Dembski feels stung by another argument I present in my book.  I point out that in his discourse, it is really Michael Behe’s claims about irreducible complexity that are doing all the work.  The probability calculations do nothing to strengthen the argument.  Recall that Behe, in &lt;em&gt;Darwin’s Black Box&lt;/em&gt; wrote:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The result of these cumulative efforts to investigate the cell---to investigate life at a molecular level---is a loud, clear, piercing cry of “design!”  The result is so unambiguous and so significant that it must be ranked as one of the greatest achievements in the history of science.  The discovery rivals those of Newton and Einstein, Lavoisier and Schrodinger, Pasteur and Darwin. (&lt;em&gt;Darwin’s Black Box&lt;/em&gt;, p. 233)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
How interesting that Behe did not say, “Irreducible complexity in the cell is interesting and all, but what we &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; need is a probability calculation to seal the deal.”
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Returning to the review, after several paragraphs spent retreating from his own calculation, Dembski writes: 
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The fact is that they [Rosenhouse and his fellow Darwinists] have no probability estimates at all for the evolution of these systems.  Worse yet, because they are so convinced that these systems evolved by Darwinian means, they know in advance, simply from their armchairs, that the probabilities must be high.  The point of that section in &lt;em&gt;No Free Lunch&lt;/em&gt; was less to do a definitive calculation for the flagellum as to lay out the techniques for calculating probabilities in such cases (such as the perturbation probabilities)”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Of course&lt;/em&gt; we have no probability estimates for the evolution of these systems.  That is because probability theory is fundamentally the wrong tool for this particular job.  That’s the whole point!  Not only can you not rigorously calculate the probability of evolving a particular complex system, you cannot even estimate it in any reasonable way.  Martin Nowak had it exactly right.  
&lt;p&gt;
Dembski’s claim to have presented techniques for evaluating these probabilities is pure fantasy.  His calculations are just biological numerology.  He assigns numbers to objects in random ways and then, by manipulating the numbers, pretends that he has learned something about the objects.  Actually, he has only learned something about the way he assigned the numbers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And just to show that Dembski cannot be counted on to get even the simplest things right, let me also note that I certainly do not just assume that the probability of evolving a flagellum is high.  I distinctly remember writing “[T]he course of evolution is affected by so many chance events that the probability of any specific modern outcome of the process could be extremely low, but this does not make us suspect design, because &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; had to happen.  Therefore, some additional argument is needed to go from low probability to a conclusion of design” (p. 131).  I revisit this issue again on page 132, where I note that in considering anti-evolutionist probability, we need to pay attention to how they propose to get around this point (that low probability by itself does not mean much).  It arises again on page 139 in the context of Dembski’s flagellum calculation, and yet again on page 157 in the context of Behe’s probability calculations in &lt;em&gt;The Edge of Evolution&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To review: I argued that Dembski’s flagellum calculation was biologically ridiculous.  For obvious reasons, he is unable to offer any response to this simple point and does not even try.  Instead, he just whines about phrasing, presents ludicrous caricatures of what I said, and misses every important point.  This is representative of his entire review. 
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
 &lt;strong&gt;SPECIFICATION&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Dembski argues that it is not low probability by itself that implies design, but rather the combination of low probability with a recognizable pattern.  He refers to such a pattern as a “specification”.  
&lt;p&gt;
In simplistic examples it is easy to see what he means.  Any sequence of Hs and Ts in 100 coin tosses is as unlikely as any other, but 100 Hs, or a perfect alternation of Hs and Ts, embody patterns that make us think that something other than pure chance is involved.  Any pattern of crags and grooves on a mountain is incredibly unlikely, but the faces on Mt. Rushmore are such that we immediately infer design.
&lt;p&gt;
But there is an obvious problem with applying this notion to evolutionary questions:  How do we distinguish design-suggesting patterns from those we impose on nature through excessive imagination?  Dembski claims that we can use the function of a complex adaptation as its specification, but biologists claim that natural selection crafts functional structures as a matter of course.  Given this, does the function of a system suggest design or just natural selection?  How can we be confident that in using function as a specification we are not doing the equivalent of looking at a fluffy, cumulus cloud and seeing a dragon?  
&lt;p&gt;
In practical situations, we always make such judgements with the benefit of extensive background knowledge.  We know what usually happens when coins are tossed, and we know what mountains look like when people do not carve faces into them.  But we have no such background knowledge for evolution.  When considering the endpoints of billions of years of evolution, we have no base of experience for distinguishing design-suggesting patterns from those that can arise through natural selection.
&lt;p&gt;
How does Dembski respond to all of this?  Mostly by complaining that I do not discuss “specification” as an abstract concept.  He writes (in Section 10 of his review):
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Events become probabilistically more complex as they become more improbable (this is consistent with, as pointed out earlier, longer, more improbable sequences of coin tosses requiring longer bit strings to be recorded).  At the same time, descriptive complexity characterizes patterns that describe events via a descriptive language.  Descriptive complexity differs from probabilistic complexity and denotes the shortest description that will describe an event.  The specification in specified complexity thus refers to patterns with short descriptions, and specified complexity refers to events that have high probabilistic complexity but whose identifying patterns have low descriptive complexity.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
On and on he goes in this manner, for paragraph after tedious paragraph.
&lt;p&gt;
Dembski accuses me of being “especially hung up on [his] notion of specification.” This is a weird charge since actually I barely discuss the notion at all.  My only extended consideration of the concept occupies a mere seven pages (pp. 140-146), and the only reason the section is &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; long is that I spend several pages trying to bring clarity to Dembski’s frequently murky and overly-technical prose.  
&lt;p&gt;
Those seven pages appear in a section called, “Is the Flagellum Complex and Specified?” and that should give you a clue as to why I do not dwell on Dembski’s argle-bargle about complexity measures.  I did not discuss them because Dembski himself does not discuss them when he applies his ideas to the bacterial flagellum.  I was not discussing “complex, specified information” as a general approach to design-detection.  Instead, I was quite explicitly restricting my discussion to how Dembski applies his machinery to a biological case.  (More on this in the next section). 
&lt;p&gt;
With that in mind, let me show you Dembski’s treatment of the specification of the flagellum:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
[I]n the case of the bacterial flagellum, humans developed outboard rotary motors well before they figured out that the flagellum was such a machine.  This is not to say that for the biological function of a system to constitute a specification humans must have independently invented a system that performs the same function.  Nevertheless, independent invention makes the detachability of a pattern from an event or object all the more stark.  (&lt;em&gt;No Free Lunch&lt;/em&gt;, p. 289)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That is his entire discussion, and there is no mention of complexity measures at all.  When it comes time to apply his notions to a given biological system, Dembski apparently considers it sufficient just to refer vaguely to its function.  If Dembski does not think complexity measures are important in this context, then why should I?
&lt;p&gt;
The concern I raised was that saying of a flagellum that it resembles an outboard motor is comparable to saying of a cloud that it resembles a dragon.  There is nothing to allay this concern in Dembski’s review, but he &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; mention something called “detachability” in the quotation above.   And that is why I discuss the notion of detachability at some length in my book.  I present Dembski’s incredibly technical definition in full (p. 141-142), carefully explain what it means, and then discuss why it does not address the concern I raised.
&lt;p&gt;
Dembski’s definition includes numerous abstract objects: a reference class of possibilities, a chance hypothesis, a probability measure, a rejection function, and a notion of background knowledge that is defined in terms of certain conditional probabilities.  It is basically a bowdlerized version of Fisherian hypothesis testing, for those with some statistical background. 
&lt;p&gt;
But if we have little hope of defining a probability space sufficient for carrying out calculations about flagella, we have even less hope of finding real-world counterparts for any of the abstract objects in Dembski’s definition of “detachable”.  This is especially true for the part about background information, as I have noted.  
&lt;p&gt;
In &lt;em&gt;No Free Lunch&lt;/em&gt;, Dembski does not even try to define the real-world counterparts of his abstract constructs.  He presents no reference classes, probability measures, rejection functions, or relevant background knowledge.  He just looks at the flagellum and says, “Kinda looks like an outboard motor.”  Dembski’s liberal use of notation and jargon is useful for creating the illusion that something deep has been said, but all of that machinery goes clean out the window when it is time to apply it to evolution.
&lt;p&gt;
 &lt;strong&gt;CONSERVATION OF INFORMATION&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another aspect of Dembski’s discourse is his use of the “No Free Lunch” theorems.  These are actual mathematical results that say, roughly, that the average performance of a search algorithm over all possible landscapes is no better than blind search.  This might make us wonder why nature presents us with just the sort of fitness landscapes on which evolution is effective.  
&lt;p&gt;
Dembski, Robert Marks, and Winston Ewert claim to have extended these theorems.  They refer to their results as “conservation of information” theorems.  They define a quantity called “active information”, which roughly refers to the background information brought by a researcher to a specific search problem.  Their main theorem then shows that within their formalism, the amount of information outputted by the algorithm cannot exceed the active information brought by the researcher to the problem.
&lt;p&gt;
In this way, they argue that evolutionary algorithms cannot create novel information.  They also spend a lot of time criticizing “artificial life” experiments on the grounds that they achieve such results as they do only because the researchers bring illicit active information to their work.
&lt;p&gt;
In my book, I offer many points in reply.  Among other things, I note that it is very unclear that evolution really is a search in the precise technical sense assumed by the No Free Lunch theorems.  We have here another instance of Dembski bringing difficult mathematical formalism into his discussions, but then not really using the formalism to do anything.  This is why David Wolpert, one of the discoverers of the original No Free Lunch theorems, described Dembski’s arguments as “fatally informal and imprecise” and as being “written in jello.”  He elaborated:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
There simply is not enough that is firm in his text, not sufficient precision of formulation, to allow one to declare unambiguously “right” or “wrong”. . . .The values of the factors arising in the NFL theorems are never properly specified in his analysis. . . .[T]hroughout, there is a marked elision of the formal details of the biological processes under consideration.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Dembski’s arguments do not improve when he starts extolling the virtues of his so-called conservation theorems.  As applied to biology, his argument is nothing more than the claim that nature has to be a certain way for evolution to work.  Most of us did not need difficult mathematical theorems to understand this.  The fitness landscapes confronted by evolving organisms arise ultimately from the laws of physics, and Dembski and his collaborators are really just asking why the universe is as it is.  It's a perfectly good question, but hardly one within biology’s domain.
&lt;p&gt;
How does Dembski respond to this?  Mostly by complaining that I did not cite his technical papers laying out the theoretical apparatus underlying his theorems (we are now in Section 13 of the review):
&lt;blockquote&gt;
As with specified complexity, in proving conservation of information theorems, we have taken a largely pre-theoretic notion and turned it into a full-fledged theoretic notion.  In the idiom of Rosenhouse, we have moved the concept from level 1 to level 2.  A reasonably extensive technical literature on conservation of information theorems now exists.  Here are three seminal peer-reviewed articles addressing these theorems on which I’ve collaborated. . .
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
He now presents the bibliographic information for three of his papers and writes “Rosenhouse cites none of this literature.”
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, first of all, my idiom was “track 1” and “track 2”. Just saying.
&lt;p&gt;
Secondly, do take a moment to savor the planet-sized ego it takes for anyone to describe his own work as “seminal”.  For those unfamiliar with this term, academics use it to refer to work that was not only original and important when it first appeared, but which also inspired new avenues of investigation for other researchers.  It is a term of respect bestowed by others years after a work is published and has proven its fruitfulness.  Big egos are an occupational hazard in academe, but absolutely nobody describes his own work as seminal, especially when few other researchers seem to have paid any attention to it.  See my earlier comment regarding arrogance and self-puffery.
&lt;p&gt;
Now let us see if we can come up with a reason why I did not cite those papers in my book.  In fact, maybe we should check to see if I explained precisely this point in the book itself:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
[W]e find ourselves in the same position we were in back in Section 5.6.  We saw that Dembski claimed to have produced a piece of mathematical machinery---complex, specified information---that could be used to distinguish things that must have been designed from things that could be explained in some other way.  He then proposed to apply this machinery to biology and claimed thereby to show that intelligent design is in some way implicated in natural history.  We decided that we did not need to examine every piece of the machinery since we only cared about its claimed application to biology.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And so it is here.  It would take many pages to explain and analyze the mathematical formalism proposed by [Marks, Dembski, and Ewert], but it would not further our agenda to do so.  If they want to apply their techniques to abstract problems in combinatorial search, then they are welcome to do so.  Whether such proposed applications have any merit would be a topic for a different book.  Our interest here is solely in the manner in which they apply their machinery to biology.  (pp. 212-213)
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I based my discussion of “conservation of information” on their book &lt;em&gt;Introduction to Evolutionary Informatics&lt;/em&gt;, published in 2017.  They rather pompously describe their book as a monograph, which I took to mean they regarded it as primarily a work of scholarship as opposed to mere popularization.  The book is far more recent than the papers Dembski mentions, and it is specifically about the proposed applications of their ideas to evolution.  
&lt;p&gt;
See the point? I was writing a book about mathematical anti-evolutionism (note the title).  The three papers Dembski faults me for not citing do not discuss biological questions.  That is why I did not cite them.  I cited recent writing that addresses the subject of my book, and I ignored older work that was irrelevant to my subject.  How does this reflect poorly on me?
&lt;p&gt;
We are now in Sections 12 and 13 of Dembski’s review.  True to form, he goes on and on about his own brilliance and technical sophistication.   He hurls plenty of personal insults, out-of-context sentence fragments, and silly caricatures of my arguments.  But it is worth wading through this because when he eventually turns his attention to what I actually said, the result is wonderfully demented.  Demsbki writes:
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
True, he [Rosenhouse] dismisses conservation of information theorems as in the end “merely asking why the universe is as it is.” (p. 217)  But when discussing artificial life, he admits, in line with the conservation of information theorems, the crucial information is not just in the algorithm but also in the environment. (p. 214)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let us have a look at what I actually said on page 214.  I had just quoted a paragraph (a whole paragraph, mind you, in contrast to Dembski’s habit of just quoting sentence fragments from me) from their book in which they were critical of the well-known Avida experiment. I replied thusly:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
It is on the basis of such arguments that [Marks, Dembski, and Ewert] dismiss computer simulations of evolution as unrealistic, but their logic is hard to follow.  It is self-evident that the Avida organisms found evolutionary success in part because the researchers created an environment in which success was possible.  However, it is equally self-evident that the algorithm plays a big role in the success.  That is, Avida’s organisms achieved success because a particular algorithm interacted with a particular environment.  The algorithm and the environment are both critical, and therefore it is plainly wrong to say, “This active information source is the reason for Avida’s success.” (p. 214)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some admission.  What could be more obvious than that the environment and the algorithm are both important in evolution?  Who needs difficult mathematical theorems to grasp that point?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Dembski now writes:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Yet if the crucial information for biological evolution (as opposed to artificial life evolution) is built into the environment, where exactly is it and how exactly is it structured?  It does no good to say, as Rosenhouse does, that “natural selection serves as a conduit for transmitting environmental information into the genomes of organisms.”  (p. 215) That’s simply an article of faith.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
He now presents a somewhat cryptic quote from Holmes Rolston.  Picking up the action on the other side:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
So no, the information was not always there.  And no, Darwinian evolution cannot, according to the conservation of information theorems, create information from scratch.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Dembski is descending into gibberish here, and his point is becoming hard to discern.  I do not know what he means by “the information was not always there”.  &lt;em&gt;What&lt;/em&gt; information was not always &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt;?  Since evolution requires an interaction between the genetic systems of organisms and the environments in which they find themselves, I do not know what it means to say that the “crucial information . . . is built into the environment.”  The environment and the organisms are both crucial; why single out one or the other?  And since Darwinian evolution assumes that we already have both organisms and environments, I do not know what it means to suggest that Darwinian evolution “creates information from scratch”. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So let us back up a bit and try to bring some blessed clarity to the discussion.  
&lt;p&gt;
First, there is no mystery as to how standard evolutionary processes can create new genes and adaptations.  Every step in the process has been observed and is well-understood.  Genes really do mutate, sometimes leading to new functionalities.  Natural selection really can string together several such mutations, leading to changes in gene pools and to better adapted organisms.  Gene duplication with subsequent divergence plainly leads to increased genome sizes and to new opportunities for innovation.  There is no article of faith here, just simple empirical facts.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Plainly, such processes lead to the creation of novel genetic information by any reasonable definition of the term “information”.  When biologists say that natural selection is a mechanism through which new genetic information can be created, this is what they mean.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now let us turn to that sentence fragment about natural selection being an information conduit.  Had Dembski quoted even a little of the surrounding context, it would have been clear that I was referring back to a discussion from earlier in the book in which I explored these issues at length.  Dembski asks for where nature’s information is and for how it is structured.  I addressed that question thusly:
 &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
[T]here is nothing wrong with viewing natural selection as an information conduit between the environment and a population’s gene pool.  Recall that according to Shannon’s conception, information content is something possessed by an event in a probability space.  Seen in that way, any physical system that can exist in more than one state can contain information.  This is because if the system can exist in more than one state, then there must, in principle, be a probability distribution that describes the likelihood of being in one state versus another.  And since the local environments in which gene pools find themselves can certainly exist in many states, it is not an abuse of language to say the environment contains information.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This can actually be an illuminating metaphor.  There is a strong sense in which the gene pools of modern organisms can be said to record information about the ancestral environments in which they evolved.  The process is not much different from receiving medical information from your doctor and then making lifestyle changes as a result.  Just as your doctor gives you information on how to live a healthier life, so too does the environment give information to a gene pool about how better to survive.  In the language of information theory, we would say this is communication through a noisy channel because natural selection is not the only mechanism of change, and evolution is not always adaptive.  But it is an interesting way of looking at things nevertheless.  (p. 204)
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, does this constitute evolution creating information “from scratch”?  Since Dembski and his coauthors are the only ones who talk like that, I am not sure what the question means.  But in my book, I make the following point:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Standard evolutionary mechanisms have the ability both to increase the information storage capacity of the genome through gene duplication, and to refine, via mutation and natural selection, the information stored there, resulting in better-adapted organisms.  This is what is meant when scientists attribute to evolution the ability to create new information.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you now want to play gotcha, and argue that evolution did not &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; create information but only transformed preexisting information in the environment, then you are welcome to do so.  However, it is no great accomplishment to make this observation.  If you are just saying that nature has to be a certain way for evolution to work then you can just assert it as obvious without further argument.  You do not need to write lengthy books to defend this claim, or to deploy difficult mathematical theorems in support of it. (p. 205)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, what of Dembski’s assertion that “the information was not always there”?  Well, what was “there” was a source of information that had the potential to be modified by organisms into functional structures.  That information is found in the collection of possible environmental states, which in turn determine what constitutes fitness for the organisms living in those environments.  
&lt;p&gt;
Does that preexisting environmental information need to be explained by reference to intelligent design?  According to Dembski, that would only follow if environmental information were an instance of complex, specified information.  Good luck showing that it is.  You will run into all the same problems we have already seen.
&lt;p&gt;
 &lt;strong&gt;MISCELLANEOUS WEIRDNESS&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I have shown that Dembski has not replied seriously to any of the major points I raised about his work.  But I do not think I have really done justice to just how poorly done his review really is.  You can start reading at any random point, and you will very quickly come to something stupid.  
&lt;p&gt;
In Section 4, Dembski writes, “But Rosenhouse’s Darwinism plays to the lowest common denominator.  Throughout the book, he hammers on the primacy of natural selection and random variation, entirely omitting such factors as symbiosis, gene transfer, genetic drift, the action of regulatory genes in development, to say nothing of self-organizational processes.”
&lt;p&gt;
I do not discuss those things because I was not writing a general treatise on evolutionary biology.  The way you could tell is that in the Preface I wrote, “I am not writing a general treatise on evolutionary biology.”  I elaborate on this as follows:
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Let me be clear that this is a mathematics book that also discusses biology, as opposed to a biology book that also discusses mathematics.  Inevitably, there are places where we must get our hands dirty by digging into the biological details, but my central points are mathematical and not biological.  Biologists will rightly criticize me for presenting a simplistic version of evolutionary theory.  I focus almost entirely on natural selection acting at the level of genes, but everyone understands that there is far more to evolution than this . . . My argument is essentially that even if we take this narrow understanding of evolution as out starting point, we still have more than enough resources to refute any gambit coming from the other side. (p. xiv)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Moving on, in my book I often use the image of “track one” and “track two” mathematics.  Track one is our intuitive understanding of abstract objects, while track two is the rigorous technical detail found in textbooks and journal articles.  I use this distinction in part as a convenient way of describing different sorts of errors in mathematical anti-evolutionism.  Sometimes they argue vaguely at a track one level, but the rigorous details needed to make the argument convincing are just completely lacking.  Other times they provide very technical track two arguments, but when you try to understand what is really going on you find that it is all just meaningless gobbledygook.  All I am really saying is that a good mathematical argument should be both precise and comprehensible.  
&lt;p&gt;
I thought I was stating the obvious, but my track one/track two distinction seems to have driven Dembski completely insane.  Section 7 of his review consists of ten full paragraphs of bizarre ranting about it, all of it nonsensical.  He declares that in making this distinction I am setting myself up as a “math cop, stipulating the rules by which design proponents may use mathematics against Darwinism and for intelligent design.”  He then accuses me of not playing by own rules:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Even so, having set the standard, Rosenhouse should meet it.  But he doesn’t.  For instance, when he describes a standard statistical mechanical set up of gas molecules in a box, he remarks: “We are far more likely than not to find the molecules evenly distributed,” (p. 234)  I would agree, but what exactly is the probability space and probability distribution here.  . . . But given the weight he puts on statistical mechanics in refuting appeals by creationists to the Second Law of Thermodynamics, once could argue that he had no business confining himself to track 1. 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Of course&lt;/em&gt; my description of statistical mechanics took place at a track one level.  That is because I was simply trying to explain a few basic points to a non-scientific audience.  But if instead I was arguing that physicists from Boltzmann onward were hopelessly incompetent at their discipline, and that they clung to their views only out of morbid anti-religious bias, then I think the physicists could reasonably request that some track two details be provided.
&lt;p&gt;
And just as another example of Dembski being unable to get even the simplest things right, I should point out that actually I barely discuss statistical mechanics at all.  The only reason I even mention it is that certain specific anti-evolutionists bring it up in their own writing.  But the fact is that I devote far more space to the classical understanding of the second law than I do to statistical mechanics.
&lt;p&gt;
I am not setting myself up as a cop, I am not making arbitrary rules, and I do not just make random declarations about what is track one and what is track two.  Dembski just made up all of that. I use the track one/track two distinction simply as a way of organizing broad classes of errors that anti-evolutionists make.  When they equate entropy to randomness, or when they model the formation of a protein as a simple problem in discrete probability, then they are making track one arguments that fail as soon as you try to formulate them with track two rigor.  When they produce elaborate technical models with copious jargon and notation, but then fail to link up their abstract constructs to anything in reality, they are presenting track two arguments with no track one interpretation.
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, I cannot let this one go by.  In Section 13 Dembski writes:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
What this means is that conservation of information is not tied to uniform probability or equiprobability.  Rosenhouse, by contrast, claims that all mathematical intelligent design arguments follow what he calls the Basic Argument from Improbability, which he abbreviates BAI (p. 126).  BAI attributes to design proponents the most simple-minded assignment of probabilities (namely uniform probability or equiprobability).  
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
There is a reason Dembski does not quote me actually saying that all mathematical intelligent design arguments follow the pattern of the BAI.  He does not even provide an out-of-context sentence fragment to give the false impression that I am claiming such a thing.  
&lt;p&gt;
My discussion of the BAI occurs in Section 5.5 of my book, in the chapter on probability theory.  If I really believed that all mathematical ID arguments fall under the BAI, then one wonders why this chapter went on for another 30 pages after this section was finished.  Not to mention that the book goes on for more than 150 pages past this point.  I even conclude this section by explicitly contrasting the extreme simple-mindedness of the BAI with the superficially more sophisticated probability arguments of certain ID proponents.  Dembski’s characterization of this section is just completely made up.
&lt;p&gt;
 &lt;strong&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We have barely scratched the surface of all that is wrong with Dembski’s review.  He has not responded effectively to any of the main arguments of my book, and he has made no attempt even to characterize them with any honesty or integrity.  
&lt;p&gt;
Ultimately, for all his interminable ranting, blather, and self-admiration, the bottom line is this:  His notion of complex, specified information is a complete non-starter in the context of evolution.  We cannot establish complexity because we cannot even approximate, much less calculate, the probabilities his model requires,  and we cannot establish specificity because we have nothing like the background knowledge we would need to distinguish design-suggesting patterns from those that can be explained by natural selection.  His arguments about the No Free Lunch/Conservation of Information theorems likewise have no relevance to evolutionary questions.  It is not even clear that these theorems apply straightforwardly to biological evolution, but regardless, they imply nothing more than that nature has to be a certain way for evolution to be viable.
&lt;p&gt;
Looks like I could have written a shorter book!  Dembski does not even lay a finger on any of these points.  And he never will be successful in doing so, even if he writes another 18000 words.
&lt;p&gt;
Dembski understandably focused on that portion of my book that dealt with his own writing, but this is only a very small portion of the book overall.  Have a look for yourself!
&lt;p&gt;
 &lt;strong&gt;Related Posts&lt;/strong&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
 Jerry Coyne reviews the book at his site Why Evolution Is True &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2022/06/28/jason-rosenhouses-new-anti-id-book/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;p&gt;
 Matt Young reviews the book at Panda's Thumb &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/Mathematical-Anti-Evolutionism.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;p&gt;
 Joe Felsenstein reviews the book at Panda's Thumb &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/rosenhouse-on-mathematical-anti-evolutionism.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;p&gt;
 I announced the book and offer some general thoughts about mathematical anti-evolutionism at Panda's Thumb &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/futility-anti-evolutionary.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  I also provided some additional commentary on this subject &lt;a href=&quot;https://skepticalinquirer.org/2022/05/the-failures-of-mathematical-anti-evolutionism/&quot;&gt;in an article&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;em&gt;Skeptical Inquirer&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jason Rosenhouse</name></author><summary type="html">William Dembski has now reviewed my new book The Failures of Mathematical Anti-Evolutionism. His review comes to roughly 18000 words. According to at least one standard classification scheme, that makes it a novella. The full review can be found here. It is also appearing in sections at the Discovery Institute's site Evolution News (see here). It is a person of rare talent who can write at such length without getting anything right. Dembski’s response consists mostly of lengthy, irrelevant digressions that have little to do with anything I actually wrote, out-of-context sentences and sentence fragments from my book that seem specifically intended to mislead his readers about my arguments, and his usual arrogance and self-puffery about his own brilliance. He obsesses over minor comments I include in a chapter’s endnotes, while ignoring the main argument I made in the chapter itself. When he does get around to responding to an argument, he seems in most cases not even to understand the point I was making. Frankly, I could easily have written a more cogent reply to my own book. I will only respond to what I regard as the most important points and will simply ignore large swaths of his review. To anything that I do not specifically address, you can assume my response is to roll my eyes and say, “Whatever. Let him blather.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Religious Conservatism on the Supreme Court: Implications for Creationism?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/religious-conservatism-on-the-Supreme-Court.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Religious Conservatism on the Supreme Court: Implications for Creationism?" /><published>2022-06-28T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-28T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/religious-conservatism-on-the-Supreme-Court</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/religious-conservatism-on-the-Supreme-Court.html">&lt;p&gt;It’s always a risky game to predict what the Supreme Court will do about anything, but we can always discern the general trends, and as a decades-long member of the (spooky, scary!) Federalist Society, I thought I’d take a crack at answering the first three of Joe Felsenstein’s questions about the future of teaching evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;What would this court do if asked to decide a case similar to the Dover School Board case?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kitzmiller_v._Dover_Area_School_District&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;the Dover case&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; — which, believe it or not, is going on 20 years ago, now — the district court found that the school board violated the First Amendment by adopting an “Intelligent Design Policy.” This policy required that a statement be read to students in ninth grade biology class which said that biological evolution “is not a fact,” that it contained “gaps ... for which there is no evidence,” and that “Intelligent Design ... differs from Darwin’s view.” It encouraged students to consult &lt;em&gt;Of Pandas and People&lt;/em&gt;, a book which advocated ID creationism, and which was made available to students. After a thorough trial on the factual issues, the court found this unconstitutional using two different legal tests: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Endorsement_test&quot;&gt;“Endorsement Test”&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lemon_v._Kurtzman#Lemon_test&quot;&gt;“Lemon test.”&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;
These tests are intellectual devices judges use to answer whether government has crossed the constitutional lines that bar it from either establishing a religion — that is, creating an official church or creed of some kind — or inhibiting the free exercise of religion — that is, punishing or burdening someone for practicing a faith. And these two tests are quite similar. The Lemon test, however, is a three-part analysis dating back to the 1971 case of &lt;em&gt;Lemon v. Kurtzman&lt;/em&gt;. The Endorsement Test is somewhat older.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Endorsement Test asks “whether an objective observer, acquainted with the text, legislative history, and implementation of the [law being challenged in court], would perceive it as a state endorsement of prayer in public schools,” or, to put it another way, whether it “sends the ancillary message to members of the audience who are non-adherents that they are outsiders, not full members of the political community, and an accompanying message to adherents that they are insiders, favored members of the political community.”
&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;em&gt;Lemon&lt;/em&gt; test is somewhat more comprehensive. It asks three questions: whether the challenged law has a secular purpose, whether its principal or primary effect is to advance or inhibit religion, and whether it creates an “excessive entanglement” with religion — meaning, whether it draws government too close to a church.
&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;em&gt;Lemon&lt;/em&gt; test has come under a lot of criticism over the years, primarily by religious conservative justices such as Antonin Scalia and Clarence Thomas, who view it as either too vague to be helpful or as inherently biased against religion. They think courts applying the Lemon test tend to unfairly block the government from engaging in policies that do nothing more than treat religious people or institutions equally. Personally, I’ve never found this argument persuasive — and I’ve never seen anyone offer a really good alternative to Lemon — but it’s been a major issue among conservative lawyers, who think Lemon does not lead to true religious neutrality, but instead tends to exclude religious perspectives from government policy even where those perspectives do not amount to compelling someone to pray or to subsidize a church.
&lt;p&gt;
This morning, in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/21pdf/21-418_i425.pdf&quot;&gt;Kennedy v. Bremerton School District&lt;/a&gt;, the Supreme Court overruled both the Endorsement Test and &lt;em&gt;Lemon&lt;/em&gt;, although it did so in language intended to make readers think these tests had been overruled “long ago.” The Court says, for example, that “[over] time, [the &lt;em&gt;Lemon&lt;/em&gt; test] came to involve estimations about whether a ‘reasonable observer’ would consider the government’s challenged action an ‘endorsement’ of religion.” The fatal flaws of the &lt;em&gt;Lemon&lt;/em&gt; and Endorsement Tests, it claims, is that they used an “abstract, and ahistorical approach to the Establishment Clause” instead of relying on “historical practices and understandings.” Going forward, courts should “focus[] on original meaning and history.”
&lt;p&gt;
What precisely does this mean? Unfortunately, one of the fatal flaws in the now-dominant constitutional theory of Originalism is that it substitutes appeals to past generations’ subjective understandings for any conceptual and logical &lt;em&gt;legal&lt;/em&gt; argument. Since such a substitution is not literally possible, some of the better Originalist thinkers have fashioned clever ways to smuggle in the latter by dressing up “abstract and ahistorical” arguments in ancient clothing (this is called “the Construction Zone”). Pointing to historical practice is not only confusing, since these practices sometimes conflicted and can be interpreted in different ways, but because we must infer general rules from those practices, and inferring general rules is, like it or not, necessarily an “abstract and ahistorical” undertaking. It’s no surprise, therefore, that the Kennedy decision itself employs an “abstract an ahistorical” principle, when it bases its decision on the presence or absence of “coercion” — which is an abstraction; a concept, not a list of specific historical events. Obviously history can inform a proper grasp of the law — just as the views of previous generations of scientists can help us understand a natural phenomenon — but actually understanding what the law is requires an objective analysis, which must rely on abstractions and “ahistorical” appeals to principle rather than, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brainyquote.com/quotes/alexander_hamilton_408694#:~:text=Alexander%20Hamilton%20Quotes&amp;amp;text=The%20sacred%20rights%20of%20mankind%20are%20not%20to%20be%20rummaged,and%20can%20never%20be%20erased.&quot;&gt;as Alexander Hamilton put it&lt;/a&gt;, rummaging through musty parchments. Given this confusion, it’s unsurprising that the Court drops the entire issue at that point, and gives us no guidance as to what exact kinds of “historical practices and understandings” should govern the question of whether something constitutes an “establishment of religion” or the “free exercise thereof.” 
&lt;p&gt;
Given that government-funded schools are a century and a half older than the Constitution itself, and were in America’s early years quite heavily saturated in religion, it seems unlikely that a court relying on history alone — without any “abstract and ahistorical principle” to reinforce its constitutional understanding — would reach the same conclusion as the district court in the &lt;em&gt;Dover&lt;/em&gt; case. Of course, schools — both public and private — were teaching Intelligent Design in 1791 (when the First Amendment was ratified), since it was the state of the art back then. And the Establishment Clause itself expressly allowed states to maintain their state-established churches; it was only over the course of the nineteenth century that they were abolished, and later still that the Fourteenth Amendment was viewed as forbidding states to force people to subsidize churches. Just the other day, Justice Barrett &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/21pdf/20-843_7j80.pdf#page=82&quot;&gt;observed&lt;/a&gt; that the Court has “not conclusively determine[d] the manner and circumstances in which post-ratification practice may bear on the original meaning of the Constitution,” and therefore that it’s unclear whether “whether courts should primarily rely on the prevailing  understanding of an individual right when the Fourteenth Amendment was ratified in 1868 [when the Fourteenth Amendment was ratified] or when the Bill of Rights was ratified in 1791.” If 1791 were our guide, it seems quite clear that the &lt;em&gt;Dover&lt;/em&gt; would be decided differently. But if we instead take 1868 as our starting point, and draw from the understanding of that time that the schools were intended to be secular institutions devoted to teaching the natural world rather than religious doctrine, then the question becomes more complicated: our creationist friends will then seek to argue that teaching a sort of broadly theistic “creator” doesn’t cross the line — indeed, many religious conservative lawyers have argued that for decades already. They contend that the First Amendment only bars sectarianism in government classrooms, not what they call “general” religious views (whatever those are).
&lt;p&gt;
In the &lt;em&gt;Dover&lt;/em&gt; case, the judge found that “a reasonable, objective observer who knows the policy’s language, origins, and legislative history, as well as the history of the community and the broader social and historical context in which the policy arose,” would understand that the school board’s Intelligent Design policy was “creationism re-labeled,” and was intended to reach students “that the intelligent designer is God.” Since an objective observer would understand that the ID policy was intended to express official government endorsement of religion, it constituted an unconstitutional establishment of religion. But if schools are allowed to teach vaguely defined “Judeo-Christian values,” because that was permitted in 1791 or 1868, then it’s hard to see how a court would decide the &lt;em&gt;Dover&lt;/em&gt; case today.
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, there’s the abstraction of “coercion.” In the &lt;em&gt;Kennedy&lt;/em&gt; decision, the Court says 
&lt;blockquote&gt;
government may not, consistent with a historically sensitive understanding of the Establishment Clause, “make a religious observance compulsory. Government “may not coerce anyone to attend church,” nor may it force citizens to engage in “a formal religious exercise.” Members of this Court have sometimes disagreed on what exactly qualifies as impermissible coercion in light of the original meaning of the Establishment Clause. But in this case Mr. Kennedy’s private religious exercise did not come close to crossing any line one might imagine separating protected private expression from impermissible government coercion.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Everyone, of course, agrees that coercion is &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; of the things the Establishment Clause forbids: the devil’s in the detail of “what exactly qualifies as impermissible coercion.” For students — ninth graders, in the &lt;em&gt;Dover&lt;/em&gt; case — to be pressured by authority figures in school with more than a wink and a nudge, can certainly be coercive, especially in a mandatory science class, in a school the law requires them to attend. Being compelled to pay taxes that fund a public school system where religious dogma being taught is certainly coercive. But if those things are not enough, then today’s decision does little to help guide future courts about what “coercion” means, except to undermine the intellectual foundations on which any genuine answer would have to depend.
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Would all lower courts rule against such a school board, with the case appealed to the Supreme Court?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
It would require a court-by-court analysis to answer this. Some recent judicial appointees are &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2004/03/the-calpundit-w.html&quot;&gt;well known&lt;/a&gt; for being open advocates of ID creationism. Others would no doubt continue to hold that the First Amendment prohibits religious indoctrination in public schools.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Or would the increasing number of conservative justices who have been vetted by the Federalist Society allow the Supreme Court to dodge such an issue by letting the pro-ID or pro-creationism ruling of an appeals court stand, by refusing to hear the case?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Supreme Court takes fewer than one percent of the cases it’s asked to take, so it’s overwhelmingly likely that virtually any appellate court ruling will “stand,” regardless of what it’s about or whether it’s right. I suspect that there’s little interest on the Supreme Court to take a creationism case, however. While I can’t speak for the Court, or even for the whole Federalist Society (having been a Society member for some 25 years now, I know well enough it’s impossible to speak for the whole Society), I can say that I’m not aware of a prominent contingent within it that’s particularly enthusiastic about creationism. Instead, the religious conservative faction of lawyers is more concerned with school prayer in general, and I think it more likely that the Court will be interested in cases involving that, than those involving creationism specifically. This is reading tea-leaves, of course, so take that for what it’s worth.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;How soon can we expect the Discovery Institute to lawyer-up and decide that its original position of “Teach The Controversy” is maybe not such a bad approach after all?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;p&gt; 
Any reasonable observer would assume they were on the phone with their lawyers at about 10:30 am eastern time yesterday morning.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Timothy Sandefur</name></author><summary type="html">It’s always a risky game to predict what the Supreme Court will do about anything, but we can always discern the general trends, and as a decades-long member of the (spooky, scary!) Federalist Society, I thought I’d take a crack at answering the first three of Joe Felsenstein’s questions about the future of teaching evolution. What would this court do if asked to decide a case similar to the Dover School Board case? In the Dover case — which, believe it or not, is going on 20 years ago, now — the district court found that the school board violated the First Amendment by adopting an “Intelligent Design Policy.” This policy required that a statement be read to students in ninth grade biology class which said that biological evolution “is not a fact,” that it contained “gaps ... for which there is no evidence,” and that “Intelligent Design ... differs from Darwin’s view.” It encouraged students to consult Of Pandas and People, a book which advocated ID creationism, and which was made available to students. After a thorough trial on the factual issues, the court found this unconstitutional using two different legal tests: the “Endorsement Test” and the “Lemon test.” These tests are intellectual devices judges use to answer whether government has crossed the constitutional lines that bar it from either establishing a religion — that is, creating an official church or creed of some kind — or inhibiting the free exercise of religion — that is, punishing or burdening someone for practicing a faith. And these two tests are quite similar. The Lemon test, however, is a three-part analysis dating back to the 1971 case of Lemon v. Kurtzman. The Endorsement Test is somewhat older.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Predicting rough times ahead for teaching about evolution?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/predicting-rough-times-ahead.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Predicting rough times ahead for teaching about evolution?" /><published>2022-06-24T19:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-24T19:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/predicting-rough-times-ahead</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/predicting-rough-times-ahead.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/at-the-supreme-court.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Demonstration at the Supreme Court (figure to be added soon)&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Demonstration at the Supreme Court&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The shocking-but-not-surprising decision of the U.S. Supreme Court today raises many questions.  Even setting aside the
issues in the case, there are interesting questions that arise.  Here are some that puzzle me:
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; What would this court do if asked to decide a case similar to the Dover School Board case?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Would all lower courts rule against such a school board, with the case appealed to the Supreme
Court?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Or would the increasing number of conservative justices who have been vetted by the Federalist 
Society allow the Supreme Court to dodge such an issue by letting the pro-ID or pro-creationism
ruling of an appeals court stand, by refusing to hear the case?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; How soon can we expect the Discovery Institute to lawyer-up and decide that its original position of
&quot;Teach The Controversy&quot; is maybe not such a bad approach after all?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; What's the latest on threats to the teaching of evolution in countries where ultraconservative
nationalist movements are in power or nearing it?  Hungary? Poland? Russia? Turkey? Brazil? India?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; In countries such as Australia or Canada where there are more conservative and less conservative
provinces, what local controversies are there about the teaching of evolution?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will evaluating the flaws in arguments against evolutionary biology have any effect
on legal or political decisions?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Discuss. I suspect that there is enough to 
discuss without going around in endless circles in the same old abortion rights debate.
(Click on the title of this post to go to the comments).  
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Demonstration at the Supreme Court The shocking-but-not-surprising decision of the U.S. Supreme Court today raises many questions. Even setting aside the issues in the case, there are interesting questions that arise. Here are some that puzzle me: What would this court do if asked to decide a case similar to the Dover School Board case? Would all lower courts rule against such a school board, with the case appealed to the Supreme Court? Or would the increasing number of conservative justices who have been vetted by the Federalist Society allow the Supreme Court to dodge such an issue by letting the pro-ID or pro-creationism ruling of an appeals court stand, by refusing to hear the case? How soon can we expect the Discovery Institute to lawyer-up and decide that its original position of &quot;Teach The Controversy&quot; is maybe not such a bad approach after all? What's the latest on threats to the teaching of evolution in countries where ultraconservative nationalist movements are in power or nearing it? Hungary? Poland? Russia? Turkey? Brazil? India? In countries such as Australia or Canada where there are more conservative and less conservative provinces, what local controversies are there about the teaching of evolution? Will evaluating the flaws in arguments against evolutionary biology have any effect on legal or political decisions? Discuss. I suspect that there is enough to discuss without going around in endless circles in the same old abortion rights debate. (Click on the title of this post to go to the comments).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Crepuscular Rays</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/crepuscular-rays.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Crepuscular Rays" /><published>2022-06-20T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-20T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/crepuscular-rays</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/crepuscular-rays.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Paul Strode&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Strode_Crepuscular_Rays_Santa_Fe_May_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Crepuscular Rays&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crepuscular_rays&quot;&gt;Crepuscular Rays&lt;/a&gt;, Santa Fe, New Mexico, May 2022.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See also a brief discussion of crepuscular rays &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/crepuscular-rays.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Paul Strode. Crepuscular Rays, Santa Fe, New Mexico, May 2022. See also a brief discussion of crepuscular rays here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">‘Humans Descended from Dinosaurs! Hilarious/Sad “Paleontology Journal”’</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/humans-descend-from-dinosaurs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘Humans Descended from Dinosaurs! Hilarious/Sad “Paleontology Journal”’" /><published>2022-06-18T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-18T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/humans%20descend-from-dinosaurs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/humans-descend-from-dinosaurs.html">&lt;p&gt;On June 13, I received an invitation to publish in what was obviously a predatory paleontology journal. (The “Assistant Managing Editor” incorrectly assumed I have a doctorate (I don’t)).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the email, preceded by my curt response:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Phelps_Predatory_Journal.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Letter&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On June 14,  the “Assistant Managing Editor” made this reply:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dear Dr. Daniel Phelps,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Thank you for your reply,

We would like to inform you that ours is not a predatory journal. We have received the ISSN which is provided in our previous email. For your convenience, we are providing the link of our journal where you can find complete information of our journal and Editorial Board members.
Link: https://medwinpublishers.com/IJPBP/index.php 

Kindly revert back if you have any queries.

Look forward hear from you soon.

Kind Regards,
  
&lt;strong&gt;Jackie Crystal&lt;/strong&gt;
  
Assistant Managing Editor
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I clicked on the link and found, sadly, several papers by people that were probably starting their careers. Then there were a couple of absolute crackpot papers. One featured a &lt;a href=&quot;https://medwinpublishers.com/IJPBP/the-saint-loup-of-the-col-du-fam-a-smilodon-caught-in-a-lava-bubble.pdf&quot;&gt;weird claim&lt;/a&gt; about a supposed saber-tooth cat fossil, that was  comically just weathered rocks (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareidolia&quot;&gt;pareidolia&lt;/a&gt;, no actual bones), but the topper was this “&lt;a href=&quot;https://medwinpublishers.com/IJPBP/Proving-that-Dinosaurs-are-Distant-Ancestors-of-Humans–The-East-Asian-Locus-of-Evolution-that-disproves-definitively-the-Out-of-Africa-Theory.pdf&quot;&gt;Research Article&lt;/a&gt;” that claims humans are the descendants of dinosaurs!
Here is a screenshot of the start of the “Research Article” in case it is removed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Phelps_Predatory_Journal_Screenshot.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This “science journal” is taking money from naive and delusional people. They should be ashamed. The “&lt;a href=&quot;https://medwinpublishers.com/IJPBP/editorial-board.php&quot;&gt;Editorial Board&lt;/a&gt;” should be forced to help the unfortunate authors who publish with them and should be publicly exposed and shamed for being associated with this “paleontology journal.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My apologies for so many scare quotes in this post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">On June 13, I received an invitation to publish in what was obviously a predatory paleontology journal. (The “Assistant Managing Editor” incorrectly assumed I have a doctorate (I don’t)). Here is the email, preceded by my curt response: On June 14, the “Assistant Managing Editor” made this reply:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Evolution of T-URF13: Does Irreducible Complexity Count or Not?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/evolution-of-t-urf13.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Evolution of T-URF13: Does Irreducible Complexity Count or Not?" /><published>2022-06-17T08:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-17T08:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/evolution-of-t-urf13</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/evolution-of-t-urf13.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A response to the evangelical Discovery Institute (and others)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Neukamm_Figure_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig. 1&lt;/strong&gt; Quaternary structure of a pore-forming membranous protein. The subunits (different colors) form a multimeric complex. The structure of the unique protein URF-13 is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Staphylococcus_aureus_alpha_toxin &quot;&gt;quite similar&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;small&gt;(CC-BY-SA-3.0.)&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Discovery Institute, principal advocate of the Intelligent Design (ID) movement in the US, attempts to invalidate scientific results demonstrating that so-called &lt;i&gt;irreducibly complex (IC)&lt;/i&gt; biological traits can evolve naturally. According to the ID protagonist Michael Behe (1996), a system is &lt;i&gt;by definition&lt;/i&gt; irreducibly complex if it consists of several specifically interacting components which together produce a function such that the removal of any single component leads to the failure of this function. Most biochemical systems are irreducibly complex in that sense. Since they cannot be less complex without losing their function, unguided natural processes based on random mutations and selection cannot build them up gradually, according to Behe. Instead, multiple coordinated mutations would be required &lt;i&gt;simultaneously&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behe postulates that a stepwise evolution of such systems is too improbable to have happened if more than two coordinated mutations, two specific binding sites among proteins, or two specific interdependencies between the parts of a system were established in one fell swoop. Such systems are beyond the “edge of evolution,” Behe says, and need an intelligent creator. This is the so-called &lt;i&gt;argument from irreducible complexity&lt;/i&gt; (IC argument).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, within the last 25 years, ID advocates were faced with more and more logical arguments and empirical data which made apparent that their perception of how evolution works is untenable. One intriguing example is the evolution of a mitochondrial gene in the corn plant &lt;i&gt;Zea mays&lt;/i&gt; named &lt;i&gt;T-URF13&lt;/i&gt; which encodes a ligand-gated pore forming receptor protein called URF13 protein (Hunt 2007).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This membrane protein evolved in cultivars bred for male sterility called &lt;i&gt;Texas cytoplasmatic male-sterile maize&lt;/i&gt; (cms-T maize). Data show that T-URF13 has arisen by rearrangements involving recombination events from two different fragments of the mitochondrial gene coding for &lt;i&gt;26S rRNA&lt;/i&gt; (see Fig. 2–4). The latter is a special type of non-coding but functional RNA molecule, which is a pivotal component of ribosomes, essential to all cells. In short, male sterility in the cms-T cytotype is linked to the chimeric mitochondrial gene T-URF13 (Bosacchi et al. 2015).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Neukamm_Figure_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig. 2&lt;/strong&gt; The origin of the T-URF13 region. This figure shows the mitochondrial 26S rRNA gene in maize, and T-URF13 at the bottom. In between are depictions of the two segments that pieced together to form T-urf13. Both segments originated from the same strand of 26S rRNA. The question mark denotes a small part of T-URF13 for which no homologous sequence could be identified. Most likely, it arose by non-homologous DNA repair processes during the recombination process. &lt;small&gt;Figure from Hunt (2007).&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remarkably, the URF13 protein comprises various distinct, specifically interacting elements that are functionally independent of each other. But all of them are needed to accomplish its specific function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The URF13 molecules have specific contact regions organizing themselves to a multimeric protein complex in the membrane (Fig. 1).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The complex forms an ion channel switching between two defined conformational shapes which open and close the ion channel. This trait requires additional specific complex boundary conditions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The protein complex comprises a specific binding site for certain signaling molecules that open or close the channel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;URF13 thus displays all fundamental properties of gated ion channels, which, interacting with other transport proteins, control the uptake or excretion of substances into or out of cells. It was found that the sensitivity of cms-T maize for the toxin of the fungus &lt;i&gt;Bipolaris maydis&lt;/i&gt; is also linked to this property: The toxin binds to URF13 protein and opens the ion channel, resulting in a massive loss of vital ions such as Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; and NAD&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; (Braun et al. 1989). There is some evidence that an analogous mechanism is responsible for the male sterility (Levings 1990, p. 947). URF13 protein specifically reduces mitochondrial activity in the tapetum cells of the anthers. The resulting lack of energy leads to the degeneration of the tapetum cells. This suggests that a signaling molecule inside the tapetum cells also binds to URF13 protein and opens the ion channel, leading to the loss of energy carriers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the pivotal point? Notably, according to Behe, those specifically interacting parts and their coordinated binding sites constitute an irreducibly complex system. Intriguingly, the URF13 protein is equivalent, regarding its complexity and functional role, to another irreducibly complex three-component system discussed by Behe (1996, pp.108–110); see Hunt (2007). But whereas Behe asserts that billions of years would not suffice to get such systems naturally, URF13 evolved within a ridiculously short period of less than a hundred years, barely a blink in evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accordingly, Lents (2019) criticized Michael Behe’s new book &lt;i&gt;Darwin Devolves&lt;/i&gt; and advocated T-URF13 as a result of “random tinkering.” The natural evolution of such a system from functionally unrelated genes which do not even encode proteins (and never did so in their history) indeed disproves Behe’s IC argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The response of the evangelical Discovery Institute&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McLatchie (2019) tries to invalidate the T-URF13 protein as an example for the evolvability of irreducibly complex systems. He summarizes his refutation in four points (given below in different order):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is exceedingly unlikely that T-URF13 arose &lt;i&gt;de novo&lt;/i&gt; by unguided mutations. This, in itself, is a &lt;i&gt;prima facie&lt;/i&gt; reason to consider alternative explanations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The T-URF13 evolutionary claim is a “just-so story,” and no demonstration is offered of “textbook” evolutionary mechanisms accounting for its origins.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;T-URF13 turns out to be a deleterious feature, rather than one that is beneficial to the organism. Therefore, the case is possibly consistent with Behe’s thesis in &lt;i&gt;Darwin Devolves&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;URF13 is a mitochondrial protein regulated by a nuclear gene, suggesting a scheme where T-URF13 did not arise from scratch, but arose instead from a “devolutionary” process which broke the regulatory mechanism of some normally useful protein.&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The flawed probability argument&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main objection against an “unguided” evolutionary origin of T-URF13 refers to the well-known probability argument. The premise is as follows: Neither the phylogenetic timeline nor the limited number of individuals involved seems sufficient (in such a case) for the emergence of an irreducibly complex system, since it allegedly requires synchronized, complex mutational events consisting of several independent steps. Yet such evolutionary processes obviously &lt;i&gt;did&lt;/i&gt; happen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we will see, all data support the finding that the irreducibly complex URF13 protein emerged within a few decades from sequences lacking any genuine protein-coding capability. That supports the thesis that gene sequences which accomplish irreducibly complex functions are not as improbable as Behe supposes. The immunization tactic of the Discovery Institute, once again, aims at disputing the evidence, which refutes their premise, by referencing to just the same, obviously flawed, probability argument!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Such a combination of events in, to borrow Hunt’s words, ‘one fell swoop’ does indeed seem highly improbable to occur by chance. This is especially the case given that it is estimated that only 10&lt;sup&gt;40&lt;/sup&gt; organisms have lived in the entire history of life on Earth … That is too few by a factor of 10&lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt; for T-URF13 to evolve de novo. And, of course, if we consider the numbers of eukaryotes, or individuals of maize, the number of trials available to generate a complex feature like T-URF13 is drastically reduced by many orders of magnitude. In fact, surely such a strong improbability should prima facie cause us to consider alternative explanations to the one offered by Hunt, namely, that the T-URF13 ion-gated channel arose by chance ‘in one fell swoop.’ [McLatchie (2019)]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a circular argument that can be used to reject &lt;i&gt;all conceivable evidence&lt;/i&gt; for the origin of irreducibly complex systems &lt;i&gt;a priori&lt;/i&gt;! It is therefore clear that the probabilistic calculations are based on false premises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a couple of friends sitting at a table and playing cards. One of the players notes the order in which the cards are dealt. Then the probability of the cards appearing in exactly that order is calculated. The probability turns out to be so small that the friends could have played cards since the Big Bang without ever being dealt the same card sequence again (Kitcher 2007, p. 93). Nevertheless, the cards were dealt exactly in this order the very first time! This tells us that the &lt;i&gt;a priori&lt;/i&gt; probability of the occurrence of any specific event does not tell us whether it actually happened or not. Literally any event can be calculated as improbably as you wish, after the fact. But since it actually happened, the probability of this specific event equals 1. The fallacy of the probability argument is that it presumes the necessity of reaching a &lt;i&gt;pre-specified&lt;/i&gt; target. This is not the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One could object that every conceivable card sequence would serve the players to continue their game, while in biology only a small fraction of all mutations (of all “deals”) is actually “allowed” or functional. Nonetheless, there is no need to demand pre-specified mutations or pre-defined functions. Instead, there are countless potentially functional mutations, which are completely unknown to us. For example, if every thousandth or only every millionth double mutation has a positive effect under certain conditions, the statement that a specific double mutation occurs with a probability of only 10&lt;sup&gt;-20&lt;/sup&gt; becomes meaningless. This historically unique event will be just one of an unthinkable number of possibilities to benefit the organism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, why does the Discovery Institute keep on overusing the same flawed probability calculations, which correspond to the GIGO concept from computer science (which means: “garbage in, garbage out”), for decades?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Note that there are at least five discrete evolutionary events that must occur in order for &lt;i&gt;T-URF13&lt;/i&gt; to arise: First two sections of DNA … must be brought together by random mutation. But this alone is not sufficient to produce a functional gene. The second step is that the atp 6 promoter must be brought into a position to control the gene. Third, fourth, and fifth: The three binding sites needed for T-URF13 to operate must evolve … Presumably, unless all of these events occur, T-URF13 cannot function to provide any selectable advantage in certain contexts. [McLatchie (2019)]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what? Again, for two reasons there is no “probabilistic hurdle” at all:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Behe is wrong in assuming that there are pre-specified target sequences evolution has to “work towards”. There are many &lt;i&gt;completely different sequences&lt;/i&gt; that could serve to accomplish a particular function. Even when starting from random sequences, one or two mutations are often sufficient to gain a particular (or a total new) function (Tonkin et al. 2008; De Kraker &amp;amp; Gershenzon 2011; Yona et al 2018). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The respective mutations have to arise neither simultaneously nor in one single organism. Instead, there is a contemporary, parallel accumulation of random mutations in thousands of individuals which share a gene pool. Then, the different mutations can be combined via sexual recombination in various ways. Such a parallel process tremendously accelerates the evolution of innovations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Monte Carlo experiments do show that there is a good chance of producing irreducibly complex systems – even if that would require three, four, or even more “matching” mutations at the same time&lt;/i&gt; (Trotter et al. 2014). As the authors demonstrate, the evolution of such complex innovations is particularly promising by using genes that are under weak selection pressure like cryptic genes. The number of cryptic genes in a given genome can be rather high. For instance, the proportion of endogenous retroviruses in the human genome alone amounts to at least 8 %. Finlay (2006) speaks of 400,000 insertion points – a huge playing field for evolution!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We summarize that probability calculations against evolution are nonsense since we do not know the entire number of viable variants in the protein space:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;A mathematical argument against evolution requires a detailed knowledge of both the probabilistic and geometric structures of protein space (or possibly genotype space, depending on the context). This knowledge is always lacking in practical situation. When you see a probability calculation in some piece of anti-evolution writing, you can be certain that it is based on biologically unrealistic assumptions.” (Rosenhouse 2022, p. 160)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is the evolutionary explanation a “just-so story”?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Discovery Institute claims that homology or sequence similarities are “not enough to establish an evolutionary pathway”; Hunt’s mechanistic scenario is a “just-so-story” that did not prove T-URF13 arose through recombinant evolutionary events:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;[H]ow does Hunt know that &lt;i&gt;T-URF13&lt;/i&gt; evolved by unguided mutational events from scratch? He doesn’t. Or, at the very least, he has not established that &lt;i&gt;T-URF13&lt;/i&gt; evolved by blind evolution.... If an event is observed to have happened that is highly improbable, having taken into account the available probabilistic resources, that in itself is evidence against the chance hypothesis, and it should drive us to investigate other possible options. [McLatchie (2019)]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a very odd argument, since ID proponents always demanded evolutionary (breeding) experiments to falsify the IC argument! The moment they are confronted with such an experiment, they pirouette and demand more. But what more? The evolution of mechanisms at a molecular level is &lt;i&gt;always&lt;/i&gt; reconstructed &lt;i&gt;indirectly&lt;/i&gt; (by hypothetico-deductive reasoning). Therefore, their demand for “more” is either naive empiricist or an immunization strategy. What do they expect – a microscopic film exposure of how the genes fused together? No one sits in a cell nucleus and watches in real time how mutations happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, Hunt was able to show that T-URF13 evolved by recombinant processes during the breeding of certain maize varieties. Crucially, T-URF13 is unique to cms-T maize plants (Von Allmen et al. 1991; Rhoads et al. 1995; Dill et al. 1997; Arun et al. 2011; Yi et al. 2021). No other sources for T-URF13 except the two mitochondrial DNA sequences we will discuss below have been found. Additionally, data exclude exceptional pollen transmission of organelles or multiple horizontal gene transfer events as the source of T-URF13 (Bosacchi et al. 2015).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words: If the gene did not just fall out of the blue (and oddly enough, turned out to be identical for 94 % of the ORF* length to pre-existing fragments of the mitochondrial genome), we cannot help but state that it arose (de novo) from available resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What other mechanisms than unguided evolutionary processes could be brought into play? Note that the experiments worked exclusively by selective breeding, that is by a Darwinian mechanism. &lt;i&gt;T-URF13 is neither a result of “rational design,” nor of directed evolution. No intentional processes were involved except the selection for pollen sterile variants.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, all biochemical mechanisms that are involved in the origination of T-URF13 are well understood.†  Hunt (2019) correctly mentioned in his response:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Recombination has been studied for decades, and we know enough about the enzymes to know that the attendant chemical mechanisms are all that are needed to promote the genomic shuffling that gave rise to T-URF13.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we are able to identify the homologs of the T-URF13 sequence in the ancestor’s genome, the recombination scenario is currently the only plausible explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Does T-URF13 originate by a “devolutionary process”?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could one argue that URF13 admittedly evolved but originated from an &lt;i&gt;ancestral&lt;/i&gt; pore-forming protein? In that case, the highly specific interdependencies of URF13 would have pre-existed somewhere in the DNA. Therefore, a simple mutation could have restored the receptor gene or altered its activity and specificity. Indeed, the Discovery Institute prefers speculations about a pre-existing gene that became T-URF13 by some so-called &lt;i&gt;devolutionary process&lt;/i&gt; – whatever this may mean:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; One scenario is that the &lt;i&gt;URF-13&lt;/i&gt; complex is involved in some other process, and that it became broken such that it was no longer properly regulated. Indeed, the first identification of &lt;i&gt;T-URF13&lt;/i&gt; long pre-dates the sequencing of the maize genome in the early 2000s (Chandler and Brendel, 2002; Schnable et al., 2009; Soderlund et al., 2009; Gore et al., 2009; Vielle-Calzada et al. 2009). It thus was impossible to determine whether the &lt;i&gt;T-URF13&lt;/i&gt; gene had indeed arisen &lt;i&gt;de novo&lt;/i&gt; ‘from scratch,’ or whether it was already present and doing something else. [McLatchie (2019)]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, no evidence supports these scenarios. There is no reason in sight to pursue them at all. By now, more than a hundred crop genomes, including mitochondriomes, have been &lt;i&gt;completely&lt;/i&gt; sequenced and are available in public databases. There is no gene, there is no sequence resembling T-URF13 except the mentioned 26S rDNA gene (plus the adjacent intergenic region).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the sequences of thousands of genes coding for rRNA are known from many taxa. Among them is not a single example of any pre-existing protein-coding gene with significant structural similarity to rDNA, with a structure which is even remotely resembling T-URF13. Neither is any example known so far of an exaptation of rDNA-fragments for coding a membrane protein. This is indeed the first one! In distinct contrast to the claims of the Discovery Institute, a scenario that proposes the devolution of a pre-existing protein-coding gene is nothing but a just-so story, not supported by any data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A renewed similarity search (&lt;a href=&quot;https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi&quot;&gt;BLAST&lt;/a&gt; on May 26 2022, carried out by A.B.) confirmed the result. The origin of the sequences coding for T-URF13 was identified without a trace of doubt: The two major fragments form part of the maize gene for the 26S rRNA and the adjacent non-coding region, respectively. There are no better and more specific search hits than these two perfect hits. Moreover, there is not any other significant hit than those in 26S rDNAs (see the Appendix). Also, in protein databases, there are no significant hits for any part of the URF13 protein apart from URF13 itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is there a “hidden” protein-coding frame inside the 26S rDNA?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As already mentioned, T-URF13 is a chimera of two parts of the mitochondrial chromosome: an intergenic region that is not transcribed and therefore does not code for a protein (yellow), and part of the 26S rDNA gene encoding the 26S rRNA (green). The latter gene is transcribed into RNA but not translated. That means it also does not code for a protein (Pring &amp;amp; Lonsdale 1989).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, (26S) rDNA encoding for (26S) rRNA molecules does not contain a protein-coding reading frame – and obviously never did. Why do we know this? If one compares the coding regions (ORFs) of &lt;i&gt;protein-coding genes&lt;/i&gt; from different species, one repeatedly finds so-called &lt;i&gt;InDels&lt;/i&gt; (= insertions or deletions) of 3, 6, 9, etc. bases, that is, integral multiples of 3. On the other hand, if one compares the coding regions of &lt;i&gt;genes that code for functional RNA molecules&lt;/i&gt;, particularly the ribosomal RNAs and specifically intergenic regions, one finds InDels that do &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; comply with the “3-step-rule”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biological explanation for this phenomenon is simple: Tiny insertions and deletions usually produce no or little effects in many regions of ribosomal RNAs, in proteins, and especially in intergenic regions. However, InDels containing 1, 2, 4, 5, 7, 8, 10, etc. bases shift the reading frame of an ORF. From the affected point on, the protein is completely changed – and almost always loses its biological function. As a result, such mutations in protein coding parts (ORFs) are negatively selected. &lt;i&gt;Consequently, the fact that rRNAs are not subject to the “3-step-rule” is direct evidence that such rRNAs/rDNA never coded for proteins. Therefore, the present state of knowledge is that the highly specific T-URF13 gene evolved from sequences which never coded for proteins in evolutionary history.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Neukamm_Figure_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig. 3&lt;/strong&gt; Protein coding region of the T-URF13 gene.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Neukamm_Figure_4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig. 4&lt;/strong&gt; URF13 protein (amino acids in IUPAC one-letter code). The colors indicate the origin of the relevant shares. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do deleterious features invalidate the evolutionary argument?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper goes to some lengths to explain that URF13 is not a beneficial but a deleterious feature – a “loss-of-function change” – for the domestic plant. However, the conclusion from this fact amounts to an attempt to mislead readers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;It is thus quite telling that, as their flagship example of a new protein complex arising &lt;i&gt;de novo&lt;/i&gt;, Arthur Hunt, Nathan Lents, and others choose to promote a system that in fact causes harm to the organism that bears it. Surely if there were a better example — one that is functionally advantageous to the organism — then they would be touting that instead. [McLatchie (2019)]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, this “loss-of-function change” is not a case of structural &lt;i&gt;degradation&lt;/i&gt; but a case of structural &lt;i&gt;formation&lt;/i&gt; caused by &lt;i&gt;a completely new protein and IC system&lt;/i&gt;. Such formative structures occur, under special conditions, also in the wild: As Hunt (2019b) mentions, male sterility is a feature of so-called gynodioecious plants. In gynodioecious plants, females are male sterile, often via mechanisms that recall those that underlie male sterility in cms-T corn. Therefore, such structures can evolve not only by artificial, but also by natural selection. Hunt (2019b): “To claim that this trait causes harm is to badly misunderstand many aspects of plant biology.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from that, it is impossible to believe that McLatchie does not know that the effect of selective forces does not depend upon a “benefit” in the sense of a quasi-technical optimization, but solely upon a fitness benefit. There is simply no causal link between mutations and mutation mechanisms on the one hand, and the question how selection works on them on the other. There is also no link between the complexity of mutational pathways and the question if the product is beneficial or deleterious. For the discussion of the probability of an event to occur in evolution, it is completely irrelevant if this event might be labeled “advantageous” or “deleterious” in any “technical” sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Once again, the question whether a trait can be considered “beneficial” or “harmful” from a functional point of view, is completely independent of the question, how complex it is and how it arose&lt;/i&gt;. A machine gun can be considered a harmful tool, surgical instruments as beneficial. That does not mean one is developed easier than the other one. The fact that counts is that URF13 is irreducibly complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Does URF13 originate from a signal peptide of &lt;i&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/i&gt;?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The institute’s final contention is a prime example of an argumentative chaos. Below, the argument is quoted in full. Notice, for example, the phrase: “…an insertion of DNA into a pre-existing gene that was itself a membrane protein for mitochondria…” There is a gene that concurrently is a protein? That’s remarkable! Or look at this: “RLF32_ARATH is a signal peptide for import into mitochondria for a gene in &lt;i&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/i&gt;.” Experts know that the plant gene is not imported into mitochondria but rather its product, a protein. But anybody without expertise will become hopelessly confused. Just savor the whole passage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Proteins embedded in the mitochondrial membrane are synthesized in the cytosol, and therefore they possess an alpha helical a[m]phipathic coil at the N-terminus that is recognized by transport complexes (see this section from the textbook &lt;i&gt;Molecular Biology of the Cell&lt;/i&gt; for details). It follows that there ought to be a signal peptide for mitochondrial membrane insertion. That implies that what we have is actually an insertion of DNA into a pre-existing gene that was itself a membrane protein for mitochondria and perhaps a channel — and perhaps a regulated channel since it is affected by nuclear genes. A tool called Signal-BLAST, available at the website of the Center for Applied Molecular Engineering (CAME), allows a user to identify signal peptides in a protein sequence (Frank and Sippl, 2008). Entering the FASTA file for T-URF13 yields a result output of a signal peptide, putative cleavage site after AA 35 (by similarity to RLF32_ARATH). RLF32_ARATH is a signal peptide for import into mitochondria for a gene in Arabidopsis. That protein is involved in cell-cell signaling by way of Ca++ influx. What all this means is that T-URF13 probably came from a fully functional, pre-existing gene, and did not arise &lt;i&gt;de novo&lt;/i&gt;. [McLatchie (2019)]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic argument, disentangled from the chaos, runs as follows: An analytic tool which allows “high-performance signal peptide prediction based on sequence alignment techniques” shows that the mitochondrial gene T-URF13 contains a sequence similar to one coding a signal peptide in the plant &lt;i&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/i&gt;. The claim is that the peptide is needed to transport a mitochondrial membrane protein which is synthesized in the cytosol (the cell body) into the membrane of mitochondria. That must happen because the gene encoding the mitochondrial protein is located in the cell nucleus. Most of the genes coding mitochondrial proteins indeed are located there. Also, the membrane protein which contains the signal peptide in question forms a regulated ion channel. It is said that it regulates the influx of Ca2+ ions into the mitochondria of &lt;i&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/i&gt;. Therefore, so the argument, T-URF13 could have originated from such an ion channel gene and does not have to be evolved &lt;i&gt;de novo&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can refute the argument easily. Hunt (2019a), for good reasons, has rated it as “jaw-droppingly bad.”‡ For one thing, the T-URF13 gene is located not in the nucleus but in the mitochondrial genome. Thus, no import into mitochondria happens, neither for URF13 protein nor for T-URF13. That is simply a matter of fact. There is no trace of T-URF13 or anything similar in the nuclear genome. So why should a hypothetical predecessor gene code for a signal peptide which transfers cytosol proteins from outside into the mitochondrial membrane? That simply makes no sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the claim that the analytic tool detects a gene sequence similar to that coding for a signal peptide known from &lt;i&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/i&gt; is dubious. The match is incomplete at best. Strangely enough, the particular &lt;i&gt;A. thaliana&lt;/i&gt; protein, to which the signal peptide in question belongs, is &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; transported into mitochondria but into the plasma membrane, so there is something seriously wrong with the whole claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, there is no significant match between this protein family and URF13. There is even no remotely significant match with &lt;i&gt;any&lt;/i&gt; protein in the whole protein database (Protein BLAST @ NCBI: https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi?PAGE=Proteins). Obviously, whatever the &lt;i&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/i&gt; genes are and do, there is no evolutionary connection to T-URF13. But only experts in molecular genetics realize that the so-called data are fabricated. Everybody else is overwhelmed by the maze of technical jargon. That is the Discovery Institute’s strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Literature&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arun, V. et al. (2011) Transformation and analysis of tobacco plant var Petit havana with T-urf13 gene under anther-specific TA29 promoter. 3 Biotech 1, 73–82.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behe, M. (1996) Darwin’s black box: The biochemical challenge to evolution. The Free Press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bosacchi, M.; Gurdon, C. &amp;amp; Maliga, P. (2015) Plastid genotyping reveals uniformity of cms-T maize cytoplasms. Plant Physiology 169, 2129–2137.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Braun, C.J.; Siedow, J.N.; Williams, M.E. et al. (1989) Mutations in the maize mitochondrial T-urf13 gene eliminate sensitivity to a fungal pathotoxin. PNAS 86, 4435–4439.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De Kraker, J.-W. &amp;amp; Gershenzon, J. (2011) From amino acid to glucosinolate biosynthesis: Protein sequence changes in the evolution of methylthioalkylmalate synthase in Arabidopsis. The Plant Cell 23, 38–53.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dill, C.L.; Wise, R.P. &amp;amp; Schnable, P.S. (1997) Rf8 and Rf* mediate unique T-urf13-transcript accumulation, revealing a conserved motif associated with RNA processing and restoration of pollen fertility in T-cytoplasm maize. Genetics 147, 1367–1379.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finlay, G. (2006) Human genetics and the image of God. http://www.cis.org.uk/ireland/documents/God&amp;amp;Science_Paper2_Finlay.pdf&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hunt, A. (2007) On the evolution of Irreducible Complexity. https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2007/05/on-the-evolutio-1.html&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hunt, A. (2019a) T-URF13 and devolution. https://discourse.peacefulscience.org/t/T-URF13-and-devolution/5696&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hunt, A. (2019b) Where gynodioecy is cast out of God’s creation https://discourse.peacefulscience.org/t/where-gynodioecy-is-cast-out-of-god-s-creation/5651&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kanzaki, H.; Takeda, M. &amp;amp; Kameya, T. (1991) Sequence analysis of a mitochondrial DNA fragment isolated from cultured cells of carrot cytoplasmic male-sterile strain. The Japanese Journal of Genetics 66, 719–724.
https://www.jstage.jst.go.jp/article/jjg/66/6/66_6_719/_article&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kitcher, P. (2007) Living with Darwin. Evolution, design, and the future of faith. Oxford University Press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lents, N.H. (2019) Behe’s last stand: the lion of Intelligent Design roars again. https://www.skeptic.com/reading_room/michael-behes-last-stand-lion-of-intelligent-design-roars-again/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Levings 3rd, C.S. (1990) The Texas cytoplasm of maize: cytoplasmic male sterility and disease susceptibility. Science 250, 942–947.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McLatchie, J. (2019) Does T-URF13 Refute Irreducible Complexity? A Response to Arthur Hunt. https://evolutionnews.org/2019/04/does-T-URF13-refute-irreducible-complexity-a-response-to-arthur-hunt/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pring, R.D. &amp;amp; Lonsdale M. (1989) Cytoplasmic male sterility and maternal inheritance of disease susceptibility in maize. Annual Review of Phytopathology 27, 483–502.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rhoads, D.M.; Levings 3rd, C.S. &amp;amp; Siedow, J.N. (1995) URF13, a ligand-gated, pore-forming receptor for T-toxin in the inner membrane of cms-T mitochondria. Journal of Bioenergetics and Biomembranes 27, 437–445.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rosenhouse, J. (2022) The failures of mathematical anti-evolutionism. Cambridge University Press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonkin, C.J.; Foth, B.J.; Ralph, S.A. et al. (2008) Evolution of malaria parasite plastid targeting sequences. PNAS 105, 4781–4785.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trotter, M.V.; Weissman, D.B.; Peterson, G.I.; Peck, K.M. &amp;amp; Masel, J. (2014) Cryptic genetic variation can make “Irreducible Complexity” a common mode of adaptation in sexual populations. Evolution 68, S. 3357–3367.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;von Allmen, J.-M.; Rothmann, W.H.; Gengenbach, B.G. et al. (1991) Transfer of methomyl and HmT-toxin sensitivity from T-cytoplasm maize to tobacco. Molecular &amp;amp; General Genetics 229, 405–412.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yi, H. et al. (2021) Identification and genetic analysis of two maize CMS-T mutants obtained from out-space-flighted seeds. Genetic Resources and Crop Evolution 68, 1–11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yona, A.H.; Alm, E.J. &amp;amp; Gore, J. (2018) Random sequences rapidly evolve into de novo promoters. Nature Communications 9, 1530.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix: The mysterious PKT5 “gene”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, a recent BLAST search corroborated the notion that T-URF13 had been composed of two fragments of the mitochondrial genome (mtDNA) of maize. The yellow and the green region (Fig. 3) perfectly match to other parts of the mtDNA as described. The red part finds no match in the maize nuclear genome or mitogenome corroborating the notion that this part has been created by mitochondrial DNA double strand repair. The shortness of this part further supports that idea. Furthermore there are quite a few nearly perfect matches simply by chance in very different organisms – as to be expected by the shortness of this part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, however, a very surprising full-length match with a gene in a male-sterile lineage of carrot &lt;i&gt;Daucus carota&lt;/i&gt; (Fig. 5). Kanzaki et al. (1991) named it &lt;i&gt;PKT5 gene&lt;/i&gt;. Their paper seems to suggest that very similar (in fact: identical) rearrangements took place independently in maize and carrots to produce male-sterile lines and a full-length match with T-URF13. Since this is not a particularly satisfying explanation, how can this be conundrum be explained? Some facts will help:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

&lt;li&gt;The alignment contains only two mismatches, but beyond that eight (!) single-base deletions – all of them in &lt;i&gt;D. carota&lt;/i&gt; PKT5. However, mismatch mutations occur 4 to 10 times more frequent than insertions or deletions. Moreover, they should have occurred in both genes at about the same rate. Here, however, the green and yellow parts of T-URF13 match perfectly to maize mitochondrial DNA, whereas all mismatches occur in the carrot “gene”. Such characteristics are typical for sequencing errors. This is further substantiated by the fact that all of those deletions would destroy almost half of the open reading frame creating a substantially changed protein, which surely cannot work like URF13 protein.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;The similarity of &lt;i&gt;D. carota&lt;/i&gt; PKT5 to maize mtDNA is almost perfect on the one hand. On the other hand, its similarity to &lt;i&gt;D. carota&lt;/i&gt; mtDNA is much weaker as easily can be seen in BLAST search. How should a carrot gene arise from maize mitochondrial genome? The only possibility would be &lt;i&gt;horizontal gene transfer&lt;/i&gt; which is also not convincing since there is no further evidence.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;The experimental approach of Kanzaki et al. is questionable since their hybridisation experiment does not make sense: T-URF13 has been assembled from maize mitochondrial genome and shows – except for the red part – perfect sequence identity. So, it will hybridise to any mitochondrial genome with sufficient sequence similarity. So why even try&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;To corroborate the mere existence of carrot PKT5 gene, the presence of the coded protein has to be demonstrated. To our knowledge, this has not happened so far.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Neukamm_Figure_5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 5&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig. 5&lt;/strong&gt; Alignment between Zea mays T-URF13 (top line) and Daucus carota PKT5 ORF (bottom line). Colours correspond to Figs. 3 and 4.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all does not make any sense. By the way: It also does not fit into a design scenario (unless you would like to argue: “The Designer in his unfathomable will can do whatever he/she/it wants”). Such patterns, however, are typical of artefacts produced experimentally: mix-up of clones and sequencing errors, which in most cases are never cured in the databases. First author (A.B.) experienced such cases during his time in the human genome project – to mention only three examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;

&lt;li&gt;At that time, a significant portion of clones from cDNA and gDNA libraries were interchanged (meaning the accession or ordering number was assigned to a wrong clone). &lt;/li&gt; 

&lt;li&gt;During assembly of chromosomes from reads always some sequences fall out of the alignments for a simple reason. They originated from different species and erroneously were inserted into the processing pipeline. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Erroneous sequences produced either by PCR/cloning artefacts or by low quality sequence runs. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, LIMS (Laboratory information management systems) have reduced such errors by some orders of magnitude. The respective paper (Kanzaki et al.), however, is from 1991, when such systems did not exist or were in their infancy. It fits well into this scenario that the authors were provided with a cloned version of T-URF13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: Obviously, the carrot PKT5 gene simply does not exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* ORF (Open Reading Frame) is the protein-coding region of a gene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;†They even explain the origin of the red marked intermediate area illustrated in Fig. 3 and 4: When mismatched ends are assembled (via non-homologous double strand break repair mechanisms), the sequence at the junction often changes rather randomly. That is why no significant homologs are found in the databases for this area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‡Further pseudo-arguments against the T-URF13 example presented by the “Uncommon Descent” guys are debunked by Hunt: https://www.ag-evolutionsbiologie.net/html/2019/T-URF13.html&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may find a pdf version of this paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ag-evolutionsbiologie.net/pdf/2022/evolution-of-t-urf13-irreducible-complexity.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About the authors.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Prof. Dr. Andreas Beyer&lt;/strong&gt; studied biology at the Ruhr University in Bochum (Germany) with a focus on biochemistry, physiology, cytology and microbiology. Doctorate on the topic “molecular biological characterization of the AAA gene family, a new group of putative ATPases”. Research on the phosphorylation of phosphorylase kinase at the Institute for Physiological Chemistry at the Ruhr University. Applied research in various industrial projects. Lecturer at the Westfälische Hochschule Gelsenkirchen, Bocholt, Recklinghausen (Germany) as Professor of Molecular Biology. Chairman of the working group “AG Evolutionsbiologie” which is associated with the German Association of Biologists (VBio).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Hansjörg Hemminger&lt;/strong&gt; received his postdoctoral qualification as a university teacher of behavioral biology (Habilitation) from the University of Freiburg (Germany). He was commissioner for world view questions, especially for the dialogue between science and religion, in the Protestant Church until retirement.  As an expert member of a parliament commission (Bundestag) he investigated fanatic and sectarian forms of religion. He published numerous articles and books in German and English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Martin Neukamm&lt;/strong&gt; is a German chemist and managing editor of the “AG Evolutionsbiologie” (www.ag-evolutionsbiologie.de), a German scientific association that deals with evolutionary biology and creationism. He has published various articles and books on evolution and creationism in the German language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgement&lt;/strong&gt;. Arthur G. Hunt, Professor in the Department of Plant and Soil Sciences, University of Kentucky, very kindly read and commented on a draft of this paper. Matt Young will be the moderator of this thread. Copyright © 2022 by AG EvoBio, all rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</content><author><name>Andreas Beyer, Hansjörg Hemminger, and Martin Neukamm</name></author><summary type="html">A response to the evangelical Discovery Institute (and others) Fig. 1 Quaternary structure of a pore-forming membranous protein. The subunits (different colors) form a multimeric complex. The structure of the unique protein URF-13 is quite similar. (CC-BY-SA-3.0.) The Discovery Institute, principal advocate of the Intelligent Design (ID) movement in the US, attempts to invalidate scientific results demonstrating that so-called irreducibly complex (IC) biological traits can evolve naturally. According to the ID protagonist Michael Behe (1996), a system is by definition irreducibly complex if it consists of several specifically interacting components which together produce a function such that the removal of any single component leads to the failure of this function. Most biochemical systems are irreducibly complex in that sense. Since they cannot be less complex without losing their function, unguided natural processes based on random mutations and selection cannot build them up gradually, according to Behe. Instead, multiple coordinated mutations would be required simultaneously. Behe postulates that a stepwise evolution of such systems is too improbable to have happened if more than two coordinated mutations, two specific binding sites among proteins, or two specific interdependencies between the parts of a system were established in one fell swoop. Such systems are beyond the “edge of evolution,” Behe says, and need an intelligent creator. This is the so-called argument from irreducible complexity (IC argument). However, within the last 25 years, ID advocates were faced with more and more logical arguments and empirical data which made apparent that their perception of how evolution works is untenable. One intriguing example is the evolution of a mitochondrial gene in the corn plant Zea mays named T-URF13 which encodes a ligand-gated pore forming receptor protein called URF13 protein (Hunt 2007).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Failures of Mathematical Anti-Evolutionism: Review</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/Mathematical-Anti-Evolutionism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Failures of Mathematical Anti-Evolutionism: Review" /><published>2022-06-14T12:07:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-14T12:07:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/Mathematical-Anti-Evolutionism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/Mathematical-Anti-Evolutionism.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Rosenhouse_Cover_Crop_660.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridge.org/us/academic/subjects/life-sciences/evolutionary-biology/failures-mathematical-anti-evolutionism&quot;&gt;The Failures of Mathematical Anti-Evolutionism&lt;/a&gt; by Jason Rosenhouse, Cambridge University Press, 2022, 274 pp.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jason Rosenhouse’s newest book, &lt;i&gt;The Failures of Mathematical Anti-Evolutionism&lt;/i&gt;, is a mathematics book, not a book on evolution, and not a book on creationism or theology. Though the author plainly believes in – no: though the author plainly &lt;i&gt;accepts&lt;/i&gt; evolution, his main purpose is to show that the mathematical arguments of anti-evolutionists are flatly wrong, rather than to defend evolution explicitly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jason_Rosenhouse&quot;&gt;Jason Rosenhouse&lt;/a&gt; is an American author who has written several books, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://oxford.universitypressscholarship.com/view/10.1093/acprof:osobl/9780199744633.001.0001/acprof-9780199744633&quot;&gt;Among the Creationists: Dispatches from the Anti-Evolutionist Front Line&lt;/a&gt;. His experience as a mathematician and of actually wading into the swamp of creationism make him uniquely qualified to have written the present book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe Felsenstein has posted an &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/rosenhouse-on-mathematical-anti-evolutionism.html&quot;&gt;annotated table of contents&lt;/a&gt;, and Prof. Rosenhouse himself has presented an essay &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/futility-anti-evolutionary.html&quot;&gt;The futility of anti-evolutionary mathematics&lt;/a&gt; on PT; I will not try to duplicate either of those. Additionally, if you want to get a feeling for some of the more egregious nonsense, you might want to read &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/has-michael-egnor-shown-everything.html&quot;&gt;Has Michael Egnor shown that everything is intelligently designed?&lt;/a&gt;, also by Joe Felsenstein. I cannot make, um, head or tail of Dr. Egnor’s argument, except that he seems to think that if you use tossing coins in an illustrative manner, then you must think that the coins themselves were formed by natural causes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things I took away from this book – and which I thought should have been stressed more – was Prof. Rosenhouse’s distinction between Track-1 and Track-2 explanations. This very important distinction is not shown in what looked like an otherwise comprehensive index.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Track-1 explanation is “our intuitive understanding,” a descriptive explanation, possibly written in plain English. A Track-2 explanation is a rigorous mathematical exposition, including precise definitions and proved theorems. Track 1 is not definitive; as I would put it, Track 1 gives you a hunch and guides you toward developing a mathematical proof. Track 2 is the rigorous mathematical proof itself. You need both tracks, because, if you stick to Track 1, you will find it too easy to make “logical oversights.” If you cannot prove something rigorously, then you have not proved it at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creationists typically develop a Track-1 explanation, then simply rephrase it as a Track-2 explanation, but they do not prove anything rigorously. They might, for example, note that proteins are extremely complex and therefore so improbable that they could not have arisen by chance. They then apply combinatorial analysis and indeed calculate what they set out to calculate: that proteins almost certainly did not originate by chance. No one thinks that they did. Rather, they originated by a complex sequence of processes that cannot be modeled as a simple combinatorics problem, à la the famous &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Junkyard_tornado&quot;&gt;tornado in a junkyard&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, the creationists’ supposed Track-2 explanation is mere window dressing that repeats the Track-1 explanation using mathematical notation in place of words. Indeed, as we see as we progress through the book, all the creationists’ mathematics, bar none, is sophisticated gobbledygook designed to appear rigorous to people who would not understand a word of it. That the purveyors of such window dressing accept it as proof is testament to the power of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confirmation_bias&quot;&gt;confirmation bias&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of intelligent-design creationism relies on irreducible complexity, the claim that a system has well matched, interacting parts, all of which are essential to the functioning of the system. That is, if any one of the parts is broken or removed, the system will not function. Professor Rosenhouse explains how the claim is false by showing how an eye might evolve step by step until it consists of well matched, interacting parts, all of which are critical to its functioning. But where he jabs the knife in and twists it is in this quotation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;It is clever marketing to refer to these systems as &quot;irreducibly complex.&quot; A more accurate description is &quot;easily broken,&quot; and his [Michael Behe's] argument could then be rephrased like this: &quot;The prevalence of easily broken systems in nature is strong evidence of intelligent design.&quot; In &lt;i&gt;that&lt;/i&gt; form the argument is not terribly persuasive.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is not to like about a book that comes up with gems like this one?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or this one, after discussing Kelvin’s estimate of the age of the earth and the possibly spurious “proof” that a bumblebee cannot fly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;If copious physical evidence suggests that something has occurred, but someone's mathematical model says the thing is impossible, then it is probably the model that is wrong.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a section on “The perils of long-term modeling,” he notes similarly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; We have copious physical evidence that modern life forms are the end results of a lengthy evolutionary process.… And since no mathematical model could possibly include enough of nature's complexity to be convincing, we are not worried that a few back-of-the-envelope calculations will provide a good reason for abandoning that hypothesis [that is, the theory of evolution].&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A section called “The basic argument from improbability” explains in some detail why simple combinatorial analysis is not a good model for the evolution of proteins. I cannot go into detail, but Prof. Rosenhouse notes that, given enough opportunity, even improbable events actually happen (an occurrence with odds of one million to one, for example, happens eight times a day in New York), so it is not enough to say that a particular protein is so improbable that a special explanation is required. Those who favor what Prof. Rosenhouse calls the Basic Argument from Improbability provide no argument in favor of a special explanation, but merely (blindly, if I may say so) apply combinatorial analysis where it is completely inapt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the same chapter, Prof. Rosenhouse takes on William Dembski’s concept of complex specified information. There is too much to discuss here, but I will note that Dembski requires us to distinguish designed “patterns” from undesigned. Professor Rosenhouse notes, however:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; We know what mountains look like when we do not carve faces into them, and that makes it easy to recognize Mount Rushmore as something designed. This background knowledge is precisely what we lack in the biological context. No one has intuitions about what will arise after billions of years of evolution starting from a relatively simple sort of life. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, one of the main stumbling blocks in Dembski’s analysis is that he thinks we can recognize design in the same way that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/I_know_it_when_I_see_it&quot;&gt;Mr. Justice Stewart thinks he can recognize obscenity&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is more about Dembski, including his misapplication of the No Free Lunch theorems, which is well worth reading. I liked the chapter on thermodynamics as well, though the editor in me feels obliged to point out that heat is &lt;i&gt;transferred&lt;/i&gt;, not necessarily &amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;radiated&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;. Professor Rosenhouse notes that the second law of thermodynamics does &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; preclude increases or decreases of entropy. He correctly inveighs against conflating entropy with order and disorder, but perhaps confusingly sometimes uses disorder as an analogy to entropy. The analogy is often useful, but it is important to recognize that it is only an analogy and proves nothing; Prof. Rosenhouse notes that a jagged chunk of ice looks less orderly than a smooth pool of water, but its thermodynamic entropy is actually less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to use thermodynamics to describe evolution, you have to perform a rigorous Type-2 analysis. How, asks Prof. Rosenhouse, do you calculate the change in entropy between an ancestral organism and an elephant? How do you apply the laws of thermodynamics to the theory of evolution? No one knows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reviewer’s quibbles&lt;/strong&gt;. The book is well prepared and very readable. I found only a few errors, such as “adaption” and “few 1,000” (and Watt where it should have been watt, but that is getting &lt;i&gt;really&lt;/i&gt; picky). The entropy of the ice is calculated incorrectly (p. 241); the correct calculation is left as an exercise for the reader, who is advised to remember that it is necessary to extract heat from the water before it will freeze. I thought the book possibly could have used a few more figures, but I did not particularly care for Figure 5.2, which lacks axis labels and looks too much like a graph of some quantity as a function of time; in fact, it represents some kind of protein space in 2 dimensions. Figure 6.1 also lacks axis labels; it is drawn with very thick curves whose thickness is not explained. The discussion of a thrown ball on p. 65 is not incorrect but seems to imply that the ball’s velocity increases linearly with time, a property I wish were true of my forehand drive. Finally, I was a bit put out by Prof. Rosenhouse’s disparagement, several times, of high school math classes. I do not remember exactly enjoying high school math, but I certainly recognized its importance and was not terrifically bored. An editor should have caught that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgment and disclosure&lt;/strong&gt;. Jason Rosenhouse very kindly sent me a review copy of the book. He and I are members of the PT “Crew.” We communicated once as I was preparing this review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Dembski has responded to Prof. Rosenhouse’s book &lt;a href=&quot;https://billdembski.com/intelligent-design/success-of-mathematics-in-advancing-intelligent-design/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">The Failures of Mathematical Anti-Evolutionism by Jason Rosenhouse, Cambridge University Press, 2022, 274 pp. Jason Rosenhouse’s newest book, The Failures of Mathematical Anti-Evolutionism, is a mathematics book, not a book on evolution, and not a book on creationism or theology. Though the author plainly believes in – no: though the author plainly accepts evolution, his main purpose is to show that the mathematical arguments of anti-evolutionists are flatly wrong, rather than to defend evolution explicitly. Jason Rosenhouse is an American author who has written several books, including Among the Creationists: Dispatches from the Anti-Evolutionist Front Line. His experience as a mathematician and of actually wading into the swamp of creationism make him uniquely qualified to have written the present book. Joe Felsenstein has posted an annotated table of contents, and Prof. Rosenhouse himself has presented an essay The futility of anti-evolutionary mathematics on PT; I will not try to duplicate either of those. Additionally, if you want to get a feeling for some of the more egregious nonsense, you might want to read Has Michael Egnor shown that everything is intelligently designed?, also by Joe Felsenstein. I cannot make, um, head or tail of Dr. Egnor’s argument, except that he seems to think that if you use tossing coins in an illustrative manner, then you must think that the coins themselves were formed by natural causes.</summary></entry></feed>