<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-05T04:46:41-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Editorial board of human evolution journal resigns en masse</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/editorial-board-journal-resigns.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Editorial board of human evolution journal resigns en masse" /><published>2024-12-27T14:10:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-12-27T14:10:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/editorial-board-journal-resigns</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/editorial-board-journal-resigns.html">&lt;p&gt;I once published an article in a proprietary journal. It was new, it had no page charges, and I had no funding. Little did I know that it was the bare tip of an iceberg of proprietary journals that would, among other faults, strain university libraries to the breaking point. I have been apologizing ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It gets worse. A day or so ago, a colleague sent us a post that included a press release to the effect that the editorial board of the &lt;i&gt;Journal of Human Evolution&lt;/i&gt;, a proprietary Elsevier journal, &lt;a href=&quot;https://bsky.app/profile/markgrabowski.bsky.social/post/3le7wqrryhc2y&quot;&gt;had resigned en masse&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elsevier&quot;&gt;Elsevier&lt;/a&gt; is an academic publishing firm that, according to Wikipedia, enjoyed a profit of £2.3 billion and a profit margin of 33 % in 2023.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the press release, which was posted by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/journal/journal-of-human-evolution &quot;&gt;Mark Grabowski, a co-editor with Andrea B. Taylor&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;i&gt;Journal of Human Evolution&lt;/i&gt; is the “flagship journal in paleoanthropological and human evolution research,” but “Elsevier has steadily eroded the infrastructure essential to the success of the journal while simultaneously undermining [its] core principles and practices….” The editors note, among other complaints, that Elsevier has eliminated the position of copy editor on the grounds that “the editors should not be paying attention to language, grammar, readability, consistency, or accuracy of proper nomenclature or formatting.” The result is that errors that were not found in the original manuscript are introduced during the production of the paper. The editors further complain about the cost of page charges and open access charges to institutions, and the relative paucity of institutions with whom Elsevier has negotiated open access agreements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two editors-in-chief, the emeritus editors, and all associate editors but one, “with heartfelt sadness and great regret,” therefore have resigned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is an elephant in the room, and he is hiding in plain sight in footnote 2: artificial intelligence. The press release notes that, without telling anyone, Elsevier introduced artificial intelligence during some phase of production and generated articles in which proper nouns (including epochs, site names, countries, cities, and genera) were not capitalized, and genera and species were not italicized. Thus, papers that had been properly formatted became embarrassingly wrong, and it took the persistent efforts of the editors over six months to resolve the problem. The footnote concludes, “AI processing … regularly reformats submitted manuscripts to change meaning and formatting and require extensive author and editor oversight during proof stage.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://retractionwatch.com/2024/12/27/evolution-journal-editors-resign-en-masse-to-protest-elsevier-changes/&quot;&gt;Evolution journal editors resign en masse to protest Elsevier’s changes&lt;/a&gt; in Retraction Watch. You may find Elsevier’s open access agreements &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.elsevier.com/open-access/agreements&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;; there are only a couple of dozen or so in the United States. My thanks to several Panda’s Thumbelinos for providing the press release and making perceptive suggestions ahead of my drafting the present post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I once published an article in a proprietary journal. It was new, it had no page charges, and I had no funding. Little did I know that it was the bare tip of an iceberg of proprietary journals that would, among other faults, strain university libraries to the breaking point. I have been apologizing ever since. It gets worse. A day or so ago, a colleague sent us a post that included a press release to the effect that the editorial board of the Journal of Human Evolution, a proprietary Elsevier journal, had resigned en masse. Elsevier is an academic publishing firm that, according to Wikipedia, enjoyed a profit of £2.3 billion and a profit margin of 33 % in 2023. According to the press release, which was posted by Mark Grabowski, a co-editor with Andrea B. Taylor, the Journal of Human Evolution is the “flagship journal in paleoanthropological and human evolution research,” but “Elsevier has steadily eroded the infrastructure essential to the success of the journal while simultaneously undermining [its] core principles and practices….” The editors note, among other complaints, that Elsevier has eliminated the position of copy editor on the grounds that “the editors should not be paying attention to language, grammar, readability, consistency, or accuracy of proper nomenclature or formatting.” The result is that errors that were not found in the original manuscript are introduced during the production of the paper. The editors further complain about the cost of page charges and open access charges to institutions, and the relative paucity of institutions with whom Elsevier has negotiated open access agreements. The two editors-in-chief, the emeritus editors, and all associate editors but one, “with heartfelt sadness and great regret,” therefore have resigned. Finally, there is an elephant in the room, and he is hiding in plain sight in footnote 2: artificial intelligence. The press release notes that, without telling anyone, Elsevier introduced artificial intelligence during some phase of production and generated articles in which proper nouns (including epochs, site names, countries, cities, and genera) were not capitalized, and genera and species were not italicized. Thus, papers that had been properly formatted became embarrassingly wrong, and it took the persistent efforts of the editors over six months to resolve the problem. The footnote concludes, “AI processing … regularly reformats submitted manuscripts to change meaning and formatting and require extensive author and editor oversight during proof stage.” For more, see Evolution journal editors resign en masse to protest Elsevier’s changes in Retraction Watch. You may find Elsevier’s open access agreements here; there are only a couple of dozen or so in the United States. My thanks to several Panda’s Thumbelinos for providing the press release and making perceptive suggestions ahead of my drafting the present post.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Polygonia c-album</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/polygonia-c-album.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Polygonia c-album" /><published>2024-12-23T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-12-23T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/polygonia-c-album</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/polygonia-c-album.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Marilyn Susek&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Susek_Comma_Butterfly_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Comma butterfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polygonia_c-album&quot;&gt;Polygonia c-album&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; comma butterfly, September, 2020. The photographer writes, &quot;I was in the garden when this butterfly startled me, as it was so close and came in to land and rest under the log. Very well camouflaged. I didn't see its open wing. It didn't mind me being there. I've never seen one before.&quot; Additionally, BugGuide discusses why &quot;c&quot; and why &quot;album&quot; &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugguide.net/node/view/722347&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Album means white, but the creature looks anything but white to me.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Marilyn Susek. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Polygonia c-album &amp;ndash; comma butterfly, September, 2020. The photographer writes, &quot;I was in the garden when this butterfly startled me, as it was so close and came in to land and rest under the log. Very well camouflaged. I didn't see its open wing. It didn't mind me being there. I've never seen one before.&quot; Additionally, BugGuide discusses why &quot;c&quot; and why &quot;album&quot; here. Album means white, but the creature looks anything but white to me.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Merry Kitzmas! 2025 is the 20th anniversary of Kitzmiller v. Dover and the 100th of the Scopes Trial</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/KvDv19.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Merry Kitzmas! 2025 is the 20th anniversary of Kitzmiller v. Dover and the 100th of the Scopes Trial" /><published>2024-12-20T12:01:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-12-20T12:01:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/KvDv19</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/KvDv19.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Matzke_Scopes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Nick Matzke at the Dayton County Courthouse, site of the 1925 Scopes Monkey Trial]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Nick Matzke at the Dayton County Courthouse where the Scopes Trial was held in 1925. (photo from ~2014)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;UPDATE, Dec. 22: I have now listed 52 separate events I found, including links and quotes of the summaries where available. Please contribute more in the comments!&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merry Kitzmas to all!  Today is the 19th anniversary of the &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover Area School District&lt;/i&gt; trial, aka the Dover Panda Trial, held from September-November 2005, and decided on December 20, 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year, 2025, will be the 20th anniversary of Kitzmiller, as well as the 100th anniversary of &lt;i&gt;Tennessee v. Scopes&lt;/i&gt;, aka the Scopes Monkey Trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stuck as I am, in Australia/New Zealand with 3 little kids, I expect I will have to follow events from afar.  But I will use this thread to accumulate links &amp;amp; dates for relevant events as they come up. And please contribute ones you come across!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect that many are glum about current politics and science, but I recall a similar feeling in 2004, and that &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover&lt;/i&gt; was one of the early signs that committed citizens could move events in a pro-science direction. May 2025 be another such time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summaries of events are posted below, with abstracts where available:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vanderbilt-university-scopes-trial-symposium-july-12-13-2025&quot;&gt;Vanderbilt University, Scopes Trial Symposium, July 12-13, 2025&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/2025-07-12_Scopes_Trial_Symposium_at_Vanderbilt.png&quot; alt=&quot;[Vanderbilt Scopes Trial Symposium schedule, July 12-13, 2025]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Vanderbilt Scopes Trial Symposium schedule, July 12-13, 2025&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vanderbilt.edu/evolution/scopes-symposium/&quot;&gt;Scopes &quot;Monkey&quot; Trial Centennial Symposium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Vanderbilt University, July 12-13, 2025&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vanderbilt.edu/evolution/scopes-symposium/&quot;&gt;https://www.vanderbilt.edu/evolution/scopes-symposium/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
...following on from...&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;ISEMPH 2025 Meeting&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
International Society for Evolution, Medicine, and Public Health&lt;br /&gt;
Vanderbilt University, July 8-10, 2025&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The weekend following the ISEMPH conference (7/12/25 – 7/13/25), we will host an academic symposium featuring dozens of wonderful guest speakers from around the world. This event is sponsored in part by the National Center for Science Education. Leading experts (Ed Larson, Randy Moore, and Adam Laats) on all things Scopes will speak about the history of the trial. Next, we’ll hear about issues facing teachers today as they try to navigate teaching evolution (Barbara Forrest, Kenneth Miller, Amanda Townley). Then, we will hear from folks at the forefront of their evolution-focused fields about their research (Sean Carroll, Jonathan Losos, Marlene Zuk, Stephen Brusatte, and Briana Pobiner). We’ll finish off Day 1 with a roundtable discussion on evolutionary science in the 21st century.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Day 2 will kick off with evolutionary research in fields other than biology, such as medicine (Paul Turner), agriculture (Sophien Kamoun), and the law (Owen Jones). After that, we’ll have another section on teaching evolution in a broader sense (Gale Sinatra, Patricia Hawley, Corrie Moreau, Riley Black, and Joseph Graves, Jr.). Our last proper session will be on the relationship of evolution and religion (Jamie Jensen, Katy Hinman, Liz Barnes and Lee Meadows). We’ll end with a second roundtable discussion on the future of evolution education.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-scopes-trial-centennial-at-the-university-of-tennessee-knoxville&quot;&gt;The Scopes Trial Centennial at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Scopes Trial Centennial Celebration&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://artsci.utk.edu/scopes-trial-centennial-celebration/&quot;&gt;https://artsci.utk.edu/scopes-trial-centennial-celebration/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Scopes Trial Centennial at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville, is a year-long program that marks the 100th anniversary of the July 1925 trial of John Thomas Scopes. As a high-school teacher in Dayton, Tennessee, Scopes was accused of violating the state’s Butler Act, which made it illegal to teach human evolution in any public school or university.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The trial generated intense national publicity, as reporters flocked to Dayton to cover the high-profile lawyers facing each other in court. William Jennings Bryan, a three-time presidential candidate and former secretary of state, argued for the prosecution against ACLU lawyer Clarence Darrow, who served as the defense attorney for Scopes. The trial reflected a tension between religious fundamentalists and modern science that persists in America today.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Scopes Trial Centennial program will include Clarence Brown Theatre’s production of Inherit the Wind (February 14–March 2, 2025), which portrays a fictionalized version of the trial.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The program will also showcase the university’s annual Darwin Day, hosted by the McClung Museum on a Sunday afternoon the week of Darwin’s birthday in early February.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Throughout the year, a rich variety of speakers and exhibitions are being planned to address issues related to religion and science, American history, evolution, eugenics, journalism, law, and related topics. Additional programming is being developed that will be included as it is finalized.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Scopes Trial Centennial is organized by the UT College of Arts and Sciences (involving all three divisions) in collaboration with the College of Law, UT Libraries, the Institute for American Civics, Phi Beta Kappa Epsilon of Tennessee, and the Knoxville History Project.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Historical images are from the public domain, originally taken by the Associated Press in 1925.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A variety of talks on Scopes history and evolutionary science...I will quote the abstracts of the Scopes ones below.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Events&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Religion vs. Science? The Scopes Trial and Beyond&lt;br /&gt;
November 12, 2024, 4:30 – 5:30 P.M., John C. Hodges Library, Room 100&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Simone des Roches: Conserving Intraspecific Variation for Ecosystems and People&lt;br /&gt;
November 13, 2024, 12:40 – 1:30 P.M., Science and Engineering Building&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Evolution, Intelligent Design, and a Pennsylvania School Board – a discussion with Gordy Slack&lt;br /&gt;
November 14, 2024, 4:00 P.M., Student Union Executive Dining Room 377A&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
An evening with Gordon Burghardt on the Scopes Trial and Evolution in East Tennessee&lt;br /&gt;
November 19, 2024, 7:00 – 9:00 P.M., Student Union 262 A/B&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Naturalist Club Photo Gallery&lt;br /&gt;
January &amp;amp; February 2025, Hodges Library Starbucks&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Naturalist Club Photo Gallery – Reception&lt;br /&gt;
January 27, 2025, 1:00 – 3:00 P.M., Mary Greer room in Hodges Library&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Catherine Schuman: Evolution and Computing&lt;br /&gt;
January 29, 2025, 12:40 – 1:30 P.M., Science and Engineering Building 307&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Pamela Soltis: Polyploid Evolution: Integration across scales and biological systems&lt;br /&gt;
February 12, 2025, 12:40 – 1:30 P.M., Science and Engineering Building 307&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Inherit the Wind&lt;br /&gt;
February 14-March 2, 2025, Times Vary, Clarence Brown Theatre&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Ed Larson: The Scopes Trial in History and Folklore&lt;br /&gt;
February 13, 2025, 5:30 – 6:30 P.M., Student Union 262&lt;br /&gt;

Darwin Day at the McClung Museum&lt;br /&gt;
February 23, 2025, Frank H. McClung Museum of Natural History and Culture&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Sara Lipshutz: Fighting for fitness: Integrating behavioral, hormonal and neurogenomic perspectives on the evolution of female competition&lt;br /&gt;
February 24, 2025, 12:40 – 1:30 P.M., Science and Engineering Building&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Charles Israel: Before Scopes: Evangelicals, Education and Evolution in Tennessee, 1870-1925&lt;br /&gt;
March 25, 2025, 12:00 – 1:00 P.M., College of Law&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Matthew Sutton: The Scopes Trial and the Rise of Evangelical Politics&lt;br /&gt;
March 27, 2025, 5:00 – 6:00 P.M., Mossman 102&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Paul A. Lombardo: “Apes, Men &amp;amp; Morons”: Evolution, Eugenics, and the Scopes Trial&lt;br /&gt;
March 31, 2025, 7:30 – 9:30 P.M., Strong Hall B1&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Menno Schilthuizen: “Darwin Comes to Town: How the Urban Jungle Drives Evolution”&lt;br /&gt;
April 7, 2025, 3:30 – 5:00 P.M., Student Union 169&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Jessica Ware: Dragonflies and damselflies: genomics, systematics and evolution
May 5, 2025, 12:40 – 1:30 P.M., Science and Engineering Building
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/religion-vs-science-the-scopes-trial-and-beyond&quot;&gt;Religion vs. Science? The Scopes Trial and Beyond&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/religion-vs-science-the-scopes-trial-and-beyond&quot;&gt;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/religion-vs-science-the-scopes-trial-and-beyond&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Religion vs. Science? The Scopes Trial and Beyond&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Tuesday, November 12, 2024 4:30pm to 6pm&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
About this Event&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
John C Hodges Library, 100&lt;br /&gt;
1015 Volunteer Blvd, Knoxville TN&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The 1925 Scopes “Monkey” Trial often stands as a classic case demonstrating a fundamental conflict between religious and scientific worldviews. However, such characterizations mask the deeper complexities involved both in the trial and other historical engagements between religious and scientific perspectives. This panel brings together four scholars of religious studies to discuss how academic approaches to religion, culture, science, and media help move beyond the conflict thesis, demonstrating avenues for collaboration and understanding between diverse stakeholders as the 21st century progresses.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Panel Participants: &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Dr. Joseph Witt: Associate Professor of Religious Studies, focusing on Religion, the Natural World, and Appalachia&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Dr. David Kline: Senior Lecturer of Religious Studies, focusing on Religion, Media, and Political and Contextual Christian Thought&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Dr. Megan Bryson: Associate Professor of Religious Studies, focusing on Asian Religions and Scientific Discourse&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Dr. Erin Darby: Associate Professor of Religious Studies, focusing on Judaism and the interpretation of Hebrew Bible/Old Testament&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
If you are unable to attend inperson, we welcome you to join my registering with the link below.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/evolution-intelligent-design-and-a-pennsylvania-school-board-gordy-slack&quot;&gt;Evolution, Intelligent Design and a Pennsylvania School Board - Gordy Slack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/evolution-intelligent-design-and-a-pennsylvania-school-board-gordy-slack&quot;&gt;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/evolution-intelligent-design-and-a-pennsylvania-school-board-gordy-slack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
Thursday, November 14, 2024 4pm to 5:30pm&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Evolution, Intelligent Design and a Pennsylvania School Board - Gordy Slack&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Flyer for talk&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
About this Event&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Student Union, 377A&lt;br /&gt;
1502 Cumberland Ave. Knoxville, TN 37996&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A first-hand account by an author who witnessed the 2005 trial challenging the  teaching of intelligent design alongside evolution, in the school district of Dover PA. 
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/an-evenng-with-gordon-burghardt-on-the-scopes-trial-and-evolution-in-east-tennessee
&quot;&gt;An evening with Gordon Burghardt on the Scopes Trial and Evolution in East Tennessee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/an-evenng-with-gordon-burghardt-on-the-scopes-trial-and-evolution-in-east-tennessee
&quot;&gt;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/an-evenng-with-gordon-burghardt-on-the-scopes-trial-and-evolution-in-east-tennessee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Tuesday, November 19, 2024 7pm to 9pm&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
An evening with Gordon Burghardt on the Scopes Trial and Evolution in East Tennessee&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
About this Event&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Student Union, Su262 A/B&lt;br /&gt;
1502 Cumberland Ave. Knoxville, TN 37996&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Part of a seminar series on Innovations In Evolution  on the 100th anniversary of the Scopes Trial
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/the-scopes-trial-in-history-and-folklore&quot;&gt;The Scopes Trial in History and Folklore&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/the-scopes-trial-in-history-and-folklore&quot;&gt;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/the-scopes-trial-in-history-and-folklore&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Thursday, February 13, 2025 5:30pm to 6:30pm&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Scopes Trial in History and Folklore&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Edward Larson&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Event description&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A century ago in Dayton, Tennessee, sensation-loving journalists of the 1920s transformed a small-town misdemeanor trial, brought under a new state law against teaching the theory of evolution in public schools, into a legendary clash of worldviews pitting populist orator, politician William Jennings Bryan and libertarian secularist, attorney Clarence Darrow. Over the ensuing years, fact and fiction blurred into the mythical version of the Tennessee Monkey Trial celebrated in bestselling books, Broadway plays, and Hollywood movies. In his lecture, Pulitzer Prize winning historian Edward Larson separates history from folklore in relating the story of the Scopes trial then and thereafter.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Ed Larson holds the Darling Chair in Law and is a University Professor of History at Pepperdine University. Recipient of the 1998 Pulitzer Prize in History, Larson served as Associate Counsel for the U.S. House of Representatives and taught for twenty years at the University of Georgia, where he chaired the history department. The author of fifteen books and over eighty published articles, his books include A Magnificent Catastrophe: The Tumultuous Election of 1800; Evolution: The Remarkable History of a Scientific Theory; the Pulitzer Prize winning Summer for the Gods: The Scopes Trial and America's Continuing Debate Over Science and Religion, and the New York Times bestsellers, The Return of George Washington, 1783-1789 and Franklin &amp;amp; Washington: The Founding Partnership. Larson recently published, American Inheritance: Liberty and Slavery in the Birth of a Nation, 1765-1795. Larson has served as a visiting professor at Yale Law School, Stanford Law School, the University of Melbourne, Leiden University, and the University of Richmond.

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Darwin Day at the McClung Museum&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
February 23, 2025, Frank H. McClung Museum of Natural History and Culture&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[Details TBA it looks like]
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/before-scopes-evangelicals-education-and-evolution-in-tennessee-1870-1925-3274&quot;&gt;Before Scopes: Evangelicals, Education and Evolution in Tennessee, 1870-1925&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/before-scopes-evangelicals-education-and-evolution-in-tennessee-1870-1925-3274&quot;&gt;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/before-scopes-evangelicals-education-and-evolution-in-tennessee-1870-1925-3274&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Tuesday, March 25, 2025 12pm to 1pm&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Before Scopes: Evangelicals, Education and Evolution in Tennessee, 1870-1925&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Dr. Charles Israel, Auburn University, will discuss his award winning book as part of the Scopes series of events. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Event dates&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Tuesday, March 25, 2025 12pm to 1pm&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/the-scopes-trial-and-the-rise-of-evangelical-politics&quot;&gt;The Scopes Trial and the Rise of Evangelical Politics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/the-scopes-trial-and-the-rise-of-evangelical-politics&quot;&gt;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/the-scopes-trial-and-the-rise-of-evangelical-politics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Event description&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Part of &quot;Scopes Trial Centennial&quot; series of events&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
2025 Milton Klein Lecture Series&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
with speaker Matt Sutton, Edward R. Meyer Distinguished Professor of History at Washington State University&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In recent years, evangelicals have become the largest and most powerful multi-issue interest group in the Republican Party. Historians have long focused on the Scopes Trial as the start of evangelical political engagement, setting the trajectory that runs through the 2024 presidential campaign. Sutton will argue that Scopes marked an important turning point, but not necessarily for the reasons we usually think.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Matthew Avery Sutton is the Berry Family Distinguished Professor in the Liberal Arts and the chair of the Department of History at Washington State University. His most recent book is Double Crossed: The Missionaries Who Spied for the United States During the Second World War (Basic Books, 2019). He is also the author of American Apocalypse: A History of Modern Evangelicalism (Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 2014), and Aimee Semple McPherson and the Resurrection of Christian America (Harvard University Press, 2007). He has written for the New York Times, Washington Post, and New Republic. In 2016 he was appointed a Guggenheim Foundation Fellow.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Event dates&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Thursday, March 27, 2025 5pm
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/apes-men-and-morons-evolution-eugenics-and-the-scopes-trial&quot;&gt;Apes, Men, and Morons: Evolution, Eugenics, and the Scopes Trial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/apes-men-and-morons-evolution-eugenics-and-the-scopes-trial&quot;&gt;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/apes-men-and-morons-evolution-eugenics-and-the-scopes-trial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Event description&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Dr. Paul Lombardo, Regents’ Professor and Bobby Lee Cook Professor of Law at Georgia State University, is a noted historian of eugenics and compulsory sterilization laws in the United States. He will be speaking on the role that eugenics played in the Scopes &quot;Monkey&quot; Trial. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The “Monkey Trial” Centennial provides an opportunity to examine the widespread misunderstanding about how ideas of evolution and eugenics were implicated in the famous Scopes controversy.  George William Hunter’s textbook Civic Biology was the focus of the case. It endorsed evolution, a theory “that denies the story of the Divine Creation of man as taught in the Bible” -- content prohibited by a 1925 Tennessee law. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Hunter text also contained a chapter on eugenics. In recent years an elaborate mythology has arisen suggesting that the case, and William Jennings Bryan’s advocacy at trial, represented a challenge to eugenics. That claim is demonstrably false. The teaching of eugenics in its many forms was supported not only by educators, but also by members of the clergy and politicians all across the United States. That support was evident before the Scopes case and continued for decades afterwards, persisting even in full awareness of the Nazi government program that sterilized almost 1/2 million Germans.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
This talk will explain that while William Jennings Bryan rejected the monkey- to-man account of evolution and the cruelties he associated with Darwinian “natural selection,” he made no blanket condemnation of eugenics. To the contrary, Bryan and his wife readily allied themselves with several famous eugenists and supported eugenic ideology when it coincided with the social policies they favored.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Event dates&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Monday, March 31, 2025 7:30pm to 9:30pm&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Event Location&lt;br /&gt;
Strong Hall , B1 &lt;br /&gt;
1621 West Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scopes-trial-centennial&quot;&gt;Scopes Trial Centennial&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;March-July 2025, Dayton, Tennessee&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dayton, Tennessee, back to and including 1925, has promoted the town and the region as the site of the famous Scopes Monkey Trial, the (first) “Trial of the Century”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the 100th, they do not disappoint, with a variety of events ranging from scholarly to artistic and stage, and including even a Strawberry Festival.  Naturally, some of this involves fundamentalist Bryan College in Dayton, which itself traces right back to the Scopes Trial and William Jennings Bryan, so your mileage may vary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, having attended some similar events in 2014-2015, I expect many of these are worth going to.  In 2014 or 2015 I went to a stage production called something like “Our Story”, which was in a sense about the Scopes Trial, but more about the perspective of the locals, which they felt had been left out with the usual discussion of the huge science/religion issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
Dayton, Tennessee&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/&quot;&gt;Scopes Trial Centennial 2025&lt;/a&gt;
March-July 2025, Dayton, Tennessee&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
For more information about the celebration of the Scopes Trial Centennial visit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;b&gt;Events&lt;/b&gt;
Throughout the balance of 2024 and through 2025, we will be celebrating the Scopes Trial Centennial in a variety of ways. We invite you to participate in as many of these events as possible. Check the website and our social media links (Facebook and Instagram) regularly for updates.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Centennial Exhibit at Rhea County Heritage and Scopes Trial Museum&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The museum will display a special collection of historic items during the Scopes100 Centennial.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Student Visits to Courthouse &amp;amp; Museum&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Rhea County’s historic courthouse offers a unique and convenient educational experience for students.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
March 18-20: How It Started (and Why?)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Junior high and high school students can enjoy a one-hour play, followed by a lecture &amp;amp; tour.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/centennial-exhibit&quot;&gt;Centennial Exhibit at Rhea County Heritage and Scopes Trial Museum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/centennial-exhibit&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/centennial-exhibit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Oct 11&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Centennial Exhibit&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Museum open 8:00 a.m. – 4:30 p.m. daily. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Rhea County Heritage and Scopes Trial Museum&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In conjunction with Scopes100 Centennial activities and events, the Scopes Trial Museum, located in the basement of the historic Rhea County courthouse. The museum will display a special collection of historic items during the Scopes100 Centennial.  Details regarding these items will be provided on this page as we move closer to 1925.  The museum is designed for free, self-guided touring, but a representative of the historical Society will be available to assist and answer questions.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/ongoing-student-tours-of-courthouse-museum&quot;&gt;Student Visits to Courthouse &amp;amp; Museum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/ongoing-student-tours-of-courthouse-museum&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/ongoing-student-tours-of-courthouse-museum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Courthouse &amp;amp; Museum Visits&lt;br /&gt;
Museum open 8:00 a.m. – 4:30 p.m. daily. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Historic Rhea County Courthouse&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Call (423) 775-7801 to schedule a visit for your class.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Rhea County’s historic courthouse  offers a unique and convenient educational experience for to students. A national historic landmark which served as the setting for the nation’s most famous courtroom trial, the courthouse, its courtroom and its museum enable students to travel back in time and learn about the debate between “creationist” and “evolutionist.”  They will also come to understand the current issue of who decides a public school’s curriculum -- the parents or the teachers – is one which is long-standing.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/how-it-started-and-why&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/how-it-started-and-why&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/how-it-started-and-why&quot;&gt;March 18-20: How It Started (and Why?)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;How It Started&quot; Play &amp;amp; Discussion&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
March 18, 19, 20, 2025&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Historic Rhea County Courthouse
&lt;br /&gt;
FREE - Email admin@rheaheritage.com for reservations&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Junior high and high school students are invited to learn about the Scopes Trial through a one-hour fact-based play, followed by a lecture/discussion and a tour of the Rhea Heritage &amp;amp; Scopes Trial Museum. A study guide will be given to teachers and students. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Space is limited, so reservations are necessary for this free event.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/march-21-22-centennial-kickoff-event&quot;&gt;March 21-22: Centennial Kickoff Event
Scopes Trial Centennial Kick-Off Dinner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/march-21-22-centennial-kickoff-event&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/march-21-22-centennial-kickoff-event&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Friday, March 21, 2025, &lt;br /&gt;
Bryan College&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
TICKETS SALES (coming soon)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Join us for an evening of commemoration at the Scopes Trial Centennial Kick-Off Dinner, honoring the legacy of the Butler Act with distinguished speaker Ed Larson, Pulitzer Prize-winning author of Summer for the Gods: The Scopes Trial and America's Continuing Debate Over Science and Religion. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The evening will begin with a dinner featuring a prominent Tennessean, who will be announced closer to the event. Following the dinner, Ed Larson will unveil newly acquired and previously unseen photographs of the Scopes Trial, donated by a private party. These significant images will be presented to Bryan College and the Rhea County Historical Genealogical Society. Attendees will have the opportunity to view enlarged displays of the newly revealed photos, offering a unique glimpse into the historical significance of the Scopes Trial.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Tickets for this event are available for purchase, but seating is limited, so be sure to secure your spot for this important occasion!&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Breakfast and Lecture Discussion&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Saturday, March 22, 2025&lt;br /&gt;
Breakfast, (this event for educators only) 8:00 a.m.-9:00 a.m., Bryan College
Lecture-Discussion, 9:30 a.m.-12:00 p.m., Rhea County Courthouse&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Reservations are FREE, but are required&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Join us for a stimulating morning of conversation and insights with Dr. Edward J. Larson,&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Pulitzer Prize-wining author of Summer for the Gods. Dr. Larson will meet with teachers forbreakfast at Bryan College, then move to the Rhea County Courthouse where he will deliver the keynote address, “Why we Celebrate the Scopes Trial,” offering a profound exploration of this pivotal moment in American history. Following his lecture he will take questions from the audience, including selected students.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The lecture will be presented in the Scopes Trial Courtroom of the Rhea County Courthouse.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Ticket reservations will be available soon, so stay tuned for your opportunity to participate in this engaging discussion! Don’t miss out on this chance to deepen your understanding of the Scopes Trial and its lasting implications and to introduce students to an eminent historian.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/college-debate-at-the-courthouse&quot;&gt;April 17: College Debate at the Courthouse: A Debate on School Choice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/college-debate-at-the-courthouse&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/college-debate-at-the-courthouse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Thursday, April 17, 2025, &lt;br /&gt;
Rhea County Courthouse&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Reservations are FREE, but are required&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Join us for an engaging debate featuring two talented students from the Bryan College Debate Team on Thursday, April 17th at 6:30 PM, held at the historic Rhea County Courthouse. The topic of discussion will be &quot;School Choice,&quot; a crucial issue affecting education today. This event is free to attend, but registration is required due to limited seating. It promises to be an excellent educational opportunity for students and the Rhea County community alike. Don’t miss your chance to participate in the Scopes100 Centennial Celebration and witness a thought-provoking exchange of ideas!
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/78th-annual-tennessee-strawberry-festival&quot;&gt;May 5-10: 78th Annual Tennessee Strawberry Festival&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/78th-annual-tennessee-strawberry-festival&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/78th-annual-tennessee-strawberry-festival&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Dec 13&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Theme: The Great Berry Debate&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Join us for the 78th Annual Tennessee Strawberry Festival from May 5-10, 2025, with the exciting theme &quot;The Great Berry Debate!&quot; This year, we are not only celebrating the beloved strawberry but also commemorating 100 years since the Scopes Trials. Our unique theme will feature a strawberry debate that promises to engage and entertain participants of all ages.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The festival is packed with fun activities for everyone, from delicious strawberry treats to engaging events. Be sure to check the schedule for details on your favorite parts of the festival.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Don’t miss out on this delightful celebration! For more information, visit our website at &lt;a href=&quot;https://tnstrawberryfestival.com/&quot;&gt;https://tnstrawberryfestival.com/&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-11-heritage-days-expo&quot;&gt;July 11-12: Heritage Days&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-11-heritage-days-expo&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-11-heritage-days-expo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Dec 13&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Heritage Days Celebration&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Friday, July 11 - Saturday, July 12, 2025&lt;br /&gt;
Lawn of Historic Rhea County Courthouse&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Booths and displays on the grounds of the historic Rhea County Courthouse will offer educational and entertaining information about Rhea County and its heritage. Games, displays – some hands-on – and food will make for a fun outing for the whole family. Most activities will be free. If you are interested in exhibiting, email admin@rheaheritage.com for information.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-11-12-heritage-days-expo&quot;&gt;July 11-12: Destiny in Dayton Drama&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-11-12-heritage-days-expo&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-11-12-heritage-days-expo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Oct 12&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Scopes Trial Dramatization&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Fri., July 11, 2025, 7:00 PM / Sat., July 12, 2025, 2:00 PM&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Scopes Trial Courtroom, Historic Rhea County Courthouse&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
BUY TICKETS&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
See a dramatization of the Scopes Trial in the courtroom where the trial was held in 1925. Destiny in Dayton adapts the trial transcript to an engrossing account of the trial, giving viewers an accurate picture of this duel of great men and great ideas.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-11-12-buttram-cemetery-tour&quot;&gt;July 11-12: Visit Historic Buttram Cemetery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-11-12-buttram-cemetery-tour&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-11-12-buttram-cemetery-tour&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Nov 4&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Burial Site of Notable Scopes Trial Participants &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
July 11 &amp;amp; 12, 2025&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Historic Rhea County Courthouse&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Free transportation provided on demand.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Buttram Cemetery, situated north of Dayton, Tennessee, and east of U.S. Highway 27, serves as the final resting place for numerous individuals having historical significance to Rhea County. Dating back to 1811, it is the burial location for no less than thirteen local citizens who played a notable role in trial of John Scopes.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
To those wishing to visit the cemetery, transportation to and from Dayton’s historic courthouse will be provided upon demand at no charge. A representative of the Rhea County Historical Society will be available at the cemetery to answer questions. For those wishing to visit the cemetery on their own, a brochure will be available at the courthouse which allows for a self-guided tour.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-13-return-to-1925&quot;&gt;July 13: Return to 1925&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-13-return-to-1925&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-13-return-to-1925&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Oct 11&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
What Life Was Like During the Scopes Trial
Sunday, July 13, 1:00 PM – 7:30 PM&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Historic Rhea County Courthouse Courtroom and Courthouse Lawn&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Silent films free to public on  a first-come/first serve basis.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Spend the day traveling back to the year 1925 and walk into the world of those local residents who attended the trial of John Scopes. See a collection of circa 1915-1925 vintage automobiles at the historic courthouse which were likely parked around its grounds. Attend one or more showings of silent films of the day in the courtroom where John Scopes was brought to trial. View the advertising art of the most popular commercial products available to consumers at the time of the trial.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-17-scopes-trial-symposium-in-the-historic-courtroom&quot;&gt;July 16-17: Evolving Conflict: Scopes at 100&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-17-scopes-trial-symposium-in-the-historic-courtroom&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-17-scopes-trial-symposium-in-the-historic-courtroom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Oct 12&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;A Symposium on the Scopes Trial&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Wednesday, July 16, 2025; 9:00 a.m.–10:00 a.m./10:30 a.m.–11:30 a.m./ 1:00p.m–2:00 p.m.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Thursday, July 17, 2025, 9:00 a.m. – 10:00 a.m. / 10:30 a.m. – 11:30 a.m. /
1:00 p.m. – 2:00 p.m. / 2:30 p.m. – 3:30 p.m.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Scopes Trial Courtroom&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
BUY TICKETS&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In 1925, the legal question debated during the Scopes Trial was whether John Scopes broke the law by teaching the Darwinian theory of human origins. But lawyers also debated questions which still are at the center of public discussion today: Parental rights in public education, can the majority impose its will on the minority, academic freedom (of teachers and students), the role of religion in public life. Hotly debated then, still capable of raising temperatures today, these questions were not settled in 1925 – and probably won’t be settled during this discussion.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In 1925, both sides had their say; in this symposium you will hear more than one viewpoint presented by experts in their disciplines, and you will have an opportunity to interact with the presenters.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The program begins promptly at 9 a.m. Wednesday and Thursday, July 16 and 17, in the Scopes Trial courtroom of the historic Rhea County Courthouse.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Dr. Nick Spencer will lead off with a presentation on “Science, Religion and How We Got Here;” followed by Attorney Jerry Summers, speaking on “The Trial and Its People.” After a break for lunch, Dr. Edward Larson, recipient of the Pulitzer Prize in History for his book “Summer for the Gods,” will speak on the legacy of the trial in American life. Following Dr. Larson’s program, the afternoon will be open for tours of historic sites in and near Dayton.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
On Thursday, Dr. Neal Doran will discuss ”Science at the Scopes Trial and Since;” and Dr. John Hawks will present his findings on “Human Origins: What Paleontology Tells Us.” After lunch, Dr. Joel Duff will speak on “Christians and Evolution after the Trial,” and Dr. Todd Wood and Mr. Paul Garner will discuss “A History of Creationism and the Future of the Creation/Evolution Debate.” Free time will be available for tours Thursday afternoon.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There will be breaks between sessions and for lunch both days. A study guide will be provided for your further reflection on the presentations.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Scopes Trial Symposium Dinner&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Wednesday, July 17, 2025, 6:30 – 9:00 PM&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Trinity Chapel&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
BUY TICKETS&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Join us for a festive 1920s-themed dinner in historic Trinity Chapel on Wednesday, July 16. Trinity Chapel, today an event venue but Dayton’s Northern Methodist Church in 1925, has its own unique place in the Scopes Trial story. The congregation and the minister disagreed about hearing a sermon on evolution – and we’ll tell the rest of the story when you get here!&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
After a hearty meal, serenaded by music from the era, Dr. Randy Moore, author of the recently published John Thomas Scopes: A Biography, will speak on “John Scopes: The Rest of the Story.” After you hear his talk, you definitely will want to read the book.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Space is limited, so order your tickets soon.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-18-19-local-history-expo&quot;&gt;July 18-19: Local History Expo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-18-19-local-history-expo&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-18-19-local-history-expo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Dec 13&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Learn More About the Educational and Commercial History of Rhea County&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Friday, July 18  - Saturday, July 19, 2025&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Historic Courthouse and Lawn&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
FREE to the General Public&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Booths and displays located on the grounds of the historic Rhea County courthouse will provide educational information regarding the history of Rhea County and surrounding southeastern Tennessee counties. Historical societies and site-specific historic groups will display historic items associated with their activities. Major employers will present their origin stories and highlight their historic contributions to the local economy. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
If you are an organization in the East Tennessee area whose mission is history-related and you would like be a part of the Expo, please contact the Rhea County Historical Society at 916-710-1747.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-18-19-buttram-cemetery-tour&quot;&gt;July 18-19: Visit Historic Buttram Cemetery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-18-19-buttram-cemetery-tour&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-18-19-buttram-cemetery-tour&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Nov 4&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Burial Site of Notable Scopes Trial Participants&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
July 11 &amp;amp; 12, 2025&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Historic Rhea County Courthouse&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Free transportation provided on demand.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Buttram Cemetery, situated north of Dayton, Tennessee, and east of U.S. Highway 27, serves as the final resting place for numerous individuals having historical significance to Rhea County. Dating back to 1811, it is the burial location for no less than thirteen local citizens who played a notable role in trial of John Scopes.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
To those wishing to visit the cemetery, transportation to and from Dayton’s historic courthouse will be provided upon demand at no charge. A representative of the Rhea County Historical Society will be available at the cemetery to answer questions. For those wishing to visit the cemetery on their own, a brochure will be available at the courthouse which allows for a self-guided tour.

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-18-19-destiny-in-dayton-drama&quot;&gt;July 18-19: Destiny in Dayton Drama&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-18-19-destiny-in-dayton-drama&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-18-19-destiny-in-dayton-drama&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Oct 12&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Scopes Trial Dramatization &lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Fri., July 18, 2025, 7:00 PM / Sat., July 19, 2025, 2:00 PM (Dinner with Cast included)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Scopes Trial Courtroom, Rhea County Courthouse&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
BUY TICKETS&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
See a dramatization of the Scopes Trial in the courtroom where the trial was held in 1925. Destiny in Dayton adapts the trial transcript to an engrossing account of the trial, giving viewers an accurate picture of this duel of great men and great ideas. Following Saturday’s show, enjoy a 1920s-themed Dinner with the Cast of Destiny in Dayton under tents on the courthouse lawn, in the shade of trees – some of which were there for the trial!
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-19-destiny-in-dayton-dinner&quot;&gt;July 19: Play and Dinner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-19-destiny-in-dayton-dinner&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-19-destiny-in-dayton-dinner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Dec 9&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Dinner with the Cast and Crew &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Saturday. July 19. 2025, Immediately following the play &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Rhea County Courthouse lawn&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
BUY TICKETS&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
See a dramatization of the Scopes Trial in the courtroom where the trial was held in 1925. Destiny in Dayton adapts the trial transcript to an engrossing account of the trial, giving viewers an accurate picture of this duel of great men and great ideas. Following the show, enjoy a 1920s-themed Dinner with the Cast of Destiny in Dayton under tents on the courthouse lawn, in the shade of trees – some of which were there for the trial!
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Matzke</name></author><summary type="html">Nick Matzke at the Dayton County Courthouse where the Scopes Trial was held in 1925. (photo from ~2014) UPDATE, Dec. 22: I have now listed 52 separate events I found, including links and quotes of the summaries where available. Please contribute more in the comments! Merry Kitzmas to all! Today is the 19th anniversary of the Kitzmiller v. Dover Area School District trial, aka the Dover Panda Trial, held from September-November 2005, and decided on December 20, 2005. Next year, 2025, will be the 20th anniversary of Kitzmiller, as well as the 100th anniversary of Tennessee v. Scopes, aka the Scopes Monkey Trial. Stuck as I am, in Australia/New Zealand with 3 little kids, I expect I will have to follow events from afar. But I will use this thread to accumulate links &amp;amp; dates for relevant events as they come up. And please contribute ones you come across! I expect that many are glum about current politics and science, but I recall a similar feeling in 2004, and that Kitzmiller v. Dover was one of the early signs that committed citizens could move events in a pro-science direction. May 2025 be another such time! Summaries of events are posted below, with abstracts where available:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Eric Hedin, meet Granville Sewell</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/eric-hedin-meet-granville-sewell.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Eric Hedin, meet Granville Sewell" /><published>2024-12-11T22:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2024-12-11T22:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/eric-hedin-meet-granville-sewell</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/eric-hedin-meet-granville-sewell.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Nuucichthys.png&quot; alt=&quot;[An intermediate step]&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;One of the intermediate steps that Granville Sewell does not 
mention, and which Eric Hedin sort-of-knows occur.  (a), Reconstruction 
of a very early vertebrate, the fossil &lt;em&gt;Nuucichthys&lt;/em&gt;, which lived 
518 million years ago, with (b) its inferred position shown on the vertebrate phylogeny.  From &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; class=&quot;external free&quot; href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1098/rsos.240350&quot;&gt;a paper by Rudy Lerosey-Aubril &amp;amp; Javier Ortega-Hernández&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0&quot; title=&quot;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0&quot;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt; From Wikimedia.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Physicist Eric Hedin has posted to the Discovery Institute site 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2024/11/theres-a-limit-to-what-nature-can-do&quot;&gt;Evolution News on 27 November 2024&lt;/a&gt;
an argument that the processes of physics cannot 
account for intelligent life.  As he is a well-trained physicist (whose Ph.D. 
degree was from my university), and who has done experimental 
work on plasma physics, we can expect a mathematically sophisticated 
argument which would give us all pause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, here’s the guts of his argument, from the Evolution News post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In fact, for making anything other than large-scale conglomerations of matter (such as stars and planets), nature has only one tool in its bag — the electromagnetic force. This tool primarily manifests as the electric force, causing opposite charges (such as electrons and protons) to attract, and like charges to repel. It is completely indiscriminate, and cannot select between multiple options, preferring one charge over another, except for the rule that the bigger the charges and the closer the distance between them the stronger the resulting force. Can you imagine such blind, brute forces pulling together countless atoms of specific elements into the necessary configurations to result in a functioning laptop computer?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The “boundaries of science” refers to the common-sense conclusion that nature is limited in what it can produce to outcomes consistent with the laws and forces of nature. Natural processes are sought and found to be sufficient for natural phenomena, such as star formation or precipitation.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;However, attempting to naturally explain the origin of some things found within our universe comes into conflict with the boundaries of science. Positing a natural explanation for the origin of the universe itself, the origin of the specific suite of physical parameters finely tuned to allow life, the origin of life itself, and the origin of conscious, intelligent minds, all defy what we have discovered about the limits of natural processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And basically, that’s the argument.  Evolutionary biology does not pretend to address the origin of the universe, or the issue of fine-tuning in physics, and even the origin of life is outside its scope, though adjacent.  But somehow Hedin knows that physical forces cannot explain “the origin of conscious, 
intelligent minds”.   I wonder how he knows that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;meet-granville-sewell&quot;&gt;Meet Granville Sewell&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hedin’s argument is quite similar to Granville Sewell’s. Sewell asks (rhetorically) whether it is not implausible that advanced technology such as iPhones could have resulted from natural forces, which involve only random collisions of particles.   An example of his argument will be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2021/04/some-problems-can-be-proved-unsolvable/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, where he asks whether it is possible to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Explain how life could have originated and evolved into intelligent humans, through entirely natural (unintelligent) processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granville Sewell is a mathematician, who is Professor Emeritus in the Departrment of Mathematical Sciences at the University of Texas at El Paso.  He is a specialist in numerical solution of differential equations. Here is how he invokes physics to solve this problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Well, I have a very simple proof that the biological problem #3  [the one mentioned above] posed above is also impossible to solve, that does fit in the margin of this document. All one needs to do is realize that if a solution were found, we would have proved something obviously false, that a few (four, apparently) fundamental, unintelligent forces of physics alone could have rearranged the fundamental particles of physics into libraries full of science texts and encyclopedias, computers connected to monitors, keyboards, laser printers and the Internet, cars, trucks, airplanes, nuclear power plants and Apple iPhones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are from a 2021 post at Evolution News (which I linked to above). It should be obvious that Hedin’s and Sewell’s  arguments are similar, since they invoke physics.  They are also similar in lacking mathematical details, although elsewhere Sewell does present a partial differential equation for the simple diffusion of a chemical element outwards from an area of concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-sewell-has-left-out&quot;&gt;What Sewell has left out&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granville Sewell’s argument has been repeatedly promoted by him, in various versions.  In addition to the link in the previous section, examples of his advocacy will be found in blogs such as Evolution News and Uncommon Descent and in papers, book chapters and videos (here I take a deep breath)
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.utep.edu/faculty/sewell/articles/mathint.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.utep.edu/faculty/sewell/articles/open.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://spectator.org/47666_evolutions-thermodynamic-failure/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.utep.edu/faculty/sewell/AML_3497.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2012/02/looking_for_the/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/new-video-evolution-is-a-natural-process-running-backward-2/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://bio-complexity.org/ojs/index.php/main/article/view/BIO-C.2013.2/BIO-C.2013.2&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://dx.doi.org/10.1142/9789814508728_0007&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Beginning-Other-Essays-Intelligent-Design/dp/1936599279/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.utep.edu/faculty/sewell/articles/pe_sewell.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2018/05/i-believe-in-the-evolution-of-life-and-the-evolution-of-automobiles/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2018/08/who-is-doing-pseudoscience/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2018/11/why-evolution-and-reproduction-are-unnatural/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2019/05/two-schemes-to-defeat-the-second-law/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2020/01/how-science-lost-its-mind/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2020/06/new-video-why-evolution-is-different/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2020/10/my-failed-computer-simulation/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2022/01/the-underlying-principle-behind-the-second-law/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2022/06/three-realities-chance-cant-explain-that-intelligent-design-can/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2023/03/yes-extraordinary-claims-require-extraordinary-evidence-lets-hear-some-for-darwinian-evolution/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2023/07/in-summary-presenting-the-evidence-for-intelligent-design/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2023/08/how-the-supernatural-entered-science/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2024/03/life-and-the-underlying-principle-behind-the-second-law-of-thermodynamics/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2024/07/introduction-to-the-scientific-theory-of-intelligent-design/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I may have missed a few, but you get the idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granville Sewell’s argument has been commented on many times over the years. The late physicist Mark Perakh 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.talkreason.org/articles/sewell.cfm&quot;&gt;(here)&lt;/a&gt;, 
the mathematician Jason Rosenhouse &lt;a href=&quot;https://skepticalinquirer.org/exclusive/does-evolution-have-a-thermodynamics-problem/&quot;&gt;(here)&lt;/a&gt;, and physicist Dan Styer 
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.oberlin.edu/physics/dstyer/SandE/StyerRemarksOnSewellPE.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.oberlin.edu/physics/dstyer/SandE/ObviousImplausibility.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)
sternly criticized his assertions that evolution contradicts the Second Law of Thermodynamics.  Sewell has since 
quietly backed away from his original assertions about the Second Law of Thermodynamics, instead coming up 
with an ill-defined concept of “X-entropy”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His arguments have been 
commented on many times here.  I have posted a number of times at Panda’s Thumb and at The Skeptical Zone 
(&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2010/02/evidence-that-t.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2011/02/granville-sewel.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2011/11/granville-sewel-1.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/Granville-Sewell-thinks-its-obvious.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
and &lt;a href=&quot;http://theskepticalzone.com/wp/what-is-obvious-to-granville-sewell/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my 2021 post (the fourth one above), I noted that the processes 
that Sewell thinks that the “rearrangement” of fundamental particles includes quite 
a few steps that we generally don’t attribute to Design Intervention, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Elementary particles aggregating to form larger particles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Those particles forming atoms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Atoms becoming connected by bonds to form chemicals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Chemicals interacting to form cosmic dust&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Cosmic dust forming clouds by the attraction of gravity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Gravity in dust clouds leading to clumps that become a solar system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; ... including the formation of a star and planets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Lots of geology (steps omitted)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; An early Earth with interesting organic chemicals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Origin of life&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Evolution of protists and single-celled eukaryotes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Evolution of multicellular life&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Evolution of people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; People producing tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; People producing agriculture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; and civilization,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; and technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include processes of physics, astronomy, geology, and chemistry.  Those are fields that get 
along fine without any Design Intervention.  Likewise we know people can produce agriculture, 
civilization, and technology.  That’s already an awful lot of Granville Sewell’s process of “particles 
rearranging themselves”.  There are numerous parts of the evolution of life (and the origin of life) 
that ID advocates dispute, but much of their concentration is on two of the list items, the 
origin of life and the evolution of humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hedin-compared-to-sewell&quot;&gt;Hedin compared to Sewell&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Hedin faces similar issues, but is more cautious in his assertions.    He focuses on fine-tuning arguments, which are outside of the domain of evolutionary biology, but also on the origin of life and on the origin of conscious, 
intelligent minds.   Hedin has written many posts on Evolution News (for a list of them see &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/author/ehedin/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).  In &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2023/05/is-life-an-information-ratchet/&quot;&gt;one of the earlier ones&lt;/a&gt; last year, he argued that a conservation-of-information argument showed that an evolving species could not gain specified information.  I disputed this 
in &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/08/Hedin-information-principle.html&quot;&gt;a post here at Panda’s Thumb&lt;/a&gt;.  Reading Hedin’s post closely, it could be seen that while he didn’t think it was possible for evolving organisms to 
produce “novel complex functionality”, he did acknowledge that natural selection can accumulate information:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But what can this “ratchet” do? No more than it was designed to do — namely to reproduce daughter organisms according to its inherent mechanism of reproduction. Variations in the organism’s genome, by any unguided process, may lead to an increase in fitness and therefore survivability. But natural processes cannot produce unnatural results. Selection based on the ratchet mechanism of increased fitness cannot of itself produce novel complex functionality if each successive small change does not give some increased advantage towards survival and reproduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while Granville Sewell implies, without proof, that accumulation of favorable mutants by natural selection is a thermodynamic impossibility, Eric Hedin acknowledges that it is a possibility.  He confines his objections to “novel, complex functionality”.  The chief example he gives of this is the origin of a conscious, intelligent “mind”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;intelligent-brains--or-minds&quot;&gt;Intelligent brains?  Or “minds”?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to be careful here.  It is tempting to think that Hedin is describing conscious, intelligent &lt;em&gt;brains&lt;/em&gt;.  After all, our mind is just stuff that happens in our brains, isn’t it?  In Hedin’s terminology, “mind” is quite distinct from the mere activity of the brain.  Hedin is a dualist, in that he thinks that our brain exists in the real world, while our “mind” exists in a spiritual world (see an article of his &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2024/04/mind-matter-and-intelligent-design/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no understanding of how minds might evolve in a spiritual world, so I am going to discuss only brains, under the assumption – or perhaps the delusion – that we should think about the evolution of brains, and leave the issue of “mind” to those who understand things spiritual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;can-brains-evolve-to-get-smarter-more-conscious&quot;&gt;Can brains evolve to get smarter? More conscious?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can brains get better at thinking?  They certainly vary from species to species in the ability to think.  In their simplest forms they can’t do very much thinking.   That’s where the image at the start of this article becomes relevant.  It shows &lt;em&gt;Nuucichthys&lt;/em&gt;, a recently-discovered early vertebrate, from the early Cambrian.  It has eyes near its front, and it is quite a good assumption that they connect to a primitive brain.  Given that bigger brains are needed to have more intelligent behavior, there is really no reason to imagine a barrier to the evolution of more intelligence by ordinary evolutionary processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what about consciousness?  We usually think about consciousness in terms of conscious behavior of humans, contemplating beauty, morality, and mortality.  All very lofty and difficult.  But if we take an evolutionary view of it, 
we can ask whether much earlier species could show the basics of consciousness.  If a mouse is looking at its surroundings and is able to have some representation of them, a representation that includes itself, then if it can 
choose a route for itself to its burrow, that seems to me to be an early form of consciousness.  “Let’s see, 
if I am &lt;em&gt;there&lt;/em&gt; and the bush is &lt;em&gt;there&lt;/em&gt; and the log is &lt;em&gt;there&lt;/em&gt;, and my burrow is behind the tree, then I should go 
to the left of the bush, over the log, and to the right of the tree, and there will be the burrow.”  The mouse is making a representation of its environment which includes a representation of itself, viewed from outside.  From there, more elaborate forms of consciousness could, I think, evolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there is, in fact, evidence of such a map of the surroundings in the brains of rats.   See, for example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hhmi.org/news/uncovering-the-neural-basis-for-hypothetical-thinking-in-rats&quot;&gt;this report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If any of this makes sense then there is no reason to suppose that there is some barrier to the evolution of conscious, intelligent brains.  In which case Eric Hedin’s argument boils down to simple incredulity, without any logical proof of a barrier to evolution by ordinary evolutionary processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is where Granville Sewell’s argument ended up, too.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">One of the intermediate steps that Granville Sewell does not mention, and which Eric Hedin sort-of-knows occur. (a), Reconstruction of a very early vertebrate, the fossil Nuucichthys, which lived 518 million years ago, with (b) its inferred position shown on the vertebrate phylogeny. From a paper by Rudy Lerosey-Aubril &amp;amp; Javier Ortega-Hernández, CC BY 4.0 From Wikimedia. &amp;nbsp; Physicist Eric Hedin has posted to the Discovery Institute site Evolution News on 27 November 2024 an argument that the processes of physics cannot account for intelligent life. As he is a well-trained physicist (whose Ph.D. degree was from my university), and who has done experimental work on plasma physics, we can expect a mathematically sophisticated argument which would give us all pause. Well, here’s the guts of his argument, from the Evolution News post: In fact, for making anything other than large-scale conglomerations of matter (such as stars and planets), nature has only one tool in its bag — the electromagnetic force. This tool primarily manifests as the electric force, causing opposite charges (such as electrons and protons) to attract, and like charges to repel. It is completely indiscriminate, and cannot select between multiple options, preferring one charge over another, except for the rule that the bigger the charges and the closer the distance between them the stronger the resulting force. Can you imagine such blind, brute forces pulling together countless atoms of specific elements into the necessary configurations to result in a functioning laptop computer? and The “boundaries of science” refers to the common-sense conclusion that nature is limited in what it can produce to outcomes consistent with the laws and forces of nature. Natural processes are sought and found to be sufficient for natural phenomena, such as star formation or precipitation. However, attempting to naturally explain the origin of some things found within our universe comes into conflict with the boundaries of science. Positing a natural explanation for the origin of the universe itself, the origin of the specific suite of physical parameters finely tuned to allow life, the origin of life itself, and the origin of conscious, intelligent minds, all defy what we have discovered about the limits of natural processes. And basically, that’s the argument. Evolutionary biology does not pretend to address the origin of the universe, or the issue of fine-tuning in physics, and even the origin of life is outside its scope, though adjacent. But somehow Hedin knows that physical forces cannot explain “the origin of conscious, intelligent minds”. I wonder how he knows that.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ellipes minuta</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/ellipes-minuta.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ellipes minuta" /><published>2024-12-09T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-12-09T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/ellipes-minuta</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/ellipes-minuta.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Mark Sturtevant&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Sturtevant.Pygmy_mole_cricket.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pygmy mole cricket&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bugguide.net/node/view/110363&quot;&gt;Ellipes minuta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; pygmy mole cricket.  Dr. Sturtevant notes, &quot;This insect is a small oddity. Despite its name, the diminutive pygmy mole crickets are not true mole crickets, or even crickets for that matter. They are classified as belonging in the same sub-order as grasshoppers.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Mark Sturtevant. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Ellipes minuta &amp;ndash; pygmy mole cricket. Dr. Sturtevant notes, &quot;This insect is a small oddity. Despite its name, the diminutive pygmy mole crickets are not true mole crickets, or even crickets for that matter. They are classified as belonging in the same sub-order as grasshoppers.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Confidence in scientists rises</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/confidence-scientists.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Confidence in scientists rises" /><published>2024-11-26T10:34:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-11-26T10:34:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/confidence-scientists</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/confidence-scientists.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/AIP_Pew_Views_Of_Scientists_Fig_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Public's views of scientists.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Figure 1. Intelligent, but closed-minded. Not entirely flattering.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the Pew Research Center, confidence in scientists has ticked up slightly, though it remains lower than it was before the pandemic. That is one of the conclusions of a report, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/science/2024/11/14/public-trust-in-scientists-and-views-on-their-role-in-policymaking/&quot;&gt;Public Trust in Scientists and Views on Their Role in Policymaking&lt;/a&gt;, by Alec Tyson and Brian Kennedy. Pew surveyed nearly 10,000 US adults in October and discovered that Americans (mostly) perceive scientists as intelligent, honest, and focused on real-world problems. They see communication as a weak area and think that we are good at working in teams, though how they know about teamwork is a puzzle to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least they think we are reasonably bright; they also find us socially awkward, cold, superior, and closed-minded. Figure 1 shows how these perceptions break down according to political party: Democrats and their fellow travelers (whom I shall call Democrats) have a considerably more favorable view of scientists than Republicans and their fellow travelers (whom I shall call Republicans). I was somewhat bemused by the claim of roughly half of Republicans that scientists &quot;[d]on't pay attention to moral values of society,&quot; and wondered precisely what and whose moral values they have in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pew notes, somewhat to my surprise,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;In an era of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewtrusts.org/en/trend/archive/fall-2024/americans-deepening-mistrust-of-institutions&quot;&gt;low public trust in institutions&lt;/a&gt;, scientists continue to be held in higher regard than several other prominent groups we’ve asked about, including journalists, elected officials, business leaders and religious leaders. Confidence ratings for scientists are even slightly higher than those for public school principals and police officers – two groups that receive positive overall ratings. [I did not follow the preceding link.] &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pew also notes differences by race and ethnicity; you may find these by following the link in the first paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/AIP_Pew_Role_In_Policy_Fig_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Scientists' role in public policy.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Figure 2. Approximately half of those surveyed think that scientists should be active in policy debates.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding science policy, I would wager, assuming it is legal to do so, that a very significant fraction of those reading this article would privilege scientists over laypersons when it came to setting science policy. Figure 2 shows that almost exactly half of the respondents to the Pew survey disagree with that contention and think that scientists should stay out of policy. Only about one-third of Republicans think that scientists should &quot;[t]ake an active role in public policy debates about scientific issues,&quot; as opposed to two-thirds of Democrats. Only 7&amp;nbsp;% of Democrats think that scientists have too much influence in public policy debates. One important question, of course, is whether laypersons who weigh in on scientific issues have informed opinions, and another is whether scientists who weigh in on issues outside their own fields have opinions that are more informed than anyone else's.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A science policy bulletin from the American Institute of Physics, &lt;a href=&quot;https://us17.campaign-archive.com/?e=480f65d998&amp;amp;u=be8b78d2ef406eb6026a6ba21&amp;amp;id=539a20766c&quot;&gt;Public Opinion Divided over Role of Scientists in Policymaking&lt;/a&gt;, by Lindsay McKenzie, synopsized the Pew article and stated,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Perceptions that scientists are poor communicators and feel superior to others “pain me to my core,” said Sudip Parikh, CEO of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, during [an] event discussing the survey results. “Humility is an absolute requirement for science communication,” said Parikh. “If you can’t be humbled about the fact that science is done by humans and we are all subject to all the fallibility and all the extraordinary talents that humans have, then you can’t relate.” &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;i&gt;Times&lt;/i&gt; article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2024/11/14/health/trust-science-americans.html&quot;&gt;Americans Have Regained Modest Trust in Scientists, Survey Finds&lt;/a&gt;, by Teddy Rosenbluth, incidentally, speculates,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Recent high-profile medical and scientific advancements — like the new gene therapy for sickle cell and ambitious space exploration missions — have done the most to rebuild confidence in scientific institutions, [Parikh] added.&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Figure 1. Intelligent, but closed-minded. Not entirely flattering. According to the Pew Research Center, confidence in scientists has ticked up slightly, though it remains lower than it was before the pandemic. That is one of the conclusions of a report, Public Trust in Scientists and Views on Their Role in Policymaking, by Alec Tyson and Brian Kennedy. Pew surveyed nearly 10,000 US adults in October and discovered that Americans (mostly) perceive scientists as intelligent, honest, and focused on real-world problems. They see communication as a weak area and think that we are good at working in teams, though how they know about teamwork is a puzzle to me. At least they think we are reasonably bright; they also find us socially awkward, cold, superior, and closed-minded. Figure 1 shows how these perceptions break down according to political party: Democrats and their fellow travelers (whom I shall call Democrats) have a considerably more favorable view of scientists than Republicans and their fellow travelers (whom I shall call Republicans). I was somewhat bemused by the claim of roughly half of Republicans that scientists &quot;[d]on't pay attention to moral values of society,&quot; and wondered precisely what and whose moral values they have in mind. Pew notes, somewhat to my surprise,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bombus mixtus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/bombus-mixtus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bombus mixtus" /><published>2024-11-25T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-11-25T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/bombus-mixtus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/bombus-mixtus.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Ken Phelps&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Phelps_Bombus_mixtus_Spring_Rain.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bumblebee&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bombus_mixtus&quot;&gt;Bombus mixtus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; bumblebee, photographed on a thistle immediately after a spring shower. The hairs on the abdomen are wetted where a raindrop hit. Located Nanaimo Lakes, Vancouver Island. Canon 20D, 100&amp;nbsp;mm macro.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Ken Phelps. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Bombus mixtus &amp;ndash; bumblebee, photographed on a thistle immediately after a spring shower. The hairs on the abdomen are wetted where a raindrop hit. Located Nanaimo Lakes, Vancouver Island. Canon 20D, 100&amp;nbsp;mm macro. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Every Living Thing: book report</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/every-living-thing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Every Living Thing: book report" /><published>2024-11-12T19:15:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-11-12T19:15:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/every-living-thing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/every-living-thing.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Roberts_Every_Living_Thing_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The cover is kind of &quot;busy,&quot; but I shall try not to judge the book by its cover.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0C7TNQHKK/&quot;&gt;Every Living Thing&lt;/a&gt;, The Great and Deadly Race to Know All Life&lt;/i&gt;, by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jason_Roberts_(author)&quot;&gt;Jason Roberts&lt;/a&gt;. It is sort of a double biography of Carl Linnaeus (1707-1778) and Georges-Louis Leclerc, Comte de Buffon (1707-1788), but it continues to follow their legacies well beyond their lifetimes to the present. I cannot recommend it more highly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not know what impression Mr. Roberts intended, but if you thought Linnaeus was a young man on the make, something of a scoundrel who might say anything in the interests of self-promotion, you might not be too far from the truth. The hero of this book is not Linnaeus but rather his sometime rival, Buffon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let us deal with Linnaeus first. Linnaeus obtained a phony doctor’s degree from what we would now call a diploma mill. He anointed 14 (or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ikfoundation.org/books-and-art/linnaeus-apostles-full-set/&quot;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;
 of what he called his “apostles” (!), sent them on long journeys from which many never returned, and completely abandoned one who returned with no specimens. He has been criticized for not allowing his daughters their educations, to a degree, says Roberts, that was extreme even for the time (but he supported his daughter Elisabeth in her interest in botany. She wrote a paper devoted to what is now known as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nybg.org/blogs/science-talk/2013/12/flashes-in-the-twilight/&quot;&gt;Elizabeth Linnaeus phenomenon&lt;/a&gt;). Linnaeus also believed in the fixity of species, not to mention some very bizarre creatures, but in that he was probably not alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linnaeus developed a taxonomy that is largely in use today; that is a major accomplishment, to say the least. After defining and then apparently rejecting some ridiculous species within the genus &lt;i&gt;Homo&lt;/i&gt;, he divided &lt;i&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/i&gt; into four subspecies: in essence, European, African, indigenous American, and Asian. Europeans, to Linnaeus, were governed by laws, whereas Africans were governed by whim, Americans by customs, and Asians by opinions. Roberts notes that “apologists have attempted to absolve Linnaeus of racism,” but he insists that claiming that Europeans alone were governed by laws is a clear statement of superiority. He cannot forgive Linnaeus, who stood by these characterizations for the rest of his life. I do not know whether Roberts is engaging in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Presentism_(historical_analysis)&quot;&gt;presentism&lt;/a&gt;, but I suspect not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linnaeus occasionally defined species on the basis of scant evidence and sometimes published reviews of his own work using a pseudonym. Roberts accuses him of drawing “unmoored conclusions” in “an act of ignorance masquerading as savantry.” Buffon was the real thing; he would have been called a scientist, but the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/scientist&quot;&gt;first known use of the word&lt;/a&gt; was in 1834. Where Linnaeus required scant evidence, Buffon studied his “private menagerie” for years and concluded, in Roberts’s words, “The essence of species lay in reproduction, the ability of one generation to propagate another.” On the basis of what is essentially this definition, Buffon further concluded that there was only one human species, which “underwent diverse changes from the influence of the climate, food, mode of living, epidemical distempers, and the intermixture of individuals[.]” Charles Darwin, a century or so later, thought that Buffon’s theories were “laughably like mine.” Like Darwin, Buffon opposed slavery, and he did not care for the slave-owner Jefferson. Roberts does not discuss Linnaeus’s views on slavery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buffon ultimately published 35 volumes of his encyclopedia, &lt;i&gt;Histoire naturelle&lt;/i&gt;. According to the author, he outsold Rousseau, Voltaire, and Montesquieu, and his work continued in print for over 150 years. Roberts says it is the longest nonfiction work written by a single author and rivals encyclopedias written by many authors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides evolution, Buffon developed what Roberts calls “the first rough sketch of a working theory of reproduction,” which included an “internal matrix” that sort of resembles DNA. Where Linnaeus insisted on the fixity of species, Buffon studied fossil remains and concluded that some species had gone extinct and others had been born. Species, he thought, changed by adaptation to the environment, and later species were demarcated from their ancestors when they could no longer interbreed (cf. the modern &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution.berkeley.edu/biological-species-concept/&quot;&gt;biological species concept&lt;/a&gt;). He thought that related families may have a common ancestor and indeed that all life could be further traced to a yet earlier common ancestor. Buffon realized that these were dangerous thoughts in the mid-1700’s; he wrote to a friend, “One can slip ideas into a quarto volume which would cause a public outcry if they appeared in a pamphlet.” In consequence, he was very careful and penned a disclaimer any time he drew a conclusion that might offend the religious hierarchy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buffon also suggested that single-celled organisms may not all be animals or plants but rather “indeterminate species and in-between objects which we do not know where to place…” and suggested that living organisms might consist of building blocks now known as cells. On a less biological note, he opened an ironworks, which Roberts calls “a template for factories to come.” A gazebo that he had cast was the “first all-iron structure in Paris.” Its roof is a lattice shaped as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperboloid&quot;&gt;one-sheeted hyperboloid&lt;/a&gt; (a hyperboloid of revolution), which did not appear in architecture until the 20th century. According to Wikipedia, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buffon%27s_needle_problem&quot;&gt;Buffon’s needle&lt;/a&gt; was the first solved problem in geometric probability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buffon deduced that the earth was much older than a few thousand years and divided its history into seven “epochs.” Apart from not knowing the duration of any epoch, he got their chronology about right. (In fact, he used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.geolsoc.org.uk/Geoscientist/Archive/April-2018/Buffon-the-geologist&quot;&gt;cannonballs&lt;/a&gt; to estimate the rate of cooling of the earth and concluded that its age was around 75,000 years.) Roberts calls his work a deliberate provocation and an attack on the fixity of species. For his pains he was denounced by the Sorbonne and required to sign a retraction, which he promptly ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buffon speculated – &lt;i&gt;very&lt;/i&gt; carefully – as to whether nonhuman animals had souls, for which transgression apparently Madame Pompadour smacked him in the face with a fan. He recognized, nearly 300 years ago, that humans could “despoil and impoverish” the earth by out-producing its capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;History was kinder to Linnaeus than to Buffon. Buffon’s star began to fade during the French Revolution, when the Société de Linné took advantage of the turmoil to promote Linnaeus and minimize Buffon. By the 1860’s in England, Buffon’s &lt;i&gt;Natural History&lt;/i&gt; was sold in badly abridged, perhaps caricatured form alongside &lt;i&gt;Aesop’s Fables&lt;/i&gt;. Shaw remembers as a child hearing Buffon called “Buffoon” and says that within 10 years he was forgotten. Perhaps this book will succeed in &lt;strike&gt;reviving&lt;/strike&gt; enhancing his legacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I liked the writing very well and noticed only four editorial mistakes: seraphim for seraph, &lt;i&gt;Camillia sinsesis&lt;/i&gt; for &lt;i&gt;Camellia sinensis&lt;/i&gt;, counsel for consul, and Ernest Haeckel for Ernst Haeckel. Well, maybe one more: Rosalind Franklin arguably did not win a Nobel Prize because she had died before the prize was awarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgment. &lt;/strong&gt;Thanks to Ron Wittmann for discussing taxonomy and other topics with me. Deanna Young read a draft and offered several useful comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">The cover is kind of &quot;busy,&quot; but I shall try not to judge the book by its cover. The book is Every Living Thing, The Great and Deadly Race to Know All Life, by Jason Roberts. It is sort of a double biography of Carl Linnaeus (1707-1778) and Georges-Louis Leclerc, Comte de Buffon (1707-1788), but it continues to follow their legacies well beyond their lifetimes to the present. I cannot recommend it more highly. I do not know what impression Mr. Roberts intended, but if you thought Linnaeus was a young man on the make, something of a scoundrel who might say anything in the interests of self-promotion, you might not be too far from the truth. The hero of this book is not Linnaeus but rather his sometime rival, Buffon. But let us deal with Linnaeus first. Linnaeus obtained a phony doctor’s degree from what we would now call a diploma mill. He anointed 14 (or 17 of what he called his “apostles” (!), sent them on long journeys from which many never returned, and completely abandoned one who returned with no specimens. He has been criticized for not allowing his daughters their educations, to a degree, says Roberts, that was extreme even for the time (but he supported his daughter Elisabeth in her interest in botany. She wrote a paper devoted to what is now known as the Elizabeth Linnaeus phenomenon). Linnaeus also believed in the fixity of species, not to mention some very bizarre creatures, but in that he was probably not alone. Linnaeus developed a taxonomy that is largely in use today; that is a major accomplishment, to say the least. After defining and then apparently rejecting some ridiculous species within the genus Homo, he divided Homo sapiens into four subspecies: in essence, European, African, indigenous American, and Asian. Europeans, to Linnaeus, were governed by laws, whereas Africans were governed by whim, Americans by customs, and Asians by opinions. Roberts notes that “apologists have attempted to absolve Linnaeus of racism,” but he insists that claiming that Europeans alone were governed by laws is a clear statement of superiority. He cannot forgive Linnaeus, who stood by these characterizations for the rest of his life. I do not know whether Roberts is engaging in presentism, but I suspect not.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Butorides virescens</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/butorides-virescens.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Butorides virescens" /><published>2024-11-11T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-11-11T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/butorides-virescens</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/butorides-virescens.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Denelsbeck_Butorides_virescens.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Green heron&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Green_Heron/overview&quot;&gt;Butorides virescens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; green heron. Mr. Denelsbeck blogs at &lt;a href=&quot;https://wading-in.net/&quot;&gt;Wading-In Photography&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Al Denelsbeck. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Butorides virescens &amp;ndash; green heron. Mr. Denelsbeck blogs at Wading-In Photography. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dembski and Ewert wish upon a star</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/dembskiewert2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dembski and Ewert wish upon a star" /><published>2024-11-10T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-11-10T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/-dembskiewert2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/dembskiewert2.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;600px&quot; src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Six_Grandfathers.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Six grandfathers image]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;The mountain called &lt;em&gt;Six Grandfathers&lt;/em&gt; by the 
Lakota people before it was renamed Mount&lt;br /&gt; Rushmore. An image of Mount Rushmore adorns the cover of Dembski and 
  Ewert's book,&lt;br /&gt; as an example of a design inference we make. Does the Lakota name&lt;br /&gt; reflect 
a design inference? &lt;em&gt;Wikimedia, public domain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/dembskiewert1.html&quot;&gt;post of 12 June&lt;/a&gt;, I commented on the first part of William 
Dembski and Winston Ewert’s new book, the second edition of Dembski’s 
1998 book &lt;em&gt;The Design Inference: Eliminating Chance 
Through Small Probabilities&lt;/em&gt;.   I noted that to make the argument 
for a Design Inference they had set aside Dembski’s previous criterion 
of Complex Specified Information, and instead replaced it by 
Algorithmic Specified Complexity (ASC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a measure of the difference between the length of a bitstring and the length of a bitstring that describes it. 
It originates from the mathematical work on “randomness deficiciency”, where the bitstring is a binary number, and the smaller bitstring is a computer program that computes it.  In that field, numbers that are considered truly random are those generated by programs that are almost as long as the number.  A number that can be generated by a short program is not considered random.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dembski and Ewert intend to apply this to biology.  The longer number somehow specifies a phenotype (or maybe a 
genotype), while the shorter number “describes” it.  In my previous review, I had reached Chapter 7, “Evolutionary Biology”.  Here, let’s consider how they argue the ASC criterion can be applied to biological adaptations.  (Spoiler – we’re going to be disappointed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was full of expectations when I started reading Chapter 7.  I had a number of questions in mind, ones I have 
asked before in posts and comments about their ASC criterion for design inference (for example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/12/Is-Algorithmic-Specified-Complexity-Useless-for-Analyzing-Evolution.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Any-new-arguments.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/worst-of-2021.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What did the bitstring represent? A genotype?  A phenotype?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Was the “description” string a program for computing the larger string?  Was it perhaps some genetic encoding of developmental instructions?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the difference between the lengths of the two is large enough, this is supposed to be astronomically improbable.  Under what distribution?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the probability somehow able to take into account the possibility of natural selection building up such
large difference step by step?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 7 has a number of sections.  Let me describe briefly what each covers, and what it accomplishes.  I will summarize their arguments.  I will add comments of my own, in parentheses, or otherwise explicitly identified:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;insulating-evolution-against-small-probabilities-pages-321-326&quot;&gt;Insulating Evolution against Small Probabilities (pages 321-326)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dembski and Ewert describe the success and wide acceptance of their design inference in evolutionary biology.  They then say “And now back to the real world”.  The success and acceptance, they accept, has not happened in reality.  This is because evolutionary biologists have been resistant to accepting that evolution of biological systems involves 
probabilities that small.  The evolutionary biologists have done so by invoking mechanisms of cumulative selection.  As an example Dembski and Ewert describe Richard Dawkins’s teaching example of a simple form of simulated natural selection starting with a random 28-letter sequence of letters and spaces, and reaching the target phrase “METHINKS IT IS LIKE A WEASEL” in hundreds or thousands of steps, instead of the 10&lt;sup&gt;40&lt;/sup&gt; steps it would take if one simply drew new 28-letter sequences at random.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;variations-on-the-weasel-pages-326-330&quot;&gt;Variations on the WEASEL (pages 326-330)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evolutionary biologists are obsessed by the Weasel example (I would say it is creationists and advocates of Design that 
are actually the ones obsessed with it). “Perhaps design theorists should shift focus to the origin of life”.  (The infamous OTOOL diversion – Off To the Origin Of Life).  There cumulative selection cannot play a role, they argue.  Simulations like the Weasel are declared to be “suggestive but misleading, so removed from biological reality that they cannot decide the matter”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;resetting-darwinian-evolutions-bayesian-prior-pages-331-336&quot;&gt;Resetting Darwinian Evolution’s Bayesian Prior (pages 331-336)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering the choice between design and natural selection as a Bayesian Inference, it is important what prior probabilities one assigns these two hypotheses.  If one gives design a low enough prior probability, it cannot have any reasonably high posterior probability.  A design inference can be used to “sweep the field clear of all relevant chance hypotheses”. (Actually they could only do that if they could show that the probability of the data, given natural selection, was zero, but Demsbki and Ewert don’t quite mean that, they mean showing that the data is astronomically improbable).  Biologists argue that there may be many other “chance hypotheses”, but this is an argument by mere possibility as the biologists do not produce these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;who-is-arguing-from-ignorance-pages-337-339&quot;&gt;Who Is Arguing from Ignorance? (pages 337-339)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biologists are, since they essentially never produce the exact sequence of events needed to evolve these biological systems.  However, the biologists accuse the design theorists of arguing from ignorance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;john-stuart-mills-method-of-difference-pages-340-345&quot;&gt;John Stuart Mill’s Method of Difference (pages 340-345)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mill argued that if two situations differ in only one circumstance and a phenomenon occurs in one and not in the other, this circumstance is the effect, or cause.   Biologists such as Kenneth Miller say that all that is needed for natural selection to work is the presence of selection, replication, and mutation.  But these do not automatically lead to “complexity” or something “interesting”.  The evolution experiments of Sol Spiegelman and of Richard Lenski do not show those, but have genomes that rapidly decay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-challenge-of-multiple-simultaneous-mutations-pages-345-352&quot;&gt;The Challenge of Multiple Simultaneous Mutations (pages 345-352)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is basically a discussion of Michael Behe’s argument that major innovations require multiple mutations, each of which is individually disadvantageous, with an advantage only when they get together.  It is extremely improbable that these can be brought together by natural selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-to-make-of-bad-design-pages-353-to-368&quot;&gt;What to Make of Bad Design? (pages 353 to 368)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bad design arguments are not plausible for a number of reasons.  Quotes from “some naturalistic thinkers” who do not think there is actual design but are impressed with the design of the  cell.  These include James Shapiro.  Discussion of whether there is junk DNA, giving great credit to the 2012 (supposed) refutation of junk DNA by the ENCODE Consortium.  Dembski and Ewert cite an embarrassing quote by Richard Dawkins in 2012 accepting the ENCODE result and arguing that it is compatible with his views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;doing-the-calculation-pages-368-378&quot;&gt;Doing the Calculation (pages 368-378)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(At last, are we to be shown how?  Well, partly.)  Calculates the probability of a “biological system”, using protein folds as one example, invoking Douglas Axe’s experiments which that only one in 10&lt;sup&gt;-77&lt;/sup&gt; randomly constructed proteins would have enough of the proper structure and sequence 
to make a minimally functional β-lactamase enzyme.  Axe’s paper was in &lt;em&gt;Journal of Molecular Biology&lt;/em&gt;, volume 341, issue 5, page 1295 in 2004. The argument is based on the view that to get started evolving a β-lactamase enzyme one must have random assembly of such a protein, before natural selection can act. The example uses the protein sequence, with a 20-letter alphabet, as the string, equivalent to about a 648-bit string.  Dembski and 
Ewert do not try to quantitate the length of the “description” needed.  They acknowledge that evolutionary biologistss would argue that there might be other paths to the same functionality, without using these specific structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-breakdown-of-evolvability-pages-378-381&quot;&gt;The Breakdown of Evolvability (pages 378-381)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“whence the confidence that Darwinian evolution should allow untrammeled interconnectivity from any one living form to any other, whether by direct evolution or by indirect evolution from a common evolutionary precursor?”  They talk about protein alphabets, then uses a word game of changing a letter in a word, or deleting it, or adding a letter to change to another English word.  Argues that one cannot go from any word to any other this way.  Therefore although we have not proven that such interconnectedness in biological organisms cannot exist, we have shown it may not exist.  Therefore “there are indeed good reasons to think that a gradualist Darwinian form of evolution is very limited in what it can accomplish in biology, and that some features of biological systems not only resist Darwinian explanations but also invite design inferences”.  (This last part, the “some features” part, does not follow).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;where-to-look-for-small-probabilities-in-biology-pages-382-394&quot;&gt;Where to Look for Small Probabilities in Biology? (pages 382-394)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, the last section in Chapter 7, talks about Michael Behe’s arguments about Irreducible Complexity.  Lots of discussion of how the bacterial flagellum could or could not have arisen.  Evolutionary biologists never seem to come up with a detailed series of steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-have-dembski-and-ewert-accomplished&quot;&gt;What have Dembski and Ewert accomplished?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the questions I asked above, they have not answered most of them.   The one example that they give that involves a sequence of digital symbols 
asks about the probability of a particular protein sequence arising from random sequences of amino acids.  What they give is really not an Algorithmically 
Specified Complexity agument, but a much older argument.   Usually that argument takes the lengths of modern proteins as a necessary requirement for protein function, and does not take into account that many random protein sequences (and random RNA sequences) show a variety of weak enzymatic function.  And small changes in those sequences often lead to similar amounts of function.  It is therefore not impossible for evolution to follow steps uphill on a fitness surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difficulty with Dembski and Ewert’s definition of Algorithmically Specified Complexity is that when the quantity is large, it means that there is a long sequence (of something) which is “described” by a short sequence.  And there is simply no point in their argument that explains why (a) natural selection cannot achieve that, step by step, or (b) why achieving that is needed to result in any adaptation.  The matter is left without discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a large difference between the new argument and the previous specified complexity arguments.  As I noted in the first section of this review (12 June), the new concept is not a Functional Information argument.  The “probability” is not the probability that a random sequence has this much &lt;em&gt;or more&lt;/em&gt; of the desired trait.  It is just the probability of this sequence.  There is simply no discussion of how to compute a tail probability in some relevant distribution.  Or even in some nonrelevant distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are left with the questions I asked, and re-asked, above.  How does this argument work?  What are the relevant distributions?  What is the “sequence”?  How does the “description” relate to some relevant probability?  Is it a tail probability under some relevant null distribution?  Is it a probability that ordinary evolutionary processes could achieve something?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-burden-of-proof&quot;&gt;A burden of proof&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By not explaining how their arguments work, in spite of 400+ pages of explanation, Dembski and Ewert are engaged in wish-fulfillment.  They have “wished upon a star”.  But it is not true that, as the song claims, that if you do, “your dreams come true”.  Dembski and Ewert do not fill in the blanks, not even close.  They do go off sideways into irreducible complexity arguments, and they do repeatedly claim that evolutionary biologists argue that natural selection will always succeed in meeting challenges.  Ask the passenger pigeon about that, or the Great Auk, or the Dodo, or the Carolina Paroquet, or the mammoth.  Or the trilobites, or the seed ferns. or the ammonites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is still possible for them to answer my objections by filling in the blanks.  Saying that this is unfair, because biologists have not outlined every last step of the evolution of a complicated biological adaptation is no excuse.   I’ll be happy to hear from them how their arguments actually work.  We’re waiting …&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">The mountain called Six Grandfathers by the Lakota people before it was renamed Mount Rushmore. An image of Mount Rushmore adorns the cover of Dembski and Ewert's book, as an example of a design inference we make. Does the Lakota name reflect a design inference? Wikimedia, public domain &amp;nbsp; In my post of 12 June, I commented on the first part of William Dembski and Winston Ewert’s new book, the second edition of Dembski’s 1998 book The Design Inference: Eliminating Chance Through Small Probabilities. I noted that to make the argument for a Design Inference they had set aside Dembski’s previous criterion of Complex Specified Information, and instead replaced it by Algorithmic Specified Complexity (ASC). This is a measure of the difference between the length of a bitstring and the length of a bitstring that describes it. It originates from the mathematical work on “randomness deficiciency”, where the bitstring is a binary number, and the smaller bitstring is a computer program that computes it. In that field, numbers that are considered truly random are those generated by programs that are almost as long as the number. A number that can be generated by a short program is not considered random. Dembski and Ewert intend to apply this to biology. The longer number somehow specifies a phenotype (or maybe a genotype), while the shorter number “describes” it. In my previous review, I had reached Chapter 7, “Evolutionary Biology”. Here, let’s consider how they argue the ASC criterion can be applied to biological adaptations. (Spoiler – we’re going to be disappointed).</summary></entry></feed>