<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-14T14:02:40-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Ed Brayton Passed Away</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/Brayton.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ed Brayton Passed Away" /><published>2020-08-13T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-13T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/Brayton</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/Brayton.html">&lt;p&gt;Ed Brayton was an amazing man and one of the founders of Pandasthumb. I’m saddened to report that after a long battle with his health, he died last night. It happened a few days after &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patheos.com/blogs/dispatches/2020/08/10/saying-goodbye-for-the-last-time/&quot;&gt;he decided to enter hospice care&lt;/a&gt;. He died on his own terms and as peacefully as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all grateful to have known him and been influenced by him. His voice will be missed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reed A. Cartwright</name></author><summary type="html">Ed Brayton was an amazing man and one of the founders of Pandasthumb. I’m saddened to report that after a long battle with his health, he died last night. It happened a few days after he decided to enter hospice care. He died on his own terms and as peacefully as possible. We are all grateful to have known him and been influenced by him. His voice will be missed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">We are almost back</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/we-are-almost-back.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We are almost back" /><published>2020-08-07T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-07T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/we-are-almost-back</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/we-are-almost-back.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[Added 14th of August:  comments now work correctly, so Panda’s Thumb is now back “on the air” as of the 11th.  The outage was 56 days, or 8 weeks.]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

Panda's Thumb has been down since the 16th of June, owing to a hardware failure in its server machine.
Reed has been working to fix that, and I have been adapting the site to be served by Github Pages.  This
has been possible since it was already using a locally-served version of Github Pages since 2016,
in its previous configuration.
&lt;p&gt;

Currently most features of PT work.  The comments do not appear at the end of articles, even though
the count of the number of comments appears for each article on the front page of the site, and the
Recent Comments list appears correctly.  Current and archived posts are available.
We hope to get comments working very soon.  In the meantime,
please be patient, and watch this space.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">[Added 14th of August: comments now work correctly, so Panda’s Thumb is now back “on the air” as of the 11th. The outage was 56 days, or 8 weeks.] Panda's Thumb has been down since the 16th of June, owing to a hardware failure in its server machine. Reed has been working to fix that, and I have been adapting the site to be served by Github Pages. This has been possible since it was already using a locally-served version of Github Pages since 2016, in its previous configuration. Currently most features of PT work. The comments do not appear at the end of articles, even though the count of the number of comments appears for each article on the front page of the site, and the Recent Comments list appears correctly. Current and archived posts are available. We hope to get comments working very soon. In the meantime, please be patient, and watch this space.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reason for optimism in the evolution wars</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/reason-for-optimism-evolution-wars.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reason for optimism in the evolution wars" /><published>2020-06-13T12:13:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-13T12:13:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/reason-for-optimism-evolution-wars</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/reason-for-optimism-evolution-wars.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Plutzer_2020_Graph.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Graph&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&quot;Teachers classified by the scientific accuracy of the messages reportedly conveyed to students, 2007 and 2019.&quot; Note, in particular, that the number of teachers who teach evolution as settled science has increased from around 50 to nearly 70&amp;nbsp;%, whereas the number who give mixed messages or outright teach creationism has decreased. &lt;small&gt;Plutzer, E., Branch, G. &amp;amp; Reid, A. Teaching evolution in U.S. public schools: a continuing challenge. &lt;i&gt;Evo Edu Outreach&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;13&lt;/strong&gt;, 14 (2020). https://doi.org/10.1186/s12052-020-00126-8. Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0).&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of this article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution-outreach.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12052-020-00126-8&quot;&gt;Teaching evolution in U.S. public schools: a continuing challenge&lt;/a&gt;, seems to me a little sterile and possibly unduly pessimistic. The main conclusions of the article are given in the figure: The fraction of teachers who teach evolution has increased from 50 to nearly 70 % in the 12 years since an &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.0060124&quot;&gt;earlier survey&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, the fraction who teach creationism has fallen, and the fraction who give “mixed messages” has fallen precipitously, from the low 20’s to the low teens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among other conclusions, the authors credit the Next Generation Science Standards for the improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article is too detailed to regurgitate here, but it is easy to read (and free!). The authors, for example, compare responses from teachers in states that have adopted the NGSS or a similar &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nap.edu/catalog/13165/a-framework-for-k-12-science-education-practices-crosscutting-concepts&quot;&gt;Framework&lt;/a&gt; with teachers in the remaining states before crediting NGSS with the improvements. They looked at other data to conclude that the improvements were not the result of new teachers being hired after &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kitzmiller_v._Dover_Area_School_District&quot;&gt;Kitzmiller&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; and NGSS. Rather, older teachers, on the job before &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller&lt;/i&gt;, took advantage of professional-development courses and improved their teaching of evolution and increased the time they devoted to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the fraction of teachers who “strongly disagreed” with the statement, “I emphasize that intelligent design is a valid, scientific alternative to Darwinian explanations for the origin of species,” increased from 20 to 43 % in the 12 years between the polls. Likewise, the fraction who strongly disagreed with the statement, “I emphasize that many reputable scientists view creationism or intelligent design as valid alternatives to Darwinian theory,” increased from 13 to 20 %. Only 3 % “strongly agreed” with the either statement, a number that remained constant across the 12 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I thought it was a pretty good decade or so.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">&quot;Teachers classified by the scientific accuracy of the messages reportedly conveyed to students, 2007 and 2019.&quot; Note, in particular, that the number of teachers who teach evolution as settled science has increased from around 50 to nearly 70&amp;nbsp;%, whereas the number who give mixed messages or outright teach creationism has decreased. Plutzer, E., Branch, G. &amp;amp; Reid, A. Teaching evolution in U.S. public schools: a continuing challenge. Evo Edu Outreach 13, 14 (2020). https://doi.org/10.1186/s12052-020-00126-8. Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0). The title of this article, Teaching evolution in U.S. public schools: a continuing challenge, seems to me a little sterile and possibly unduly pessimistic. The main conclusions of the article are given in the figure: The fraction of teachers who teach evolution has increased from 50 to nearly 70 % in the 12 years since an earlier survey. Additionally, the fraction who teach creationism has fallen, and the fraction who give “mixed messages” has fallen precipitously, from the low 20’s to the low teens. Among other conclusions, the authors credit the Next Generation Science Standards for the improvement.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ondatra zibethicus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/Ondatra-zibethicus_1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ondatra zibethicus" /><published>2020-06-08T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-08T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/Ondatra-zibethicus_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/Ondatra-zibethicus_1.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/IMG_3570_Muskrat_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Muskrat&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muskrat&quot;&gt;Ondatra zibethicus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; muskrat, munching what I think is a broad-leaved cattail, Elmer's Two-Mile Creek, Boulder, Colorado, May, 2020. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;… And please don’t forget the photography contest!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Ondatra zibethicus &amp;ndash; muskrat, munching what I think is a broad-leaved cattail, Elmer's Two-Mile Creek, Boulder, Colorado, May, 2020. … And please don’t forget the photography contest!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ken Ham, AIG statement opposing racism</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/ken-ham-aig-statement-racism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ken Ham, AIG statement opposing racism" /><published>2020-06-06T10:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-06T10:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/ken-ham-aig-statement-racism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/ken-ham-aig-statement-racism.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Ham_Racism_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other day I received an e-mail from AIG, advertising a number of books that appear to be about racism, including, in particular, &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/store/product/biblical-answer-racism&quot;&gt;The Biblical Answer to Racism&lt;/a&gt;, by Ken Ham. The book was offered to me for $0.49, which was waived if I inserted a certain code. I found that I already had an account with AIG, so “buying” the book was trivial, and it came essentially instantaneously as a pdf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biblical answer to racism, I am happy to report, is that there is no such thing as race. As Mr. Ham writes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All&lt;/em&gt; human beings in the world today, however, are classified as &lt;em&gt;Homo sapiens sapiens&lt;/em&gt;. Scientists today admit that, biologically, there really is only one race of humans. For instance, a scientist at the [American Association for the?] Advancement of Science Convention in Atlanta stated, “Race is a social construct derived mainly from perceptions conditioned by events of recorded history, and it has no basic biological reality.” This person went on to say, “Curiously enough, the idea comes very close to being of American manufacture.” [Italics in original.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, after the mandatory attack on evolution, quoting Stephen Jay Gould out of context, and claiming that &lt;em&gt;On the Origin of Species&lt;/em&gt; is an inherently racist document, because many people who followed it were racists. The argument, which is kind of irrelevant, is close to the genetic fallacy, but we need not get into that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Biblical Answer to Racism&lt;/em&gt; is essentially a pamphlet, 39 pages long. It has a fairly clear and I assume correct description of how different varieties of melanin make us come in different shades. (I had no idea that blue eyes were the result of light scattering rather than pigment, which perhaps accounts for why my eyes appear as different hues in different environments.) It argues that we should not use the term &lt;em&gt;race&lt;/em&gt; at all and opts instead for &lt;em&gt;people group&lt;/em&gt;, perhaps because &lt;em&gt;ethnic group&lt;/em&gt; has already been taken. Mr. Ham also takes pains to debunk the argument that his biblical namesake, Ham, the putative ancestor of the black people groups, was cursed (Gen. 9:18-27) – an argument that has been used in the United States to justify slavery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The dispersion at Babel” and its consequences are a significant fraction of the pamphlet. Mr. Ham “explains” that after the dispersion at Babel, people groups, um, evolved different features, such as skin color. Skin color, however, is not to be confused with race, and he has noted earlier that differences &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; people groups greatly exceed differences &lt;em&gt;among&lt;/em&gt; people groups. We are, after all, all descended from Adam. Therefore, so-called interracial marriage is not prohibited. Intermarriage between Christians and non-Christians, however, is another matter; non-Christians are “dead in trespasses and sin” (I have no idea what that means, but it does not sound complimentary).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Ham’s bottom line or lines seem to be the quotation above and the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;1. There is no biblical justification for claiming that people from different so-called races (best described as people groups) should not marry.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

2. The biblical basis for marriage makes it clear that a Christian should marry only a Christian. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When Christians legalistically impose nonbiblical ideas, such as no interracial marriage, onto their culture, they are helping to perpetuate prejudices that have often arisen from evolutionary influences. If we are really honest, in countries like America, the main reason for Christians being against interracial marriage is, in most instances, really because of skin color.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

The church could greatly relieve the tensions over racism (particularly in countries like America), if only the leaders would teach biblical truths about our shared ancestry ....&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Ham is not free of prejudice against non-Christians. Nevertheless, I have to give him a lot of credit for producing this document, because I have a suspicion that a great many of his right-wing, evangelical Christian followers may be inherently racists (birthers, for example), and Mr. Ham has done us all a great service by opposing racism in terms that they can perhaps appreciate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">The other day I received an e-mail from AIG, advertising a number of books that appear to be about racism, including, in particular, The Biblical Answer to Racism, by Ken Ham. The book was offered to me for $0.49, which was waived if I inserted a certain code. I found that I already had an account with AIG, so “buying” the book was trivial, and it came essentially instantaneously as a pdf. The biblical answer to racism, I am happy to report, is that there is no such thing as race. As Mr. Ham writes, All human beings in the world today, however, are classified as Homo sapiens sapiens. Scientists today admit that, biologically, there really is only one race of humans. For instance, a scientist at the [American Association for the?] Advancement of Science Convention in Atlanta stated, “Race is a social construct derived mainly from perceptions conditioned by events of recorded history, and it has no basic biological reality.” This person went on to say, “Curiously enough, the idea comes very close to being of American manufacture.” [Italics in original.] This, after the mandatory attack on evolution, quoting Stephen Jay Gould out of context, and claiming that On the Origin of Species is an inherently racist document, because many people who followed it were racists. The argument, which is kind of irrelevant, is close to the genetic fallacy, but we need not get into that.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest XII</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/photography-contest-xii.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest XII" /><published>2020-06-05T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-05T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/photography-contest-xii</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/photography-contest-xii.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/IMG_3500_Zeiss_Camera_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Zeiss Ikon 35-mm folding camera&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Zeiss Ikon 35-mm folding camera. Camera courtesy of Angie Spiegel.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 11th annual photography contest begins now, Friday, June 5, at 12:00 p.m., MDT (MDT = UTC(GMT) – 6 h). Entries will be accepted between now and Friday, June 19, at 12:00 p.m., MDT. The rules are precisely the same as &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/06/photography-contest-xi.html&quot;&gt;last year’s&lt;/a&gt;, except, obviously, that the dates have been updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We encourage entries in a single, general category, which includes pictures of just about anything of scientific interest: any object of experimentation or observation, from single-celled organisms, through nematodes, fruit flies, rats, chimpanzees, and college sophomores to volcanoes, stars, and galaxies. In order not to omit theoreticians, we will consider computer-generated pictures and also photographs of equipment. Photomicrographs and electron micrographs are likewise welcomed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winner and the runner-up will receive a copy of Sahotra Sarkar’s &lt;i&gt;Doubting Darwin?&lt;/i&gt; or a copy of Elliott Sober’s &lt;i&gt;Did Darwin Write the Origin Backwards?&lt;/i&gt;, both generously donated by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.com/&quot;&gt;National Center for Science Education&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we get enough entries, consistently with Rules 11 and 12, we may add categories and award additional prizes, presuming, of course, that we can find more prizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rules of the contest are simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will consider any photograph that displays scientific interest – biological, paleontological, geological, or astronomical, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Submit photographs in JPEG format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Reduce photographs to an information content of 600 pixels horizontally. If creationists require a definition of information, they may apply in writing to the management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Photographs may be enhanced but may not be montages. High dynamic range photographs are, however, accepted. Submit a maximum of 3 photographs (or 5 photographs per family) to thousandwords@pandasthumb.org.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Submit the photographs as attachments to an e-mail (not embedded in the body of the e-mail). The subject line to the e-mail must have the form YourLastName_PhotographyContest. The filenames for the photographs must have the form YourLastName_Descriptor as, for example, Young_Oxytropis_sericea or Young_Table_Mountain, as appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In your e-mail, identify the subject of the photograph: common and biological name, mineral type, or geological formation, for example. Provide a link that will allow a reader to learn more about the subject. You may add descriptive text in the body of the e-mail if you like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Depending on the number of photographs submitted, we may post the best submissions and ask our readers to vote for the best photograph. Likewise, we may establish several categories with separate entries and separate ballots. In particular, students 16 and under should so identify themselves; if we receive enough entries, we will establish a student category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By submitting a photograph, you stipulate that you are the owner of the copyright and grant The Panda’s Thumb a nonexclusive license to publish the photograph on its blog. The photograph will be subject to a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-No Derivatives license.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Regular contributors to The Panda’s Thumb are not eligible to enter the contest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The decision of the judges is irrevocable. The judges remain irrepressibly and irreducibly irascible, irreverent, and irredeemable, irregardless and irrespective, but not, we hope, irrational or irritable. We hope for a veritable irruption of entries this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Even though we are getting fairly good at running contests, we reserve the right to change any of the rules, or add or subtract rules at any time at our discretion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will choose a number of finalists and open voting for the winner at 12:00 p.m., Monday, June 22. Voting will end Monday, June 29, &lt;i&gt;at 9:00 a.m.&lt;/i&gt;, and the winner will be announced at 12:00. Note, only 1 week for voting this year.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Zeiss Ikon 35-mm folding camera. Camera courtesy of Angie Spiegel. The 11th annual photography contest begins now, Friday, June 5, at 12:00 p.m., MDT (MDT = UTC(GMT) – 6 h). Entries will be accepted between now and Friday, June 19, at 12:00 p.m., MDT. The rules are precisely the same as last year’s, except, obviously, that the dates have been updated. We encourage entries in a single, general category, which includes pictures of just about anything of scientific interest: any object of experimentation or observation, from single-celled organisms, through nematodes, fruit flies, rats, chimpanzees, and college sophomores to volcanoes, stars, and galaxies. In order not to omit theoreticians, we will consider computer-generated pictures and also photographs of equipment. Photomicrographs and electron micrographs are likewise welcomed. The winner and the runner-up will receive a copy of Sahotra Sarkar’s Doubting Darwin? or a copy of Elliott Sober’s Did Darwin Write the Origin Backwards?, both generously donated by the National Center for Science Education.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is Teaching Natural Selection a “Mass-Mind Tool of Financial Interests”?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/mazur-khan-academy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Teaching Natural Selection a “Mass-Mind Tool of Financial Interests”?" /><published>2020-06-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/mazur-khan-academy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/mazur-khan-academy.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/butterflies.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Picture credit, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.khanacademy.org/science/biology/her/evolution-and-natural-selection/a/darwin-evolution-natural-selection&quot;&gt;Khan Academy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a look at this article from the Khan Academy, in particular the section entitled Natural Selection:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.khanacademy.org/science/biology/her/evolution-and-natural-selection/a/darwin-evolution-natural-selection&quot;&gt;Darwin, evolution, &amp;amp; natural selection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think?  Is it a reasonably accurate and informative, if perhaps a bit bland and prosaic, summary of some of the key elements of the theory of evolution, suitable for the average high school student?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if someone was to tell you that it is, instead, a “mass-mind tool of financial interests”, designed to indoctrinate unwitting students into accepting an outdated concept that is no longer accepted by modern science?  That is the view of Suzan Mazur, who has written a scathing response to this seemingly benign article on  &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://oscillations.net/2020/05/23/sal-khan-end-mass-mind-teaching-of-darwinian-natural-selection/&quot;&gt;her blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mazur, for those not familiar with her (which I suspect will be most of you) is a freelance writer who mostly writes about science.  In the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sandwalk.blogspot.com/2016/12/suzan-mazur-doesnt-like-carl-zimmer.html&quot;&gt;opinions of some&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; however, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2016/12/06/susan-mazur-vs-carl-zimmer-really/&quot;&gt;she is not very good at this&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  Her main stock in trade is arguing that the theory of evolution is a failed idea that needs to be replaced by a new scientific paradigm.  As a result of this, she has a tendency to pump up and proselytize for the claims of creationists and other assorted and sundry crackpots.  Though, as we shall see, there are times where she will also misunderstand and/or misrepresent the views of legitimately informed scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As best as I can tell from this rather brief missive, Mazur is very concerned that Khan Academy is a large and profitable business and that many of the people involved in running the organization come from a business background.  She seems to believe that the website’s mention of natural selection is part of some larger, corporatist agenda, though exactly what that agenda might be is not entirely clear from this article alone.  Regardless, her claim is based on the premise that natural selection is no longer viable as a scientific idea.  As she writes: “Natural selection is a metaphor that was decommissioned at the end of the 20th century. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huffpost.com/entry/eugene-koonin-the-new-evo_b_14597840&quot;&gt;‘No one in the mainstream scientific community now takes selection literally.’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That hyperlink is in the original blog post, and if you click on it you will be taken to an interview Mazur did with computational biologist &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://irp.nih.gov/pi/eugene-koonin&quot;&gt;Eugene Koonin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  It’s an interesting and revealing read, and not only because Koonin gives lucid explanations of complex concepts in evolutionary biology.  It seems to me that Mazur is trying to goad Koonin into making some comment that will support her anti-evolutionary  agenda, but Koonin isn’t biting.  Here is the passage from which that quote is taken:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Darwin did not mean natural selection to be taken literally. But we have to be, I guess, a little more specific about what it means to take natural selection or any kind of selection literally. It means, one would assume, the existence of a selecting agent. Perhaps making all these parallels between natural selection and artificial selection, the way Darwin does in his book, could be somewhat dangerous because in artificial selection there is someone who is selecting, even if unconsciously. In that respect, the evolutionary process is very different in nature where nothing is there to actually select. Darwin certainly realized this and wrote more precisely of “survival of the fittest.” In modern evolutionary biology, it is sometimes “random survival” but the key point remains the same: organisms survive and leave progeny differentially. I think it is quite alright to denote some forms of differential survival selection, metaphorically. And there is no confusion here, within mainstream thinking. No one in the mainstream scientific community now takes selection literally.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t see how that can be honestly construed, in any way, as Koonin saying that the concept of natural selection no longer applies in evolutionary biology.  In fact, I think the phrase “organisms survive and leave progeny differentially” would serve as a concise summary of the Khan Academy’s discussion of natural selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So perhaps that gives some idea of why Mazur may not be much taken seriously as a science writer by knowledgeable scientists.  However, it probably will not come as a surprise that one place where she &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; taken seriously is within the Intelligent Design Creationist community.  As it happens, the Discovery Institute’s website Uncommon Descent ran a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/evolution/asked-at-oscillations-why-is-the-khan-academy-so-stuck-on-natural-selection-in-evolution/&quot;&gt;breathlessly enthusiastic response to Mazur’s blog post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  And while I am not at all certain what, if any, ideological bias drive Mazur’s antipathy to evolution, I have no such doubts regarding the fact that the DI is motivated by its conservative, fundamentalist religious agenda.  Which makes this comment in the UD article all the more curious:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Here’s a thought: The problem with natural selection (survival of the fittest) as a concept is that it inevitably leads to notions of superiority/inferiority, which come to dominate thinking about evolution. That’s probably the main reason that evolution got mixed up with racism.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We needn’t spend much time pointing out the several fallacies committed here.  Suffice it to say that even if were true that acceptance of natural selection made one more likely to be racist, that does not mean natural selection is false as a scientific idea.  And the DI’s assertion requires that they ignore the well-documented role in promoting racist ideology played by &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/01/arts/from-noah-s-curse-to-slavery-s-rationale.html&quot;&gt;creationist ideas such as belief in the story of Noah’s Ark&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  What I find most interesting about this UD post, apart from the odd dismissal of quantum mechanics, is the fact that, while the DI does not shy away from weighing in on political and social issues, it does not generally take any interest in social justice issues such as racism and equality.  Almost the only time the topic is brought up is when it can be wielded as a Whiffle Bat to try inflict some damage to the reputation of Charles Darwin.  That is to say, it is simply a cynical ploy to exploit anti-racist sentiment to bolster the creationist cause.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Faizal Ali</name></author><summary type="html">Picture credit, Khan Academy. Have a look at this article from the Khan Academy, in particular the section entitled Natural Selection: Darwin, evolution, &amp;amp; natural selection. What do you think? Is it a reasonably accurate and informative, if perhaps a bit bland and prosaic, summary of some of the key elements of the theory of evolution, suitable for the average high school student? What if someone was to tell you that it is, instead, a “mass-mind tool of financial interests”, designed to indoctrinate unwitting students into accepting an outdated concept that is no longer accepted by modern science? That is the view of Suzan Mazur, who has written a scathing response to this seemingly benign article on her blog.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest XII</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/photography-contest-xii-announcement.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest XII" /><published>2020-06-01T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-01T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/photography-contest-xii-announcement</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/photography-contest-xii-announcement.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/IMG_3500_Zeiss_Camera_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Zeiss Ikon 35-mm folding camera&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Zeiss Ikon 35-mm folding camera, courtesy of Angie Spiegel.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since many of us are estivating on account of the coronavirus, we thought we would run our twelfth (!) annual photography contest just a little early this year. Entries will be accepted between June 5 and June 19, which gives you 2 weekends to polish your lenses or search your archives and perfect your digital techniques. The rules will be the same as &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/06/photography-contest-xi.html&quot;&gt;last year’s&lt;/a&gt;, except, obviously, that the dates will change. We will post the formal announcement at noon, MDT, June 5, and begin accepting entries immediately thereafter. We will choose a number of finalists and open voting for the winner at noon, June 22.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Zeiss Ikon 35-mm folding camera, courtesy of Angie Spiegel. Since many of us are estivating on account of the coronavirus, we thought we would run our twelfth (!) annual photography contest just a little early this year. Entries will be accepted between June 5 and June 19, which gives you 2 weekends to polish your lenses or search your archives and perfect your digital techniques. The rules will be the same as last year’s, except, obviously, that the dates will change. We will post the formal announcement at noon, MDT, June 5, and begin accepting entries immediately thereafter. We will choose a number of finalists and open voting for the winner at noon, June 22.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ardea herodias – Ardea alba</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/05/ardea_herodias-ardea_alba.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ardea herodias – Ardea alba" /><published>2020-05-25T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-05-25T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/05/ardea_herodias-ardea_alba</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/05/ardea_herodias-ardea_alba.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Paul Burnett&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Burnett.Heron.Egret.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Heron and egret&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A great blue heron (&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_blue_heron&quot;&gt;Ardea herodias&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;) and a great egret (&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_egret&quot;&gt;Ardea alba&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;)
studiously ignoring each other. San Francisco Bay, off Crown Beach, Alameda, California.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Paul Burnett. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. A great blue heron (Ardea herodias) and a great egret (Ardea alba) studiously ignoring each other. San Francisco Bay, off Crown Beach, Alameda, California.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Francis Collins wins 2020 Templeton Prize</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/05/francis-collins-wins-templeton.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Francis Collins wins 2020 Templeton Prize" /><published>2020-05-20T11:46:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-05-20T11:46:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/05/francis-collins-wins-templeton</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/05/francis-collins-wins-templeton.html">&lt;p&gt;I want to congratulate &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Collins&quot;&gt;Francis Collins&lt;/a&gt; for having just &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.templetonprize.org/laureate/francis-collins-2020-templeton-prize/&quot;&gt;won the 2020 Templeton Prize&lt;/a&gt;. In Templeton’s words,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Francis Collins is the Director of the National Institutes of Health and led the Human Genome Project to its successful completion in 2003. Throughout his career, he has advocated for the integration of faith and reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In his scientific leadership, public speaking, and popular writing, including his bestselling 2006 book, The Language of God, Collins has demonstrated how religious faith can motivate and inspire rigorous scientific research. He endeavors to encourage religious communities to embrace the latest discoveries of genetics and the biomedical sciences as insights to enrich and enlarge their faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2009/07/francis-collins-3.html&quot;&gt;reviewed his book&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Language-God-Scientist-Presents-Evidence/dp/0743286391&quot;&gt;The Language of God&lt;/a&gt;: A Scientist Presents Evidence for Belief&lt;/em&gt;, I confess I found him “credulous.” His &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.templetonprize.org/laureate-sub/prepared-statement-by-francis-s-collins-2020-templeton-prize-laureate/&quot;&gt;Statement&lt;/a&gt; for the Templeton Foundation strikes me as being no less credulous. Nevertheless, I find it laudable that he manages to keep his religion and his science separate, and more importantly encourages people to accept the findings of modern science and rejects all forms of creationism. Probably no one deserves a Templeton Prize more, and I was frankly somewhat surprised when I recognized that he had not won it long ago.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I want to congratulate Francis Collins for having just won the 2020 Templeton Prize. In Templeton’s words, Francis Collins is the Director of the National Institutes of Health and led the Human Genome Project to its successful completion in 2003. Throughout his career, he has advocated for the integration of faith and reason. In his scientific leadership, public speaking, and popular writing, including his bestselling 2006 book, The Language of God, Collins has demonstrated how religious faith can motivate and inspire rigorous scientific research. He endeavors to encourage religious communities to embrace the latest discoveries of genetics and the biomedical sciences as insights to enrich and enlarge their faith. When I reviewed his book, The Language of God: A Scientist Presents Evidence for Belief, I confess I found him “credulous.” His Statement for the Templeton Foundation strikes me as being no less credulous. Nevertheless, I find it laudable that he manages to keep his religion and his science separate, and more importantly encourages people to accept the findings of modern science and rejects all forms of creationism. Probably no one deserves a Templeton Prize more, and I was frankly somewhat surprised when I recognized that he had not won it long ago.</summary></entry></feed>