<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-05-01T17:34:26-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">The Scientific Attitude: book review</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/scientific-attitude.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Scientific Attitude: book review" /><published>2022-04-29T11:10:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-04-29T11:10:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/scientific-attitude</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/scientific-attitude.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/McIntyre_Cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://leemcIntyrebooks.com/books/the-scientific-attitude/&quot;&gt;Book cover&lt;/a&gt;. The fourth monkey is known as &quot;Have No Fun,&quot; but it is a misnomer: science can be great fun, especially if it involves optical instrumentation.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chance works in mysterious ways. Shortly after I saw the philosopher Lee McIntyre discussing &lt;a href=&quot;https://centerforinquiry.org/video/how-to-talk-to-a-science-denier/&quot;&gt;How to talk to a science denier&lt;/a&gt; on the Center for Inquiry website, I ran across his splendid little book &lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/scientific-attitude&quot;&gt;The Scientific Attitude: Defending Science from Denial, Fraud, and Pseudoscience&lt;/a&gt;. Naturally, I snapped it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scientific attitude is sort of a technical term to McIntyre. He is not interested in demarcating science from non-science, nor in delineating a scientific method; rather, he considers the scientific attitude necessary for science (not that it is limited to scientists). Specifically, McIntyre writes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scientific attitude can be summed up in a commitment to two principles:&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;(1) We care about empirical evidence. &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;(2) We are willing to change our theories in light of new evidence. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you think that these principles may be “too vague and unrigorous to be helpful,” McIntyre discusses “what it means &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; to care about evidence”: those who do not care about evidence are dogmatic and maintain their beliefs even in defiance of the evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings us to Sir Karl Popper. According to the Introduction, it was Popper who made McIntyre decide to become a philosopher of science. I had known of Popper beforehand, but I was somewhat taken by Popper after I read &lt;i&gt;Conjectures and Refutations: The Growth of Scientific Knowledge&lt;/i&gt;* around 25 years ago. Popper was mistaken if he thought that scientists actively attempt to disprove their own theories experimentally. More likely, we try to confirm our theories. On the other hand, in the face of an apparent disconfirmation, we are willing to discard our theories or at least revise them. We may develop an &lt;i&gt;ad hoc&lt;/i&gt; (auxiliary) hypothesis in order to preserve our theory – but it is not enough to merely state an &lt;i&gt;ad hoc&lt;/i&gt; hypothesis, as many pseudoscientists seem to think; the &lt;i&gt;ad hoc&lt;/i&gt; hypothesis, needless to say, must itself be disprovable (testable, falsifiable).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popper himself notes that some “genuinely testable [falsifiable] theories,” even when found to be false, may be propped up by their “admirers,” who will introduce an &lt;i&gt;ad hoc&lt;/i&gt; hypothesis or otherwise reinterpret their theory in such a way that it cannot be refuted. In other words, judgement is called for, and you have to know when to discard a theory and when to patch it up. If you lack judgement, you lack the scientific attitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you decide whether you have the scientific attitude? You do not just cherry-pick facts but rather&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;act in accordance with a well-vetted set of practices that have been sanctioned by the scientific community because they have historically led to well-justified beliefs&lt;/i&gt; [italics in original]. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to McIntyre’s prescription, Ptolemaic astronomy (epicycles) was science. Phlogiston theory was science. Alchemy was science. Even though these theories were wrong science, they were science, in part because they were discarded and replaced when they were found to be wrong. Astrology, creationism, flat-earth theory are not science because their “admirers” try to prop them up with unprovable or unfalsifiable rationalizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McIntyre goes on to discuss the case of Ignaz Semmelweis, a physician who in the mid-1800’s employed careful observation and experimentation, and deduced that the cause of childbed fever (puerperal fever) was caused by what we would today call insufficient hygiene. Semmelweis had the scientific attitude, but, alas, no one else did, and Semmelweis died a failure. In his case, the “well-vetted set of practices that have been sanctioned by the scientific community” were unfortunately wrong, and it was decades before they were set right, with who knows how many lost lives. Stanley Pons and Martin Fleischmann, the “codiscoverers” of cold fusion, did not have the scientific attitude, and neither did a lot of other people, but eventually their “discovery” was falsified and laid to rest by those who did. McIntyre cites observations by Popper and Einstein to the effect that a critical attitude needs to precede the concept of falsifiability in the sense that, if you do not have a critical attitude, you will not seek to falsify your own theories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will not go into detail, but McIntyre mostly rejects the social constructivist model and insists that evidence is required for a paradigm shift. Science, to my mind, ought to have a privileged position when it comes to questions of fact because its “fads” (and it has fads) may be chosen to some extent by preference, but their direction is generally dictated by evidence, not belief or ideology. Thomas Kuhn was correct about paradigm shifts, but paradigms in science are hard to shift and, indeed, shift only when the evidence warrants a shift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not a philosopher (though a philosopher of science once called me a naïve falsificationist). I will not discuss the portions of the book that worry about demarcation theory, the social sciences, and so on, though I thought that McIntyre might have been just a wee bit supercilious in discussing how many of the social sciences were merely aspiring to be sciences. At least one of his case studies, though, was appalling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McIntyre establishes (or perhaps defines) that fraud has to be deliberate: fabrication or falsification of data. Making mistakes, however, is not fraud. McIntyre inveighs against cherry-picking data, searching data for statistical significance, drawing inferences from too small a data set, and so on, though he does not seem to consider those to be fraud. He reminds me of a colleague who once told me, with a grin, that he had to search high and low for an oscilloscope trace that he could call “typical” but which showed all the features he wanted to emphasize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another chapter details incidents of “fraud and other failures.” Many are probably familiar to readers of PT, but McIntyre provides a degree of detail that may not be so familiar. Among the frauds, I am sorry to report, is the “vaccine-autism debacle,” which features Andrew Wakefield, continues to this day, and contributes to the anti-vaccination movement and its attendant outbreaks of disease, again with the penalty of countless lost lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On what McIntyre deems a happier note, the astronomer Andrew Lyne made an error in a publication, explained it to a scientific conference, and received a standing ovation.  That is how science is supposed to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the head, “denialists, pseudoscientists, and other charlatans,” we meet those who deny well-established theories and those who insist on failed theories. Depressingly, McIntyre notes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;there has always been a human tendency to believe what we want to believe. Superstition and willful ignorance are not new to the human condition. What is new in recent years is the extent to which people can find a ready supply of &quot;evidence&quot; … on the Internet. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He goes on to observe that empirical evidence will not convince people who do not accept empirical evidence. “It is almost as if denialists are making faith-based assertions.” Almost?! He is too kind. Denialists are not skeptics; they are ideologues who refuse to believe conclusions that they do not like but which are based on what everyone else thinks is compelling evidence. Indeed, as he says, the&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;denialist pattern [is] to have impossibly high standards of proof for the things that one does not want to believe and extremely low standards of acceptance for the things that fit one's ideology. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under confirmation bias and motivated reasoning, we meet Senator Ted Cruz, who cherry-picks a particularly hot year to “prove” that climate change is a hoax by liberal politicians out for power. It is worth reading McIntyre’s dissection of an NPR interview with Sen. Cruz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will conclude with a warning. McIntyre discusses the case of Harlen Bretz and the origin of the channeled scablands in the state of Washington. Like Alfred Wegener and continental drift or Galileo and heliocentric theory, Bretz accounted for the scablands by postulating a massive flood and providing significant supporting evidence for such a flood; his theory is accepted today. In the early to mid-twentieth century, however, geologists rejected it vigorously, in part because uniformitarianism was “favored by geologists [because] it was seen as a bulwark against the creationists.” That is, geologists were putting ideology ahead of science – what McIntyre calls “an example of how ideology can infect the scientific process, whether we are on the ‘right’ side of it or not.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McIntyre tackles creationism and intelligent-design creationism, which are familiar to readers of PT, and then Robert Jahn’s study of psychokinesis, which I consider flawed science, not pseudoscience. I will not tackle either of those here.  Read the book!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* Popper, Karl R., 1968, Conjectures and Refutations: The Growth of Scientific Knowledge, Harper Torchbooks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Book cover. The fourth monkey is known as &quot;Have No Fun,&quot; but it is a misnomer: science can be great fun, especially if it involves optical instrumentation. Chance works in mysterious ways. Shortly after I saw the philosopher Lee McIntyre discussing How to talk to a science denier on the Center for Inquiry website, I ran across his splendid little book The Scientific Attitude: Defending Science from Denial, Fraud, and Pseudoscience. Naturally, I snapped it up.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creationist paleontologist misrepresents ichthyosaur fossil</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/creationist-paleontologist-misrepresents.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creationist paleontologist misrepresents ichthyosaur fossil" /><published>2022-04-27T08:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-04-27T08:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/creationist-paleontologist-misrepresents</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/creationist-paleontologist-misrepresents.html">&lt;p&gt;This well-done study of a spectacular ichthyosaur from the Jurassic Solnhofen Limestone, &lt;a href=&quot;https://peerj.com/articles/13173/&quot;&gt;Late Jurassic ichthyosaur specimens from the Solnhofen archipelago&lt;/a&gt;, was recently published and unfortunately misrepresented by Ken Ham’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/fossils/scientists-discover-fish-like-marine-reptile-buried-own-blubber/&quot;&gt;Answers News&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers News, the biweekly YouTube show put on by Answers in Genesis (creators of the Creation Museum and the Ark Encounter here in Kentucky), covered and misrepresented the find. This is par for the course for Answers in Genesis. Especially irritating are the misrepresentations of fossilization processes involved and the age of the specimen by Dr. Gabriela Haynes, an actual PhD employed by AiG. Dr. Haynes’s PhD was awarded by the Federal University of Ceará State in Brazil, in conjunction with the University of Kentucky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How could she not know that rapid burial is not the only way remarkable fossilization can occur? *&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She also claims, unsurprisingly, that the poor ichthyosaur died in Noah’s Flood about 4,500 years ago and discusses the effects of sin on ichthyosaurs. Their video can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/HVceC2BjtyU&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The inane part about the new ichthyosaur find starts about 3 min 45 s in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* See, for example, the description &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solnhofen_Limestone&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and in this well-known and widely available classic book: Barthel, K.W., Swinburne, N.H.M., and Conway Morris, S. 1994. Solnhofen: A Study in Mesozoic Palaeontology. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan Phelps is a professional geologist. This article is derived with permission from an e-mail he circulated yesterday. Matt Young will be the principal moderator of this post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">This well-done study of a spectacular ichthyosaur from the Jurassic Solnhofen Limestone, Late Jurassic ichthyosaur specimens from the Solnhofen archipelago, was recently published and unfortunately misrepresented by Ken Ham’s Answers News. Answers News, the biweekly YouTube show put on by Answers in Genesis (creators of the Creation Museum and the Ark Encounter here in Kentucky), covered and misrepresented the find. This is par for the course for Answers in Genesis. Especially irritating are the misrepresentations of fossilization processes involved and the age of the specimen by Dr. Gabriela Haynes, an actual PhD employed by AiG. Dr. Haynes’s PhD was awarded by the Federal University of Ceará State in Brazil, in conjunction with the University of Kentucky. How could she not know that rapid burial is not the only way remarkable fossilization can occur? * She also claims, unsurprisingly, that the poor ichthyosaur died in Noah’s Flood about 4,500 years ago and discusses the effects of sin on ichthyosaurs. Their video can be found here. The inane part about the new ichthyosaur find starts about 3 min 45 s in. * See, for example, the description here and in this well-known and widely available classic book: Barthel, K.W., Swinburne, N.H.M., and Conway Morris, S. 1994. Solnhofen: A Study in Mesozoic Palaeontology. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge. Dan Phelps is a professional geologist. This article is derived with permission from an e-mail he circulated yesterday. Matt Young will be the principal moderator of this post.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Methinks it is sort-of like two weasels</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/methinks-it-is-sort-of-like-two-weasels.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Methinks it is sort-of like two weasels" /><published>2022-04-26T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-04-26T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/methinks-it-is-sort-of-like-two-weasels</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/methinks-it-is-sort-of-like-two-weasels.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/weasel.png&quot; alt=&quot;[Weasel results]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Part of a run of a Dawkins's Weasel simulation,
showing it approaching the target phrase &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

Eric Holloway has written an article &lt;a href=&quot;https://mindmatters.ai/2022/03/dawkins-dubious-double-weasel-and-the-combinatorial-cataclysm/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; at the Discovery Institute's
 site &lt;em&gt;Mind Matters&lt;/em&gt;, in which he presents a variant on Richard
Dawkins's famous Weasel simulation, one in which there is not
just one target phrase, but two.  You may recall that the
original Weasel program had a target phrase, which was &quot;METHINKS
IT IS LIKE A WEASEL&quot;.  Counting blanks, this is 28 characters
long.  We start with a random string of 28 characters.  Each
generation the single string of 28 characters produces offspring
and they mutate, each character having a chance of changing to one
of the 26 other possibilities (the alphabet is
26 characters plus a blank).  If there are 10 offspring in each
generation, some may match the target phrase in more positions than other do.
In the original Weasel, natural selection occurs by having the
the offspring closest to the target string
replace the previous parent string.
&lt;p&gt;
In Dawkins's original computer simulation, the target phrase was
found in a few hundred to a few thousand steps, depending on the
number of offspring and the mutation rate.  We can compare this
to what would occur without natural selection, by having
a random offspring string replace the parent string. 
In that case, the string just changes at random by mutation, and
one can show that the number of generations that would be needed
to come across the target phrase would be about 10&lt;sup&gt;40&lt;/sup&gt;.
That's an awful lot more than a few thousand.
&lt;p&gt;
Holloway's article claims to show that by using not one, but two
target phrases, it can be seen that natural selection is in most
cases ineffective.  A commenter, &quot;Roy&quot;, at Josh Swamidass's
Peaceful Science forum took issue &lt;a href=&quot;https://discourse.peacefulscience.org/t/misunderstanding-weasel-programming/14968&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; with Holloway.  Roy's argument
there is fairly convincing, but there is more to be said.
&lt;p&gt;
Let me explain ...

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Weasel&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Richard Dawkins introduced his &quot;Weasel&quot; computer simulation
in 1976 in his book *The Blind Watchmaker*.  It was a dramatic
example of how natural selection could achieve a goal far faster
than purely undirected random change.  Many advocates of
creationism are insistent on characterizing natural evolutionary
processes as &quot;random&quot;.  This in hopes of convincing their audience
that evolutionary process are hopelessly bad at achieving
adaptations.  Dawkin's example demonstrates why natural selection
is not making &quot;random&quot; change. The example is an enormously effective
teaching example.
&lt;p&gt;
The result has been that many creationists are obsessed with
showing that Dawkins's argument does not work. By contrast, evolutionary
biologists are only mildly interested, as they have had many
empirical and theoretical examples of natural selection
working to achieve adaptations. Theoretical population genetics
dates back over 120 years, and the mathematics of natural
selection solidified 100 years ago: they have not been
waiting to hear from Richard Dawkins.  For a discussion of
how a Weasel simulation can be made to use the standard
Wright-Fisher model of theoretical population genetics,
see &lt;a href=&quot;http://theskepticalzone.com/wp/wright-fisher-and-the-weasel/&quot;&gt;a post by me at The Skeptical Zone in 2016&lt;/a&gt;.
But that carries us away from the present issues.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Previous criticisms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here are some of the most common creationist objections:
&lt;p&gt;
(1) &quot;But unlike evolution, Weasel programs have an explicit
target&quot;.  Yes, Richard Dawkins said so himself at the time.  The
purpose of his simulation was as a teaching example to show
readers how natural selection could be strongly nonrandom.
&lt;p&gt;
(2) &quot;But Dawkins never provided his source code.&quot;  He described
the simulation clearly, and it is very simple.  Many people have
written Weasel programs in various computer languages, and all
have shown results very similar to his.  There is no mystery that
would be solved by inspecting the original code.
&lt;p&gt;
(3) &quot;But the program is intelligently designed!&quot;  So what?  We can
intelligently design computer simulation programs of many natural
phenomena (motion of planets, soil erosion, change of weather,
etc.) and that does not show that those natural phenomena must be
intelligently designed.
&lt;p&gt;
(4) &quot;The Weasel shows 'locking' (or 'a partitioned search'), so that a position does not change
once it matches the target.  That is why it works.&quot;
Consideration of examples published by Dawkins shows that they
do not show &quot;locking&quot;.  But when Weasels have &quot;locking&quot; added, they
 are only slightly better than ones without, and both show adaptation that
is far faster than random wandering.  So this is a minor issue.
&lt;p&gt;
It is rather remarkable how obsessed many creationists are with
the Weasel.  Consider that many of them declare that change within
species is irrelevant to their arguments, because they are only
talking about the origin of major changes of body-plan.  They 
claim to not be making a general argument that natural selection is
ineffective.   Actually, they used to make such arguments, but
they have sworn off doing that.  But the minute someone claims to have an argument that
shows that natural selection is generally ineffective, they &quot;fall off the
wagon&quot; and once again succumb to this obsession.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holloway's criticism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mindmatters.ai/2022/03/dawkins-dubious-double-weasel-and-the-combinatorial-cataclysm/&quot;&gt;Eric Holloway's&lt;/a&gt; 
modified Weasel has two target strings.  In his
trials, the second string was &quot;IT LOOKS LIKE A WEASEL TO ME&quot;.  There
is still one parent string, which starts out being random, and it undergoes
the same mutational process as before.  But this time natural selection
acts by checking each offspring against both targets.  The score
is how many positions match at least one of the targets.  Thus if
a string has 12 positions that match only the first target, another 3
that match only the second target, and one position that matches
both targets, we count 12+3+1 = 16 matches. As before, the offspring
that has the highest score replaces the previous string in each
generation becoming the new parent.. 
&lt;p&gt;
The result is typically a string that matches one target or the other
in every position, but is not identical to either target.  An example
would be &quot;IE LINKS LTKIS  IEA EL EASME&quot;.  How many outcomes have a
score of 28?  There are 26 positions in which there are two possible
matches, and two positions in which there is only one possible match,
positions 7 and 8.  The number of strings achieving a perfect score
is then 2&lt;sup&gt;26&lt;/sup&gt;, which is 67,108,864.  &lt;em&gt;Oops! Roy has pointed out that I
 made the same mistake that Holloway did, and which Roy corrected.  There are
 three positions that match between the two targets, positions 7, 8, and 9,
 which  means that the number of strings achieving a perfect score is
 2&lt;sup&gt;25&lt;/sup&gt;, which is 33,554,432.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Aha, cries Holloway.  The strings he calls targets are two strings out of this large number,
and we reach all these possible perfect-scoring strings with equal
probability, so the chance that natural selection and mutation succeed in 
finding one of the two target strings in this case is very small.
All he has done, he says, is add
an additional target, but natural selection does not know to go
to one or the other targets, but instead mistakenly &quot;splits the
difference&quot;:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
It is like natural selection is driving the evolution bus down the road and encounters a fork with either a left or right turn. Unable to choose either alternative, natural selection decides to split the difference and plow straight ahead, leaving evolution a smoking wreck.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&quot;Roy&quot; replies to Holloway&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At Josh Swamidass's &quot;Peaceful Science&quot; forum, a frequent commenter
whose handle is &quot;Roy&quot; presented a rebuttal of Holloway which started
a discussion thread on &lt;a href=&quot;https://discourse.peacefulscience.org/t/misunderstanding-weasel-programming/14968&quot;&gt;&quot;Misunderstanding weasel programming&quot;&lt;/a&gt;.
Roy demonstrates some misunderstandings on Holloway's part.  His main
criticism is 
&lt;blockquote&gt;
... natural selection does not only select one character at a time. It selects the combination of characters in an individual
organism. If a mouse is born with two mutations that give it respectively larger ears and darker eyes, it’s not possible for
natural selection to retain one but not the other - that would require only half the mouse to have a litter of pinkies.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
...
&lt;blockquote&gt;
What happened is that @EricMH implemented the wrong selection criterion. He’s scoring single characters, when he should actually be
scoring the entire string.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Roy is correct, as far as Roy's argument goes.  I want to discuss the matter a little more generally.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Holloway and different cases&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In natural examples, natural selection could work either like Eric's program or like
Roy's program.  These are two legitimate possibilities (and there are others, too).
But what about the target strings?  In natural evolutionary processes there are no
targets.  Different genotypes simply have different fitnesses, and that is the
result of how the genotype affects the phenotype, and how that phenotype
interacts with the environment.   The closest thing to a target is the set
of genotypes of high fitness.
&lt;p&gt;
So if you use Holloway's program, the targets that it is seeking are not the two
sentences.  They are the set of all 2&lt;sup&gt;26&lt;/sup&gt; strings that achieve the highest
fitness.   On the other hand if you use Roy's program, the strings that
achieve highest fitness are only the two strings that Holloway describes.
&lt;p&gt;
Yes, there is a behavior of &quot;splitting the difference&quot;, but it is Holloway, not
a simulated evolutionary process, that is doing the splitting.  Holloway is 
running a program that would have 2&lt;sup&gt;26&lt;/sup&gt; targets, but declaring that there are
only two target strings.  Holloway would be right about that if he were
running, not his own program, but Roy's.  But he isn't, he's splitting the
difference and instead running his program, which has far more than two
strings of high fitness.
&lt;p&gt;
Both case are possible, but you shouldn't go around arbitrarily declaring
strings as being the targets, when evolution is acting as if there are
far more or far fewer strings of high fitness.  Your argument might be left
&quot;a smoking wreck&quot;.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Part of a run of a Dawkins's Weasel simulation, showing it approaching the target phrase Eric Holloway has written an article here at the Discovery Institute's site Mind Matters, in which he presents a variant on Richard Dawkins's famous Weasel simulation, one in which there is not just one target phrase, but two. You may recall that the original Weasel program had a target phrase, which was &quot;METHINKS IT IS LIKE A WEASEL&quot;. Counting blanks, this is 28 characters long. We start with a random string of 28 characters. Each generation the single string of 28 characters produces offspring and they mutate, each character having a chance of changing to one of the 26 other possibilities (the alphabet is 26 characters plus a blank). If there are 10 offspring in each generation, some may match the target phrase in more positions than other do. In the original Weasel, natural selection occurs by having the the offspring closest to the target string replace the previous parent string. In Dawkins's original computer simulation, the target phrase was found in a few hundred to a few thousand steps, depending on the number of offspring and the mutation rate. We can compare this to what would occur without natural selection, by having a random offspring string replace the parent string. In that case, the string just changes at random by mutation, and one can show that the number of generations that would be needed to come across the target phrase would be about 1040. That's an awful lot more than a few thousand. Holloway's article claims to show that by using not one, but two target phrases, it can be seen that natural selection is in most cases ineffective. A commenter, &quot;Roy&quot;, at Josh Swamidass's Peaceful Science forum took issue here with Holloway. Roy's argument there is fairly convincing, but there is more to be said. Let me explain ...</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chinavia hilaris</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/chinavia-hilaris.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chinavia hilaris" /><published>2022-04-25T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-04-25T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/chinavia%20hilaris</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/chinavia-hilaris.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Green_Stink_Bug_Alex.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Green stink bug&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green_stink_bug&quot;&gt;Chinavia hilaris&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; green stink bug, Boulder, Colorado, April, 2022. My ever alert granddaughter Alex captured this picture using a small, handheld computer that she calls her &quot;phone.&quot; She has promised to watch for any changes in the eggs, but neither of us has any idea what the hatchlings are going to eat; the eggs are normally planted on the underside of a leaf. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Chinavia hilaris &amp;ndash; green stink bug, Boulder, Colorado, April, 2022. My ever alert granddaughter Alex captured this picture using a small, handheld computer that she calls her &quot;phone.&quot; She has promised to watch for any changes in the eggs, but neither of us has any idea what the hatchlings are going to eat; the eggs are normally planted on the underside of a leaf.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Baptist News criticizes Ark Park</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/baptist-news-criticizes-ark.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Baptist News criticizes Ark Park" /><published>2022-04-20T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-04-20T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/baptist-news-criticizes-ark</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/baptist-news-criticizes-ark.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Ark_Bow.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bow of Ark&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Ark on opening day.  &lt;small&gt;Credit: Photograph by Dan Phelps.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They did not exactly do a hatchet job, but Baptist News Global just posted an article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://baptistnews.com/article/creationism-is-big-business-in-northern-kentucky/#.YmAq2-jMKwU&quot;&gt;Creationism is big business in Northern Kentucky&lt;/a&gt;, by Mark Wingfield, which is fairly critical of the Ark Park, and indeed draws on an earlier article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/anti-museum&quot;&gt;The Anti-Museum&lt;/a&gt;, by our colleague and sometime contributor Dan Phelps. &lt;a href=&quot;https://baptistnews.com/more/about/#.YmA2XOjMKwU&quot;&gt;Baptist News Global&lt;/a&gt; is an independent publication that, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baptist_News_Global&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, is affiliated with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cooperative_Baptist_Fellowship&quot;&gt;Cooperative Baptist Fellowship&lt;/a&gt;, a relatively liberal denomination that has withdrawn from the Southern Baptist Convention. Mr. Wingfield, the Executive Director of the publication, notes in his article that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;creationism has no support in mainstream science. A 2019 Gallup Poll found that 40% of Americans say they believe in creationism, with the likelihood of holding that belief corresponding heavily toward lower levels of education.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the risk of cherry-picking, he notes further,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Phelps envisioned the museum and life-size ark appealing to home-schooling parents but also wondered if its presence could put a damper on the teaching of accepted science in the region’s schools. He called the teaching of Answers in Genesis “outrageous and remarkable pseudoscience.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a hatchet job, granted, but at least they went after the Ark with a tackhammer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the same day, William Trollinger, of the blog Righting America, posted an article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/ken-ham-and-the-fog-that-enshrouds-ark-encounter/&quot;&gt;Ken Ham and the fog that enshrouds Ark Encounter&lt;/a&gt;, which outlines the financial shenanigans that accompanied the founding of the Ark Park. Of particular note,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/ken-ham-and-the-government-subsidy-that-makes-ark-encounter-possible/&quot;&gt;75% of what Ark Encounter would have paid in property taxes instead goes to paying off the bonds that made the Ark possible&lt;/a&gt;. Quite obviously, this is a government subsidy.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Mr. Trollinger, the bonds will be fully paid off this month, meaning April. He asks,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;[D]oes that mean that, after nine years of this very generous local government subsidy, Ark Encounter will finally begin to pay its fair share of property taxes? &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us hope so, but anyone who thinks that the Ark Park has brought prosperity to Williamstown needs to watch &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt6316506/&quot;&gt;We believe in dinosaurs&lt;/a&gt;.  Williamstown helped subsidize the Ark Park, but now unfortunately finds itself on the other side of the Interstate highway, a fact that must have been withheld from them when the Ark was begging for subsidies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Ken Ham, in his blog, notes on March 26 that there is a labor shortage and proposes &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/ministry-news/issues-facing-ministry/&quot;&gt;building dormitories&lt;/a&gt; for summer students or, indeed, year-round students whose Christian colleges allow them to study remotely. You do not have to read very deeply between the lines to recognize that he may call these jobs “internships,” which means that he can pay anywhere from $0.00 upward. These interns will of course be a source of cheap labor and will compete with the citizens of Williamstown and elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Ark on opening day. Credit: Photograph by Dan Phelps. They did not exactly do a hatchet job, but Baptist News Global just posted an article, Creationism is big business in Northern Kentucky, by Mark Wingfield, which is fairly critical of the Ark Park, and indeed draws on an earlier article, The Anti-Museum, by our colleague and sometime contributor Dan Phelps. Baptist News Global is an independent publication that, according to Wikipedia, is affiliated with the Cooperative Baptist Fellowship, a relatively liberal denomination that has withdrawn from the Southern Baptist Convention. Mr. Wingfield, the Executive Director of the publication, notes in his article that creationism has no support in mainstream science. A 2019 Gallup Poll found that 40% of Americans say they believe in creationism, with the likelihood of holding that belief corresponding heavily toward lower levels of education. At the risk of cherry-picking, he notes further, Phelps envisioned the museum and life-size ark appealing to home-schooling parents but also wondered if its presence could put a damper on the teaching of accepted science in the region’s schools. He called the teaching of Answers in Genesis “outrageous and remarkable pseudoscience.” Not a hatchet job, granted, but at least they went after the Ark with a tackhammer. On the same day, William Trollinger, of the blog Righting America, posted an article, Ken Ham and the fog that enshrouds Ark Encounter, which outlines the financial shenanigans that accompanied the founding of the Ark Park. Of particular note, 75% of what Ark Encounter would have paid in property taxes instead goes to paying off the bonds that made the Ark possible. Quite obviously, this is a government subsidy. According to Mr. Trollinger, the bonds will be fully paid off this month, meaning April. He asks, [D]oes that mean that, after nine years of this very generous local government subsidy, Ark Encounter will finally begin to pay its fair share of property taxes? Let us hope so, but anyone who thinks that the Ark Park has brought prosperity to Williamstown needs to watch We believe in dinosaurs. Williamstown helped subsidize the Ark Park, but now unfortunately finds itself on the other side of the Interstate highway, a fact that must have been withheld from them when the Ark was begging for subsidies. Finally, Ken Ham, in his blog, notes on March 26 that there is a labor shortage and proposes building dormitories for summer students or, indeed, year-round students whose Christian colleges allow them to study remotely. You do not have to read very deeply between the lines to recognize that he may call these jobs “internships,” which means that he can pay anywhere from $0.00 upward. These interns will of course be a source of cheap labor and will compete with the citizens of Williamstown and elsewhere.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Aythya collaris</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/aythya-collaris.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aythya collaris" /><published>2022-04-11T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-04-11T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/aythya-collaris</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/aythya-collaris.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/IMG_0107_Ring-Necked_Duck_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ring-necked duck&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Ring-necked_Duck/overview&quot;&gt;Aythya collaris&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; ring-necked duck, Goose Creek, Boulder, Colorado, February, 2022. This bird seemed to be dabbling alongside a pair of mallards. All About Birds (see link) tells us that the ringed neck may be useless as an identifying mark; 19th century biologists named the species using dead specimens. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Aythya collaris &amp;ndash; ring-necked duck, Goose Creek, Boulder, Colorado, February, 2022. This bird seemed to be dabbling alongside a pair of mallards. All About Birds (see link) tells us that the ringed neck may be useless as an identifying mark; 19th century biologists named the species using dead specimens.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Darwinism” confers tolerance</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/darwinism-confers-tolerance.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Darwinism” confers tolerance" /><published>2022-04-06T14:17:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-04-06T14:17:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/darwinism-confers-tolerance</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/darwinism-confers-tolerance.html">&lt;p&gt;The head is my gloss on an article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://phys.org/news/2022-04-disbelief-human-evolution-linked-greater.html&quot;&gt;Disbelief in human evolution linked to greater prejudice and racism&lt;/a&gt;, that was just published on the website Phys.org. It is something of a leap to infer causality, but as we shall see in a moment it is a leap made by the authors of the article. (Incidentally, I put “Darwinism” into scare quotes because I do not believe that evolutionary biology is an -ism.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At any rate, in brief, Stylianos Syropoulos, a Ph.D. candidate in the War and Peace Lab at the University of Massachusetts Amherst, and his colleagues found that in the US and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;across the globe—in 19 Eastern European countries, 25 Muslim countries and in Israel—low belief in evolution was linked to higher biases within a person's group, prejudicial attitudes toward people in different groups and less support for conflict resolution.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The researchers theorized that belief in evolution would tend to increase people's identification with all humanity, due to the common ancestry, and would lead to fewer prejudicial attitudes,&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which I think is a more positive phrasing than the title of the article. More specifically,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;People who perceive themselves as more similar to animals are also people who tend to have more pro-social or positive attitudes toward outgroup members or people from stigmatized and marginalized backgrounds,&quot; Syropoulos explains. &quot;In this investigation, we were interested in examining whether belief in evolution would also act in a similar way, because it would reinforce this belief that we are more similar to animals.&quot; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the UMass article quotes the technical paper to the effect that “the disbelief in human evolution is the driving factor and most consistent predictor of prejudice in comparison to other relevant constructs.” The actual paper is behind a paywall, so I cannot ascertain how they established causality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the authors note that others have claimed that the theory of evolution perpetuates racism, prejudice, and homophobia, partly because of the concept of natural selection and the phrase “survival of the fittest.” Senior author Bernhard Leidner, also of the University of Massachusetts, may have gloated a little bit when he said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;There have been theoretical accounts that predict the opposite of what we found, so it was exciting for us to show that this actually is not the case, that the opposite is true and that belief in evolution seems to have pretty positive effects, &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but I think maybe he had a right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul Braterman of the University of Glasgow brought the Phys.org article to our attention. The technical paper is Syropoulos, S., Lifshin, U., Greenberg, J., Horner, D. E., &amp;amp; Leidner, B. (2022). Bigotry and the human–animal divide: (Dis)belief in human evolution and bigoted attitudes across different cultures. &lt;i&gt;Journal of Personality and Social Psychology&lt;/i&gt;. Advance online publication. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1037/pspi0000391&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/pspi0000391&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">The head is my gloss on an article, Disbelief in human evolution linked to greater prejudice and racism, that was just published on the website Phys.org. It is something of a leap to infer causality, but as we shall see in a moment it is a leap made by the authors of the article. (Incidentally, I put “Darwinism” into scare quotes because I do not believe that evolutionary biology is an -ism.) At any rate, in brief, Stylianos Syropoulos, a Ph.D. candidate in the War and Peace Lab at the University of Massachusetts Amherst, and his colleagues found that in the US and across the globe—in 19 Eastern European countries, 25 Muslim countries and in Israel—low belief in evolution was linked to higher biases within a person's group, prejudicial attitudes toward people in different groups and less support for conflict resolution.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Zebra Stone</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/03/zebra-stone.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Zebra Stone" /><published>2022-03-28T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-03-28T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/03/zebra-stone</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/03/zebra-stone.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Dan Phelps&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/7_Zebra_Stone_600.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Zebra stone&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://museum.wa.gov.au/research/collections/earth-and-planetary-sciences/rock-collection/zebra-rock&quot;&gt;Zebra stone&lt;/a&gt;, Kununurra region of Western Australia. Mr. Phelps says that there is debate as to whether zebra stone is an odd metamorphic rock or an odd &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/science/Ediacara-fauna&quot;&gt;Ediacaran&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://ucmp.berkeley.edu/bacteria/cyanofr.html&quot;&gt;stromatolite&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Dan Phelps. Zebra stone, Kununurra region of Western Australia. Mr. Phelps says that there is debate as to whether zebra stone is an odd metamorphic rock or an odd Ediacaran stromatolite.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Herschel Walker isn’t the only one wrong about humans and apes</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/03/herschel-walker-isnt-the-only-one.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Herschel Walker isn’t the only one wrong about humans and apes" /><published>2022-03-24T19:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-03-24T19:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/03/herschel-walker-isnt-the-only-one</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/03/herschel-walker-isnt-the-only-one.html">&lt;p&gt;About a week ago there was a media flap when the leading Republican running for senator from Georgia, football great
Herschel Walker, asked why there were still apes, if humans have evolved from apes.  This is a common silly creationist
talking point.  It is usually stated as the question “why are there still monkeys”.  There's really not much
reason to spend time refuting it; it reflects an elementary misunderstanding of what evolutionary biologists say
about human evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what was more astonishing was how our knowledgeable and sophisticated press explained the matter to its readers.  Here are some
jaw-dropping explanations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CNN’s Editor-at-large Chris Cilizza explained
&lt;a href=&quot;https://amp.cnn.com/cnn/2022/03/16/politics/herschel-walker-geogia-senate-candidate-evolution-apes/index.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
that “Humans and apes evolved from the same genetic ape ancestors, a species now long extinct. (It’s known as “common
descent.”) We did not, however, evolve directly from the current occupants of your local zoo. They are one branch of
descent from their ape ancestors. Humans are another.”  And he quotes an evolutionary biologist, Fabio Mendes, as
saying that “Humans and apes evolved from the same genetic ape ancestors, a species now long extinct. (It’s known as
“common descent.”) We did not, however, evolve directly from the current occupants of your local zoo. They are one
branch of descent from their ape ancestors. Humans are another.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The digital media report The Hill &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehill.com/media/598393-herschel-walker-asks-why-are-there-still-apes-in-discussion-about-evolution&quot;&gt;played it
safe&lt;/a&gt;, relying on PBS: “According to a PBS FAQ about evolution, “Humans
are more closely related to modern apes … but we didn’t evolve from apes, either. Humans share a common ancestor
with modern African apes. … Scientists believe this common ancestor existed 5 to 8 million years ago. Shortly
thereafter, the species diverged into two separate lineages. One of these lineages ultimately evolved into gorillas and
chimps, and the other evolved into early human ancestors called hominids.” (The PBS FAQ was actually from a 2001 science
program “Evolution”, a series funded by a foundation of Paul Allen’s.  It &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/evolution/library/faq/cat02.html&quot;&gt;can be found
here&lt;/a&gt;).  It in turn has links to some respectable sources,
some to the Talk.Origins site, which itself cites a couple of articles here at Panda’s Thumb.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A fact-checking site, Politifact, has its article
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politifact.com/factchecks/2022/mar/17/herschel-walker/yes-evolution-proves-humans-and-apes-can-coexist/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
It is slightly more vague on the issue, but does say that “Humans and the apes known today both evolved from ancient apes, who are now extinct. This split occurred between 6-8 million years ago based on genetic and fossil evidence.  Over time, humans and apes have been evolving in their own ways to adapt in their respective environments.”
and also that “Humans and modern-day apes both evolved from ancient apes, who are now extinct. Anthropologists using
genetic and fossil evidence pinpoint it between 6-8 million years ago. Humans and the apes seen today evolved
differently over time.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The message is clear.  Apes, who, us?  We evolved from something, but it wasn’t an ape.  Nosiree!  Apes evolved
separately from us, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not right&lt;/em&gt;, of course.  Which means we ought to discuss why so many people who know evolution happened can’t seem to
say that we evolved from apes, that in fact &lt;em&gt;we are apes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s think about this …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick summary of the situation might be to note that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;About 60 years ago it was still thought that the most recent common ancestor of humans and apes lived 25 million years
ago.  That would place most apes in a sister-group to humans.  It was thus possible to say that the common ancestor wasn’t
an ape.  This was much less upsetting to the public than saying that any of their ancestors had been apes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The “evolutionary systematics” position on classification, which was dominant then, did not require groups in the
classification system to be monophyletic (to have their very own common ancestor).  Apes could be placed in one group,
humans in another, even though some of the descendants of the common ancestor of all apes included humans.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By this point, biologists should have started admitting that humans were descended from apes.  They sort-of did,
though usually reassuring the public that they weren’t descended from any hairy and gross animal like &lt;em&gt;present-day&lt;/em&gt; apes such
as chimpanzees and gorillas.  This evades the question of whether any of our ancestors were hairy and gross.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;But by the 1970s it was becoming clear that humans were in a clade that included chimps and gorillas.  And that our lineage
connected with apes less than 10 million years ago.  And monophyletic
classification (“phylogenetic systematics”) was becoming the dominant approach.  In the 1980s it became clear that the lineage with the two species of
chimpanzees was the sister lineage of hominids.  From that point on, it was inevitable that popular-science discussions
of human ancestry would finally admit that we had ancestors that &lt;em&gt;were&lt;/em&gt; apes.  And that we ourselves were apes.
Jared Diamond was straightforward about that in his book &lt;em&gt;The Third Chimpanzee: The Evolution and Future of the Human Animal&lt;/em&gt; in 1991.
But Francisco Ayala was more circumlocuitous in his 2010 book &lt;em&gt;Am I a Monkey? Six Big Questions about Evolution&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has taken an extraordinary amount of time for popular writings in biology to admit that you not only have an inner fish,
but an inner monkey and an inner ape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have I got this picture wrong?  Discuss …&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">About a week ago there was a media flap when the leading Republican running for senator from Georgia, football great Herschel Walker, asked why there were still apes, if humans have evolved from apes. This is a common silly creationist talking point. It is usually stated as the question “why are there still monkeys”. There's really not much reason to spend time refuting it; it reflects an elementary misunderstanding of what evolutionary biologists say about human evolution. But what was more astonishing was how our knowledgeable and sophisticated press explained the matter to its readers. Here are some jaw-dropping explanations: CNN’s Editor-at-large Chris Cilizza explained here that “Humans and apes evolved from the same genetic ape ancestors, a species now long extinct. (It’s known as “common descent.”) We did not, however, evolve directly from the current occupants of your local zoo. They are one branch of descent from their ape ancestors. Humans are another.” And he quotes an evolutionary biologist, Fabio Mendes, as saying that “Humans and apes evolved from the same genetic ape ancestors, a species now long extinct. (It’s known as “common descent.”) We did not, however, evolve directly from the current occupants of your local zoo. They are one branch of descent from their ape ancestors. Humans are another.” The digital media report The Hill played it safe, relying on PBS: “According to a PBS FAQ about evolution, “Humans are more closely related to modern apes … but we didn’t evolve from apes, either. Humans share a common ancestor with modern African apes. … Scientists believe this common ancestor existed 5 to 8 million years ago. Shortly thereafter, the species diverged into two separate lineages. One of these lineages ultimately evolved into gorillas and chimps, and the other evolved into early human ancestors called hominids.” (The PBS FAQ was actually from a 2001 science program “Evolution”, a series funded by a foundation of Paul Allen’s. It can be found here). It in turn has links to some respectable sources, some to the Talk.Origins site, which itself cites a couple of articles here at Panda’s Thumb. A fact-checking site, Politifact, has its article here. It is slightly more vague on the issue, but does say that “Humans and the apes known today both evolved from ancient apes, who are now extinct. This split occurred between 6-8 million years ago based on genetic and fossil evidence. Over time, humans and apes have been evolving in their own ways to adapt in their respective environments.” and also that “Humans and modern-day apes both evolved from ancient apes, who are now extinct. Anthropologists using genetic and fossil evidence pinpoint it between 6-8 million years ago. Humans and the apes seen today evolved differently over time.” The message is clear. Apes, who, us? We evolved from something, but it wasn’t an ape. Nosiree! Apes evolved separately from us, right? Not right, of course. Which means we ought to discuss why so many people who know evolution happened can’t seem to say that we evolved from apes, that in fact we are apes. Let’s think about this …</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kentucky Attorney General Gets a Personal Tour of the Ark Park from Ken Ham</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/03/kentucky-attorney-general.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kentucky Attorney General Gets a Personal Tour of the Ark Park from Ken Ham" /><published>2022-03-16T15:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-03-16T15:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/03/kentucky-attorney-general</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/03/kentucky-attorney-general.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Phelps_Figure.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Attroney General and friends&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Clockwise from upper left: Figure 1. Kentucky Attorney General Daniel Cameron and his wife Makenze Evans learn from Ken Ham why Noah took only baby dinosaurs on the Ark.  Figure 2. Kentucky’s Attorney General learns from Ken Ham why climate change is wrong.   Figure 3. AG Cameron gets a view from the top deck of the Ark (mere tourists, even the most faithful, typically do not get to go here for the view).  Figure 4. With Answers in Genesis attorney John Pence (on far right). &lt;small&gt;Source: KORA request, Kentucky Attorney General. Fair use.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guest post by Dan Phelps. Mr. Phelps’s most recent contribution to PT was &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/your-brain-as-walnut.html&quot;&gt;Your Brain as a Walnut&lt;/a&gt; in November 2021. Matt Young will be the principal moderator of this thread.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been using the Kentucky Open Records Act (KORA) for several years to keep up with attempts by creationists to infiltrate schools, receive tax incentives for the Ark Encounter theme park, and monitor attendance levels at the Ark Encounter. Usually, government entities have been cooperative with my efforts. The public, after all, should have the right to know how the government, at all levels, conducts its business. Alas, the Kentucky Attorney General has protected himself from public scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On September 8, 2021, Kentucky Attorney General (AG) Daniel Cameron visited the Ark Encounter near Williamstown, Kentucky. On September 12, 2021, a brief, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kyoag/status/1437026455171575813&quot;&gt;professionally done video of his visit&lt;/a&gt; was posted to the Kentucky Attorney General’s official state Twitter page (this is not a political campaign site, but an official Commonwealth of Kentucky account for the AG’s Office). The video ends by displaying a &lt;a href=&quot;https://ag.ky.gov/Pages/default.aspx&quot;&gt;link to the AG’s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video shows that the AG and his entourage received a personal tour from Ken Ham, even viewing the quasi-spectacular vista on the upper deck where tourists generally are not allowed. Interestingly, there isn’t any audio of Cameron or Ham, just quick edit clips of Ham leading a tour set to music. It is difficult to imagine anything helpful or informative to Kentuckians about the video, and it appears to be nothing more the AG pandering to the most conservative Kentucky voters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniel Cameron has been Kentucky’s Attorney General since 2019. He is the first Republican to hold the office since the 1940s and the first African American to hold the office, ever. For two years after receiving his law degree from the University of Louisville in 2011, he was a law clerk to US District Judge Gregory F. Van Tatenhove of the US District Court for the Eastern District of Kentucky. Judge Tatenhove is well-known for ruling in favor of Answers in Genesis (AiG) receiving $18.25 million in tax rebate incentives from the Commonwealth of Kentucky in the case of &lt;a href=&quot;https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/district-courts/kentucky/kyedce/3:2015cv00013/77195/56/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ark Encounter LLC et al. vs Bob Stewart et al.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Later, Daniel Cameron served as a legal counsel to then Senate Majority Leader Mitch McConnell of Kentucky from 2015 to 2017. Cameron led legal efforts to see that numerous federal judges were confirmed during the Trump administration. After this, he worked for a Kentucky law firm before winning the race for AG in 2019. Controversies during his tenure as AG have included his handling of the grand jury during the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Killing_of_Breonna_Taylor&quot;&gt;Breonna Taylor case&lt;/a&gt; (Breonna Taylor was an unarmed young African American woman killed when the Louisville police enforced a no-knock warrant). Cameron also has challenged emergency Covid mask mandates by Kentucky Governor Andy Beshear. In early November 2021, he sued the Federal Government in an attempt to block the Biden Administration’s mandate that employees of federal contractors be vaccinated. In August 2020 Cameron spoke at the Republican National Convention. In September 2020, his name appeared on a list by then President Donald Trump as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.courier-journal.com/story/news/2020/09/09/daniel-cameron-named-possible-supreme-court-nominee-donald-trump/5762899002/&quot;&gt;potential candidate for the US Supreme Court&lt;/a&gt;. It is no secret in Kentucky political circles that he may be a future candidate for Governor of Kentucky, or a candidate to replace Senate Minority Leader Mitch McConnell when McConnell eventually retires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intrigued and disturbed by the Twitter video, which I failed to see until mid-October 2021, I filed a Kentucky Open Records Act (KORA) request with the Attorney General’s Office on October 20. I requested: (1) All electronic mail, messages, mail, or other correspondence between the Office of Kentucky Attorney General and Answers In Genesis, between January 1 and October 15, 2021; (2) Any receipts and other evidence of taxpayer funds expended on the visit to the Ark Encounter facility; (3) A list of attendees employed by the Commonwealth of Kentucky in connection with the visit; (4) Any mileage logs, travel receipts, or other statements reflecting travel to or from the Ark Encounter; and finally (5) Any written material, or other documents provided to the Attorney General or other employees of the Commonwealth of Kentucky during or following the above-referenced visit. I had help drafting this letter and appeals from Tony Sammons, a retired local attorney, David MacMillan, a law school student, and Amye Bensenhaver of the Kentucky Open Government Coalition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked for all of the information above because I want to know the details of Answers in Genesis’s influence on Kentucky’s politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the AG’s Office asked for an extension, I eventually received an empty and broken-open envelope on November 9. After further communication, I finally received the KORA package electronically via Dropbox on November 12. This was more than 20 days after my initial request. To my surprise, I received only a copy of the video that was posted to Twitter and approximately 70 still photographs of Attorney General Cameron, his wife, and their entourage (presumably attorneys and security guards) getting the personal tour from Ken Ham. Particularly disturbing, and in an odd sense comical, were the photos of the AG with Ham standing in front of displays explaining why Noah took only baby dinosaurs on the Ark (Figure 1) and why anthropogenic climate change is wrong (Figure 2). AG Cameron also is on the top deck of the Ark with Ken Ham (Figure 3). There was also a photo that included Answers in Genesis’ attorney John Pence (Figure 4). That, along with random photos of other unnamed staff and security guards, was &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; I received. I wasn’t even given information as to the exact date of the event (info in the photo metadata tags indicates September 8, 2021). Interestingly, if the metadata on the photographs is correct, the KY AG’s entourage arrived at 10:45 am, but did not enter the Ark-shaped building until about 1:40 pm. This gave ample time for discussions between the Attorney General, Ken Ham, and their staffs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I received nothing concerning how much tax money was expended on this propaganda. I again contacted the Open Records Officer at the Attorney General’s Office, thinking information had been mistakenly omitted. The AG’s Office explained it was withholding everything else that I requested. The KY AG’s Office claimed not to have records on who accompanied Daniel Cameron or any expenses related to the trip; not even mileage or fuel expenses. The AG’s Office admitted that three emails that initiated the event, but claimed that these were exempt from KORA. The excuse given for not providing the three emails was that records related to meetings and calendar invitations are exempt in a rather broad interpretation of a case about the Kentucky Open Records Act: &lt;a href=&quot;https://casetext.com/case/courier-journal-v-jones&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Courier-Journal v. Jones&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. KY AG’s Office has notoriously interpreted several court cases in odd ways as limiting open records requests. I decided to appeal the decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the Kentucky AG’s Office oversees all appeals to the Kentucky Open Records Act in Kentucky, unless one opts to go directly to Circuit Court. An attorney is essential to have a chance of success in Circuit Court. Thus, the appeal was ruled on by the &lt;em&gt;very agency&lt;/em&gt; involved in the complaint. My appeal was responded to by a political appointee from the KY AG’s Office, which was not surprising or improper. My appeal was ultimately rejected on the grounds that the information requested was broadly, and in my opinion inappropriately, interpreted to be part of the AG’s schedule and exempt from KORA because of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ag.ky.gov/Resources/orom/2022/22-ORD-026.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Courier-Journal v. Jones&lt;/em&gt; ruling mentioned above&lt;/a&gt;. Most remarkably, the rejection of my appeal was also written by a political appointee at the KY AG’s Office. At a minimum a Kentucky Merit System employee, who supposedly would not be subject to political pressure, should have written the final decision. I was given 30 days to appeal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Filing an appeal to the KY AG’s decision in Circuit Court would require more complex legal skills than I am capable of (I’m a geologist with a background in paleontology/paleoecology.) An appeal without legal counsel had the prospect of me arguing the case in circuit court.* It also would require considerable money unless an attorney would accept the case &lt;em&gt;pro bono&lt;/em&gt;. I attempted for some time to get the ACLU and local attorneys to help. Unfortunately, every attorney I contacted had too many &lt;em&gt;pro bon&lt;/em&gt;o cases already in litigation. Sadly, no one representing the ACLU even bothered to contact me. Thus, the deadline to appeal passed on March 16, 2022. Perhaps others with legal resources can request the three emails between the Kentucky Attorney General and Ken Ham/AiG.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most plausible explanation for the AG visiting the Ark Park was that he was playing to his political base and affirming that he supported ultraconservative Christians. In all probability this visit was merely an attempt by Daniel Cameron to get support for his future political ambitions. Given the lengthy time span between arrival and touring the Ark, were other things done during the trip? The three emails I was denied could have clarified the trip’s full purpose. Was this meeting to get additional financial support or new tourism tax incentives for AiG’s building of a Tower of Babel “replica” on the Ark property? Does Ken Ham want the AG to support teaching creationism in Kentucky public schools? Or does this have something to do with AiG’s opposition to mask and vaccine mandates, which Daniel Cameron has also vigorously worked against? These questions are necessary because of the importance of science education, public health, the separation of church and state, financial integrity in the use of taxpayer’s money by the Commonwealth of Kentucky, and how public servants use their time when they are supposed to be doing their job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the transparency of a useful government open records policy, we may never know the answers. At the very least, the refusal to supply the information I requested is antithetical to the reasons open records laws were created in the first place. “Democracy Dies in Darkness” is the official slogan of the Washington Post. The adage applies not only to the media investigating the government, but citizens of all stripes with concerns about government activity. All parts of the political spectrum should support open records and government transparency. Since newspapers, which have large budgets for legal representation are shrinking, how are local advocates and activists such as I to receive information from an increasingly evasive and secretive government? Ordinary citizens concerned about government activities increasingly have less access to information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Before you act, it’s Prudence soberly to consider; for after Action you cannot recede without dishonour: Take the Advice of some Prudent Friend; for &lt;em&gt;he who will be his own Counsellour, shall be sure to have a Fool for his Client.&lt;/em&gt; – &lt;a href=&quot;https://quoteinvestigator.com/2019/07/30/lawyer/&quot;&gt;William De Britaine, 1682&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Clockwise from upper left: Figure 1. Kentucky Attorney General Daniel Cameron and his wife Makenze Evans learn from Ken Ham why Noah took only baby dinosaurs on the Ark. Figure 2. Kentucky’s Attorney General learns from Ken Ham why climate change is wrong. Figure 3. AG Cameron gets a view from the top deck of the Ark (mere tourists, even the most faithful, typically do not get to go here for the view). Figure 4. With Answers in Genesis attorney John Pence (on far right). Source: KORA request, Kentucky Attorney General. Fair use. Guest post by Dan Phelps. Mr. Phelps’s most recent contribution to PT was Your Brain as a Walnut in November 2021. Matt Young will be the principal moderator of this thread. I have been using the Kentucky Open Records Act (KORA) for several years to keep up with attempts by creationists to infiltrate schools, receive tax incentives for the Ark Encounter theme park, and monitor attendance levels at the Ark Encounter. Usually, government entities have been cooperative with my efforts. The public, after all, should have the right to know how the government, at all levels, conducts its business. Alas, the Kentucky Attorney General has protected himself from public scrutiny. On September 8, 2021, Kentucky Attorney General (AG) Daniel Cameron visited the Ark Encounter near Williamstown, Kentucky. On September 12, 2021, a brief, professionally done video of his visit was posted to the Kentucky Attorney General’s official state Twitter page (this is not a political campaign site, but an official Commonwealth of Kentucky account for the AG’s Office). The video ends by displaying a link to the AG’s website. The video shows that the AG and his entourage received a personal tour from Ken Ham, even viewing the quasi-spectacular vista on the upper deck where tourists generally are not allowed. Interestingly, there isn’t any audio of Cameron or Ham, just quick edit clips of Ham leading a tour set to music. It is difficult to imagine anything helpful or informative to Kentuckians about the video, and it appears to be nothing more the AG pandering to the most conservative Kentucky voters.</summary></entry></feed>