<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-02-17T20:48:14-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Melanoplus sp.</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/02/melanoplus-sp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Melanoplus sp." /><published>2026-02-16T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2026-02-16T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/02/melanoplus-sp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/02/melanoplus-sp.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2026/IMG_0994_Melanoplus_Grasshopper_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Grasshopper mymph&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melanoplus&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Melanoplus&lt;/i&gt; sp.&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; grasshopper nymph. Thanks to Brandon Woo and Tyler Hedlund of BugGuide for identifying the grasshopper and explaining how to identify a nymph &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bugguide.net/node/view/978476&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Melanoplus sp. &amp;ndash; grasshopper nymph. Thanks to Brandon Woo and Tyler Hedlund of BugGuide for identifying the grasshopper and explaining how to identify a nymph here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The DI site S&amp;amp;C says something sensible</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/02/something-sensible.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The DI site S&amp;amp;C says something sensible" /><published>2026-02-12T13:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2026-02-12T13:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/02/something-sensible</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/02/something-sensible.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2026/Minipig.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[a miniature pig]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;A miniature pig developed for medical&lt;br /&gt; research.  Source: Wikimedia Commons&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re used to seeing all sorts of silliness at the Discovery Institute’s website 
“Science &amp;amp; Culture Today”  (formerly called Evolution News).  A staple of the 
site is an article describing how wonderfully well-adapted some feature of an organism is, with 
the implied conclusion that this could only have come from Design Intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent posts there have continued their tradition of being even more 
astonishing than that.  Here are three examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An expert on German literature, Neil Thomas, wrote on &lt;a href=&quot;https://scienceandculture.com/2026/01/the-monster-in-the-sky-revisiting-atheisms-creation-myth/&quot;&gt;“The Monster in the Sky”: Revisiting Atheism’s Creation Myth&lt;/a&gt;, in which he 
said:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My hope in this endeavor is to throw additional light on the subject of Victorians’ reception of Darwin’s Origin of Species, asking specifically what factors might explain our ancestors’ acquiescence in accepting a theory bereft of empirical documentation.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Yes, he really means that.  See my earlier discussion of his views &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/Darwinist-changes-his-mind.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emily Reeves, trained in nutritional biochemistry, discovered a remarkable 
feature of evolutionary change.  In her post &lt;a href=&quot;https://scienceandculture.com/2025/12/merry-christmas-no-8-story-for-2025-optimization-and-evolution-before-our-eyes/&quot;&gt;Merry Christmas! No. 8 Story for 2025: Optimization and “Evolution Before Our Eyes”&lt;/a&gt; 
she reported on studies on evolutionary tradeoffs in Darwin’s Finches, using the 
studies of Peter and Rosemary Grant and others.  She finds the fatal flaw!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We see that, in the most classic example of “evolution happening before our eyes,” genetic variation was present &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; the adaptive radiation. Whether this is truly “evolution” is, then, a question worth discussing.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And just to round off a trifecta, Granville Sewell shows up, for the n-th time, summarizing his surpassingly silly old argument that there is something-like-a-Second-Law preventing chaotic physical processes from leading to adaptations, human achievements, and technology.  This latest effusion will be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://scienceandculture.com/2026/02/a-friend-asks-for-darwin-skeptics-what-does-the-second-law-argument-accomplish/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But occasionally there is a post that argues an 
important case for common sense.  On January 7 of 
this year, their house bioethicist Wesley J. Smith 
made this agonized plea:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a post on January 7, Wesley Smith wrote an impassioned plea for 
Robert F. Kennedy Jr. not to defund animal research, as he has announced he 
will do.  It will be found 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://scienceandculture.com/2026/01/for-mahas-sake-dont-eliminate-animal-experimentation/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article makes a plea for common sense.
I am in agreement, and you should be too. Here is 
a major statement of his argument:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But scientists do not engage these methodologies out of sadistic purpose. Rather, their goals are to find new medical treatments, cure diseases, and generally reduce human (and animal) suffering. Indeed, without animal research, the many medical and veterinary advances achieved since World War II would have been impossible. That is why we must think about this important moral issue and not just “feel.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is encouraging that common sense can occasionally 
prevail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;and-why-does-animal-research-work&quot;&gt;And why does animal research work?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wesley Smith does not go further into why animal 
research turns out to be useful.  Why should we expect that 
advances in understanding of human hearts might come from studying 
mammals, rather than, say, carrots?  &lt;em&gt;Because we’re 
much more closely related to mammals than to carrots&lt;/em&gt;.
There is where medical research makes use of evolutionary 
biology every day, no matter how rarely medical 
researchers talk about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can hope that Wesley Smith will ponder whether 
his friends at S&amp;amp;C are helping our understanding of humans 
by rejecting evidence for evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conspiracies&quot;&gt;Conspiracies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course there are any more issues.  Vaccines, 
anyone?  There are rampant nonsensical conspiracy 
theories saying that messenger RNA in vaccines is 
intended to kill you, or at least change who you 
vote for.  Wesley Smith’s colleagues 
at S&amp;amp;C have repeatedly described evolutionary 
biologists as deliberate liars whose basic motive is 
not to understand evolution, but to destroy 
religion.  That too is a conspiracy theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The broader right-wing movement is saturated 
with conspiracy theories, from the delusion that 
there is a Great Replacement conspiracy to the fantasy 
that the 2020 election was stolen.  RFKJr is a 
crackpot’s crackpot who is busy appointing his 
crackpot friends to HHS, to NIH, and to CDC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wesley Smith has shown that he can see clearly what 
is going on, at least in one important case.  We 
look forward to more of his honest appraisals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">A miniature pig developed for medical research. Source: Wikimedia Commons &amp;nbsp; We’re used to seeing all sorts of silliness at the Discovery Institute’s website “Science &amp;amp; Culture Today” (formerly called Evolution News). A staple of the site is an article describing how wonderfully well-adapted some feature of an organism is, with the implied conclusion that this could only have come from Design Intervention. Recent posts there have continued their tradition of being even more astonishing than that. Here are three examples: An expert on German literature, Neil Thomas, wrote on “The Monster in the Sky”: Revisiting Atheism’s Creation Myth, in which he said: My hope in this endeavor is to throw additional light on the subject of Victorians’ reception of Darwin’s Origin of Species, asking specifically what factors might explain our ancestors’ acquiescence in accepting a theory bereft of empirical documentation.” Yes, he really means that. See my earlier discussion of his views here Emily Reeves, trained in nutritional biochemistry, discovered a remarkable feature of evolutionary change. In her post Merry Christmas! No. 8 Story for 2025: Optimization and “Evolution Before Our Eyes” she reported on studies on evolutionary tradeoffs in Darwin’s Finches, using the studies of Peter and Rosemary Grant and others. She finds the fatal flaw! We see that, in the most classic example of “evolution happening before our eyes,” genetic variation was present before the adaptive radiation. Whether this is truly “evolution” is, then, a question worth discussing. And just to round off a trifecta, Granville Sewell shows up, for the n-th time, summarizing his surpassingly silly old argument that there is something-like-a-Second-Law preventing chaotic physical processes from leading to adaptations, human achievements, and technology. This latest effusion will be found here. &amp;nbsp; But occasionally there is a post that argues an important case for common sense. On January 7 of this year, their house bioethicist Wesley J. Smith made this agonized plea:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Darwin Day festivities begin today</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/02/darwin-day-festivities.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Darwin Day festivities begin today" /><published>2026-02-07T15:06:00-07:00</published><updated>2026-02-07T15:06:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/02/darwin-day-festivities</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/02/darwin-day-festivities.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2026/Charles_Darwin_1816_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chalk drawing of Charles Darwin at age 6, by Ellen Sharples.&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;Charles Darwin, age 6. &lt;small&gt;An 1816 chalk drawing of Charles Darwin at age 6, derived from: Charles and Catherine Darwin, 1816, chalk drawing by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ellen_Sharples&quot;&gt;Ellen Sharples&lt;/a&gt;. Public domain.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the National Center for Science Education, International Darwin Day, which is technically Darwin’s birthday on February 12, actually begins today in Denver. You may find a worldwide schedule &lt;a href=&quot;https://darwinday.org/events/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. A plurality of celebrations occurs on February 12, but you may find other events into April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, NCSE reminds us, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theclergyletterproject.org/rasweekend2026.html&quot;&gt;Religion and Science Weekend&lt;/a&gt; is February 13-15 and approximately coincides with Darwin Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For further details, see NCSE’s article &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/darwin-day-2026-approaches&quot;&gt;Darwin Day 2026 approaches&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Charles Darwin, age 6. An 1816 chalk drawing of Charles Darwin at age 6, derived from: Charles and Catherine Darwin, 1816, chalk drawing by Ellen Sharples. Public domain. According to the National Center for Science Education, International Darwin Day, which is technically Darwin’s birthday on February 12, actually begins today in Denver. You may find a worldwide schedule here. A plurality of celebrations occurs on February 12, but you may find other events into April. Additionally, NCSE reminds us, Religion and Science Weekend is February 13-15 and approximately coincides with Darwin Day. For further details, see NCSE’s article Darwin Day 2026 approaches.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ludwigia peruviana</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/02/ludwigia-peruviana.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ludwigia peruviana" /><published>2026-02-02T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2026-02-02T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/02/ludwigia-peruviana</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/02/ludwigia-peruviana.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Ole Lundin&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2026/lundin_Ludwigia_peruviana.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Yellow flower of Peruvian primrose-willow&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ludwigia_peruviana&quot;&gt;Ludwigia peruviana&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; Peruvian primrose-willow. Mr. Lundin submitted the picture to the 2023 Photography Contest saying, &quot;sp. unknown, found at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.visitsarasota.com/parks/lemon-bay-park-and-environmental-center&quot;&gt;Lemon Bay Park and Environmental Center&lt;/a&gt;, Englewood, Florida, April, 2012.&quot; Google Lens thinks it is &lt;i&gt;L. peruviana&lt;/i&gt;. The US Geological Survey shows the &lt;a href=&quot;https://nas.er.usgs.gov/queries/FactSheet.aspx?SpeciesID=2954&quot;&gt;range&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;i&gt;L. peruviana&lt;/i&gt; in North America to include Florida and thereabout. The plant is native to South America. Comments invited!
&lt;/figcaption&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Ole Lundin. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Ludwigia peruviana &amp;ndash; Peruvian primrose-willow. Mr. Lundin submitted the picture to the 2023 Photography Contest saying, &quot;sp. unknown, found at Lemon Bay Park and Environmental Center, Englewood, Florida, April, 2012.&quot; Google Lens thinks it is L. peruviana. The US Geological Survey shows the range of L. peruviana in North America to include Florida and thereabout. The plant is native to South America. Comments invited!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2025 – Record Low Ark Ticket Sales (and Martyn Iles’s Salary at AIG and Other Goodies)</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/01/2025-record-low-ark-ticket-sales.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2025 – Record Low Ark Ticket Sales (and Martyn Iles’s Salary at AIG and Other Goodies)" /><published>2026-01-30T10:04:00-07:00</published><updated>2026-01-30T10:04:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/01/2025-record-low-ark-ticket-sales</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/01/2025-record-low-ark-ticket-sales.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2026/Coracle_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Coracles&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2015/10/noahs-ark-was-a.html&quot;&gt;Coracles&lt;/a&gt;, probably Baghdad; what the real Noah's Ark would have looked like. &lt;small&gt;By Nile and Tigris. Journeys in Egypt and Mesopotamia on behalf of the British Museum between the years 1886 and 1913 (1920), showing coracles, or circular boats woven from reeds and sealed with pitch. Wikimedia, public domain.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to my monthly Kentucky Open Records Act (KORA) request, December Ark ticket sales were the lowest ever (with the exception of 2020 – during the Covid pandemic). In December, 2025, the Ark sold 35,223 tickets, about 4,000 less than December, 2024. Of course, these ticket sales numbers don’t include lifetime pass members or children under 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The December ticket sales number means that the Ark sold 652,342 tickets in 2025. These numbers indicate that the Ark will never come close to the 1.4 to 2.2 million attendees per year projected when the Ark was begging/shaking down Grant County, Williamstown, and Kentucky Tourism for perks including 100 acres of land for $2, $200K cash, reduced taxes, a $62 million bond, and $1.825 million/year in sales tax rebates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of massive donations, AIG and its shell companies are not in danger of collapse. They, are not, however, doing as well as in previous years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to AIG opponent, Evangelical Christian, and biologist Dr. Joel Duff, there have been layoffs recently at AIG and the Ark. See his analysis &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/VwWadriLUjc?si=kluLk88_IttXh5hc&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;: apparently, there have been numerous layoffs, retirements, and other departures from AIG.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More and more of the content on &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org&quot;&gt;AIG’s website&lt;/a&gt;, coming exclusively from Ken Ham himself. Most notably, no one appears to be a replacement for Mr. Ham if he ever retires. His onetime appointed successor, Martyn Iles, somehow ended his employment with AIG and returned to Australia to form his own conservative ministry. There have been no official reasons given for this departure by either AIG or Martyn Iles himself (if you know, let us hear about it in the comments).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although ticket sales are noticeably declining, AIG continues to build new buildings at both the Ark and the Creation Museum, and upgrade their existing infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AIG also did a large advertising campaign for the Ark in 2025. Mostly, this was in the form of television commercials featuring a family of talking giraffes that was rerun extensively on FOX News and elsewhere. According to an article that appeared in Adweek (USA) on December 22, 2025, by Brittaney Kiefer, the ad, titled “Giraffes First Time,” aired an estimated 100 times and cost $631,311.00 (thanks to NCSE’s Glenn Branch for getting me this Adweek article).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed that the corporate jet owned by Answers Collective (a for-profit controlled by AIG, funded by AIG’s “Parking Lot Ventures,” with at least two other major stockholders), was extensively refurbished in September. Apparently, a 25% share in the jet is now available for purchase, in case you need an airplane. This 8 seater jet has many amenities as detailed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aircraft.com/aircraft/198951549/n190jk-1995-cessna-citation-v-ultra&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AIG has also expanded out of Kentucky. They have partnered with a for-profit company which shows a version of the 3D virtual reality biblical show “Truth Traveler – from Eden to Eternity” in &lt;a href=&quot;https://truthtraveler.com/pigeon-forge&quot;&gt;Pigeon Forge&lt;/a&gt;, Tennessee and &lt;a href=&quot;https://truthtraveler.com/branson&quot;&gt;Branson&lt;/a&gt;, Missouri. The show apparently includes a planetarium that gives creationist explanations on how light made it from galaxies billions of light years away to earth in only 6,000 years. Although Pigeon Forge and Branson are well-known as blue-collar tourist destinations, I’m not sure how successful these creationist venues will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IRS Form 990’s ending in December, 2024, for Answers in Genesis and Crosswater Canyon (the for-profit Ark Encounter’s non-profit organization), and Twelve Stones Christian Academy (AIG’s private school located at their headquarters) are now available (late January, 2026) via &lt;a href=&quot;https://projects.propublica.org/nonprofits&quot;&gt;ProPublica&lt;/a&gt;. Alas, the IRS now redacts the identities of donors to non-profits on Form 990. These Form 990’s need to be reviewed by someone with a background in accounting and non-profit organizations. Unfortunately, Form 990 is always out of date by the time it becomes available; the 2025 Form 990 for AIG, Crosswater Canyon, and 12 Stones Academy are unlikely to be available before late January, 2027.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers in Genesis’ 2024 Form 990 indicates a surge in both revenue and expenses. Their revenue less expenses totals $17.1 million, up from $14.6 million in 2023. AIG has net assets of &amp;gt;$153.5 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2024 AIG’s Founding CEO Ken Ham earned about $267K, plus $24K in additional compensation. Executive CE Martyn Iles earned $203K plus $9.2K in additional compensation. It is still unclear what he actually did for AIG. Ham and AIG might have the same question. You can see other top salaries on Form 990 itself. Interestingly, at least five members of the Ham family are on the payroll (Schedule L, Part IV).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crosswater Canyon’s Form 990 indicates $11.75 million net for 2024. The organization has a net worth &amp;gt;$82 million. After depreciation, the Ark Encounter and other buildings on the Ark property are valued in Part X as $115,649,125. Yet, the Grant County PVA office values the Ark for tax purposes at only $48 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to 12 Stones Academy’s Form 990, the school lost more than $1.7 million in 2024 and now has a net assets or fund balance of –$2.9 million. I guess, given this financial crisis, along with their anti-science teachings, that it is a good thing they aren’t in charge of Kentucky education (at least not yet).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ken Ham has acknowledged at least some attendance problems in 2025 and notes that visits to his “boat” and “museum” are down because of “will previous years’ economic impact. During a 2025 fundraiser, AIG raised more than $10 million with a $10 million matching fund, totaling more than $20 million. Ham’s admission of attendance problems can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2025/11/15/god-working-these-unprecedented-times/&quot;&gt;here &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Coracles, probably Baghdad; what the real Noah's Ark would have looked like. By Nile and Tigris. Journeys in Egypt and Mesopotamia on behalf of the British Museum between the years 1886 and 1913 (1920), showing coracles, or circular boats woven from reeds and sealed with pitch. Wikimedia, public domain. According to my monthly Kentucky Open Records Act (KORA) request, December Ark ticket sales were the lowest ever (with the exception of 2020 – during the Covid pandemic). In December, 2025, the Ark sold 35,223 tickets, about 4,000 less than December, 2024. Of course, these ticket sales numbers don’t include lifetime pass members or children under 10. The December ticket sales number means that the Ark sold 652,342 tickets in 2025. These numbers indicate that the Ark will never come close to the 1.4 to 2.2 million attendees per year projected when the Ark was begging/shaking down Grant County, Williamstown, and Kentucky Tourism for perks including 100 acres of land for $2, $200K cash, reduced taxes, a $62 million bond, and $1.825 million/year in sales tax rebates. Because of massive donations, AIG and its shell companies are not in danger of collapse. They, are not, however, doing as well as in previous years. According to AIG opponent, Evangelical Christian, and biologist Dr. Joel Duff, there have been layoffs recently at AIG and the Ark. See his analysis here: apparently, there have been numerous layoffs, retirements, and other departures from AIG.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Killing the Golden Goose: article in Righting America</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/01/killing-golden-goose.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Killing the Golden Goose: article in Righting America" /><published>2026-01-21T15:18:00-07:00</published><updated>2026-01-21T15:18:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/01/killing-golden-goose</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/01/killing-golden-goose.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2026/Goose_Golden_Eggs_Aesop.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;From The Æsop for Children, by Æsop, illustrated by Milo Winter, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gutenberg.org/etext/19994&quot;&gt;Project Gutenberg etext 19994&lt;/a&gt;, public domain.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just a short note, with no comment, to alert our readers to a splendid article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/killing-the-golden-goose-evangelicals-trump-and-the-war-on-science/&quot;&gt;Killing the Golden Goose: Evangelicals, Trump, and the War on Science&lt;/a&gt;, by Rodney Kennedy. Dr. Kennedy is a writer and was formerly pastor at the First Baptist Church of Dayton, an American Baptist Church, and several other churches. His article is hosted by &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/&quot;&gt;Righting America&lt;/a&gt;, which is a forum for scholarly conversation run by William Trollinger and Susan Trollinger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In brief, Kennedy argues that science is the goose that laid the golden eggs and made America prosperous. Evangelicals, he says, have targeted science for over a century. But now something has changed, and conservative evangelicals allied with Donald Trump have taken direct aim at the entire scientific enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kennedy outlines “only a few of [Robert F.] Kennedy’s devastating moves,” “Trump’s disastrous handling of the pandemic,” and how “[s]cience before MAGA [made America] the greatest scientific nation in the world.” As a result, he says, scientists are desperate to find jobs in Europe, Canada, and elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To comment on this article, click on its title, which will bring up the article on its own page, with its Disqus comments section after the post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">From The Æsop for Children, by Æsop, illustrated by Milo Winter, Project Gutenberg etext 19994, public domain. This is just a short note, with no comment, to alert our readers to a splendid article, Killing the Golden Goose: Evangelicals, Trump, and the War on Science, by Rodney Kennedy. Dr. Kennedy is a writer and was formerly pastor at the First Baptist Church of Dayton, an American Baptist Church, and several other churches. His article is hosted by Righting America, which is a forum for scholarly conversation run by William Trollinger and Susan Trollinger. In brief, Kennedy argues that science is the goose that laid the golden eggs and made America prosperous. Evangelicals, he says, have targeted science for over a century. But now something has changed, and conservative evangelicals allied with Donald Trump have taken direct aim at the entire scientific enterprise. Kennedy outlines “only a few of [Robert F.] Kennedy’s devastating moves,” “Trump’s disastrous handling of the pandemic,” and how “[s]cience before MAGA [made America] the greatest scientific nation in the world.” As a result, he says, scientists are desperate to find jobs in Europe, Canada, and elsewhere. &amp;nbsp; To comment on this article, click on its title, which will bring up the article on its own page, with its Disqus comments section after the post.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Taygete decemmaculella</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/01/taygete-decemmaculella.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Taygete decemmaculella" /><published>2026-01-19T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2026-01-19T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/01/taygete-decemmaculella</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/01/taygete-decemmaculella.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2026/DSC06038_Moth_Taygete_decemmaculella_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Moth: Taygete decemmaculella&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.butterfliesandmoths.org/species/Taygete-decemmaculella&quot;&gt;Taygete decemmaculella&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;, Boulder, Colorado, July17, 2025. Found inside house. I have no idea whether this moth is rare, but Butterflies and Moths of North America (the link above) shows only a handful of sightings and none in Colorado.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Taygete decemmaculella, Boulder, Colorado, July17, 2025. Found inside house. I have no idea whether this moth is rare, but Butterflies and Moths of North America (the link above) shows only a handful of sightings and none in Colorado.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From Groundwater Grift to Comet Claptrap: Allen Whitt and 20 Years of Cosmic Confusion</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/01/from-groundwater-grift.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Groundwater Grift to Comet Claptrap: Allen Whitt and 20 Years of Cosmic Confusion" /><published>2026-01-07T20:07:00-07:00</published><updated>2026-01-07T20:07:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/01/from-groundwater-grift</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/01/from-groundwater-grift.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2026/Boslough_Sodom_Frontispiece.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Windmill and wind-shaped tree located 5.5 miles (8.8 km) north of the small community of Bellview, Curry County, Eastern New Mexico.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Curry_County_Eastern_New_Mexico_2010.jpg&quot;&gt;Curry County Eastern New Mexico 2010&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;small&gt;Photograph by &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Leaflet&quot;&gt;Leaflet&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/deed.en&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 3.0 Unported.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Mark Boslough is a Research Associate Professor at the University of New Mexico. For a short biography, see the first link below.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2006 new-age book, “Cycle of Cosmic Catastrophes,” introduced what is now called the Younger Dryas impact Hypothesis (often abbreviated as “YDIH”). The lead author was Richard Firestone, a nuclear chemist at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, who had dabbled in alternative archaeology and speculations about cosmic catastrophes caused by supernovas and interstellar comets. Allen West, the second author, was entirely unknown, and there is no record of his existence before 2006. He wrote most of the book in the first person. The third author, Simon Warwick-Smith, appears to have been West’s publicist, whose main contribution was to spice up his prose. The 2nd printing of the book came out on June 5, 2006, and included better graphics and some other changes, including the addition of “PhD” to West’s name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month, as the 20th anniversary of this book approached, I spent some time trying to learn more about West’s background and qualifications. What led him to the prominent leadership role as sample collector and preparer, protocol developer, drafter of data graphs, interpreter of virtually all the evidence on which the YDIH is based, and corresponding author on many of their papers?  How did he emerge, seemingly from nowhere, to become the primary founder and director of the Comet Research Group, which describes itself as a group of more than 63 scientists from more than 55 universities in more than 26 countries? How did he form a collaboration with biblical literalists and publish their most widely reported (but now retracted) &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/04/retraction-biblical-literalist.html&quot;&gt;Sodom comet paper&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had already learned that West had changed his name from Allen Whitt in 2006 after being convicted in California of a crime associated with fraudulent groundwater survey reports in 1998, but I was never able to lay my hands on his sham reports to see for myself what was wrong with them. Last month, I ran across a USGS report that cited two previous groundwater reports that he had written in 1997, and I was able to check them out from the library of the state engineer in New Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also found public records with Allen Whitt’s name associated with earlier lawsuits involving new age businesses, which might shed some light on how he made the transition from purveyor of Sedona woo, to groundwater grifter, to the most prominent and visible member of a group of scientists that claims to have overturned paradigms in multiple established fields, including geology, archaeology, planetary science, impact physics, and paleontology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have started a blog series in which I will describe the trail of documents he has published, including the groundwater reports, his new age book, and his peer-reviewed papers. The first installment is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.boslough.us/blog/the-younger-dryas-impact-hypothesis-at-20-years&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Comments can be made at that blog, and also here. To make them here, click on the title of this post, and the area for comments will appear on that page.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mark Boslough</name></author><summary type="html">Curry County Eastern New Mexico 2010. Photograph by Leaflet. Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 3.0 Unported. Mark Boslough is a Research Associate Professor at the University of New Mexico. For a short biography, see the first link below. The 2006 new-age book, “Cycle of Cosmic Catastrophes,” introduced what is now called the Younger Dryas impact Hypothesis (often abbreviated as “YDIH”). The lead author was Richard Firestone, a nuclear chemist at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, who had dabbled in alternative archaeology and speculations about cosmic catastrophes caused by supernovas and interstellar comets. Allen West, the second author, was entirely unknown, and there is no record of his existence before 2006. He wrote most of the book in the first person. The third author, Simon Warwick-Smith, appears to have been West’s publicist, whose main contribution was to spice up his prose. The 2nd printing of the book came out on June 5, 2006, and included better graphics and some other changes, including the addition of “PhD” to West’s name. Last month, as the 20th anniversary of this book approached, I spent some time trying to learn more about West’s background and qualifications. What led him to the prominent leadership role as sample collector and preparer, protocol developer, drafter of data graphs, interpreter of virtually all the evidence on which the YDIH is based, and corresponding author on many of their papers? How did he emerge, seemingly from nowhere, to become the primary founder and director of the Comet Research Group, which describes itself as a group of more than 63 scientists from more than 55 universities in more than 26 countries? How did he form a collaboration with biblical literalists and publish their most widely reported (but now retracted) Sodom comet paper? I had already learned that West had changed his name from Allen Whitt in 2006 after being convicted in California of a crime associated with fraudulent groundwater survey reports in 1998, but I was never able to lay my hands on his sham reports to see for myself what was wrong with them. Last month, I ran across a USGS report that cited two previous groundwater reports that he had written in 1997, and I was able to check them out from the library of the state engineer in New Mexico. I’ve also found public records with Allen Whitt’s name associated with earlier lawsuits involving new age businesses, which might shed some light on how he made the transition from purveyor of Sedona woo, to groundwater grifter, to the most prominent and visible member of a group of scientists that claims to have overturned paradigms in multiple established fields, including geology, archaeology, planetary science, impact physics, and paleontology. I have started a blog series in which I will describe the trail of documents he has published, including the groundwater reports, his new age book, and his peer-reviewed papers. The first installment is here. &amp;nbsp; Comments can be made at that blog, and also here. To make them here, click on the title of this post, and the area for comments will appear on that page.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dryocopus pileatus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/01/dryocopus-pileatus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dryocopus pileatus" /><published>2026-01-05T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2026-01-05T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/01/dryocopus-pileatus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/01/dryocopus-pileatus.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Joel Eissenberg&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2026/Eissenberg Dryocopus pileatus.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pileated woodpecker&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Pileated_Woodpecker/overview#&quot;&gt;Dryocopus pileatus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; (male) pileated woodpecker, Ten Mile River Greenway, Rumford, R.I. Mr. Eissenberg writes, &quot;Pileated woodpeckers not only feed on grubs and other insects in rotting wood, they also carve meticulously sculpted nesting holes in the sides of dead trees. These birds make a strong visual case for the dinosaurian origin of birds!&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Joel Eissenberg. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Dryocopus pileatus &amp;ndash; (male) pileated woodpecker, Ten Mile River Greenway, Rumford, R.I. Mr. Eissenberg writes, &quot;Pileated woodpeckers not only feed on grubs and other insects in rotting wood, they also carve meticulously sculpted nesting holes in the sides of dead trees. These birds make a strong visual case for the dinosaurian origin of birds!&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Measles at the Ark</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/01/measles-at-the-ark.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Measles at the Ark" /><published>2026-01-01T21:26:00-07:00</published><updated>2026-01-01T21:26:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/01/measles-at-the-ark</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2026/01/measles-at-the-ark.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2026/Measles_Public_Exposure_Phelps.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Data&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today (1/1/26) the Kentucky Department for Public Health announced that an unvaccinated, out-of-state individual with measles visited the Ark Encounter in Williamstown, Kentucky, on December 29, 2025. Local and regional health departments are scrambling to warn and inform the public.
See this &lt;a href=&quot;https://local12.com/news/local/measles-exposure-alert-issued-northern-kentucky-ark-encounter-unvaccinated-public-health-high-risk-doctors&quot;&gt;local news story&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually laugh heartily at the buffoonery and ignorance associated with the Ark.  This latest news, however, is just sad. I can’t laugh. Anti-science is putting large numbers of people in danger, not just anti-vaxx clowns. If not for the known views of the people running the Ark, one could argue this latest news is an excusable random event. Alas, the audience for the Ark Encounter and its leadership are dominated by anti-science and anti-vaccination advocates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Covid pandemic and lockdown, Ken Ham railed against mask mandates, was involved in &lt;a href=&quot;https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/appellate-courts/ca6/21-4032/21-4032-2021-12-17.html#:~:text=Justia%20%E2%80%BA%20U.S.%20Law%20%E2%80%BA%20Case%20Law,61402/&quot;&gt;lawsuits against OSHA vaccine requirements&lt;/a&gt; and was ambivalent about vaccines. When writing about vaccine mandates and Covid lockdowns, Mr. Ham &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/ministry-news/essential-ministry-christian-liberty-suing-caesar/?srsltid=AfmBOoqck1Xfm_mm3hETsNKz0uhrMTzi8l1rezfRtoSi_Gua0tXiUeJF/&quot;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Certainly, people died from the virus, although I think we are all confused at what the actual statistics are. People die every day from all sorts of diseases. But once a person dies, God’s Word tells us they will spend eternity in heaven or hell. So how essential is the church, the body of Christ (of which AiG is a part of), for people’s well-being? It is vital.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several prominent creationists died of Covid during the height of the pandemic. Dr. David Menton of AiG definitely &lt;a href=&quot;https://obituaries.mankatofreepress.com/obituary/david-menton-1084014808/&quot;&gt;died of Covid&lt;/a&gt;. It is very likely that Ark Park designer Patrick Marsh died of the same cause. Henry Morris Ill, of the Institute for Creation Research also &lt;a href=&quot;https://thecreationclub.com/announcing-the-passing-of-dr-henry-morris-iii/&quot;&gt;died of Covid&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a good thing attendance at the Ark is so low this time of year and the public’s measles exposure is minimal. Hopefully, Ark tourists, employees, and Williamstown and Grant County locals will be warned about this exposure. Unfortunately, as of 6 pm January 1, 2026, neither Answers in Genesis nor Ark Encounter have mentioned this measles case on their websites or on their numerous social media accounts. Ken Ham was on his Facebook and “X” accounts today, but only posted about Zohran Mamdani and various religious topics, nothing warning about the measles case at the Ark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, many local media and public health offices have announced the measles case.  We will have to see if there are further cases of measles by tourists or Ark employees in the coming days.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Today (1/1/26) the Kentucky Department for Public Health announced that an unvaccinated, out-of-state individual with measles visited the Ark Encounter in Williamstown, Kentucky, on December 29, 2025. Local and regional health departments are scrambling to warn and inform the public. See this local news story. I usually laugh heartily at the buffoonery and ignorance associated with the Ark. This latest news, however, is just sad. I can’t laugh. Anti-science is putting large numbers of people in danger, not just anti-vaxx clowns. If not for the known views of the people running the Ark, one could argue this latest news is an excusable random event. Alas, the audience for the Ark Encounter and its leadership are dominated by anti-science and anti-vaccination advocates. During the Covid pandemic and lockdown, Ken Ham railed against mask mandates, was involved in lawsuits against OSHA vaccine requirements and was ambivalent about vaccines. When writing about vaccine mandates and Covid lockdowns, Mr. Ham said: Certainly, people died from the virus, although I think we are all confused at what the actual statistics are. People die every day from all sorts of diseases. But once a person dies, God’s Word tells us they will spend eternity in heaven or hell. So how essential is the church, the body of Christ (of which AiG is a part of), for people’s well-being? It is vital. Several prominent creationists died of Covid during the height of the pandemic. Dr. David Menton of AiG definitely died of Covid. It is very likely that Ark Park designer Patrick Marsh died of the same cause. Henry Morris Ill, of the Institute for Creation Research also died of Covid. It is a good thing attendance at the Ark is so low this time of year and the public’s measles exposure is minimal. Hopefully, Ark tourists, employees, and Williamstown and Grant County locals will be warned about this exposure. Unfortunately, as of 6 pm January 1, 2026, neither Answers in Genesis nor Ark Encounter have mentioned this measles case on their websites or on their numerous social media accounts. Ken Ham was on his Facebook and “X” accounts today, but only posted about Zohran Mamdani and various religious topics, nothing warning about the measles case at the Ark. Fortunately, many local media and public health offices have announced the measles case. We will have to see if there are further cases of measles by tourists or Ark employees in the coming days.</summary></entry></feed>