<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-12-15T19:46:51-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Breakthrough for Intelligent Design? (Part 6)</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/erkell6.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breakthrough for Intelligent Design? (Part 6)" /><published>2022-12-14T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-14T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/erkell6</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/erkell6.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Biologg_Banner_900.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Biolog(g) banner&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The text is a pun in Swedish: &quot;Logg&quot; means something like a ship´s log or a logbook.&lt;br /&gt; A blog is &quot;blogg&quot;. 
 So &quot;Biolog(g)&quot; is a biologist´s log or blog.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is part 6 of a series of 7 posts by Lars Johan Erkell, with comments on each by Ola Hössjer and a reply by Erkell.  Part 1 will be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PandasThumb/pandasthumb.github.io/edit/source/_posts/2022/2022-11-09-erkell1.md&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  They are translations of &lt;a href=&quot;https://biologg.wordpress.com/2020/11/13/genombrott-for-intelligent-design-del-3/&quot;&gt;2020 posts in Swedish&lt;/a&gt; from the Biolog(g) blog of the Department of Biology of Gothenburg University.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;breakthrough-for-intelligent-design-part-6&quot;&gt;Breakthrough for Intelligent design? (part 6)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;November 13, 2020&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Lars Johan Erkell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why was this article written?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I hope has become clear, Thorvaldsen and Hössjer’s article does not
meet the requirements that one reasonably could expect from a scientific
publication. It pretends to have results that do not exist. The article
relies entirely on a statistical method to demonstrate designs that is
useless. It contains references to an indeterminate supernatural designer
that is resorted to &lt;em&gt;ad hoc&lt;/em&gt; to achieve desired results. It introduces the
completely revolutionary concept of &quot;non-physical information&quot; without
definition or discussion. It contains a grossly garbled quote. In
addition, well-known pseudoscientific concepts such as &quot;irreducible
complexity&quot; and &quot;specified complexity&quot; are referred to as if they were
established science. This cannot be called science. It can only be called
pseudoscience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, Thorvaldsen and Hössjer have received criticism. Three biologists write in a comment to the Journal of Theoretical Biology, among other things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… The central claim of this paper is that because biological systems are complex then they must be fine-tuned. This inference is flawed and is not supported by the evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor is the mathematician Jason Rosenhaus gracious in his criticism. He concludes thus:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… The authors claim to have used probability theory to establish a scientifically rigorous and useful notion of “fine-tuning,” but they have failed because we have nothing like the information we would need to carry out meaningful probability calculations. Done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I don’t think I’ve adequately communicated just how bad this paper is. The authors are constantly tossing out bits of mathematical jargon and notation, but then they do nothing with them. There is a frustrating lack of precision, as when they variously describe fine-tuning as an object, an entity, a method, and an attribute of a system, all on the first page of the paper. They constantly cite creationist references, with only the most glancing mention that any of this work has been strongly and cogently criticized. They say we should give fair consideration to a “design model” for the origin of complex structures, but they do not give the beginning of a clue as to what such a model entails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, it’s hard to believe this paper could have gotten through an honest peer-review process (as opposed to one in which ideology played a big role). Whatever happened behind the scenes, it’s a huge black eye for the journal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review is worth reading in its entirety. It also covers things I didn’t cover here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steinar Thorvaldsen is Professor of Information Science at Norway's
Arctic University in Tromsø and Ola Hössjer is Professor of Mathematical
Statistics at Stockholm University. They are both established professors
at reputable universities. I find it hard to imagine that they would
write papers of this poor quality in their own fields (I also doubt they
would get away with it). So why have they written this article? As
experienced and competent researchers, they must reasonably be aware of
the article's devastating scientific flaws. Why are they willing to risk
name and reputation to write an article that makes me and many colleagues
facepalm and wonder what has gotten into the authors? This is not
something you expect from a professor at a respected university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My guess is that they see it as their task to spearhead a new kind of science that includes a designer, and that they feel is not limited by the materialism that characterizes established natural science. The idea of “Intelligent Design” as an alternative, non-materialistic science was launched in the USA in the 1990s by the conservative Christian think tank Discovery Institute. The institute’s agenda was revealed in 1999 when the policy document The Wedge Document was leaked and posted on the Internet. It appears that they see “materialism” and moral relativism as the cause of all evil in society. Materialism must therefore be crushed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Discovery Institute’s Center for the Renewal of Science and Culture seeks nothing less than the overthrow of materialism and its cultural legacies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important part of materialism is today’s natural science, and therefore is an overarching goal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To replace materialistic explanations with the theistic understanding that nature and human beings are created by God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design theory has been created to replace materialistic science:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Design theory promises to reverse the stifling dominance of the materialist worldview, and to replace it with a science consonant with Christian and theistic convictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The document shows very clearly that the ID project is a
political/religious project; it is about working for a society that is
completely imbued with a Christian religiosity. A theocracy, in other
words. Natural science is &quot;materialistic&quot; and therefore stands in the
way. Therefore, it must be replaced by a religiously based design
science.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; In case any reader should think that I am presenting conspiracy
theories, I would recommend a careful reading of the document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This explains why ID continues to be pursued as a science even though the
project is completely sterile - in more than 20 years it has failed to
produce a single solid result that concretely demonstrates design in
nature. On the other hand, mountains of material have been produced that
criticize established natural science in general and the theory of
evolution in particular. The goal of the activity is not primarily to
convince the researchers; it is to convince the public and decision-
makers at various levels that design theory is better science than the
established, materialistic, natural science. The document shows that the
strategy is to defeat science in the political arena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does all this have to do with Steinar Thorvaldsen and Ola
Hössjer? It turns out that they are both connected to the Norwegian
foundation BioCosmos, Thorvaldsen as chairman of the board and Hössjer as
&quot;ambassador&quot;. BioCosmos aims to spread Intelligent Design, primarily to
youth and young adults, and is Norwegian partner of the Discovery
Institute. This article falls into the same pattern as countless other
pro-ID articles: it is clearly written to give the impression that ID is
a legitimate scientific theory, it contains no results, but many
arguments against the theory of evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are Thorvaldsen and Hössjer aware that they are participating in a
crusade against natural science? They should, as professional scientists,
be aware that ID is a pseudo-scientific, indeed anti-scientific, project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the case may be, it is sad that two such competent and meritorious researchers are unable to live up to the scientific integrity one has the right to expect from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;English Wikipedia has a comprehensive and informative series on ID. See also:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara Forrest: Understanding the Intelligent Design Creationist Movement: Its True Nature and Goal. Center for Inquiry (2007)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lenny Flank: Deception by Design: The Intelligent Design Movement in America. Red and Black Publishers (2009)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comment by Ola Hössjer&lt;/strong&gt;
June 29, 2021 4:05 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 6: Why was the fine-tuning article written?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In part 6, Erkell continues and asks what prompted me and Thorvaldsen to
write the article on fine-tuning. I quote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Steinar Thorvaldsen is Professor of Information Science at Norway's
Arctic University in Tromsø and Ola Hössjer is Professor of Mathematical
Statistics at Stockholm University. They are both established professors
at reputable universities. I find it hard to imagine that they would
write papers of this poor quality in their own fields (I also doubt they
would get away with it). So why have they written this article? As
experienced and competent researchers, they must reasonably be aware of
the article's devastating scientific flaws. Why are they willing to risk
name and reputation to write an article that makes me and many colleagues
facepalm and wonder what has gotten into the authors? This is not
something you expect from a professor at a respected university. My guess
is that they see it as their task to spearhead a new kind of science that
includes a designer, and that they feel is not limited by the materialism
that characterizes established natural science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In parts 1-5 I responded to Erkell’s claims that TH2020 is a
pseudoscientific article of poor quality. Let me therefore answer
Erkell's question why I have been involved in writing this and other
articles with an ID-based or creationist focus. There are two main
reasons. Firstly, I have been part of the academic community since I
started studying university mathematics at the age of 15. This long
period taught me a lot about how (empirical) science should be conducted.
I advocate academic freedom, where all relevant theories are allowed to
take part and compete on equal footing in terms of providing the best
explanations of data, in the search for the truth. For more than 20
years, I have studied genetics and evolutionary biology, and found that
Darwin's theory of evolution contains crucial flaws that are rarely
mentioned, neither in school nor at universities. It is my duty as a
scientist (part of the third task) to engage in the public sphere and
spread the experiences that I have acquired, both from my own research
and by learning from the research of others. My conscience therefore
urges me to enter the evolution-design debate, and this is more important
than political correctness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, all empirical science is based on faith assumptions. All attempts
to let only empirical data guide natural science (such as logical
positivism) have failed. These beliefs are especially important for
questions of origin, because we cannot replicate through repeated
experiments how life arose, or how the diversity of life between
different species came about. Therefore, every researcher who engages in
origin issues will be more or less guided by their starting assumptions
and beliefs. So am I. I accepted Jesus Christ as my personal Savior and
Lord, at the age of 23-24, and over the years I have realized more and
more how trustworthy and reliable the Bible is. I am therefore convinced
that design-inspired or biblically inspired (and falsifiable) models
provide the best explanation for genetic, geological and morphological
data. But I don't want to force these explanations on others, but let the
ID and creationist models compete with secular models on equal terms.
With sadness in my heart I notice how methodological naturalism has
gradually narrowed (and forced) science into a secular direction ever
since the 18th century. This has to a large extent, driven development of
society in a materialistic direction. And the theory of evolution has had
a decisive role in this process, because it is the creation story of
naturalism, and thus influences many other sciences. If neither God nor
anything else supernatural exists, then everything must have arisen by
itself, just as the theory of evolution claims. This is precisely why it
is so sensitive to criticize the theory of evolution, of which Erkell's
article series is a typical example. To criticize the theory of evolution
is simply to question the foundations of a worldview that dominates a
secular culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Erkell’s opening question about what prompted me and Thorvaldsen to
write the fine-tuning article, he goes on to discuss an American ID think
tank, the Discovery Institute, and its efforts to influence societal
development away from materialism. The reason is that both Thorvaldsen
and myself have been involved in a Norwegian think tank that is positive
about ID:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But what does all this have to do with Steinar Thorvaldsen and Ola
Hössjer? It turns out that they are both connected to the Norwegian
foundation BioCosmos, Thorvaldsen as chairman of the board and Hössjer as
&quot;ambassador&quot;. BioCosmos aims to spread Intelligent Design, primarily to
youth and young adults, and is Norwegian partner of the Discovery
Institute. This article falls into the same pattern as countless other
pro-ID articles: it is clearly written to give the impression that ID is
a legitimate scientific theory, it contains no results, but many
arguments against the theory of evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Are Thorvaldsen and Hössjer aware that they are participating in a
crusade against natural science? They should, as professional scientists,
be aware that ID is a pseudo-scientific, indeed anti-scientific,
project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already argued (in Parts 1-5) that ID and creationism are science, and
I will therefore not repeat my arguments in parts 1-5. I will content
myself by saying that I neither consider TH2020 to be an example of
pseudo-science or anti-science. But Erkell;s claims are not
surprising, since he very strongly advocates methodological naturalism,
that is, secular science. From Erkell's point of view, a crusade against
natural science is the same as a crusade against secular natural science.
As I have stressed in this series of articles, I believe that biblically
inspired models and design-inspired models very often have much better
explanatory power than the corresponding secular models. But since I
don’t want to force others to take this approach, it’s hardly a
crusade. One can rather ask the question whether Erkell is waging a
crusade against all science that does not start from methodological
naturalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reply by Lars Johan Erkell&lt;/strong&gt;
September 8, 2021 7:21 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I discuss the possible motivations of the article authors.
In your reply, you write: &quot;For more than 20 years, I have studied
genetics and evolutionary biology, and found that Darwin's theory of
development contains crucial flaws that are rarely mentioned, neither in
school nor at university.&quot; From what you write, I suspect that you have
drawn your knowledge from creationist sources rather than from university
courses. The formulation of &quot;crucial flaws rarely mentioned&quot; is a classic
creationist theme. But there is no science that is complete or perfect;
there are gaps and &quot;critical deficiencies&quot; in all fields of science.
However, creationists are most interested in the flaws they see in
evolutionary biology. This fact that the flaws are &quot;rarely mentioned&quot; and
your talk of &quot;political correctness&quot; also connects to a well-known
creationist theme: the atheist scientists who completely dominate science
and try to stifle all opposition to the theory of evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe you have misunderstood your duties as a scientist when it comes
to engagement in the public sphere. The university pays you to present 
the science and scientific view that the university stands for, not for
you to present a scientific view (and a view of evolutionary biology)
that the university does not stand for. As a researcher, you certainly
have a lot of freedom to choose different perspectives, but I think you
are probably crossing the line here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You write that &quot;It is with sadness in my heart that I see how
methodological naturalism has gradually narrowed (and forced) science
into a secular direction since the 18th century&quot;, and here I think we
have come to the heart of the matter. You see an ideological struggle
between two cultures, one secular and the other spiritual. I, on the
other hand, see a successful, secular, research program replacing a
sterile, spiritual, program. Materialistic research has gradually
replaced research on a non-materialistic basis because it actually works
and produces results. I have never seen any example of successful natural
science on a spiritual/religious basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as I write in the seventh post in the series, I could imagine an ID-inspired 
research if it produced concrete results. But we are not there.
All you can offer are assurances that an ID-inspired research will open
up to new advances by freeing science from materialistic lock-ins.
However, I can't see any signs that this could be the case. I discuss
this further in the post &lt;a href=&quot;2016-11-16-erkell8.md&quot;&gt;&quot;Science, hypotheses and Intelligent Design&quot;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You avoid perhaps the most serious part of my criticism, namely that the
ID project is fundamentally not about science but is a
political/religious project aimed at building a society completely imbued
with Christian religiosity - a theocracy. Do you have any comment on
that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lars Johan Erkell (with comment by Ola Hössjer)</name></author><summary type="html">The text is a pun in Swedish: &quot;Logg&quot; means something like a ship´s log or a logbook. A blog is &quot;blogg&quot;. So &quot;Biolog(g)&quot; is a biologist´s log or blog. &amp;nbsp; This is part 6 of a series of 7 posts by Lars Johan Erkell, with comments on each by Ola Hössjer and a reply by Erkell. Part 1 will be found here. They are translations of 2020 posts in Swedish from the Biolog(g) blog of the Department of Biology of Gothenburg University. &amp;nbsp; Breakthrough for Intelligent design? (part 6) November 13, 2020 by Lars Johan Erkell Why was this article written? As I hope has become clear, Thorvaldsen and Hössjer’s article does not meet the requirements that one reasonably could expect from a scientific publication. It pretends to have results that do not exist. The article relies entirely on a statistical method to demonstrate designs that is useless. It contains references to an indeterminate supernatural designer that is resorted to ad hoc to achieve desired results. It introduces the completely revolutionary concept of &quot;non-physical information&quot; without definition or discussion. It contains a grossly garbled quote. In addition, well-known pseudoscientific concepts such as &quot;irreducible complexity&quot; and &quot;specified complexity&quot; are referred to as if they were established science. This cannot be called science. It can only be called pseudoscience.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Inaugural address of creationist biology professor</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/inagural-address-creationist.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inaugural address of creationist biology professor" /><published>2022-12-07T18:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T18:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/inagural-address-creationist</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/inagural-address-creationist.html">&lt;p&gt;I have just watched the “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=coJY7emvclY&quot;&gt;inaugural address&lt;/a&gt;” of Richard Buggs, a biology professor at Queen Mary University of London. According to Jerry Coyne, Prof. Buggs is “&lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2021/03/08/a-creationist-professor-of-evolutionary-biology-in-england/&quot;&gt;A creationist professor of evolutionary biology in England&lt;/a&gt;.” Professor Buggs’s lecture was entitled “Trees of life: Do they exist?” The trees in question are those tall, leafy things that we like to lie under, the Darwinian tree of life, and the Biblical tree of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Buggs is amiable, and the lecture was very clear and easy to follow. He uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-022-28312-w&quot;&gt;this figure&lt;/a&gt; by Andre S. Chanderbali and colleagues to suggest that evolutionary trees do not really exist:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Buggs_Chandervali_Fig_2b_1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cloudogram&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Superposition of phylogenetic trees, or cloudogram, Figure 2(b) of paper by Chandervali and colleagues.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my untutored eye, the figure, called a &lt;i&gt;cloudogram&lt;/i&gt;, looks like an evolutionary tree with a great deal of noise, but that is probably no more than an artifact of my background in error analysis. The paper in which it appears is largely unintelligible to me, but it is clear that the authors were not aghast when they saw the figure and did not think that it posed any problems for evolution. A pen pal informs me that the figure combines nonoverlapping trees from a number of species representing groups with different histories, so presumably no conclusion about evolution may be drawn. Indeed, my pen pal adds, “actually some very good phylogenetic trees of chromosomes are in the same paper, and those are the important ones the authors refer to,” for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Buggs_Chandervali_Fig_3b_1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Phylogenetic tree&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Single, unambiguous phylogenetic tree, detail of Figure 3(b) of paper by Chandervali and colleagues.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twenty-odd minutes in, Prof. Buggs comes very close to suggesting that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flowering_plant&quot;&gt;angiosperms&lt;/a&gt; – flowering plants – have no common ancestor, from which we are left to infer that they were created &lt;i&gt;de novo&lt;/i&gt;. According to Wikipedia, the origin of angiosperms is “contentious,” but that is no reason to hint at a God-of-the-gaps argument. With apologies to &lt;a href=&quot;https://quotepark.com/quotes/1891929/history/&quot;&gt;whoever wrote the original&lt;/a&gt;, I immediately thought&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;How odd&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of God&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To tease&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With trees. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Late in the lecture, around 53 min, Prof. Buggs notes some miracles supposedly performed by Jesus of Nazareth and catalogued in the Book of Revelation. He argues that the miracles must be veridical, or Christianity would not have spread so wildly. Such a claim, if not disingenuous, is at least wholly inconsistent with the wild spreading of disinformation in our era or of “heresies” in earlier eras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will not go into detail, but Prof. Buggs suggests that the Christians on the western Turkish coast must have verified the miracles by talking to witnesses. I do not mean to be catty, but I am afraid they could not exactly have hopped on their donkeys and flown to Jerusalem to search for witnesses. In an earlier article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2009/07/francis-collins-3.html&quot;&gt;Francis Collins and the god of the gaps&lt;/a&gt;, I noted that Dr. Collins seemed very credulous when it came to his religious beliefs. Professor Buggs is in good company and comes across as at least equally credulous and perhaps less than critical in his thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But watch the video for yourself and let us know your opinion in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I have just watched the “inaugural address” of Richard Buggs, a biology professor at Queen Mary University of London. According to Jerry Coyne, Prof. Buggs is “A creationist professor of evolutionary biology in England.” Professor Buggs’s lecture was entitled “Trees of life: Do they exist?” The trees in question are those tall, leafy things that we like to lie under, the Darwinian tree of life, and the Biblical tree of life. Professor Buggs is amiable, and the lecture was very clear and easy to follow. He uses this figure by Andre S. Chanderbali and colleagues to suggest that evolutionary trees do not really exist:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breakthrough for Intelligent Design? (Part 5)</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/erkell5.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breakthrough for Intelligent Design? (Part 5)" /><published>2022-12-07T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-07T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/erkell5</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/erkell5.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Biologg_Banner_900.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Biolog(g) banner&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The text is a pun in Swedish: &quot;Logg&quot; means something like a ship´s log or a logbook.&lt;br /&gt; A blog is &quot;blogg&quot;. 
 So &quot;Biolog(g)&quot; is a biologist´s log or blog.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is part 5 of a series of 7 posts by Lars Johan Erkell, with comments on each by Ola Hössjer and a reply by Erkell.  Part 1 will be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PandasThumb/pandasthumb.github.io/edit/source/_posts/2022/2022-11-09-erkell1.md&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  They are translations of &lt;a href=&quot;https://biologg.wordpress.com/2020/11/13/genombrott-for-intelligent-design-del-3/&quot;&gt;2020 posts in Swedish&lt;/a&gt; from the Biolog(g) blog of the Department of Biology of Gothenburg University.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;breakthrough-for-intelligent-design-part-5&quot;&gt;Breakthrough for Intelligent design? (part 5)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;November 13, 2020&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Lars Johan Erkell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why is ID not seen as science?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this series of blog posts, I have repeatedly criticized Thorvaldsen and Hössjer for not working scientifically, and I have said that ID does not meet the requirements of science. ID proponents, by contrast, often and readily claim that they are victims of a rigid atheistic scientific (Darwinian) orthodoxy that refuses to recognize intelligent Design as legitimate science. There may therefore be reason to very briefly review what actually characterizes established science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Natural science strives to &lt;em&gt;describe&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;explain&lt;/em&gt; physical reality. Explanations are limited to physical reality because that is the only reality we have the tools to investigate. So there may well be a spiritual reality beyond our explanations; We cannot know anything about that. Many scientists are believers and do not experience a conflict between science and their faith in God. Natural science is thus &lt;em&gt;agnostic&lt;/em&gt; and not atheistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scientific way of working is usually called &lt;em&gt;methodological naturalism&lt;/em&gt;, meaning that only so-called natural explanations are used because that is the only thing that is practically possible, but not commenting on what goes on beyond the method. There is another position called &lt;em&gt;philosophical naturalism&lt;/em&gt;. It involves the a priori exclusion of all kinds of supernatural or spiritual forces, thus an atheistic position. But that is a logically untenable position – it is impossible to know that there cannot be things one does not know. I have never met a colleague who is a philosophical naturalist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This distinction is rarely made among creationists and ID advocates, even though it should be obvious. Scientists are accused again and again of being “materialists” or “naturalists”, by which is meant philosophical naturalists, i.e., atheists. But this is not true; science is, again, agnostic and not atheistic. There are believing scientists and there are atheist scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even though it is untrue that science would be hostile to religion, this is a cornerstone of the ID project. More on this in the next post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientific work is based on explaining phenomena with the help of knowledge. The tides, for example, are explained by the gravitational force of the moon (and also the sun) affecting the sea water. We can measure, we can count, and we can confirm that the explanation matches reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is population genetics. It is based on knowledge of genetic and molecular processes. With the help of population genetics, we can set up models of human evolution. Here, too, we can measure and count and evaluate our models. As we saw in the third post, Ola Hössjer and co-authors in their discussion of possible causes of genetic variation address five known factors: mutations, genetic drift, natural selection, recombination and colonization/isolation/migration. All of these are mechanisms that we know exist, and that we can measure and count on. We can have a fact-based discussion about how important the various factors are and how they work together. And we can get an idea of ​​how reasonable the conclusions are. This is science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the authors add an unknown designer as a sixth mechanism. Then all opportunities to conduct a fact-based discussion disappear; we have no idea when or how such a designer would intervene. Hössjer and his colleagues seem to assume that the designer would create just enough genetic variation that their model fits. How can they know that? How can they test their model? It’s not possible. They have simply invented a designer with the characteristics they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as we stick to tangible and measurable factors, we know what we’re talking about. If, on the other hand, we invoke an unknown designer, we do not know what we are talking about. This is precisely why ID does not work as science. A designer explains everything and nothing&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientific theories tell us something about the world. Gravitational theory, again, says that the planets must move in elliptical orbits around the Sun and that they must not move in hexagonal orbits. This means that if someone comes up with a new physical theory that has as a consequence that the planets would move in hexagonal orbits, we can reject that theory. It does not match reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intelligent Design, however, says nothing about reality. Since we know nothing about the designer, anything is possible and nothing is off limits. There is no design theory or design model that says anything concrete about the world, so there is nothing to compare with reality. It cannot do that because such a model must be based on knowledge of the designer. And we don’t have that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intelligent Design has never been formulated as a concrete theory. The only thing ID can offer is a “theory” that says that since science cannot fully 
explain the world, there must be a designer who created it. The idea is old and well known. It is called the teleological proof of God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this does not mean that one can reject the idea of a designer behind everything - there could be one. Science does not comment on what is beyond the scientific method. But the project to make ID a working science is stillborn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dawes, G.W. (2007): What is Wrong with Intelligent Design? International Journal for Philosophy of Religion, vol. 61, pp. 69–81 https://ourarchive.otago.ac.nz/handle/10523/565&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nichols, R. (2003): Scientific Content, Testability, and the Vacuity of Intelligent Design Theory. The American Catholic Philosophical Quarterly, vol. 77, pp. 591 – 611. https://www.pdcnet.org/acpq/content/acpq_2003_0077_0004_0591_0611&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comment by Ola Hössjer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 5: Intelligent Design and Science&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the fifth part of his series of articles, Erkell turns to a discussion of scientific theories. This is welcome, because the major dividing line between me and Erkell concerns the philosophical starting point of science. Erkell writes the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Natural science strives to &lt;em&gt;describe&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;explain&lt;/em&gt; physical reality. Explanations are limited to physical reality because that is the only reality we have the tools to investigate. So there may well be a spiritual reality beyond our explanations; We cannot know anything about that. Many scientists are believers and do not experience a conflict between science and their faith in God. Natural science is thus &lt;em&gt;agnostic&lt;/em&gt; and not atheistic.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The scientific way of working is usually called &lt;em&gt;methodological naturalism&lt;/em&gt;, meaning that only so-called natural explanations because that is the only thing that is practically possible, but one does not comment on what goes on beyond the method. There is another position called &lt;em&gt;philosophical naturalism&lt;/em&gt;. It involves the a priori exclusion of all kinds of supernatural or spiritual forces, thus an atheistic position. But that is a logically untenable position – it is impossible to know that there cannot be things one does not know. I have never met a colleague who is a philosophical naturalist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fully agree with the distinction between methodological naturalism (allowing only natural explanations in natural science) and philosophical naturalism (excluding the existence of the supernatural), which I also discuss in my book “Becoming a Christian”&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;. Furthermore, I agree with Erkell that natural science strives to describe and explain physical reality. But then Erkell claims that natural explanations are the only explanations that are practically possible. How did he arrive at that? It is simply a secular belief that underlies Erkell’s entire reasoning. Therefore, I believe that his claim that methodological naturalism is agnostic (implied objective) is completely wrong, because naturalism is also a belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make it clear that methodological naturalism is based on a belief assumption, we can summarize this scientific method in the context of the hypothetico-deductive method. We then get the following three steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Propose a falsifiable hypothesis that contains only natural explanations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evaluate and see if the hypothesis in (1) is consistent with the data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the agreement in (2) is not good, go back to (1) and propose a better hypothesis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, therefore, in step (1) one starts from the premise that only natural explanations are allowed, it is obvious that science will only deliver such explanations. As you shout in the forest, your answer will be. I therefore believe that methodological naturalism constitutes a completely unnecessary limitation of science, since it does not allow a number of falsifiable hypotheses (which are chosen based on criteria such as simplicity, ability to explain, relevance, etc.) with different philosophical starting points to be allowed to be tested and compete on equal terms, so that the best possible model can be selected. Since science is all about searching for the truth, this is a very serious limitation of methodological naturalism. I treat this topic more extensively in two articles on secular science in the Scandinavian apologetics journal Theofilos.&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt; Furthermore, in parts 2 and 3 of this article series, I have shown that it is perfectly possible to combine the hypothetico-deductive method with a design perspective or a creationist perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After his initial discussion on methodological and philosophical naturalism, Erkell goes on to criticize creationists and ID proponents for not making this distinction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This distinction is rarely made among creationists and ID advocates, even though it should be obvious. Scientists are accused again and again of being “materialists” or “naturalists”, by which is meant philosophical naturalists, i.e., atheists. But this is not true; science is, aagain, agnostic and not atheistic. There are believing scientists and there are atheistic scientists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is another completely false claim, which makes me wonder how much ID and creationist literature Erkell actually read. Philip Johnson’s book “Darwin on Trial” formed an important part of the birth of the ID movement in the late 1980s. In this book, Johnson devotes an entire chapter to discussing the philosophical underpinnings of Darwinism. He then makes a distinction between naturalism and scientific naturalism, where the latter concept corresponds to methodological naturalism.&lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt; Stephen Meyer and other well-known ID advocates regularly touch upon the philosophical starting points of the theory of evolution in their books and lectures, without claiming that evolutionary biologists must be atheists. More recently, the ID-inspired anthology “Theistic Evolution, A Scientific, Philosophical, and Theological Critique” was published, where I contributed with two articles myself. As many as nine of its 31 chapters deal with the philosophical starting points of the theory of evolution, with methodological naturalism as a central concept. Since the book is primarily written as a polemic against, and addressed to, Christians who have chosen to embrace both the theory of evolution and methodological naturalism, it is clear that the authors make a distinction between methodological and philosophical naturalism.&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt; In Sweden, almost every issue of the creationist magazine Genesis deals with the secular starting points of the theory of evolution, without assuming that all of those that hold on to this theory are naturalists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erkell concludes Part 5 of his article series by commenting on why Intelligent Design is not science:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Intelligent Design, however, says nothing about reality. Since we know nothing about the designer, anything is possible and nothing is off limits. There is no design theory or design model that says anything concrete about the world, so there is nothing to compare with reality. It cannot do that because such a model must be based on knowledge about the designer. And we don’t have that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have already argued in Parts 2 and 3 that this reasoning is incorrect, because I believe that it is perfectly possible to formulate falsifiable hypotheses that are inspired by the Bible or by a design perspective. But interestingly enough, evolutionary theory itself faces the risk of getting into the trap that everything is conceivable and nothing is forbidden (except that one must not violate the principle of methodological naturalism). For example, it is well known that the Darwinian explanation of genetic similarities between the organs of two species looks different depending on how closely related the species are assumed to be in the postulated tree of life. If the species are assumed to be closely related, the organ is believed to have originated in a common ancestor, which was then passed it on to both species, so-called homologous or orthologous organs. If, on the other hand, the species are not assumed to be closely related, the organs are believed to have evolved independently of each other through convergent evolution, so-called analogous organs. In other words, the theory of evolution always has an explanation for observed similarity, which makes it difficult for it to fulfill one of the basic requirements of empirical science â€“ falsifiability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See chapters 2 and 11 in Hössjer, O. (2018).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hössjer, O. (2014). Is secular science unconditional? Theophilos 6(3), 489-496. Hössjer, O. (2016). Review of the secular science. Theofilos 8(2), 256-&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Johnson, P. (1991). Darwin on Trial. InterVarsity Press, Downers Grove, Illinois.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Moreland, J.P., Meyer, S., Shaw, C., Gauger, A. and Grudem. W. (eds.) (2017). Theistic Evolution. A Scientific, Philosophical, and Theological Critique. Crossway, Wheaton, Illinois.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reply by Lars Johan Erkell&lt;/strong&gt;
September 8, 2021 6:28 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We fully agree on the distinction between methodological naturalism and philosophical naturalism, and that is excellent. But then you write:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But then Erkell claims that natural explanations are the only explanations that are practically possible. How did he arrive at that? It is simply a secular belief that underlies Erkell’s entire reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, how have I come to the conclusion that the so-called natural explanations are the only ones that are practically possible to work with? For two reasons: the first is that natural science can only work with factors that can be clearly observed and that can be measured. It excludes supernatural powers that are not visible or measurable. The second reason is that, to my knowledge, no successful research program based on supernatural powers exists (correct me if I’m wrong - it would be interesting to be wrong on this point). So it is not some “secular assumption of faith” that is the basis of my reasoning. That is the reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also write&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Therefore, I believe that his claim that methodological naturalism is agnostic (implied objective) is completely wrong, because naturalism is also a belief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two comments: to claim that agnostic naturalism would implicitly see itself as objective is completely backwards. Agnosticism is a position which means that one does not think one can make objectively correct judgments in matters of faith, and therefore abstains. Then I want to point out that (methodological) naturalism is not a belief, it is an epistemic position that does not exclude non-material explanations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you’re wondering how much ID and creationist literature I’ve actually read. Far too much, is the answer. As for Phillip Johnson, I have published two posts about his book “Darwin on Trial” here on Biologg (https://biologg.wordpress.com/2011/12/08/fallet-darwin/ and https://biologg.wordpress. com/2011/12/14/creationism-and-naturalism/). However, he has a more detailed discussion of naturalism in the book “Reason in the Balance” from 1995. Here he derails already on the first page of the introduction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In our greatest universities, naturalism - the doctrine that nature is “all there is” - is the virtually unquestioned assumption that underlies not only natural science but intellectual work of all kinds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next page reads:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For professional purposes, atheistic and theistic biologists alike must assume that nature is all that is. Natural science is therefore based on naturalism. What a science based on naturalism tells us, not surprisingly, is that naturalism is true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not true. As I said, natural science is based on methodological naturalism, not on the philosophical naturalism Johnson writes about (“nature is all that is”). It is not assumed that nature is the only thing that exists, but that it is only practically possible to work with matter in its various forms. Of course, Johnson knows the difference, but in book after book he pushes the line that scientists make no difference between the two concepts, so really it’s the same thing. Natural science would thus be governed by an atheistic ideology, which would exclude ID explanations in advance. This delusion is a fundamental element of the ID movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have some difficulty understanding why intelligent and well-educated ID advocates constantly confuse methodological naturalism with philosophical naturalism, but I can think of two reasons. The first would be rooted in the fact that in practical research work it does not matter whether one is a methodological or a philosophical naturalist. Since there are no methods to study supernatural phenomena, those kinds of explanations are disregarded. A person of faith can then get the false impression supernatural forces are completely denied, and that the two positions are actually the same - one would just use different pretexts to deny the reality of God. The second reason could be tactics in the debate around ID. By calling both positions “naturalism”, even methodological naturalists can be made to appear as atheists who refuse to accept any form of supernatural forces and thus rule out ID from the start. This makes them appear rigid and intolerant, which is a rhetorical gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you write that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;it is perfectly possible to formulate falsifiable hypotheses that are inspired by the Bible or by a design perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course it is possible, but what can you test with your hypotheses? I address that in the post &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell8.html&quot;&gt;“Science, hypotheses and Intelligent Design”&lt;/a&gt;
Finally, you bring up the idea that the theory of evolution would not be falsifiable, since it contains two different mechanisms that can lead to life forms being similar. They may either be closely related to each other or they may have lived under similar selection pressures, which may cause them to evolve into similar forms. This was a problem for systematics for a long time. Today, however, it is possible to establish kinship with genetic methods, which means that the mechanisms can be separated. If you now want to claim that a certain mechanism is the explanation for observed similarities, you have to provide convincing evidence that it is the correct one. And that reasoning must be falsifiable. You can’t just go with one or the other, as you seem to think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lars Johan Erkell (with comment by Ola Hössjer)</name></author><summary type="html">The text is a pun in Swedish: &quot;Logg&quot; means something like a ship´s log or a logbook. A blog is &quot;blogg&quot;. So &quot;Biolog(g)&quot; is a biologist´s log or blog. &amp;nbsp; This is part 5 of a series of 7 posts by Lars Johan Erkell, with comments on each by Ola Hössjer and a reply by Erkell. Part 1 will be found here. They are translations of 2020 posts in Swedish from the Biolog(g) blog of the Department of Biology of Gothenburg University. &amp;nbsp; Breakthrough for Intelligent design? (part 5) November 13, 2020 by Lars Johan Erkell Why is ID not seen as science? In this series of blog posts, I have repeatedly criticized Thorvaldsen and Hössjer for not working scientifically, and I have said that ID does not meet the requirements of science. ID proponents, by contrast, often and readily claim that they are victims of a rigid atheistic scientific (Darwinian) orthodoxy that refuses to recognize intelligent Design as legitimate science. There may therefore be reason to very briefly review what actually characterizes established science.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AIG to hand out counterfeit money during Coronation</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/aig-counterfeit-money.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AIG to hand out counterfeit money during Coronation" /><published>2022-12-06T17:05:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-06T17:05:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/aig-counterfeit-money</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/aig-counterfeit-money.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Phelps_Funny_Money_900.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Counterfeit notes&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The obverse side of some million-pound notes that AIG plans to hand out at the Coronation. The reverse side will display religious tracts.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ken Ham and his fellow creationist grifters plan to disrupt King Charles’s Coronation by handing out &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/eIUY2oi20Fc&quot;&gt;religious tracts disguised as money&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is hilarious. They are raising money to print and distribute 3 million counterfeit “1 Million Pound” notes that will display fundamentalist/creationist tracts on the reverse side. They are shamelessly raising money to do this. I wonder if the British Secret Service will also be amused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To see this post together with comments on it, click on the title of the post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">The obverse side of some million-pound notes that AIG plans to hand out at the Coronation. The reverse side will display religious tracts. Ken Ham and his fellow creationist grifters plan to disrupt King Charles’s Coronation by handing out religious tracts disguised as money. This is hilarious. They are raising money to print and distribute 3 million counterfeit “1 Million Pound” notes that will display fundamentalist/creationist tracts on the reverse side. They are shamelessly raising money to do this. I wonder if the British Secret Service will also be amused. To see this post together with comments on it, click on the title of the post.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Panthera leo</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/panthera-leo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Panthera leo" /><published>2022-12-05T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-05T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/panthera-leo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/panthera-leo.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Marilyn Susek&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Susek.Lions.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lions&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lion&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Panthera leo&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; African lion, Yorkshire Wildlife Park, 16 July 2017. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Marilyn Susek. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Panthera leo &amp;ndash; African lion, Yorkshire Wildlife Park, 16 July 2017.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A tale of two papers</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/a-tale-of-two-papers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A tale of two papers" /><published>2022-12-02T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-02T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/a-tale-of-two-papers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/a-tale-of-two-papers.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gerdien de Jong was until her retirement Associate Professor in the Department of Biology at Utrecht University&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Red_Panda_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Puzzled Red Panda&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Red Panda, &lt;em&gt;Ailurus fulgens&lt;/em&gt;, wondering what part of the tree it's on.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-tale-of-two-papers&quot;&gt;A tale of two papers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2021, dr Matthew / Matyas Cserhati published two parallel articles on the affinities of the red panda &lt;em&gt;Ailurus fulgens&lt;/em&gt;, one in BMC Genomics and one in Creation Research Society Quarterly. The two articles are mostly based on the same data and have similar and sometimes identical content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bmcgenomics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12864-021-07531-3&quot;&gt;The BMC Genomics article&lt;/a&gt; has the title: “A tail of two pandas – whole genome k-mer signature analysis of the red panda (&lt;em&gt;Ailurus fulgens&lt;/em&gt;) and the Giant panda (&lt;em&gt;Ailuropoda melanoleuca&lt;/em&gt;)”. This paper concludes that on a whole genome level the red panda possibly belongs to the mustelid (marten) clade. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.creationresearch.org/classification-of-the-enigmatic-red-panda-ailurus-fulgens-based-on-molecular-baraminology-based-analysis&quot;&gt;The CRSQ article&lt;/a&gt; has the title: “Classification of the enigmatic red panda (&lt;em&gt;Ailurus fulgens&lt;/em&gt;) based on molecular baraminology-based analysis”. This paper deems it likely that the red panda belongs to the mustelid holobaramin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-bmc-genomics-paper&quot;&gt;The BMC Genomics paper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cserhati uses two types of data for the phylogenetic placement of the red panda: Whole Genome K-mer Signature (WGKS) and sequence analysis on mtDNA.  Cserhati establishes the frequency spectrum of all possible 8-mer base sequences over the whole genome of a species for 28 species. For each species pair a correlation coefficient over 8-mer frequencies can be computed, leading to a correlation matrix of genomic patterning over the species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cserhati uses the correlation matrix to find 4 clusters: the eleven cats, the five bears, the skunk, and a cluster containing the martens and the red panda. But then Cserhati writes: “Based on this evidence, (the red panda) would belong to (the marten family) as a monophyletic group.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the article derails. &lt;!--more--&gt; The clustering can be regarded as evidence that the red panda and the marten family are monophyletic sister groups, but not that the red panda belongs to the marten family. The red panda has a lower mean correlation with the marten species than the mean correlation of the marten species amongst each other, showing a clear distance between panda and martens. This difference is significant (P &amp;lt; 1.4 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-6&lt;/sup&gt;) but Cserhati writes “This difference is not too significant”, and he decides to ignore it. In his heat map of the correlation matrix the difference between red panda and marten species is clearly visible: left figure on top, lighter is higher correlation, and the red panda gives the top right ‘Finnish flag’ pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mtDNA sequences of 52 species/subspecies of bears, skunks, raccoons, martens, and both subspecies of the red panda are aligned and clustered. Cserhati finds 5 clusters: the 15 bears, the 30 martens, the two panda sequences, the two skunks and the 3 raccoons, clearly finding the traditional families. The mtDNA sequences are subjected to phylogenetic analysis by UPGMA, Maximum Likelihood and Neighbour Joining. No outgroup is mentioned, and no outgroup seems to have been specified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three phylogenetic trees on mtDNA differ in the placement of the families. The mess seems the result of the lack of outgroup. When plotting an unrooted tree in a square format, the program picks the plot. The pandas do not appear within the marten family in any of the three phylogenetic trees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cserhati gives his preferred conclusion: “The main conclusion … is that on a whole genome level (the red panda) possibly belongs to the (marten) clade”. Nowhere in his analyses does the red panda appear within the marten group. At most we see a monophyletic group of the marten and panda families. Cserhati conflates monophyly and belonging to the same family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One problem: how did a paper as bad as this ever get through review and published?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/wgks_heat_maps_4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;wgks heat map graphic&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The whole genome k-mers signature heat map used in the two papers.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;creation-research-society-quarterly-paper&quot;&gt;Creation Research Society Quarterly paper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cserhati bases the search for the baraminological placement of the red panda on three types of data: Whole Genome K-mer Signature (WGKS), sequence analysis on mtDNA and sequence analysis on cytochrome-b.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WGKS part is the article is almost identical to the WGKS paragraph in the BMC Genomics paper. The same heat map of the WGKS correlation matrix is presented, but the coloring is reversed: right top figure, darker is higher correlation, and the red panda gives the top right ‘Danish flag’ pattern. Again it is visible that the correlation between red panda and martens is lower than the correlations amongst the martens, and again the significant difference is dismissed. The red panda is held to belong to the marten holobaramin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mtDNA sequences of the same 52 species as in the BMC genomics paper were aligned and the resulting identity matrix showing global sequence similarity was visualized in a heat map. This heat map clearly shows five main groups representing the traditional families: two red panda subspecies, bears, marten family, the three skunks and the two raccoons. The two red panda subspecies form an independent cluster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cytochrome-b sequences of a total of 51 cat, bear, marten, raccoon and skunk species were aligned. The heat map of the similarity matrix shows a clear split between the cat species and all other species, in line with classical systematics. The red panda does not cluster with the marten family according to the heat map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again the data do not support including the red panda in the marten family. Yet, Cserhati judges that the panda belongs to the marten holobaramin. Of course, Cserhati might define a holobaramin containing two families, the marten family and the red panda family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As in all baraminological literature, statistical clustering to different clusters is assumed to indicate unbridgeable biological discontinuity. The reasoning obscures the discontinuity between biology and statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;strategy&quot;&gt;Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://oorsprong.info/wetenschapper-lost-creationistisch-biosystematisch-raadsel-van-de-rode-panda-ailurus-fulgens-op/&quot;&gt;A Dutch creationist website&lt;/a&gt; that recommends Cserhati’s work on the red panda wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cserhati’s work can stand as a model for how to do creation research. First, find funding for a detailed study within the creation paradigm (here, Creation Research Society Grant #62). Second, publish the results in a standard naturalistic science journal. Then, provide a more detailed study in a creation science journal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, play the system, aiming for respectability for creationist writing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gerdien de Jong</name></author><summary type="html">Gerdien de Jong was until her retirement Associate Professor in the Department of Biology at Utrecht University A Red Panda, Ailurus fulgens, wondering what part of the tree it's on. A tale of two papers In 2021, dr Matthew / Matyas Cserhati published two parallel articles on the affinities of the red panda Ailurus fulgens, one in BMC Genomics and one in Creation Research Society Quarterly. The two articles are mostly based on the same data and have similar and sometimes identical content. The BMC Genomics article has the title: “A tail of two pandas – whole genome k-mer signature analysis of the red panda (Ailurus fulgens) and the Giant panda (Ailuropoda melanoleuca)”. This paper concludes that on a whole genome level the red panda possibly belongs to the mustelid (marten) clade. The CRSQ article has the title: “Classification of the enigmatic red panda (Ailurus fulgens) based on molecular baraminology-based analysis”. This paper deems it likely that the red panda belongs to the mustelid holobaramin. The BMC Genomics paper Cserhati uses two types of data for the phylogenetic placement of the red panda: Whole Genome K-mer Signature (WGKS) and sequence analysis on mtDNA. Cserhati establishes the frequency spectrum of all possible 8-mer base sequences over the whole genome of a species for 28 species. For each species pair a correlation coefficient over 8-mer frequencies can be computed, leading to a correlation matrix of genomic patterning over the species. Cserhati uses the correlation matrix to find 4 clusters: the eleven cats, the five bears, the skunk, and a cluster containing the martens and the red panda. But then Cserhati writes: “Based on this evidence, (the red panda) would belong to (the marten family) as a monophyletic group.” Here the article derails.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breakthrough for Intelligent Design? (Part 4)</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell4.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breakthrough for Intelligent Design? (Part 4)" /><published>2022-11-30T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-11-30T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell4.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Biologg_Banner_900.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Biolog(g) banner&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The text is a pun in Swedish: &quot;Logg&quot; means something like a ship´s log or a logbook.&lt;br /&gt; A blog is &quot;blogg&quot;. 
 So &quot;Biolog(g)&quot; is a biologist´s log or blog.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is part 4 of a series of 7 posts by Lars Johan Erkell, with comments on each by Ola Hössjer and a reply by Erkell.  Part 1 will be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PandasThumb/pandasthumb.github.io/edit/source/_posts/2022/2022-11-09-erkell1.md&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  They are translations of &lt;a href=&quot;https://biologg.wordpress.com/2020/11/13/genombrott-for-intelligent-design-del-3/&quot;&gt;2020 posts in Swedish&lt;/a&gt; from the Biolog(g) blog of the Department of Biology of Gothenburg University.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;breakthrough-for-intelligent-design-part-4&quot;&gt;Breakthrough for Intelligent design? (part 4)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;November 13, 2020&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Lars Johan Erkell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non-physical information?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the article, the authors look ahead, towards a future Design Science. We read in the last paragraph:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Biologists need richer conceptual resources than the physical sciences until now have been able to initiate, in terms of complex structures having non-physical information as input (Ratzsch, 2010).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thorvaldsen and Hössjer refer to a book chapter by philosopher Del Ratzsch, who discusses the epistemological question of whether science can in principle exclude non-material explanations&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. If you now open the book and look at what Del Ratzsch has actually written, you read on page 356:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Biologists need richer conceptual resources than the physical sciences have been able to generate. Historically, design-linked ideas have provided such resources and those resources have been, and continue to be, scientifically fruitful in biology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is deplorable. Thorvaldsen and Hössjer have distorted the quote so that it has come to mean something completely different. Del Ratzsch does not mention “non-physical information” in his text at all. Thorvaldsen and Hössjer have invented that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cheating is also revealing. Steinar Thorvaldsen is a professor of Information Science, and if “non-physical information” had been a term used in the field, he would of course have referred to the scientific literature. Instead, a quote attributed to a philosopher has been fabricated. It is an acknowledgement that “non-physical information” does not exist as an established scientific concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what in the world could one imagine “non-physical information” to be? The information processing in any case I’ve heard of is always tied to matter of some kind: a brain or a computer. The information is always carried by some material medium, such as visible symbols, sound waves, patterns of magnetization, electromagnetic radiation or something else. The information itself consists, as far as I can understand, of a pattern or structure in the material medium. But how can there be pattern or structure in something that does not exist? Could “non-physical information” somehow float freely in space? Where does it come from? How could it affect matter? How do we even know it exists?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Thorvaldsen and Hössjer now want to revolutionize biology as well as information theory, they can come up with some kind of argument. But not; that “non-physical information” would exist is an ad hoc claim, something they grabbed completely out of thin air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I wonder about the claim that biologists would need “richer conceptual resources” than what the physical sciences can offer. I can reveal that as a biologist I have never felt such a need in my research. Nor can I recall any colleague ever expressing any desire to go outside the physical sciences, or the matter being discussed at all at conferences or in the scientific literature. These are fantasies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had this been a normal scientific article, the authors would have justified the sensational claims they make in the quote above, and discussed them in relation to the scientific literature. But this isn’t a normal scientific paper, so they don’t. It is not wrong to speculate, but Thorvaldsen and Hössjer have clearly lost touch with reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Del Ratzsch: There is a place for intelligent design in the philosophy of biology: intelligent design in (philosophy of) biology: some legitimate roles. In: Ayala, F. J., Arp, R. (Eds.), Contemporary Debates in Philosophy of Biology. Wiley-Blackwell (2010) pp. 343–363.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comment by Ola Hössjer&lt;/strong&gt;
June 29, 2021 3:39 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 4: What is information?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his fourth article, Erkell discusses the concept of information, which has been a basis of telecommunications theory for over 70 years. In TH2020, we argue that information has great potential to also be used in biology, as well. This is much in line with what I wrote earlier, since information is closely related to our proposed method of demonstrating fine-tuning&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;. At the end of our article, we write that “non-physical information” is a concept that can make valuable contributions to biology, as one of several input parameters of biological models. In this context, we refer to an article by the American philosophy professor Del Ratzsch, who argues that design can make valuable contributions to biology. Erkell is very critical of our way of referring to Del Ratsch, and writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is deplorable. Thorvaldsen and Hössjer have distorted the quote so that it has come to mean something completely different. Del Ratzsch does not mention “non-physical information” in his text at all. Thorvaldsen and Hössjer have invented that.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The cheating is also revealing. Steinar Thorvaldsen is a professor of Information Science, and if “non-physical information” had been a term used in the field, he would of course have referred to the scientific literature. Instead, a quote attributed to a philosopher has been fabricated. It is an acknowledgement that “non-physical information” does not exist as an established scientific concept.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;But what in the world could one imagine “non-physical information” to be? The information processing in any case I’ve heard of is always tied to matter of some kind: a brain or a computer. The information is always carried by some material medium, such as visible symbols, sound waves, patterns of magnetization, electromagnetic radiation or something else. The information itself consists, as far as I can understand, of a pattern or structure in the material medium. But how can there be pattern or structure in something that does not exist? Could “non-physical information” somehow float freely in space? Where does it come from? How could it affect matter? How do we even know it exists?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these paragraphs, Erkell mixes up two concepts, on one hand how information is conveyed and stored, and on the other hand how information arises. I completely agree with Erkell that information does not float in the air but it is rather stored in some physical medium. What we are referring to in TH2020 is the emergence of information, and this can either be physical and non-physical. A few sentences before we use the term non-physical information in TH2020, we write:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One rather needs a specificity function that, although of non-physical origin, can be quantified and measured empirically in terms of physical properties such as functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting our introduced concept of non-physical information into context, it is thus clear that we refer to the emergence and not the storage of information. Erkell further claims that we invented the concept of non-physical information. But while information theorists may not use that exact term, it’s still not taken out of thin air. In this context I would like to especially mention the Italian philosophy professor Luciano Floridi’s division into different types of information. Floridi distinguishes between “environmental information” and “semantic information”, where only the former type of information has a physical origin (such as cloud formations that give us information about the weather an hour later).&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt; Semantic information, on the other hand, conveys a meaning to the recipient , and unless one has a reductionist worldview (which Del Ratzsch, by the way, does not have), it is natural to identify semantic information with non-physical information, even if Floridi does not use the latter term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Semantic information can in turn be divided into instructions/algorithms and factual information (statements of fact). As far as I know, no one has succeeded in showing that semantic information can arise through purely material processes. Since biological systems (e.g., the DNA code) convey semantic information, it is hardly far-fetched to claim that this concept constitutes a valuable tool in biology. For this reason, semantic information that can be measured physically and quantified (so that it forms the basis of falsifiable hypotheses) constitutes a potentially important type of specification. In TH2020 we write that a very interesting future research area is to find different ways to quantify semantic (or non-physical) information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of Part 4, Erkell discusses whether biologists need to include non-physical explanatory hypotheses in their models:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Then I wonder about the claim that biologists would need “richer conceptual resources” than what the physical sciences can offer. I can reveal that as a biologist I have never felt such a need in my research. Nor can I recall any colleague ever expressing any desire to go outside the physical sciences, or the matter being discussed at all at conferences or in the scientific literature. These are fantasies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I regard this as a very weak argument. Whether non-material processes are relevant in biology is not primarily determined by what the majority of biologists write about in their research papers or speak about at their conferences. First, it is mainly for those parts of biology that deal with questions of origin, that meaning and other non-material concepts have a great potential. Secondly, biology as a science is strongly governed by a secular way of thinking (see Part 5) and it is therefore hardly surprising that a large proportion of all biologists do not use non-material explanations as working tools. Third, many natural scientists have argued for long that information has a non-physical origin. The founder of cybernetics, Norbert Wiener, believed that information cannot be attributed to matter or energy, and the well-known American physicist John Archibald Wheeler , in the same spirit, coined the concept “It from Bit”, that is, everything originates from information, measured in the unit of bits&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;. In addition, there are several biologists who point out that the concepts of meaning and codes are important tools in biology, something that Erkell does not seem to have noticed.&lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In more detail, if P=P(f(X)≥f(x), given M2) is the probability of randomly generating a system X that is at least as specified as the observed system x, given the naturalistic model M2, then I=-log&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;(P) denotes the degree of functional information in the system, see Hazen, R.M. et al. (2007). Functional information and the emergence of bio-complexity. Proceedings of the National Academy of Science of the United States 104 (suppl 1), 8574-8581. In order to demonstrate fine-tuning, it is required that the functional information I is large enough. This in turn requires that a function f, that quantifies the degree of specification is defined (step (b) of our fine-tuning definition) and that the probability P of achieving this specification by chance under model M2 is small (step a in our fine-tuning definition). If the specification function f also conveys a meaning to the recipient, then I corresponds to semantic (or non-physical) information. Note that functional and semantic information differ from syntactic information (or Shannon information) in that the probability P must be tied to a specification f.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Floridi, L. (2015). Semantic Conceptions of Information, Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thorvaldsen, S. and Öhrström, P. (2019). Faith and information science. In Faith and faith, Öhrström P. (ed.). Forlaget CKT, 210-228.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Maynard Smith, J. (2000). The concept of information in biology. Philos. Sci. 67, 177–194. Kim, H. Davies P. and Walker, S.I. (2015). New scaling relation for information transfer in biological networks. J.R. Soc. Interface 12: 20150944. Wills, P.R. (2016). DNA as information. Philos. Trans. A. 2016, 374, 2063. Barbieri, M. (2016). What is information? (Review article). Phil. Trans. R. Soc. A 2016 374 20150060. The latter two articles are part of a whole issue (Volume 374, Number 2063) of Phil. Trans. R. Soc. A., that is entitled “DNA as information”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reply by Lars Johan Erkell&lt;/strong&gt;
September 8, 2021 6:24 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of information constantly comes up in discussions about ID. You mean that I make a mistake when I do not distinguish between information and the origin of the information. But you yourselves don’t make that distinction in TH2020; it appeared in your comment above. The cause of the information could thus be non-physical, and that the information could then be transferred and stored in physical media. But how would that happen? How can something non-physical (whatever that would be) control physical processes? To get anywhere here, you need to solve the body-soul problem, a philosophical classic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it was interesting that you confirm that “non-physical” information does not exist as a concept within the established information theory. Instead, in your article you have referred to a philosopher who does not use the term. In your reply above, you now refer to another philosopher who also does not use the term. I maintain that you plucked the non-physical information out of thin air. Because what should one say when you write that “it [is] natural to identify semantic information with non-physical information”. Is it? Semantic information is interpreted in our material brains, and in that sense is physical, or at least associated with physical structures. From what I understand, it also cannot exist without physical structures. To me, it doesn’t feel natural at all to identify semantic information with non-physical information. That the thought feels natural to you, I suspect, is due to the fact that you, as a dualist, place the thinking in a non-material soul. In any case, mere emotion is not enough to establish revolutionary concepts such as “non-physical information”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also write that “biological systems (for example the DNA code) convey semantic information”. I want to question that. Semantic information conveys a meaning to the receiver, which presupposes a consciousness that interprets the information. Who/what interprets the DNA code in the cell? The ribosome, which would be the structure that “interprets” the DNA information during protein synthesis, does not think. Each step in the process occurs through chance and physical necessity. Protein synthesis is well studied, and we can see that its various steps consist of physical interactions between physical molecules. The same goes for every other cellular process I know of. Strictly speaking, we do not need information theory to understand the molecular processes in the cell. The fact that we still use the concept of information is due, I believe, to the fact that we are already familiar with it and that it makes it easier for us to understand how the cell works. Having said that, I still hope that information theory can be developed so that we get new tools to understand what happens in the cell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You further write “Whether non-material processes are relevant in biology is not primarily determined by what the majority of biologists write about in research articles or speak about at conferences”. It is true that biologists, like everyone else, have their limitations, but who would be better placed to judge biology’s need for non-material explanations? Creationist statisticians?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lars Johan Erkell (with comment by Ola Hössjer)</name></author><summary type="html">The text is a pun in Swedish: &quot;Logg&quot; means something like a ship´s log or a logbook. A blog is &quot;blogg&quot;. So &quot;Biolog(g)&quot; is a biologist´s log or blog. &amp;nbsp; This is part 4 of a series of 7 posts by Lars Johan Erkell, with comments on each by Ola Hössjer and a reply by Erkell. Part 1 will be found here. They are translations of 2020 posts in Swedish from the Biolog(g) blog of the Department of Biology of Gothenburg University. &amp;nbsp; Breakthrough for Intelligent design? (part 4) November 13, 2020 by Lars Johan Erkell Non-physical information? Towards the end of the article, the authors look ahead, towards a future Design Science. We read in the last paragraph: Biologists need richer conceptual resources than the physical sciences until now have been able to initiate, in terms of complex structures having non-physical information as input (Ratzsch, 2010). Thorvaldsen and Hössjer refer to a book chapter by philosopher Del Ratzsch, who discusses the epistemological question of whether science can in principle exclude non-material explanations1. If you now open the book and look at what Del Ratzsch has actually written, you read on page 356: Biologists need richer conceptual resources than the physical sciences have been able to generate. Historically, design-linked ideas have provided such resources and those resources have been, and continue to be, scientifically fruitful in biology. This is deplorable. Thorvaldsen and Hössjer have distorted the quote so that it has come to mean something completely different. Del Ratzsch does not mention “non-physical information” in his text at all. Thorvaldsen and Hössjer have invented that. The cheating is also revealing. Steinar Thorvaldsen is a professor of Information Science, and if “non-physical information” had been a term used in the field, he would of course have referred to the scientific literature. Instead, a quote attributed to a philosopher has been fabricated. It is an acknowledgement that “non-physical information” does not exist as an established scientific concept. But what in the world could one imagine “non-physical information” to be? The information processing in any case I’ve heard of is always tied to matter of some kind: a brain or a computer. The information is always carried by some material medium, such as visible symbols, sound waves, patterns of magnetization, electromagnetic radiation or something else. The information itself consists, as far as I can understand, of a pattern or structure in the material medium. But how can there be pattern or structure in something that does not exist? Could “non-physical information” somehow float freely in space? Where does it come from? How could it affect matter? How do we even know it exists?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breakthrough for Intelligent Design? (Part 3)</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breakthrough for Intelligent Design? (Part 3)" /><published>2022-11-23T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-11-23T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell3.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Biologg_Banner_900.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Biolog(g) banner&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The text is a pun in Swedish: &quot;Logg&quot; means something like a ship´s log or a logbook.&lt;br /&gt; A blog is &quot;blogg&quot;. 
 So &quot;Biolog(g)&quot; is a biologist´s log or blog.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is part 3 of a series of 7 posts by Lars Johan Erkell, with comments on each by Ola Hössjer and a reply by Erkell.  Part 1 will be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PandasThumb/pandasthumb.github.io/edit/source/_posts/2022/2022-11-09-erkell1.md&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  They are translations of &lt;a href=&quot;https://biologg.wordpress.com/2020/11/13/genombrott-for-intelligent-design-del-3/&quot;&gt;2020 posts in Swedish&lt;/a&gt; from the Biolog(g) blog of the Department of Biology of Gothenburg University.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;breakthrough-for-intelligent-design-part-3&quot;&gt;Breakthrough for Intelligent design? (part 3)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;November 13, 2020&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Lars Johan Erkell (with comment by Ola Hössjer)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Miracles as science?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thorvaldsen and Hössjer give a number of examples of systems that they
think are suitable for the statistical model we discussed in the previous
post. One of the examples concerns human evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One may also study the more restricted problem of human/chimp ancestry, and compare a model M2 with common ancestry of the two species, with a unique origin model M1, according to which each species is founded by one single couple (Sanford and Carter, 2014; Hössjer et al., 2016a; 2016b, Carter et al., 2018, Hössjer and Gauger, 2019).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Thorvaldsen and Hössjer raise this question as suitable to study with their statistical model, we shall look at it more closely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question they ask is whether it is possible that humanity has its
origins in a single couple, a man and a woman. It is of course about Adam
and Eve, even if they are not mentioned by name - otherwise there is
hardly any reason to ask the question. The common scientific view is that
humans did not originate in two individuals, but that our species passed
a bottleneck perhaps 70,000 years ago, when there were perhaps 10,000
individuals. One can of course imagine that the bottleneck was only two
individuals, but to be able to explain the genetic variation we see
today, we then have to extend the time to 500,000 years or more. This is
not acceptable for a young earth creationist scenario. There, creation
must have taken place 6,000 to 10,000 years ago if you want to 
read the Bible literally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ola Hössjer is a co-author in three of the referenced
articles: “Genetic Modeling of Human History Part 1: Comparison of Common
Descent and Unique Origin Approaches” and “Genetic Modeling of Human
History Part 2: A Unique Origin Algorithm”, both from 2016. Here he
reports that he, along with two co-authors, developed a population
genetic model to simulate human descent. Together with biologist Ann
Gauger (who is affiliated with the Discovery Institute), he has also
written “A Single-Couple Human Origin is Possible” from 2019, where they
developed their earlier model. They write that an origin from a single
couple 500,000 years ago is consistent with the model, but that only
small changes in the model can give an age of 100,000 years or less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three articles are published in the online journal BIO-complexity, published by the Discovery Institute, the central organization of the ID movement. The journal is not recognized as a “real” scientific journal. For example, it is not included in the scientific database SCOPUS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In “Genetic Modeling of Human History Part 1” we read on the first page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We argue that a unique origin model where humanity arose from one single couple with created diversity seems to explain the data at least as well, if not better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ola Hössjer and his co-authors thus say that their model that humans
originated in a single couple matches the data better than the standard
evolutionary model. But what data? All you find is qualitative reasoning
about published data of various kinds. Neither of the two articles with
the title “Genetic Modeling of Human History” contains any &quot;Genetic
Modeling&quot;; no quantitative data, no results from simulations with the
model developed. The approach is recognizable from Thorvaldsen and
Hössjer's current article (see the first post in the series). Here the
authors also pretend to have results they don't have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quote also mentions &quot;created diversity&quot;. Now what is that? I have
never heard of such a thing before. The text discusses five different
mechanisms for how genetic variation can develop and be limited. But then
it introduces a sixth possibility. The authors write on page 5:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… But if an intelligent designer is invoked as a possible explanation, and if humanity originates from one single couple, it is possible that their chromosomes were created with considerable diversity from the beginning [19,20]. This gives us a sixth mechanism of genetic change.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;VI. Created founder diversity is biologically plausible for DNA of non-sex chromosomes. Since there are four copies of each non-sex chromosome in two individuals, we may think of one of the founding male’s two copies as a reference or template for the other three. All differences between his reference chromosome and the other three founder chromosomes can be thought of as a very large number of mutations, all of which occurred in one generation. Since the founding pair had three copies of the X-chromosome (one in the man and two in the woman), for the same reason they may also have been different. Some founder diversity is possible for mitochondrial DNA as well. Since the founding female carried hundreds of mitochondria that could have been diverse, it is possible that she passed on some of that diversity to her daughters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The genome contains two copies of each gene. The idea is that Adam and
Eve would have been created with two different variants of each gene in
their DNA, which together would give four variants. That would increase
genetic variation so much that one could imagine a creation 6,000 to
10,000 years ago. References 19 and 20 are not to the scientific
literature, but to two creationist journals. The first of the two
articles does not justify why introducing an engineered genetic variation
would be scientifically justified. However, the other one, “On the Origin
of Eukaryotic Species' Genotypic and Phenotypic Diversity: Genetic
Clocks, Population Growth Curves, and Comparative Nuclear Genome Analyzes
Suggest Created Heterozygosity in Combination with Natural Processes as a
Major Mechanism”, by Nathaniel Jeanson and Jason Lisle, does. They write
on p. 86-87:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;No known non-miraculous mechanism exists that could play a role in this process, and invoking miracles at every juncture without biblical or scientific justification quickly moves a hypothesis from the realm of science to the realm of ad hoc speculation.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;…
On an individual organism level, hypotheses must invoke observable processes or biblically-justified miraculous processes. 
…
Again, observable processes or biblically-justified miraculous processes must be invoked, or the hypothesis quickly drifts into the realm of the ad hoc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hypothesis could thus be justified either scientifically or with the support of the Bible. However, I find no discussion of exactly how the Bible can justify God creating Adam and Eve with maximum genetic variation. Ola Hössjer and co-authors thus refer to a created variation that is not justified either scientifically or biblically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But surely this is a convenient explanation. Invoking a designer suddenly
makes it possible that genetic variation may be greater than established
science admits, and that Adam and Eve may have lived 6,000 to 10,000
years ago. It is not seen as necessary to show that there really is a
designer or that the designer really had the desire to create exactly the
genetic variation that is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are problems with this model. Without going into the genetics, one
can, for example, state that in this model there can be a maximum of four
gene variants - alleles - of a certain gene. However, there are gene
families with thousands of alleles. Where do they come from? But once you
have started to explain things with miracles, you can surely solve those
problems as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And where does the designer come from? Out of thin air. A designer has been invented that creates genetic variation to solve the problem that Adam and Eve must not have lived hundreds of thousands of years ago. And thus they have completely left science and floated out into the world of fantasy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Ola Hössjer was faced with a new statistical model that was based on
an unproven theorem, I believe he would react sharply. Theorems must be
proven, otherwise you cannot know that they are true. If there is any
part in the derivation of the model that is unproven, it cannot be used.
Grabbing something out of thin air – a theorem or something else – is
called ad hoc assumption and is not considered good scientific practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can't get your theory together, you can't just pull something to
save it. All parts of a mathematical derivation or a biological theory
must be based on knowledge, not on grabbing something out of thin air
when needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, this is exactly what Ola Hössjer and co-authors are doing. The introduction of a supernatural designer makes their work lose all scientific credibility and thus all scientific interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me add that in principle one can consider a designer as a scientific
explanation, provided it is known for sure that the designer exists, and
has such properties that they can explain a certain phenomenon. If we
have actual knowledge about the designer (as we have about the five
genetic mechanisms discussed) we can use that knowledge to explain
things. But in this case we have no knowledge of the designer at all. And
then we cannot use design as an explanation. at all. And then we cannot use design as an explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comment by Ola Hössjer&lt;/strong&gt;
June 29, 2021 3:19 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 3: Miracles and Science&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Part 3, Erkell makes a detour and comments on a number of articles on the origin of man that I wrote in collaboration with Ann Gauger and Colin Reeves&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;. In these articles we use the design model M1 that was described in Part 2 in a creationist context. More precisely, our model M1 assumes that all humans are descended from a first couple, Adam and Eve. The model thus includes the aforementioned microevolutionary mechanisms (i)-(v), as well as Adam and Eve being created with genetic variation (vi). In other words, according to this model, Adam has two genetically different copies of each non-sex chromosome, and so does Eve. Thus, in the first founder generation we get four genetically different variants of each non-sex chromosome. The degree of genetic dissimilarity between these variants, i.e. the degree of created variation, is a parameter that can be varied in the model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erkell calls our creationist model M1 a miracle model (which, by the way, I think is a good name)&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;), and he has similar high demands on this model as he had on the design model in the previous section:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A hypothesis could thus be justified either scientifically or with the support of the Bible. However, I find no discussion of exactly how the Bible can justify God creating Adam and Eve with maximum genetic variation. Ola Hössjer and co-authors thus refer to a created variation that is not justified either scientifically or biblically.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To support his thesis, Erkell starts from the quote “On an individual organism level, hypotheses must invoke observable processes or biblically-justified miraculous processes” by the creationists Jeanson and Lisle.&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; I support this formulation, if the purpose is to choose between a creationist model M1 and a naturalistic model M2. But the fact that a hypothesis can be justified based on the Bible does not mean that it is a direct quote from a Bible verse. Erkell has simply misunderstood how creationist research is conducted. In fact, it is perfectly possible to let the Bible inspire the formulation of falsifiable hypotheses. In other words, creationism can be reconciled with the hypothetical deductive method, regardless of whether we start from direct biblical quotes or simply are inspired by the contents of the Bible, according to the following three steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Propose a falsifiable hypothesis that partly contains natural explanatory mechanisms and partly explanatory mechanisms that are inspired by the Bible.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Evaluate and check if the hypothesis in (1) is consistent with data.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the agreement in (2) is not good, go back to (1) and propose a better hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Christian, I believe that God wrote two books, the Bible and nature. Therefore, it is ultimately God who is behind what we call “natural explanations” as well as the “biblically motivated explanations”. Of course, one must place the same demands on a creationist model M1 as on a secular model M2. Erkell argues that our proposed creationist miracle model is firstly ad hoc and secondly not falsifiable. I believe that both of these statements are completely wrong. The Bible states that man was created uniquely. Given this, I mean that it is not at all a far-fetched ad hoc assumption to assume that God created Adam and Eve with genetic variation, because He is creative and did not want all men and women to look alike, like monozygotic twins. By creating the first two humans with variation, the risk of inbreeding depression was also reduced when harmful mutations made their way into future generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note, however, that we only include created variation in our model, not why God created the first two humans with variation. Given this, the model is falsifiable, because then, due to recombinations (iv), our DNA is a mosaic of the four building blocks from each chromosome, with which Adam and Eve were created. Such building blocks, called haplotype blocks, were discovered by secular scientists about 20 years ago. We mention this in two of our articles, with numerous references.&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; Either Erkell has missed these references or he has not realized that the existence of haplotype blocks makes our miracle model falsifiable. And regardless of whether the haplotype blocks are identified or not, I still believe that our miracle model is falsifiable, since there are indirect methods of testing the presence of created variation by comparing the allele frequency spectra and linkage disequilibrium plots calculated from the data with those predicted by the miracle model M1. This latter approach exactly the one we use in one of our publications to test M1 against data.&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;  However, Erkell (in Part 5 of his article series) objects to our way of fitting the miracle model to the data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Then you add an unknown designer as a sixth mechanism. Then all opportunities to conduct a fact-based discussion disappear; we have no idea when or how such a designer would intervene. Hössjer and his colleagues seem to assume that the designer would create just enough genetic variation that their model fits. How can they know that? How can they test their model? It’s not possible. You have simply invented a designer who has the qualities you want.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here Erkell confuses two things, firstly, whether the miracle model M1 is falsifiable or not, which I have already commented on, and secondly, how the adaptation of the model to data has been done. All statistical models contain unknown parameters, so does our miracle model. This is precisely why the data is used to estimate the degree of created variation. Our approach is very similar to an evolutionary biologist who fits a naturalistic model M2 to data by estimating mutation rates, population sizes, and recombination rates. Of course, it is possible to overfit if one uses a model with too many parameters, without validating it. But in my joint article with Ann Gauger, on the contrary, we used a very simple model with created variation, but without geographic variation (v). We also managed to get a good fit of our miracle model to data, if Adam and Eve lived several hundred thousand years ago. However, we write that with a larger (and more realistic) variant of the miracle model, the age of the first two people can probably be lowered significantly. In addition, it is perfectly possible to test the miracle model by first estimating parameters on a data set (a so-called training of the model) and then evaluating how well the obtained model adapts to another data set (a so-called validation of the model).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erkell finally delivers a third critique of the miracle model:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There are problems with this model. Without going into the genetics, one can for example state that in this model there can be a maximum of four gene variants - alleles - of a certain gene. However, there are gene families with thousands of alleles. Where do they come from? But if you start to explain things with miracles, you can certainly solve those problems too.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a rather astonishing statement from a biologist. In fact, it is perfectly possible to explain gene families with a large number of alleles in a model where Adam and Eve were created with variation. Although there were only four raw copies of each non-sex chromosome in the first generation, mutations (i) and recombination (iv) in future generations can generate a large number of variants of different genes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erkell concludes, in Part 3 of his article series, by asking how I, as a mathematician, can allow models with ad hoc assumptions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“f Ola Hössjer was faced with a new statistical model that was based on
an unproven theorem, I believe he would react sharply. Theorems must be
proven, otherwise you cannot know that they are true. If there is any
part in the derivation of the model that is unproven, it cannot be used.
Grabbing something out of thin air – a theorem or something else – is
called ad hoc assumption and is not considered good scientific practice.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is much to say about these sentences. First, Erkell confuses mathematics (a deductive science) with biology (an empirical or inductive science). In mathematics, one starts from axioms (assumptions of faith) and proves, given these axioms, various statements. Here, the demands on accuracy are high, because a single small error can overturn an entire proof. However, there are no requirements for a theorem of mathematics to correspond to reality (despite this, mathematics has nevertheless proven to be very useful). In biology, the aim is instead to adapt models to empirical data, using the hypothetico-deductive method (and here mathematics comes in as a tool). It is therefore never possible to prove that a biological theory is true. On the other hand, if models that do not explain data well are falsified we may be left with plausible models that so far have survived all tests. Of course, even in biology you have to be strict when proposing and testing models against data, but as I have shown above, our miracle model is firstly not ad hoc and secondly it is falsifiable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hössjer, O., Gauger A. and Reeves, C. (2016a). Genetic modeling of human history part 1: Comparison of common descent and unique origin approaches. BIO-Complexity
2016(3):1-15. Hössjer, O., Gauger A. and Reeves, C. (2016b). Genetic modeling of human history part 2: A unique origin algorithm. BIO-Complexity 2016(4):1-36. Hössjer, O. and Gauger, A. (2019). A single couple of human origin is possible. BIO-Complexity 2019(1):1-21.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our sixth mechanism for genetic change, created variation (iv), assumes that this variation is part of God’s creation. However, miracles are generally defined as exceptions to the laws of nature that God has created already, see for example Keener, C.S. (2011), Miracles, the credibility of the New Testament accounts, Baker Academics, Grand Rapids, Hössjer, O. (2018). Becoming a Christian, Combining prior belief, evidence, and will. Wipf and Stock Publishers, Eugene, OR, and Grenholm (2019), Documented Miracles, Sjöberg Publishers. Alternatively, all of God’s creation can be seen as a miracle. For these reasons I don’t mind using the name miracle model for our creationist explanatory model of human genetic variation, as suggested by Erkell.
5) Jeanson, N.T., and Lisle, J. (2016). On the origin of eukaryotic species’ genotypic and phenotypic diversity: Genetic clocks, population growth curves, and comparative nuclear genome analyzes suggest created heterozygosity in combination with natural processes as a major source mechanism. Answ Res J 9:81-122.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See section 3C of Hössjer et al. (2016a) and section 1.3 of Hössjer et al. (2016b). Note, however, that created variation can be defined in different ways. For example, all of Eve’s egg cells, which were with her from the beginning, may have been created differently. In our articles (see Footnote 3) we have chosen to make the model of created variation as simple as possible, assuming that all of Eve’s eggs were genetically identical. However, one can think of different (falsifiable) models for created variation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hössjer, O. and Gauger, A. (2019).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reply by Lars Johan Erkell&lt;/strong&gt;
September 8, 2021 6:17 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this section we return to the question of how to formulate scientific hypotheses. I refer to my discussion in the post “Science, hypotheses and Intelligent design” https://biologg.wordpress.com/2021/09/08/vetenskap-hypoteser-och-intelligent-design/.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you find it astonishing that I, as a biologist, do not agree that today’s genetic diversity could be explained on the basis that Adam and Eve must have lived 6000 years ago. But I’m not the only one who thinks so. I assume that you know that Steve Schaffner and Joshua Swamidass, with their respective allele frequency spectra and recombination analysis, concluded that from a genetic point of view it is indeed quite possible that Adam and Eve could have existed, but that they must have lived at least 500,000 years ago (see eg http://richardbuggs.com/2021/03/15/video-adam-eve-and-human-genetic-diversity/). In your own article “A Single-Couple Human Origin is Possible” (https://bio-complexity.org/ojs/index.php/main/article/view/BIO-C.2019.1) you and Ann Gauger arrive at the same results. So why are you surprised that I don’t believe genetics shows a creation 6000 years ago?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The critical point here is whether there are genetic mechanisms that in
6000 years can generate today's genetic variation from a single couple.
You write &quot;Even if there were only four raw copies of each non-sex
chromosome in the first generation, mutations (i) and recombination (iv)
in future generations can generate a large number of variants of
different genes&quot;. Here's one thing I have to ask you: one of the main
points of young earth creationism is that mutations are basically always
harmful and destructive. They would cause irreversible losses of
&quot;information&quot; and an ever-increasing &quot;genetic entropy&quot;. Are you prepared
to argue contrary to this that mutations and recombinations (which are a
form of random mutation) can generate new, functional alleles of a gene?
HLA-B, the gene with most variation to my knowledge, was reported in
June 2021 to have 8,181 alleles. So can a blind process of random
mutation and selection generate thousands of functional, new gene
variants?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lars Johan Erkell</name></author><summary type="html">The text is a pun in Swedish: &quot;Logg&quot; means something like a ship´s log or a logbook. A blog is &quot;blogg&quot;. So &quot;Biolog(g)&quot; is a biologist´s log or blog. This is part 3 of a series of 7 posts by Lars Johan Erkell, with comments on each by Ola Hössjer and a reply by Erkell. Part 1 will be found here. They are translations of 2020 posts in Swedish from the Biolog(g) blog of the Department of Biology of Gothenburg University. Breakthrough for Intelligent design? (part 3) November 13, 2020 by Lars Johan Erkell (with comment by Ola Hössjer) Miracles as science? Thorvaldsen and Hössjer give a number of examples of systems that they think are suitable for the statistical model we discussed in the previous post. One of the examples concerns human evolution. One may also study the more restricted problem of human/chimp ancestry, and compare a model M2 with common ancestry of the two species, with a unique origin model M1, according to which each species is founded by one single couple (Sanford and Carter, 2014; Hössjer et al., 2016a; 2016b, Carter et al., 2018, Hössjer and Gauger, 2019). Since Thorvaldsen and Hössjer raise this question as suitable to study with their statistical model, we shall look at it more closely.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Black ant</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/unidentified-black-ant.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Black ant" /><published>2022-11-21T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-11-21T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/unidentified-black-ant</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/unidentified-black-ant.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Denelsbeck.Black_Ant.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Black ant&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Unidentified black ant. Mr. Denelsbeck writes, &quot;My subject barely let me get a sharp image, much less anything with key characteristics, so it will remain unidentified for now. In a heated dispute among two black ants, one seized the other's antenna but lost the encounter; the victor apparently sliced off everything it could reach, and was going about its business when I spotted it, carrying around the remains of its opponent dangling from one antenna. At one point it did indeed stop and try to dislodge the dead weight, without success.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Al Denelsbeck. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Unidentified black ant. Mr. Denelsbeck writes, &quot;My subject barely let me get a sharp image, much less anything with key characteristics, so it will remain unidentified for now. In a heated dispute among two black ants, one seized the other's antenna but lost the encounter; the victor apparently sliced off everything it could reach, and was going about its business when I spotted it, carrying around the remains of its opponent dangling from one antenna. At one point it did indeed stop and try to dislodge the dead weight, without success.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Science, hypotheses, and intelligent design</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell8.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science, hypotheses, and intelligent design" /><published>2022-11-16T13:15:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-11-16T13:15:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell8</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell8.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is an additional post by Lars Johan Erkell made on September 8, 2021 in Swedish at the Biolog(g) site after the seven posts 
of his “Breakthrough for Intelligent Design?” series were made.  He has requested that we post it here after 
the second post in that series, to explain his position in that post on what can be considered legitimate 
science.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A central point in the discussion I have with Ola Hössjer in the posts entitled &quot;Breakthrough for
intelligent design?&quot; concerns the limits for what can be considered legitimate science. Since my
responses to his comments on this matter are too long for the comments section, I have made a
separate post on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The central question is how to formulate a hypothesis, that is, a suggested explanation for a
phenomenon. Hypotheses are not formulated in an arbitrary way; you don't just grab something out
of the air. A hypothesis should be based on prior knowledge. It should also be falsifiable, which
means that it must be possible to show that it is incorrect. The scientific work then consists of testing
the hypothesis. Whether it proves to be true or false, something new has been learned. The
important thing here is that the hypothesis is formulated in such a way that it can be tested in
practice with a clear-cut result. If you cannot do that, you cannot learn anything new. And if you
cannot test your hypotheses, you cannot root your theories in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, just because a hypothesis is falsifiable does not mean that it is scientific. For example, &quot;the
Moon is a cheese&quot; is a falsifiable (and falsified) hypothesis. But pure nonsense. If we want to give it a
scientific touch, we can formulate it as a classical syllogism:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Premise 1: The Moon is yellow, round and has craters&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Premise 2: A cut cheese is yellow, round and has pits that look like craters&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conclusion: The Moon is a cheese&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This conclusion is not just grabbed out of thin air; it is based on an analogy. But it is still nonsense.
My point here is that just because a hypothesis is falsifiable, or is expressed in a formally correct
manner, that does not mean it is plausible or even makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example of a falsifiable hypothesis that is scientifically acceptable, let us take a classic: Darwin's
hypothesis of the common descent of life forms. It implies, among other implications, that older
forms must lie below younger forms in the fossil record. In other words, a fossil of a reliably
identified and reliably dated rabbit (or any other modern mammal) may not be found in Cambrian
deposits, i.e. from a time long before the first mammals emerged. Despite millions of fossils being
unearthed, nothing has yet been found to disprove Darwin's hypothesis. Still, in principle it could
happen, and that would be a fundamental blow to the theory of evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can hear ID proponents argue that ID can also make falsifiable hypotheses. Stephen Meyer
devotes an entire appendix to discussing the matter in his 2009 book &lt;em&gt;Signature in the Cell&lt;/em&gt;. He writes
on page 482: &quot;… the theory of intelligent design makes predictions about the kind of features we are
likely to find in living systems if they were in fact intelligently designed&quot;. What is important here is
the wording &quot;we are likely to find&quot; - ID's predictions are thus based on what one might vaguely
expect to find. Not on what one &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; find or on what one &lt;em&gt;must not&lt;/em&gt; find, i.e. not on any compelling
predictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that one cannot clearly falsify an ID hypothesis. As an example, let us take an ID-inspired
hypothesis that Meyer puts forward: &quot;The functional sequences of amino acids within amino 
acid-sequence space should be extremely rare rather than common&quot;. He argues that of all possible
combinations of the amino acids that make up proteins, there should be very few combinations that
result in functional protein structures. The first problem is that Meyer does not give a clear limit for
what would be extremely rare and what would not, so the question is impossible to decide in
practice - &quot;extremely rare&quot; can be interpreted in very different ways. The second, and bigger,
problem is that there is no logical connection to a designer - how do we know that the designer
decided that there must be only a few working combinations? We don't. So even if we could confirm
the hypothesis, it would not tell us anything about whether proteins were designed or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ID hypothesis is clearly not about proving ID, but about ruling out an evolutionary explanation. If
it could be shown that there were extremely few working combinations of amino acids, this would be
seen as an argument against the theory of evolution (which, by the way, it is not). In other words,
Meyer tries to demonstrate &quot;non-evolution&quot; and sees this as a sign of design. This is a classic fallacy -
the fact that one explanation does not hold up does not mean that another explanation must be
correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meyer in his appendix has a list of twelve &quot;ID-inspired&quot; predictions of which the above example was
the last one. The other eleven suffer from the same weaknesses. Some of them are pure arguments
against evolutionary processes and have nothing to do with design. Others assume that the designer
is working with a particular type of design which you then want to identify. But you cannot know
what type of design the designer uses, so what you are actually testing is the idea you have about
how the designer should work. Without actual knowledge of the designer, it is impossible to know
how to formulate precise hypotheses. Everything becomes pure conjecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example of empirical work based on a hypothetical designer, consider a study of the impact of
intercessory prayer on the recovery of patients who have undergone a particular type of heart
surgery.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; This is a large study with 1800 patients, carried out according to all the rules of the art. The
end result was that no significant effect of prayer was seen. Does this mean that prayer has been
shown not to work? Not at all. The results only show that intercession does not work with the
particular experimental design chosen. Perhaps it would have worked with other patients, other
experimental groups, other control groups, other prayer rituals, other people praying? We don't
know. Since we have no concrete knowledge of the designer, we do not know how the experiment
should be set up to show with certainty the effect of intercessory prayer. We can guess endlessly.
This is not how good hypothesis testing is done - that requires precise, testable hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us leave the hypotheses and move on to what is required of a scientific explanation. Explaining
something means clearly demonstrating the causes of some phenomenon; you connect cause and
effect. You also have to show how the cause leads to the observed phenomenon. A good
explanation, then, involves linking a phenomenon to a known cause through a known mechanism.
Darwin's theory of evolution is a good example. His idea of common descent was quickly accepted by
his contemporaries; it was so obvious that it explained the patterns of nature well. But with natural
selection it was not so. Darwin could not explain the mechanisms of heredity, which was a
prerequisite for understanding natural selection. That is why not many people fully accepted his
theory. However, by the turn of the 20th century, the mechanisms of genetics were starting to be
elucidated, so now the process of evolution was being understood. But it was still not clear exactly
how evolution happened. It wasn't until population genetics had developed sufficiently in the 1930s
and 40s that the theory became widely accepted. By then, the whole chain was clear: known causes
(heredity and variation) caused a known phenomenon (evolution) through a known mechanism
(natural selection).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we can understand the entire causal chain. We can understand it at the molecular level as well
as at the population level. We know the molecules and processes that cause evolution. We can
observe and measure them, which allows us to have an evidence-based discussion about the
importance of different factors, and how well different models fit reality. That is how it should be
with a good scientific explanation. It also allows us to formulate and test new hypotheses based on
the knowledge we already have - for example, can cooperation and helpfulness be explained in
evolutionary terms? It turns out that it can. The theory of inclusive fitness provides a robust
evolutionary explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare this to an ID explanation of how a complex biological structure would arise. The cause, the
designer, is unknown, and so are the mechanisms by which the design would be implemented. Thus,
we cannot assess how plausible the ID explanation is, or how it compares to other explanations. An
explanation based on unknown causes and unknown mechanisms is, strictly speaking, no explanation
at all - it doesn't make us any wiser. It provides no concrete knowledge. It has no explanatory value.
Nor does it provide a reliable basis for further hypotheses. If you are already firmly convinced that
there is a designer, it may work as a religiously based explanation, but it is scientifically uninteresting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fuzziness of ID explanations is characteristic. It is also reflected in the lack of precision in the
concepts used. For example, &quot;complex specified information&quot; is not defined in a way that makes it
measurable or practically useful. Similarly, it is impossible to clearly determine whether a structure is
irreducibly complex or not - distinct criteria are lacking. It is obviously impossible to conduct
meaningful research with such fuzzy concepts. Yet ID proponents refer to these concepts as if they
were clear, meaningful and established. But they are definitely not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conclusion is clear: ID cannot provide the kind of mechanistic explanations that are the basis of a
scientific theory. Thus ID cannot compete with established science, and can never be a scientific
alternative. On the other hand, ID could be a complementary explanation on another level: one is
free to imagine a governing intelligence behind all the mysteries of existence, while science provides
the mechanistic explanations of how the world actually works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reference:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Benson, H., et al: Study of the Therapeutic Effects of Intercessory Prayer (STEP) in cardiac bypass
patients. &lt;em&gt;American Heart Journal&lt;/em&gt; (2006) 151, pp. 934-42
https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16569567&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lars Johan Erkell</name></author><summary type="html">This is an additional post by Lars Johan Erkell made on September 8, 2021 in Swedish at the Biolog(g) site after the seven posts of his “Breakthrough for Intelligent Design?” series were made. He has requested that we post it here after the second post in that series, to explain his position in that post on what can be considered legitimate science. &amp;nbsp; A central point in the discussion I have with Ola Hössjer in the posts entitled &quot;Breakthrough for intelligent design?&quot; concerns the limits for what can be considered legitimate science. Since my responses to his comments on this matter are too long for the comments section, I have made a separate post on the subject. The central question is how to formulate a hypothesis, that is, a suggested explanation for a phenomenon. Hypotheses are not formulated in an arbitrary way; you don't just grab something out of the air. A hypothesis should be based on prior knowledge. It should also be falsifiable, which means that it must be possible to show that it is incorrect. The scientific work then consists of testing the hypothesis. Whether it proves to be true or false, something new has been learned. The important thing here is that the hypothesis is formulated in such a way that it can be tested in practice with a clear-cut result. If you cannot do that, you cannot learn anything new. And if you cannot test your hypotheses, you cannot root your theories in the real world. However, just because a hypothesis is falsifiable does not mean that it is scientific. For example, &quot;the Moon is a cheese&quot; is a falsifiable (and falsified) hypothesis. But pure nonsense. If we want to give it a scientific touch, we can formulate it as a classical syllogism: Premise 1: The Moon is yellow, round and has craters Premise 2: A cut cheese is yellow, round and has pits that look like craters Conclusion: The Moon is a cheese This conclusion is not just grabbed out of thin air; it is based on an analogy. But it is still nonsense. My point here is that just because a hypothesis is falsifiable, or is expressed in a formally correct manner, that does not mean it is plausible or even makes sense.</summary></entry></feed>