<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-10-26T03:46:37-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Ken Ham's The Lie: What's new (plenty) in the 2024 version</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/10/ken-hams-the-lie.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ken Ham's The Lie: What's new (plenty) in the 2024 version" /><published>2024-10-21T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-21T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/10/ken-hams-the-lie</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/10/ken-hams-the-lie.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Braterman_Lie_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The following is a review of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Lie-Unraveling-Evolution-Millions-Years-ebook/dp/B0DD4YLQRQ/&quot;&gt;The Lie&lt;/a&gt;, by Ken Ham (Master Book, 2024), and a comparison of the 1987, 2012, and 2024 editions. A longer article appeared &lt;a href=&quot;https://3quarksdaily.com/3quarksdaily/2024/10/reviewed-ken-hams-the-lie-unravelling-the-myth-of-evolution-millions-of-years-and-why-we-need-to-pay-attention.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; in 3 Quarks Daily.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me first remind you of the scale of Ken Ham’s political significance. He has among his friends Mike Johnson, Speaker of the US House of Representatives, whose law firm has represented AiG pro bono. And among the contributors to its magazine is Calvin Beisner, director of the Cornwall Alliance, whose entire purpose is to deny the importance of human-caused climate change. Cornwall in turn has direct links to the Heartland Institute and to the Heritage Foundation, authors of Project 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Readers here will be familiar with the destructive and anti-scientific approach of the modern creationist movement in the US. But that’s only half the story. It is not only about the beginning of the world, but about its ending. Genesis is pivotal, but so is Revelation. So are the many hints of the end of the world that are explicit in the New Testament, and can be discovered with sufficient ingenuity in the Old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such thinking underlines the apocalyptic tone, repeatedly echoed in AiG’s material, that underlies current US right-wing politics. If the Earth does not have a deep past, we cannot expect it to have a prolonged future. We should not be concerning ourselves with conservation, but with righteousness. This perspective has political implications, and comparing the 1987 and 2024 versions of &lt;i&gt;The Lie&lt;/i&gt; shows the political aspect becoming increasingly explicit. Otherwise, there is not much difference between the two editions, though The third edition is more repetitious and, where direct comparison is possible, less vigorous in its use of language, and more hectoring, than the original.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-right-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 40px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Braterman_Lie_Bible Mod Sci_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bible and Modern Science cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Cover of an earlier book, &lt;i&gt;The Bible and Modern Science&lt;/i&gt;, by Henry Morris.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A decade before &lt;i&gt;The Genesis Flood&lt;/i&gt;, Henry Morris had written a much shorter book, &lt;i&gt;The Bible and Modern Science&lt;/i&gt;, whose final chapter is devoted to claims that biblical prophecies are being fulfilled in our own times, and are signs of Christ’s imminent return. Prominent among these is the return of Jews to their ancestral homeland. Similar thinking explains why US fundamentalist evangelicals are now among Israel’s most unquestioning supporters. 
&lt;p&gt;I have recently reviewed at length the 1987 (1st ed.) and 2024 (3rd ed.) versions of &lt;i&gt;The Lie&lt;/i&gt;, and the differences between them. Here I will use material from that review to comment on some of the most extraordinary aspects of the work, draw attention to the narrowness of Ham’s portrayal of Christianity, and discuss the changes between the two editions. 
&lt;p&gt;Ham himself  tells us that it was &lt;i&gt;The Lie&lt;/i&gt; that positioned Answers in Genesis as a biblical authority ministry. That’s not true. When it was published in 1987, Ham was still an employee of Morris’ Institute for Creation Research, while his own organization was not incorporated until 1993, amid much unseemly and litigious infighting, and its title, Answers in Genesis, only dates from 1994.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ham’s approach is unsubtle, uncompromising, and unburdened with excess erudition. It is also completely devoid of originality, since all the ideas he expresses are already there in the writings of Henry Morris and his precursors. The book describes itself as concerned with “the foundational nature of the book of Genesis to all Christian doctrine.” By “the book of Genesis,” Ham means a plain literal meaning, with a 6-day 24-hour creation, ignoring two millennia of exegesis and two centuries of literary and archaeological scholarship, and reducing the beautiful, complex, many-layered text to a cardboard cutout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title of the first chapter tells us that “Christianity is Under Attack,” or, in the third edition, “Under Massive Attack.” Modern society has moved away from Christ, but the book promises to outline “a Biblical (and therefore successful)” approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Braterman_Lie_Seven Cs_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Seven C's of Ken Ham&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Seven C's of Ken Ham. &lt;small&gt;3rd ed., p. 58, fair use.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;The third edition takes the opportunity to claim victimhood for Christianity, and to attack an unspecified secular wokeness, signaling the book’s political tendency. It then shows the attached figure listing what it regards as our contemporary ills, all caused by a falling away from Ham’s version of Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an extraordinary list. Something very strange is happening when those who call themselves followers of Christ object to the idea of social justice. Of the 16 items on this list, seven (CRT, Inclusion, Identity Politics, Social Justice, Mandates, Intersectionality, and Woke) express political views, with some of which one might have expected a follower of Jesus to sympathise, and none bear any relationship to the book’s ostensive agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It gets worse. The third edition at this point questions the concept of separation of church and state, asserts that the public education system is not neutral, since it teaches naturalistic explanations, quotes Matthew 12:30 that one is either for Christ or against him, and says that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;To help parents understand the reality of the situation, I suggest we say “anti-God schools” instead of public (secular) schools to remind us of what these institutions really are.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the public school system teaches naturalistic explanation, says Ham, it is indoctrinating into a religion of atheism, thus undermining Christianity and Christian morality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we have the reason for creationist advocacy of voucher schemes, designed to use public funds for children to be educated at creationist schools, and for homeschooling. The upsurge in political support for voucher schemes, which incidentally starves the public sector of funds, is now a major problem; see, e.g., here. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussion of sexual behavior, especially homosexuality, is a fine example of Ham’s reasoning: We know that homosexuality is wrong because homosexuality is condemned in numerous Bible verses. But without the Bible, we would not have convincing reason for calling it wrong, although it clearly is. Thus homosexuality is wrong because the Bible says so, and the Bible’s condemnation of homosexuality confirms that biblical morality is correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ham uses the familiar creationist argument that the study of the past, as in evolution science, is not science at all. For science involves repeatable observations, and the past is unrepeatable. He boasts of how he used this argument, in his school-teaching days, to undermine his colleagues’ teaching. It is also very attractive argument, since those who accept it believe that they have been granted a superior insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, The third edition tells us that
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the Creation Museum, we summarize biblical history as the Seven C’s of History — Creation, Corruption, Catastrophe, Confusion, Christ, Cross, and Consummation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Susan and William Trollinger point out in their book about the Museum, these 7 C’s are strongly reminiscent of the 7 D’s of dispensationalism, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Premillennialism&quot;&gt;premillennialist&lt;/a&gt; interpretation of history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ham appears completely oblivious of the fact that his own interpretation of Genesis is heavily laden with assumptions. Or if he is, he no doubt attributes them to the operation within him of the Holy Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ham argues that Christians who accept the findings of secular science are being inconsistent. If they choose to accept millions of years, they have succumbed to the disease of naturalism, of which evolutionism is merely a symptom. And naturalism is itself a religion, since by denying God’s role it is a form of atheism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this in the book’s first chapter. The remaining 150 pages add little new, and I will content myself with a few significant points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 3, “Creationism is Religion,” tells us that the Creation took place in six days, and God called it “very good.” It follows that there was no death, all animals were vegetarians, the climate was mild from pole to pole, and there was no bad weather. However, this Edenic state of affairs did not last. Why not?
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because our first parents placed human opinion above God’s word (as we continue to do), struggle and death entered the world and God cursed the creation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wickedness of later generations brought on Flood, and the billions of fossils laid down the Flood sediments (all sediments, we take it, are Flood sediments) remind us of “God’s judgment on sin.” Nonetheless, after the Flood the earth once again became filled with corruption because of human sin. Christ’s death and resurrection conquered death, and through Him we may be born into eternal life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thus as surely as God created the world and judged the world with the Flood, our ungodly world will be destroyed by fire. For those who trust in Jesus, however, there awaits eternal life in the new heavens and new earth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note again the linking of the judgement of the Flood to the coming judgement of fire. This theme is developed further in the concluding chapter, as discussed below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third edition covers the same ground in greater detail, once again invoking the 7 C’s, and presenting Ham’s creative reinterpretations of specific verses as if they were God-given.&lt;sup&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the core of Christianity, as represented by Answers in Genesis, and the movement of which it is part. It is a curious form of Christianity, reducing it almost to a commercial transaction. What you have to do, is trust in Jesus. And He in return will give you eternal life, after this world has been destroyed. Nothing here about love your enemies, turn the other cheek, blessed are the peacemakers, who is my neighbor, I was hungry and you fed me not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A computer scan of the third edition shows 180 references to sin, and just 35 references to love, of which only 8 refer to love between human beings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 4, “The Root of the Problem,” accuses evolution of providing justification for rebellion against God. Moreover, 
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;All the evolutionists have to do is to come up with one piece of evidence that conclusively proves evolution &lt;/i&gt;[emphasis in original]. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I come across this kind of assertion all the time in social media. It is difficult to know how to deal with an argument so confidently presented while being totally at variance with reality (right now, the problem also arises in areas other than evolution). The evidence for the historical fact of evolution was conclusive, by all reasonable standards, over a century ago. Moreover, the time interval between the 1987 and 2024 editions of the book have produced further layers of evidence, based on DNA relationships. The creationist organizations themselves are well aware of these developments. However, as I mentioned earlier, Ham has set up his rules of evidence in advance, in such a way as to be free to ignore them. We see here the rhetorical device of &lt;i&gt;demanding the impossible&lt;/i&gt;. Ham is asking for proof, but has already stated that the relevant evidence is unacceptable. He then uses the absence of proof that he would regard as acceptable, as conclusive evidence that his opponents are arguing in bad faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 5 gives a few other examples of what Ham claims, to my mind completely falsely, to be biblical teaching. For example, Genesis gives us the doctrine of marriage as the union between one man and one woman for life. I am reduced to wondering whether Ham has actually &lt;i&gt;read&lt;/i&gt; Genesis. For if he did, what he would find there is arranged marriage to preserve the bloodline, fathers selling their daughters, concubinage, polygamy, women procuring their slavegirls as breeding stock for their husbands, and levirate marriage, whose purpose is to provide a dead man with an heir.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also says that the Bible tells us that from the point of conception (in the 2024 edition, of course, this becomes the point of fertilization), we are human beings, so that abortion in all instances is killing a human being. Yet the Bible chapters that he himself cites (Psalm 139, Jeremiah 1) speak of the child &lt;i&gt;being formed&lt;/i&gt; in the womb; the very opposite of what he tells us. He objects to women pastors, because (no verse cited) God created men and women for separate roles. There are also vague references, again with no verse cited, to the process of appointing deacons, and strict discipline (I think he means spanking) for children. Ham’s version of biblical Christianity is shot through with such nonbiblical opinions, in all their lamentable fallibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Chapter 6, a great deal is said of the need for clothes, in order to curb sexual arousal, and about humanity’s inherently sinful nature. As further evidence of the growing politicization of AiG, the third edition goes out of its way at this point to mention President Obama’s and President Biden’s support for gay marriage. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 7 tells us that 
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;All who believe in Jesus Christ as Lord and Savior are received back to God to spend eternity with Him. Isn’t that a wonderful message? &lt;i&gt;That is the message of Christianity&lt;/i&gt; [emphasis in original].&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are of course, as I mentioned earlier, other aspects to Christianity, such as loving your neighbor, but the book seems strangely unaware of these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 8 tells us of The Evils of Evolution, which as we have seen include lawlessness, homosexuality, and abortion. 
&lt;p&gt;The third edition now goes out of its way to mention Planned Parenthood, which it describes as “one of the biggest child-killing ‘machines’ in the world,” and mentions in linked paragraphs that its founder, Margaret Sanger, was a fervent eugenicist, and that she promoted the use of birth control. As we have seen, the changes between the first edition and The third edition tells us very plainly how AiG is developing politically, and we must take the reference to birth control very seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, with no sense of irony, Ham tells us in successive paragraphs that evolutionary thinking has been used to defend male chauvinism, and that Christian women should not be deceived by the feminist movement, which is anti-God, since God has given men and women different roles. The third edition even warns us of the danger that “women will abuse their role and want to usurp the authority of the man in regard to headship.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He then summarizes his arguments to date by a cartoon showing two opposing castles. The castle of Christianity is wasting its ammunition by firing at specific targets, while evolution, guided by Satan, attacks the Christian doctrine of creation. Such at least is what we see in the 1987 version of the cartoon, which has been discussed here before. It is one of many such drawings scattered throughout the book, which do have a certain faux naïve charm. The 2024 version, by contrast, looks so bad that I wonder whether it is AI-generated. But notice the reference in the later version to Revelation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;  
  &lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Braterman_Lie_Castles old_600.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; alt=&quot;Old castles figure&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Warring Castles. &lt;small&gt;1st ed., p.92, fair use.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Braterman_Lie_Castle new_600.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; alt=&quot;New castles figure, in color&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Warring Castles, new figure, in color. &lt;small&gt;3rd ed. p. 178, fair use.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 10, Wake Up, Shepherds! repeats the message that the only sound preaching is based on one particular interpretation of Genesis. Both editions go out of their way to attack and belittle Darwin, as is usual, but the third edition adds a remark so outrageous, that I cannot forbear from comment:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the time of Darwin, much research has shown that observational science (e.g., the study of genetics) does not confirm Darwin’s ideas but actually contradicts them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ham taught biology, and environmental biology was his degree major. He graduated in the early 1970's, and it is difficult to believe that he was unaware of the way in which the coming together of Mendelian genetics, classical paleontology, and the solving of the genetic code were placing evolution science on an ever-firmer foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 11, Creation, Flood, and Coming Fire, concludes the book’s central argument by linking the creation of this world to its imminent destruction. It starts with a quotation also used by Henry Morris in his 1951 book, &lt;i&gt;The Bible and Modern Science&lt;/i&gt;, and again in &lt;i&gt;The Genesis Flood&lt;/i&gt;. Ham devotes particular attention to this passage, and so should we:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a prophecy in II Peter concerning the last days of this earth’s history, and it very much relates to the whole creation/evolution issue:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;II Peter 3:3-7 (NIV) states: “First of all, you must understand that in the last days scoffers welcome, scoffing and following their own evil desires. They will say, ‘Where is this coming He promised? Ever since our fathers died, everything goes on as it has since the beginning of creation.’ But they deliberately forget that long ago by God’s Word the heavens existed and the earth was formed out of water with water. By water also the world of that time was deluged and destroyed. By the same word the present heavens and earth are reserved for fire, being kept for the day of judgment and destruction of ungodly men.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see this prophecy being fulfilled in front of our own eyes. The people who tell us that “everything goes on as it has since the beginning of creation” are the evolutionists and deep time geologists. They use the principle that “the present is key to the past,” and invoke the observed present-day processes of sedimentation and mutation in their discussions of geology and evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this, they are “willingly ignorant.” They have deliberately chosen not to believe in the Genesis account of creation, God’s judgement of the world at the time of Noah’s Flood, and coming judgment by fire. If they do not think that the geological record is convincing evidence of the Flood, that is because they do not want to be convinced. And the reason why they do not want to be convinced is that they do not wish to acknowledge God’s authority, obey His rules, and stand in awe of the coming judgment by fire. The very fact that the Biblical account is being questioned is itself a fulfilment of Biblical prophecy, confirming (as if confirmation were required) that the Bible account is true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sun, moon, and stars are evidence of God’s creation. The sediments are evidence of God’s judgment in the Flood, and Last Day’s prophecies are being fulfilled before our eyes. And, just in case we haven’t got the point, a final quotation in bold from II Peter 3:11-12a:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Since everything will be destroyed in this way, what kind of people ought you to be? You ought to live holy and godly lives as you look forward to the day of God and speed its coming &lt;/i&gt;[emphasis in original].&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How we are supposed to speed its coming, it may be wiser not to inquire. 

&lt;i&gt;A longer version of this post has appeared on 3 Quarks Daily.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. Ham repeatedly imposes his theologically motivated interpretation on the text. For those interested in exegesis, I pedantically present a couple of examples from the third edition, where we are given, in successive paragraphs without explanation,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;The very first time the gospel is preached is in Genesis 3:15: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;i&gt;And I will put enmity between you and the woman, And between your seed and her Seed; He shall bruise your head, And you shall bruise His heel &lt;/i&gt;[emphasis in original].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The set up of the sacrificial system and a picture of what was to come in Jesus’ sacrifice on the Cross is found in Genesis 3:21:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Also for Adam and his wife the Lord God made tunics of skin, and clothed them &lt;/i&gt;[emphasis in original]. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ham is imposing, and is expecting his readers to impose, meanings imported from commentaries. In verse 3:15, the serpent has been equated with Satan, the woman’s seed with Jesus, the bruising of the heel refers to Jesus’s suffering in His human aspect, and the bruising of the head is Jesus’ triumph over Satan. The capital H’s correspond to nothing in the Hebrew text, but are inserted because Ham thinks the pronouns refer to Christ. In 3:21, tunics of skin imply that an animal has been killed for the purpose, and for reasons I do not quite understand this is a foreshadowing of the Crucifixion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you regard all this as contorted and arbitrary, I quite agree. Or you may regard it as serious exegesis, some at least of which goes back to the Church Fathers. But whatever your opinion, the point is that this is material added to the text, not found within it, and therefore, by Ham’s own criteria, part of man’s thoughts, here misrepresented as God’s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman</name></author><summary type="html">The following is a review of The Lie, by Ken Ham (Master Book, 2024), and a comparison of the 1987, 2012, and 2024 editions. A longer article appeared here in 3 Quarks Daily. Let me first remind you of the scale of Ken Ham’s political significance. He has among his friends Mike Johnson, Speaker of the US House of Representatives, whose law firm has represented AiG pro bono. And among the contributors to its magazine is Calvin Beisner, director of the Cornwall Alliance, whose entire purpose is to deny the importance of human-caused climate change. Cornwall in turn has direct links to the Heartland Institute and to the Heritage Foundation, authors of Project 2025. Readers here will be familiar with the destructive and anti-scientific approach of the modern creationist movement in the US. But that’s only half the story. It is not only about the beginning of the world, but about its ending. Genesis is pivotal, but so is Revelation. So are the many hints of the end of the world that are explicit in the New Testament, and can be discovered with sufficient ingenuity in the Old. Such thinking underlines the apocalyptic tone, repeatedly echoed in AiG’s material, that underlies current US right-wing politics. If the Earth does not have a deep past, we cannot expect it to have a prolonged future. We should not be concerning ourselves with conservation, but with righteousness. This perspective has political implications, and comparing the 1987 and 2024 versions of The Lie shows the political aspect becoming increasingly explicit. Otherwise, there is not much difference between the two editions, though The third edition is more repetitious and, where direct comparison is possible, less vigorous in its use of language, and more hectoring, than the original.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gnaphosidae</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/10/gnaphosidae.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gnaphosidae" /><published>2024-10-14T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-14T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/10/gnaphosidae</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/10/gnaphosidae.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/DSC05853_Ground_Spider_Gnaphosidae_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ground spider&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ground_spider&quot;&gt;Gnaphosidae&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; ground spider, Boulder, Colorado, July, 2024. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this spider trapped in a porcelain sink from which it could not climb out, so I naturally snapped a few pictures. The people at &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugguide.net&quot;&gt;Bugguide&lt;/a&gt; classified it as a member of the family Gnaphosidae. They warned me that Google Lens is not good at spiders, but, just for fun, I asked. Among the first hits was my very own picture of this very spider &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugguide.net/node/view/2379696&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Gnaphosidae &amp;ndash; ground spider, Boulder, Colorado, July, 2024. I found this spider trapped in a porcelain sink from which it could not climb out, so I naturally snapped a few pictures. The people at Bugguide classified it as a member of the family Gnaphosidae. They warned me that Google Lens is not good at spiders, but, just for fun, I asked. Among the first hits was my very own picture of this very spider here. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cheiracanthium sp</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/cheiracanthium-sp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cheiracanthium sp" /><published>2024-09-30T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-30T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/cheiracanthium-sp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/cheiracanthium-sp.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/DSC05926_Spider_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Yellow sac spider&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheiracanthium&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;Cheiracanthium&lt;/i&gt; sp. &amp;ndash; yellow sac spider, Boulder, Colorado, September, 2024.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this spider inside the house the other day and managed to get a picture showing the 8 eyes. In case you were wondering &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/What_Is_It_Like_to_Be_a_Bat%3F&quot;&gt; what it is like to be a bat&lt;/a&gt;, think about what it must be like to be a spider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spiders have simple eyes, as opposed to compound eyes like those of a dragonfly. Because the eyes are so small, they cannot have good resolution: Even if the eyes were diffraction-limited, their sensors would have to be roughly the same size as the cones in human eyes, for example, and there would be many fewer of them. (In photographic terms, all diffraction-limited F/4 lenses have the same resolution limit, but a longer focal-length lens affords more detail. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.phys.ufl.edu/courses/phy3221/spring10/HaldaneRightSize.pdf&quot;&gt;This paper&lt;/a&gt; by Haldane notes that an eye is not very good until it reaches a certain size, but a colleague of mine has just pointed out that context matters and the spider does not need a better eye.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Wikipedia entry on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spider_vision&quot;&gt;spider vision &lt;/a&gt;, the two central eyes in the lower bank are the &lt;i&gt;principal eyes&lt;/i&gt;, and they do their best to form an image, but the pixels (if you will) are nowhere near the focal point. The spider is thus dreadfully nearsighted, though he must get some imaging due to the depth of field. The other, &lt;i&gt;secondary&lt;/i&gt; eyes are used for light and motion detection, and, for example, polarization detection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Cheiracanthium sp. &amp;ndash; yellow sac spider, Boulder, Colorado, September, 2024. I found this spider inside the house the other day and managed to get a picture showing the 8 eyes. In case you were wondering what it is like to be a bat, think about what it must be like to be a spider. Spiders have simple eyes, as opposed to compound eyes like those of a dragonfly. Because the eyes are so small, they cannot have good resolution: Even if the eyes were diffraction-limited, their sensors would have to be roughly the same size as the cones in human eyes, for example, and there would be many fewer of them. (In photographic terms, all diffraction-limited F/4 lenses have the same resolution limit, but a longer focal-length lens affords more detail. This paper by Haldane notes that an eye is not very good until it reaches a certain size, but a colleague of mine has just pointed out that context matters and the spider does not need a better eye.) According to the Wikipedia entry on spider vision , the two central eyes in the lower bank are the principal eyes, and they do their best to form an image, but the pixels (if you will) are nowhere near the focal point. The spider is thus dreadfully nearsighted, though he must get some imaging due to the depth of field. The other, secondary eyes are used for light and motion detection, and, for example, polarization detection. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Francis Collins: Facts do not care whether you accept them or not</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/francis-collins-facts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Francis Collins: Facts do not care whether you accept them or not" /><published>2024-09-26T15:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-26T15:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/francis-collins-facts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/francis-collins-facts.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/POTUS_visit_to_NIH_(51730034783).jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Collins meeting Pres. Biden &quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:POTUS_visit_to_NIH_(51730034783).jpg&quot;&gt; President Biden bumps fists with NIH Director Dr. Francis Collins&lt;/a&gt; during a visit to the NIH campus on December 2, 2021. I found it interesting that they were both wearing masks and they did not shake hands. &lt;small&gt;Credit: NIH/Chia-Chi Charlie Chang. Work of the United States government, not subject to copyright.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a little late out of the starting blocks, but last Sunday Francis Collins published an opinion article titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2024/09/20/opinion/covid-vaccines-truth-life-death.html&quot;&gt;Take It From a Scientist. Facts Matter, and They Don’t Care How You Feel&lt;/a&gt; in the opinion section of The New York Times. In case there are any readers who do not know it, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Collins&quot;&gt;Francis Collins&lt;/a&gt; is the former director of the Human Genome Project and more recently director of the National Institutes of Health. He presided over NIH in the early part of the pandemic and during the development of vaccines for Covid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the article, he outlines the development of the vaccines and rightly bemoans the number of Americans who refused to get vaccinated, even when vaccination was free. He notes that white evangelical Christians, of whom he is one, were the most highly resistant to getting vaccinated. He says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Public distrust, driven by social media, cable news and even some politicians, reflected a host of concerns: whether Covid-19 was real, whether it was really all that serious, whether the vaccines were rushed, whether there were common and serious side effects that had been hidden, whether the mRNA would alter the recipient’s DNA and whether companies had skirted the rules about safety. More outlandish conspiracies also circulated on social media: that the vaccines contained microchips or cells from recently aborted fetuses, for example. People of faith were particularly hard hit by misinformation.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Collins avers,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;We are in serious trouble when some believe that their faith requires them to distrust science or when others believe that political allegiances are a better source of wisdom than truth, faith or science.… In many aspects of our daily lives, the anchor to objective truth seems to have been lost.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addressing not only his coreligionists, Dr. Collins asks rhetorically, “&lt;strong&gt;What do we mean&lt;/strong&gt; by truth anyway? [Emphasis in original].” He asks us to imagine a set of concentric circles, sort of like a target, I guess. The central area, the bull’s-eye, encompasses what he calls “necessary truth,” such as 2 + 2 = 4, or A = πr&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. The next circle out (a ring or annulus, in reality) subsumes conclusions that are so overwhelmingly supported by theory and experiment that they truly ought to be considered facts: the inverse-square law of gravity and the facts that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;DNA is the hereditary material for humans. The average temperature of planet Earth is rapidly increasing — yes, it really is. And Covid vaccines were tested in rigorous trials in 2020 and found to be safe and effective. These statements are all established scientific facts.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next ring out includes claims that may be true, “but the evidence is currently insufficient to move them into the circle of firmly established facts.” For example, did mask mandates reduce Covid transmission?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, opinions, such as “Dogs make better pets than cats.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Collins stresses the importance of knowing which annular area pertains: Are you sure that everything you consider factual is well-established? Are you sure that claims you consider mere opinion are not facts? Equally, he argues that we must have serious conversations with people with whom we disagree. I was reminded of a recent comment by a pen-pal of mine, who decried calling Mr. Trump’s, um, prevarications about the election “lies.” He would prefer, and I agree, calling them “unsubstantiated claims,” so as not to immediately antagonize listeners who may be sympathetic to Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is more to the article, much of it, I thought, bordering on pabulum of the “we need to build consensus” variety. I sincerely hope, though, that Dr. Collins can convince some of his fellow evangelicals to accept facts and adjust some of their opinions accordingly, rather than succumb to mis- or disinformation, such as rumors about the Covid vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Dr. Collins says, “The consequences of vaccine misinformation have been utterly tragic.” You can say the same about misinformation about climate change, which he mentions but does not discuss.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">President Biden bumps fists with NIH Director Dr. Francis Collins during a visit to the NIH campus on December 2, 2021. I found it interesting that they were both wearing masks and they did not shake hands. Credit: NIH/Chia-Chi Charlie Chang. Work of the United States government, not subject to copyright. I am a little late out of the starting blocks, but last Sunday Francis Collins published an opinion article titled Take It From a Scientist. Facts Matter, and They Don’t Care How You Feel in the opinion section of The New York Times. In case there are any readers who do not know it, Francis Collins is the former director of the Human Genome Project and more recently director of the National Institutes of Health. He presided over NIH in the early part of the pandemic and during the development of vaccines for Covid. In the article, he outlines the development of the vaccines and rightly bemoans the number of Americans who refused to get vaccinated, even when vaccination was free. He notes that white evangelical Christians, of whom he is one, were the most highly resistant to getting vaccinated. He says,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Worst. Book about the Scopes Trial. Ever!</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/worst-book-about.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Worst. Book about the Scopes Trial. Ever!" /><published>2024-09-19T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-19T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/worst-book-about</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/worst-book-about.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Branch_Worst_Book_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bryan being questioned by Darrow&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;William Jennings Bryan (left, seated) being questioned by Clarence Darrow at the Scopes Trial in Dayton, Tennessee. &lt;small&gt;Image from the Smithsonian Archives via &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Tennessee_v._John_T._Scopes_Trial-_Outdoor_proceedings_on_July_20,_1925,_showing_William_Jennings_Bryan_and_Clarence_Darrow._(2_of_4_photos)_(2898243103)_crop.jpg&quot;&gt; Wikimedia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Reprinted with permission from &lt;/i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/worst-book-about-the-scopes-trial-ever/&quot;&gt;Worst. Book about the Scopes Trial. Ever!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;, published on September 10, 2024, by &lt;/i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;Righting America&quot;&gt;Righting America&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;, a forum for scholarly conversation about Christianity, culture, and politics in the US.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Glenn Branch is deputy director of the National Center for Science Education, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as &lt;/i&gt;Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher&lt;i&gt;, and the &lt;/i&gt;Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics&lt;i&gt;, and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of &lt;/i&gt;Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools&lt;i&gt; (2006). He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the summer of 1925, a young teacher, John T. Scopes, was on trial in Dayton, Tennessee, for violating a recently enacted state law, the Butler Act, which forbade educators in the state&amp;rsquo;s public schools to &amp;ldquo;teach any theory that denies the truth of the Divine Creation of man as taught in the Bible, and to teach instead that man has descended from a lower order of animals.&amp;rdquo; The Scopes trial was instantly a national sensation, partly thanks to the participation of two national figures &amp;mdash; William Jennings Bryan on the prosecution team and Clarence Darrow on the defense team &amp;mdash; and the reportage of a third, the brilliant but mordant journalist H. L. Mencken. With its hundredth anniversary just around the corner, the Scopes trial is understandably attracting attention again, with recent treatments including Randy Moore&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomsbury.com/in/scopes-monkey-trial-9798216184171/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Scopes &amp;ldquo;Monkey Trial&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2022), Gregg Jarrett&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/The-Trial-of-the-Century/Gregg-Jarrett/9781982198572&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Trial of the Century&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2023), and Brenda Wineapple&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/648098/keeping-the-faith-by-brenda-wineapple/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Keeping the Faith&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2024). These are all more or less readable and accurate guides to the context, personalities, conduct, aftermath, and significance of the trial. And then, in contrast, there is Jerry Bergman&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://wipfandstock.com/9798385200887/the-other-side-of-the-scopes-monkey-trial/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Other Side of the Scopes Monkey Trial&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2023).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the thesis of &lt;em&gt;The Other Side of the Scopes Monkey Trial&lt;/em&gt;? According to its subtitle, &lt;em&gt;At Its Heart the Trial was about Racism,&lt;/em&gt; while within the text, Bergman awkwardly declaims, &amp;ldquo;The trial was about human evolution, and more about &lt;em&gt;racism and eugenics&lt;/em&gt; than religion and evolution&amp;rdquo; (p. 5, emphasis in original). Later, a section complaining that commentators on the trial ignore the racism and eugenics of both classroom textbooks and the American scientific community of the 1920s is entitled &amp;ldquo;Denying the Core of the Scopes Trial&amp;rdquo;; in the following chapter, Bergman writes, &amp;ldquo;That the teaching of eugenics was at issue in the Scopes Trial was obvious to those who understood what eugenics is all about is clear&amp;rdquo; (p. 61); and the chapter after that is entitled &amp;ldquo;The Scopes Trial: A Struggle Against Eugenics and Racism.&amp;rdquo; And in the final chapter, Bergman concludes, &amp;ldquo;The racism and eugenics that was central in the Scopes Trial has been ignored, even though it is a well-documented part of the record&amp;rdquo; (p. 195). Thus, although there is a certain perplexing vacillation between racism and eugenics, the book&amp;rsquo;s thesis appears to be that the Scopes trial was about these issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a glaring obstacle to the thesis, which in fact Bergman briefly acknowledges: that &amp;ldquo;in the entire Scopes court &lt;a href=&quot;https://profjoecain.net/scopes-monkey-trial-1925-complete-trial-transcripts/&quot;&gt;transcript&lt;/a&gt; the topic of eugenics and racism was avoided&amp;rdquo; (p. 81, link added). He then clutches at a counterfactual straw, suggesting that if Bryan, a prominent Democrat, had been a Republican, then he might have focused &amp;ldquo;on the racism and eugenics core of the Hunter textbook [&lt;em&gt;A Civic Biology&lt;/em&gt;, from which Scopes taught]&amp;rdquo; (p. 81). But as matters stand, the Scopes trial was clearly not about racism and eugenics. It is equally clear that a number of the participants in and observers of the Scopes trial held various attitudes toward racism and eugenics, which were matters of public controversy in the 1920s &amp;mdash; but there would be no point in writing a book to document the fact. Is there a thesis in the neighborhood that is neither clearly false nor clearly trivial? Perhaps that the attitudes toward racism and eugenics of the participants in and the observers of the trial significantly and substantially influenced the conduct of and the public understanding of the trial? That suggestion threads the needle, but it would require meticulously collected and judiciously assessed evidence to make the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No attempt to make such a case is visible in &lt;em&gt;The Other Side of the Scopes Monkey Trial&lt;/em&gt;, and meticulous collection and judicious assessment of evidence are likewise absent. Instead, there is hagiographizing, conspiracy theorizing, and mudslinging. For example, amid Bergman&amp;rsquo;s fulsome praise for Bryan, there is no mention of what his biographer Michael Kazin described in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/90625/a-godly-hero-by-michael-kazin/9780307424358/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Godly Hero&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2006) as &amp;ldquo;Bryan&amp;rsquo;s habit of ignoring the &amp;lsquo;race problem&amp;rsquo; or minimizing it with fatuous rationales,&amp;rdquo; which culminated with his last political &lt;a href=&quot;https://newrepublic.com/article/183009/craziest-convention-american-history&quot;&gt;success&lt;/a&gt;: convincing the 1924 Democratic National Convention not to adopt a party platform plank condemning the Ku Klux Klan by name. Bergman alleges that the leaders of the American Civil Liberties Union, which coordinated Scopes&amp;rsquo;s defense, &amp;ldquo;no doubt openly, or covertly, agreed to ignore the most important part of the Scopes case, namely its racism&amp;rdquo; (p. 74), a claim for which there is no rationale evident except for the need to protect his thesis come what may. Chapter 10, the longest chapter of the book, is a sustained attempt at assassinating the moral character of Mencken &amp;mdash; who, to be sure, was not exactly a paragon on matters of race, gender, and religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even independently of the fact that it consists entirely of a string of decontextualized quotations from Mencken&amp;rsquo;s voluminous oeuvre with Bergman&amp;rsquo;s perfunctory and sometimes bizarre comments on them, intended to portray Mencken as,&lt;em&gt; inter alia&lt;/em&gt;, a vicious racist, eugenicist, and bigot, chapter 10 is deeply problematic. The problem is that Bergman&amp;rsquo;s discussion is conspicuously similar to Vincent Torley&amp;rsquo;s 2012 blog post &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.angelfire.com/linux/vjtorley/mencken.html&quot;&gt;H. L. Mencken: Is this your hero, New Atheists?&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; &amp;mdash; not only in the selection and order of the quotations but also in the language used to summarize and criticize them. For example, Torley asks, with respect to a whimsical suggestion of Mencken&amp;rsquo;s that God should have used platinum rather than carbon as a basis for life, &amp;ldquo;But has Mencken even thought for a moment about how a platinum organism would eat, excrete, reproduce and for that matter, evolve?&amp;rdquo; while Bergman declares, &amp;ldquo;Mencken had obviously not thought about how platinum-based organisms could possibly eat, grow, excrete and, for that matter, evolve&amp;rdquo; (p. 161). Bergman cites Torley&amp;rsquo;s blog post only once (p. 128, n. 15), regrettably not in a way that adequately acknowledges his apparent debt to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bergman&amp;rsquo;s scholarly practices are otherwise troubling. He often cites subpar scholarship, including from his fellow creationists, without any evident discernment. He repeatedly interpolates unwarranted text of his own into verbatim quotations, including in a passage from Martin Gilbert&amp;rsquo;s history of the twentieth century (p. 9), a letter from Leonard Darwin &amp;mdash; a son of Charles Darwin, writing on behalf of the Eugenics Education Society &amp;mdash; to Scopes (p. 61), and a passage from Edward J. Larson&amp;rsquo;s book about the trial (p. 195). Similarly, he claims that &amp;ldquo;a survey of AAAS members found that close to 99 percent are functional atheists, meaning that they live their lives as if there is no God&amp;rdquo;: he is evidently referring to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/science/2015/07/23/an-elaboration-of-aaas-scientists-views/&quot;&gt;Pew Research Center&lt;/a&gt; survey in 2014 that found that close to 99 percent of members of the American Association for the Advancement of Science accept that humans have evolved over time: the &amp;ldquo;functional atheism&amp;rdquo; claim is a confabulation. He wrongly claims that the pistol-packing pastor J. Frank Norris came to Dayton, Tennessee, during the Scopes trial, citing &amp;ldquo;Larson, &amp;lsquo;Classroom Controversy,&amp;rsquo; 54&amp;rdquo;: the article in question begins on p. 63 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.press.jhu.edu/books/title/9326/pandas-black-box&quot;&gt;The Panda&amp;rsquo;s Black Box&lt;/a&gt; (2007) and Norris is not mentioned in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A particularly interesting error is not entirely Bergman&amp;rsquo;s fault. Relying on James Gilbert&amp;rsquo;s account in &lt;a href=&quot;https://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/R/bo3615369.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Redeeming Culture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (1997), he claims that Bryan argued to the West Virginia legislature in 1923 that evolution is precluded by the second law of thermodynamics. (He then proceeds to endorse the argument, unaware or uncaring that it is scientifically &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution-outreach.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1007/s12052-009-0195-3&quot;&gt;bankrupt&lt;/a&gt;.) That would be strange if true, not only because Bryan fails to use the argument in his most famous antievolution writings, such as &lt;em&gt;In His Image &lt;/em&gt;(1922) and his planned closing address in the Scopes trial, but also because the argument seems to have gained currency only with the work of two British creationists, Robert E. D. Clark and E. H. Betts, in the 1940s. (The wrinkle that the second law is the objective correlative of the Fall would later be introduced in &lt;em&gt;The Genesis Flood&lt;/em&gt; [1961], by John C. Whitcomb and Henry M. Morris.) But it is not true. And it would not have been difficult for Bergman to locate Bryan&amp;rsquo;s speech, reprinted as the second part of &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/OrthodoxChristianityVersusModernism&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Orthodox Christanity versus Modernism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (1923), and there to find that the closest Bryan approaches the second law of thermodynamics is invoking the distinct phenomenon of radioactive decay. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bergman repeatedly, and correctly, emphasizes that the Butler Act, under which Scopes was prosecuted, only concerned the teaching of human evolution. He accordingly devotes chapter 9 to a discussion of human evolution. The result is inaccurate and incompetent. He claims that the scientific evidence for human evolution presented at the Scopes trial consisted of &amp;ldquo;Nebraska Man, Piltdown Man, Java Man, and Neanderthal Man fossils&amp;rdquo; (p. 106), and devotes most of the chapter to &amp;ldquo;Nebraska Man,&amp;rdquo; repeating whole sentences and paragraphs in the process. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&quot;https://magazine.atavist.com/curious-case-of-nebraska-man-william-jennings-bryan-scopes-trial-evolution-creationism/&quot;&gt;Nebraska Man&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; was known only from what proved to be a fossil peccary tooth &amp;mdash; not, pace Bergman, a fossil pig tooth &amp;mdash; and was not presented at the Scopes trial, although it might have been if Henry Fairfield Osborn, the president of the American Museum of Natural History and the chief promoter of the fossil, had testified. Perhaps exhausted by his Nebraskan efforts, Bergman dismisses &amp;ldquo;Java Man&amp;rdquo; as &amp;ldquo;another race of humans called &lt;em&gt;Homo erectus&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; (p. 118) &amp;mdash; not exactly a devastating rejoinder &amp;mdash; and fails to rehearse the standard, long-ago-refuted, creationist complaints about &amp;ldquo;Piltdown Man&amp;rdquo; (a never tremendously convincing hoax) and Neanderthals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all of Bergman&amp;rsquo;s myriad errors are tendentious. Stephen Jay Gould is misquoted as referring to the &amp;ldquo;populace&amp;rdquo; rather than the &amp;ldquo;populist&amp;rdquo; thinking of Bryan (p. 26); the anthropologist Ruth Benedict is rechristened Ruth Bennet (p. 37); the polling organization Gallup departs at a gallop (p. 55). Bergman reports that &amp;ldquo;the Supreme Court refused to hear the Scopes appeal&amp;rdquo; (p. 103): if he&amp;rsquo;s thinking of the Tennessee Supreme Court, he&amp;rsquo;s wrong because the court indeed heard the appeal, overturning the verdict, while if he&amp;rsquo;s thinking of the United States Supreme Court, he&amp;rsquo;s wrong because the case was not appealed to it. Two paragraphs of chapter 12, which contains only six paragraphs, rely on the conclusions of &amp;ldquo;Georgianna,&amp;rdquo; with no full name or bibliographical information provided. (&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.proquest.com/openview/c8cd810026d7c7700ecda2d5ae839f8d/1?pq-origsite=gscholar&amp;amp;cbl=18750&amp;amp;diss=y&quot;&gt;The Moral Majority and Fundamentalism: Plausibility and Dissonance&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;rdquo; Sharon Linzey Georgianna&amp;rsquo;s 1984 dissertation at Indiana University, was presumably intended.) The sole appendix presents the text of a Tennessee law: not the Butler Act, but House Bill 368/Senate Bill 893 of 2012, nicknamed &amp;ldquo;the monkey bill&amp;rdquo; and codified as &lt;a href=&quot;https://law.justia.com/codes/tennessee/2021/title-49/chapter-6/part-10/section-49-6-1030/&quot;&gt;Tennessee Code 49-6-1030&lt;/a&gt;. No explanation is offered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early in &lt;em&gt;The Other Side of the Scopes Monkey Trial&lt;/em&gt;, Bergman writes, &amp;ldquo;The present work is an attempt to fill in this important gap&amp;rdquo; (p. 7). Characteristically, there is no explicit description of a gap in the preceding text, but he appears to mean that there&amp;rsquo;s a lack of discussions of the trial sympathetic to the prosecution, which overlooks any number of works, including Marvin Olasky and John Perry&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Monkey Business&lt;/em&gt; (2005), which appears in Bergman&amp;rsquo;s bibliography. A shoddy and biased apologia for creationism, &lt;em&gt;Monkey Business&lt;/em&gt; is nevertheless head and shoulders over &lt;em&gt;The Other Side of the Scopes Monkey Trial&lt;/em&gt;: not nearly so badly conceived, researched, organized, written, and edited. After offering his description of &amp;ldquo;the present work,&amp;rdquo; Bergman continues, &amp;ldquo;and it is up to readers to determine how successful this tome was&amp;rdquo; (p. 7) &amp;mdash; for all the world as if readers are unaware of their prerogatives. Only readers who are already relatively familiar with the trial are guaranteed to recognize the abject failure of the book, unfortunately; despite the crudity and incompetence of what can only be described as Bergman&amp;rsquo;s propaganda, there is a risk that the uninformed and the gullible will be misled.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Glenn Branch</name></author><summary type="html">William Jennings Bryan (left, seated) being questioned by Clarence Darrow at the Scopes Trial in Dayton, Tennessee. Image from the Smithsonian Archives via Wikimedia. Reprinted with permission from Worst. Book about the Scopes Trial. Ever!, published on September 10, 2024, by Righting America, a forum for scholarly conversation about Christianity, culture, and politics in the US. Glenn Branch is deputy director of the National Center for Science Education, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher, and the Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics, and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools (2006). He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers. In the summer of 1925, a young teacher, John T. Scopes, was on trial in Dayton, Tennessee, for violating a recently enacted state law, the Butler Act, which forbade educators in the state&amp;rsquo;s public schools to &amp;ldquo;teach any theory that denies the truth of the Divine Creation of man as taught in the Bible, and to teach instead that man has descended from a lower order of animals.&amp;rdquo; The Scopes trial was instantly a national sensation, partly thanks to the participation of two national figures &amp;mdash; William Jennings Bryan on the prosecution team and Clarence Darrow on the defense team &amp;mdash; and the reportage of a third, the brilliant but mordant journalist H. L. Mencken. With its hundredth anniversary just around the corner, the Scopes trial is understandably attracting attention again, with recent treatments including Randy Moore&amp;rsquo;s The Scopes &amp;ldquo;Monkey Trial&amp;rdquo; (2022), Gregg Jarrett&amp;rsquo;s The Trial of the Century (2023), and Brenda Wineapple&amp;rsquo;s Keeping the Faith (2024). These are all more or less readable and accurate guides to the context, personalities, conduct, aftermath, and significance of the trial. And then, in contrast, there is Jerry Bergman&amp;rsquo;s The Other Side of the Scopes Monkey Trial (2023). What is the thesis of The Other Side of the Scopes Monkey Trial? According to its subtitle, At Its Heart the Trial was about Racism, while within the text, Bergman awkwardly declaims, &amp;ldquo;The trial was about human evolution, and more about racism and eugenics than religion and evolution&amp;rdquo; (p. 5, emphasis in original). Later, a section complaining that commentators on the trial ignore the racism and eugenics of both classroom textbooks and the American scientific community of the 1920s is entitled &amp;ldquo;Denying the Core of the Scopes Trial&amp;rdquo;; in the following chapter, Bergman writes, &amp;ldquo;That the teaching of eugenics was at issue in the Scopes Trial was obvious to those who understood what eugenics is all about is clear&amp;rdquo; (p. 61); and the chapter after that is entitled &amp;ldquo;The Scopes Trial: A Struggle Against Eugenics and Racism.&amp;rdquo; And in the final chapter, Bergman concludes, &amp;ldquo;The racism and eugenics that was central in the Scopes Trial has been ignored, even though it is a well-documented part of the record&amp;rdquo; (p. 195). Thus, although there is a certain perplexing vacillation between racism and eugenics, the book&amp;rsquo;s thesis appears to be that the Scopes trial was about these issues.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Partial lunar eclipse</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/partial-lunar-eclipse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Partial lunar eclipse" /><published>2024-09-18T09:26:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-18T09:26:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/partial-lunar-eclipse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/partial-lunar-eclipse.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/DSC05907_Partial_Eclipse.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Partial eclipse&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeanddate.com/eclipse/in/usa/boulder?iso=20240918&quot;&gt;Partial lunar eclipse&lt;/a&gt; as seen from Boulder, Colorado, approximately 8:40 local time, yesterday. Also a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.space.com/harvest-moon-supermoon-lunar-eclipse-september-photos&quot;&gt;supermoon&lt;/a&gt;, but it was hard to tell with the naked eye. Not the best display ever, yet for some reason eclipses fascinate.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post, click below.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Partial lunar eclipse as seen from Boulder, Colorado, approximately 8:40 local time, yesterday. Also a supermoon, but it was hard to tell with the naked eye. Not the best display ever, yet for some reason eclipses fascinate. To see comments on this post, click below.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Araneus gemmoides</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/araneus-gemmoides.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Araneus gemmoides" /><published>2024-09-16T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-16T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/araneus-gemmoides</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/araneus-gemmoides.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;David Young&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spider courtesy of &lt;strong&gt;Alex Young&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Cat_Faced_Orb_Weaver_MG_1184_600.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Spider&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Araneus_gemmoides&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Araneus gemmoides&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; female cat-faced orb weaver. The abdomen is over 1&amp;nbsp;cm long. The photograph is upside down to emphasize the &quot;ears&quot; and the &quot;eyes.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

The underside of the spider is displayed below the fold.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Cat_Faced_Orb_Weaver_MG_1178_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spider&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by David Young. Spider courtesy of Alex Young. Araneus gemmoides &amp;ndash; female cat-faced orb weaver. The abdomen is over 1&amp;nbsp;cm long. The photograph is upside down to emphasize the &quot;ears&quot; and the &quot;eyes.&quot; The underside of the spider is displayed below the fold.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Artificial selection is not Intelligent Design</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/artificial.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Artificial selection is not Intelligent Design" /><published>2024-09-15T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-15T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/artificial</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/artificial.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/636px-Wm19342a.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[a nice image of fancy pigeons]&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;by Karl Wagner, from a major German encyclopedia, &lt;em&gt;Meyers Großes Konversations-Lexikon, Volume 19&lt;/em&gt;, published in 1909 in Leipzig.  From Wikimedia, figure in public domain.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When evolutionary biologists argue with creationists or 
advocates of Intelligent Design about the effectiveness 
of natural selection, the biologists often use the example of 
artificial selection.  And almost invariably, the 
ID advocate or creationist tries for a “gotcha” by 
saying “but artificial selection is an example of 
intelligent design, and is nothing like natural 
selection!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re going to go into why this is not a “gotcha” 
but is a mistaken analogy on their part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial selection is a very old practice, dating 
back to inadvertent selection when wild animals were 
domesticated, with the wildest ones being eaten or chased 
away, or they successfully escaped.  With the start of 
agriculture, farmers often bred from their best animals 
(or plants).   Charles Darwin paid close attention to 
the ways animals had been changed by breeding, both for 
food production or as pets.  He was particularly attentive 
to the results of pigeon breeding. “Natural selection” was named 
in analogy to artificial selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-much-design-is-in-design&quot;&gt;How much design is in Design?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saying that artificial selection is Intelligent Design is 
wrong because plant and animal breeders, until very recently, 
had no detailed understanding of the genomes of their 
organisms or how to make detailed changes in the genomes to 
affect the phenotype.  All they could do was to choose who 
to breed from, based on their phenotype (such as the amount 
of beef produced).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 20th century this got more sophisticated, but was still 
not Intelligent Design.  Real statisticians got involved, and 
selection was based on numerical indices computed from multiple 
characters.  I remember visiting a poultry breeding operation 
and hearing how they measured 10 characters, including not 
just the production characters but such important traits as 
susceptibility to viral disease.  This was in the 1970s, and 
they had a modest mainframe computer in their offices, with 
databases of traits.  It was the natural outcome of work in 
the 1930s and 1940s by quantitative-genetics-inspired animal 
breeders at such centers as Iowa State University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they did not know the detailed genetics of these traits. 
The selection still depended on observing the traits and not 
directly knowing any of the genetics, or much about the 
developmental biology of the traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on-to-intelligent-design&quot;&gt;On to Intelligent Design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the 2010s animal and plant breeding was entering a new 
era, though with difficulty.  In 2014 I was invited to give 
a talk (on natural selection) in Vancouver BC, at the 10th World 
Congress of Genetics Applied to Livestock Production.  I was 
talking about the mathematics of natural selection.  It was 
apparent from the muted audience response that this was now of lesser 
interest to people working on livestock production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead the hot topic of the Congress was QTLs – “quantitive trait 
loci” – how could they find individual genes whose alleles 
affected the production traits and disease resistance traits. 
If these could be found, they could be used by screening potential 
parents of the next generation, and maybe even by genetically 
engineering their genotypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that lots of effort is now going on towards 
entering this new era of genomics should be enough to make it clear 
that even thousands of years of animal and plant breeding, 
with lots of human intelligence applied, is not the same as 
Intelligent Design.   So the success of that history of breeding does 
say a lot about it as exemplifying the power of selection, 
without genetic engineering or even understanding the effects 
of changes in genotypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-comparable-example&quot;&gt;A comparable example&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It occurs to me that another similar flawed critique is 
when creationists and ID advocates argue that the success 
of Genetic Algorithms in solving engineering problems is 
irrelevant, because that is an example of Intelligent 
Design.  It isn’t, if the algorithm has random mutations, 
random recombinations, and random mating, with fitnesses based 
on the final phenotypes rather than on detailed knowledge 
of how they were achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In ID books such as Robert Marks, William Dembski, and 
Winston Ewert’s “Introduction to Evolutionary Informatics” there 
is a great effort to show that in simulations of 
natural selection, they only succeed because the design 
information is built in.  For example, in Richard Dawkins’s 
famous teaching example of the “Weasel”, the target phrase 
is part of the program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet in other cases, such as Dave Thomas’s genetic algorithm 
for a Traveling Salesman problem (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2006/07/target-target-w-1.html&quot;&gt;his 2006 post here at 
Panda’s Thumb&lt;/a&gt;
) no particular solution is built in.  All Marks, Dembski and 
Ewert could do was point to places where some fine-tuning of 
the algorithm had been made to make it more successful, but 
this is not the same as building in the answer to the particular 
problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So neither the success of animal and plant breeding, nor 
the success of genetic algorithms, can be sensibly attributed 
to Intelligent Design of the answers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">by Karl Wagner, from a major German encyclopedia, Meyers Großes Konversations-Lexikon, Volume 19, published in 1909 in Leipzig. From Wikimedia, figure in public domain. &amp;nbsp; When evolutionary biologists argue with creationists or advocates of Intelligent Design about the effectiveness of natural selection, the biologists often use the example of artificial selection. And almost invariably, the ID advocate or creationist tries for a “gotcha” by saying “but artificial selection is an example of intelligent design, and is nothing like natural selection!” We’re going to go into why this is not a “gotcha” but is a mistaken analogy on their part. Artificial selection is a very old practice, dating back to inadvertent selection when wild animals were domesticated, with the wildest ones being eaten or chased away, or they successfully escaped. With the start of agriculture, farmers often bred from their best animals (or plants). Charles Darwin paid close attention to the ways animals had been changed by breeding, both for food production or as pets. He was particularly attentive to the results of pigeon breeding. “Natural selection” was named in analogy to artificial selection.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NASA astronaut promotes Ark in space</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/nasa-astronaut-promotes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NASA astronaut promotes Ark in space" /><published>2024-09-08T13:50:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-08T13:50:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/nasa-astronaut-promotes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/nasa-astronaut-promotes.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Phelps_Ham_Astronaut_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ark Encounter swag in space&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Screenshot showing AIG products worn by astronaut Barry Wilmore in the International Space Station. &lt;small&gt;Source: AIG. Fair use.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronaut Barry “Butch” Wilmore is an ardent supporter of Answers in Genesis. Captain Wilmore is stuck, possibly until next year, on the International Space Station (ISS) because of concerns with the safety of the Boeing Starliner capsule. Apparently, Ken Ham will get tons of publicity from support by astronaut Wilmore, who can be seen wearing an Ark Encounter T-shirt and hat in the photo. Captain Wilmore has also taken separate photos of two different Ark baseball caps on the ISS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Ham is already hawking “as seen in space” merchandise promoting the Ark &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2024/08/30/as-seen-in-space/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. He writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;These “as seen in space” items are available on our online store or at the attractions.&lt;/strong&gt; It’s a fun way to promote the Ark and talk about a man who is bold in his witness for Jesus Christ and the truth of God’s Word from the very first verse, even while working as an astronaut with NASA.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost to send a payload to the ISS is about $10,000/lb, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/humans-in-space/commercial-and-marketing-pricing-policy/&quot;&gt;according to NASA&lt;/a&gt;. Moreover, it was probably much more expensive to send anything on the ill-fated Boeing Starliner. If the T-shirt weighs about 5 or 6 oz and the two caps combined weigh a similar amount, then the cost of getting them into orbit was around $8,000. Although NASA allows astronauts to have personal items, both NASA and the International Space Station have explicit guidelines for advertising.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/nasa-brand-center/advertising-guidelines/&quot;&gt;NASA’s guidelines&lt;/a&gt; appear to explicitly forbid Wilmore’s advertising for Answers in Genesis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Advertising and Marketing on the International Space Station &lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Commercials and other marketing filming/activity on the International Space Station authorized by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.nasa.gov/sites/default/files/atoms/files/s1701746119060610280_1.pdf&quot;&gt; NASA Interim Directive (NID) on Use of International Space Station (ISS) for Commercial and Marketing Activities&lt;/a&gt; are additionally subject to the following guidelines: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; NASA support in filming/capturing commercials or other marketing videos, which will occur behind the scenes, shall not be used to indicate or imply that NASA approves or endorses the requesting entity or its products, services, or enterprises. No commercials or promotional materials filmed on ISS may imply such approval or endorsement, nor may NASA stock images or footage be used in a way that does so. … &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.law.cornell.edu/cfr/text/14/1214.403&quot;&gt;rules for the ISS crew&lt;/a&gt; state:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; ISS crewmembers shall refrain from any use of the position of ISS crewmember that is motivated, or has the appearance of being motivated, by private gain, including financial gain, for himself or herself or other persons or entities. …&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Wilmore certainly gives the appearance of promoting the for-profit Ark Encounter and the non-profit Answers in Genesis ministry at US taxpayer expense. Ken Ham will probably make a lot of money off the shirt and cap sales. I predict that NASA and the ISS will ignore this apparent violation of their own rules to avoid negative publicity and pushback from AIG’s supporters. Mr. Ham and AIG once again triumph in getting a benefit from the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Screenshot showing AIG products worn by astronaut Barry Wilmore in the International Space Station. Source: AIG. Fair use. Astronaut Barry “Butch” Wilmore is an ardent supporter of Answers in Genesis. Captain Wilmore is stuck, possibly until next year, on the International Space Station (ISS) because of concerns with the safety of the Boeing Starliner capsule. Apparently, Ken Ham will get tons of publicity from support by astronaut Wilmore, who can be seen wearing an Ark Encounter T-shirt and hat in the photo. Captain Wilmore has also taken separate photos of two different Ark baseball caps on the ISS. Mr. Ham is already hawking “as seen in space” merchandise promoting the Ark here. He writes: These “as seen in space” items are available on our online store or at the attractions. It’s a fun way to promote the Ark and talk about a man who is bold in his witness for Jesus Christ and the truth of God’s Word from the very first verse, even while working as an astronaut with NASA.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hexagonaria</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/hexagonaria.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hexagonaria" /><published>2024-09-02T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-02T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/hexagonaria</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/hexagonaria.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;James Kocher&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Photo Contest_JamesKocher_Hexagonaria.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hexagonaria&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hexagonaria&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Hexagonaria davidsoni&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; in-situ Upper Devonian fossilized coral, Middle/Upper Devonian Callaway Limestone, ~350 Ma, Dry Fork Creek, Mark Twain National Forest (Cedar Creek Section), Callaway County, MO. The northern red oak (&lt;i&gt;Quercus rubra&lt;/i&gt;) leaf is for scale. See also &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lakeneosho.org/MissouriFossils/Publication.html&quot;&gt;Missouri Fossils&lt;/a&gt;, by Bruce L. Stinchcomb.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by James Kocher. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Hexagonaria davidsoni &amp;ndash; in-situ Upper Devonian fossilized coral, Middle/Upper Devonian Callaway Limestone, ~350 Ma, Dry Fork Creek, Mark Twain National Forest (Cedar Creek Section), Callaway County, MO. The northern red oak (Quercus rubra) leaf is for scale. See also Missouri Fossils, by Bruce L. Stinchcomb.</summary></entry></feed>