<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-12-22T05:46:51-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Merry Kitzmas! 2025 is the 20th anniversary of Kitzmiller v. Dover and the 100th of the Scopes Trial</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/KvDv19.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Merry Kitzmas! 2025 is the 20th anniversary of Kitzmiller v. Dover and the 100th of the Scopes Trial" /><published>2024-12-20T12:01:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-12-20T12:01:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/KvDv19</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/KvDv19.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Matzke_Scopes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Ernst Mayr in caricature]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Nick Matzke at the Dayton County Courthouse where the Scopes Trial was held in 1925. (photo from ~2014)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merry Kitzmas to all!  Today is the 19th anniversary of the &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover Area School District&lt;/i&gt; trial, aka the Dover Panda Trial, held from September-November 2005, and decided on December 20, 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year, 2025, will be the 20th anniversary of Kitzmiller, as well as the 100th anniversary of &lt;i&gt;Tennessee v. Scopes&lt;/i&gt;, aka the Scopes Monkey Trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stuck as I am, in Australia/New Zealand with 3 little kids, I expect I will have to follow events from afar.  But I will use this thread to accumulate links &amp;amp; dates for relevant events as they come up. And please contribute ones you come across!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect that many are glum about current politics and science, but I recall a similar feeling in 2004, and that &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover&lt;/i&gt; was one of the early signs that committed citizens could move events in a pro-science direction. May 2025 be another such time!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Matzke</name></author><summary type="html">Nick Matzke at the Dayton County Courthouse where the Scopes Trial was held in 1925. (photo from ~2014) Merry Kitzmas to all! Today is the 19th anniversary of the Kitzmiller v. Dover Area School District trial, aka the Dover Panda Trial, held from September-November 2005, and decided on December 20, 2005. Next year, 2025, will be the 20th anniversary of Kitzmiller, as well as the 100th anniversary of Tennessee v. Scopes, aka the Scopes Monkey Trial. Stuck as I am, in Australia/New Zealand with 3 little kids, I expect I will have to follow events from afar. But I will use this thread to accumulate links &amp;amp; dates for relevant events as they come up. And please contribute ones you come across! I expect that many are glum about current politics and science, but I recall a similar feeling in 2004, and that Kitzmiller v. Dover was one of the early signs that committed citizens could move events in a pro-science direction. May 2025 be another such time!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Eric Hedin, meet Granville Sewell</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/eric-hedin-meet-granville-sewell.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Eric Hedin, meet Granville Sewell" /><published>2024-12-11T22:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2024-12-11T22:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/eric-hedin-meet-granville-sewell</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/eric-hedin-meet-granville-sewell.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Nuucichthys.png&quot; alt=&quot;[An intermediate step]&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;One of the intermediate steps that Granville Sewell does not 
mention, and which Eric Hedin sort-of-knows occur.  (a), Reconstruction 
of a very early vertebrate, the fossil &lt;em&gt;Nuucichthys&lt;/em&gt;, which lived 
518 million years ago, with (b) its inferred position shown on the vertebrate phylogeny.  From &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; class=&quot;external free&quot; href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1098/rsos.240350&quot;&gt;a paper by Rudy Lerosey-Aubril &amp;amp; Javier Ortega-Hernández&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0&quot; title=&quot;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0&quot;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt; From Wikimedia.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Physicist Eric Hedin has posted to the Discovery Institute site 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2024/11/theres-a-limit-to-what-nature-can-do&quot;&gt;Evolution News on 27 November 2024&lt;/a&gt;
an argument that the processes of physics cannot 
account for intelligent life.  As he is a well-trained physicist (whose Ph.D. 
degree was from my university), and who has done experimental 
work on plasma physics, we can expect a mathematically sophisticated 
argument which would give us all pause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, here’s the guts of his argument, from the Evolution News post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In fact, for making anything other than large-scale conglomerations of matter (such as stars and planets), nature has only one tool in its bag — the electromagnetic force. This tool primarily manifests as the electric force, causing opposite charges (such as electrons and protons) to attract, and like charges to repel. It is completely indiscriminate, and cannot select between multiple options, preferring one charge over another, except for the rule that the bigger the charges and the closer the distance between them the stronger the resulting force. Can you imagine such blind, brute forces pulling together countless atoms of specific elements into the necessary configurations to result in a functioning laptop computer?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The “boundaries of science” refers to the common-sense conclusion that nature is limited in what it can produce to outcomes consistent with the laws and forces of nature. Natural processes are sought and found to be sufficient for natural phenomena, such as star formation or precipitation.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;However, attempting to naturally explain the origin of some things found within our universe comes into conflict with the boundaries of science. Positing a natural explanation for the origin of the universe itself, the origin of the specific suite of physical parameters finely tuned to allow life, the origin of life itself, and the origin of conscious, intelligent minds, all defy what we have discovered about the limits of natural processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And basically, that’s the argument.  Evolutionary biology does not pretend to address the origin of the universe, or the issue of fine-tuning in physics, and even the origin of life is outside its scope, though adjacent.  But somehow Hedin knows that physical forces cannot explain “the origin of conscious, 
intelligent minds”.   I wonder how he knows that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;meet-granville-sewell&quot;&gt;Meet Granville Sewell&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hedin’s argument is quite similar to Granville Sewell’s. Sewell asks (rhetorically) whether it is not implausible that advanced technology such as iPhones could have resulted from natural forces, which involve only random collisions of particles.   An example of his argument will be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2021/04/some-problems-can-be-proved-unsolvable/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, where he asks whether it is possible to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Explain how life could have originated and evolved into intelligent humans, through entirely natural (unintelligent) processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granville Sewell is a mathematician, who is Professor Emeritus in the Departrment of Mathematical Sciences at the University of Texas at El Paso.  He is a specialist in numerical solution of differential equations. Here is how he invokes physics to solve this problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Well, I have a very simple proof that the biological problem #3  [the one mentioned above] posed above is also impossible to solve, that does fit in the margin of this document. All one needs to do is realize that if a solution were found, we would have proved something obviously false, that a few (four, apparently) fundamental, unintelligent forces of physics alone could have rearranged the fundamental particles of physics into libraries full of science texts and encyclopedias, computers connected to monitors, keyboards, laser printers and the Internet, cars, trucks, airplanes, nuclear power plants and Apple iPhones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are from a 2021 post at Evolution News (which I linked to above). It should be obvious that Hedin’s and Sewell’s  arguments are similar, since they invoke physics.  They are also similar in lacking mathematical details, although elsewhere Sewell does present a partial differential equation for the simple diffusion of a chemical element outwards from an area of concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-sewell-has-left-out&quot;&gt;What Sewell has left out&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granville Sewell’s argument has been repeatedly promoted by him, in various versions.  In addition to the link in the previous section, examples of his advocacy will be found in blogs such as Evolution News and Uncommon Descent and in papers, book chapters and videos (here I take a deep breath)
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.utep.edu/faculty/sewell/articles/mathint.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.utep.edu/faculty/sewell/articles/open.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://spectator.org/47666_evolutions-thermodynamic-failure/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.utep.edu/faculty/sewell/AML_3497.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2012/02/looking_for_the/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/new-video-evolution-is-a-natural-process-running-backward-2/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://bio-complexity.org/ojs/index.php/main/article/view/BIO-C.2013.2/BIO-C.2013.2&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://dx.doi.org/10.1142/9789814508728_0007&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Beginning-Other-Essays-Intelligent-Design/dp/1936599279/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.utep.edu/faculty/sewell/articles/pe_sewell.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2018/05/i-believe-in-the-evolution-of-life-and-the-evolution-of-automobiles/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2018/08/who-is-doing-pseudoscience/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2018/11/why-evolution-and-reproduction-are-unnatural/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2019/05/two-schemes-to-defeat-the-second-law/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2020/01/how-science-lost-its-mind/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2020/06/new-video-why-evolution-is-different/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2020/10/my-failed-computer-simulation/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2022/01/the-underlying-principle-behind-the-second-law/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2022/06/three-realities-chance-cant-explain-that-intelligent-design-can/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2023/03/yes-extraordinary-claims-require-extraordinary-evidence-lets-hear-some-for-darwinian-evolution/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2023/07/in-summary-presenting-the-evidence-for-intelligent-design/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2023/08/how-the-supernatural-entered-science/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2024/03/life-and-the-underlying-principle-behind-the-second-law-of-thermodynamics/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2024/07/introduction-to-the-scientific-theory-of-intelligent-design/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I may have missed a few, but you get the idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granville Sewell’s argument has been commented on many times over the years. The late physicist Mark Perakh 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.talkreason.org/articles/sewell.cfm&quot;&gt;(here)&lt;/a&gt;, 
the mathematician Jason Rosenhouse &lt;a href=&quot;https://skepticalinquirer.org/exclusive/does-evolution-have-a-thermodynamics-problem/&quot;&gt;(here)&lt;/a&gt;, and physicist Dan Styer 
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.oberlin.edu/physics/dstyer/SandE/StyerRemarksOnSewellPE.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.oberlin.edu/physics/dstyer/SandE/ObviousImplausibility.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)
sternly criticized his assertions that evolution contradicts the Second Law of Thermodynamics.  Sewell has since 
quietly backed away from his original assertions about the Second Law of Thermodynamics, instead coming up 
with an ill-defined concept of “X-entropy”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His arguments have been 
commented on many times here.  I have posted a number of times at Panda’s Thumb and at The Skeptical Zone 
(&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2010/02/evidence-that-t.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2011/02/granville-sewel.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2011/11/granville-sewel-1.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/Granville-Sewell-thinks-its-obvious.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
and &lt;a href=&quot;http://theskepticalzone.com/wp/what-is-obvious-to-granville-sewell/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my 2021 post (the fourth one above), I noted that the processes 
that Sewell thinks that the “rearrangement” of fundamental particles includes quite 
a few steps that we generally don’t attribute to Design Intervention, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Elementary particles aggregating to form larger particles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Those particles forming atoms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Atoms becoming connected by bonds to form chemicals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Chemicals interacting to form cosmic dust&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Cosmic dust forming clouds by the attraction of gravity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Gravity in dust clouds leading to clumps that become a solar system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; ... including the formation of a star and planets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Lots of geology (steps omitted)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; An early Earth with interesting organic chemicals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Origin of life&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Evolution of protists and single-celled eukaryotes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Evolution of multicellular life&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Evolution of people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; People producing tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; People producing agriculture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; and civilization,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; and technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include processes of physics, astronomy, geology, and chemistry.  Those are fields that get 
along fine without any Design Intervention.  Likewise we know people can produce agriculture, 
civilization, and technology.  That’s already an awful lot of Granville Sewell’s process of “particles 
rearranging themselves”.  There are numerous parts of the evolution of life (and the origin of life) 
that ID advocates dispute, but much of their concentration is on two of the list items, the 
origin of life and the evolution of humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hedin-compared-to-sewell&quot;&gt;Hedin compared to Sewell&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Hedin faces similar issues, but is more cautious in his assertions.    He focuses on fine-tuning arguments, which are outside of the domain of evolutionary biology, but also on the origin of life and on the origin of conscious, 
intelligent minds.   Hedin has written many posts on Evolution News (for a list of them see &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/author/ehedin/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).  In &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2023/05/is-life-an-information-ratchet/&quot;&gt;one of the earlier ones&lt;/a&gt; last year, he argued that a conservation-of-information argument showed that an evolving species could not gain specified information.  I disputed this 
in &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/08/Hedin-information-principle.html&quot;&gt;a post here at Panda’s Thumb&lt;/a&gt;.  Reading Hedin’s post closely, it could be seen that while he didn’t think it was possible for evolving organisms to 
produce “novel complex functionality”, he did acknowledge that natural selection can accumulate information:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But what can this “ratchet” do? No more than it was designed to do — namely to reproduce daughter organisms according to its inherent mechanism of reproduction. Variations in the organism’s genome, by any unguided process, may lead to an increase in fitness and therefore survivability. But natural processes cannot produce unnatural results. Selection based on the ratchet mechanism of increased fitness cannot of itself produce novel complex functionality if each successive small change does not give some increased advantage towards survival and reproduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while Granville Sewell implies, without proof, that accumulation of favorable mutants by natural selection is a thermodynamic impossibility, Eric Hedin acknowledges that it is a possibility.  He confines his objections to “novel, complex functionality”.  The chief example he gives of this is the origin of a conscious, intelligent “mind”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;intelligent-brains--or-minds&quot;&gt;Intelligent brains?  Or “minds”?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to be careful here.  It is tempting to think that Hedin is describing conscious, intelligent &lt;em&gt;brains&lt;/em&gt;.  After all, our mind is just stuff that happens in our brains, isn’t it?  In Hedin’s terminology, “mind” is quite distinct from the mere activity of the brain.  Hedin is a dualist, in that he thinks that our brain exists in the real world, while our “mind” exists in a spiritual world (see an article of his &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2024/04/mind-matter-and-intelligent-design/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no understanding of how minds might evolve in a spiritual world, so I am going to discuss only brains, under the assumption – or perhaps the delusion – that we should think about the evolution of brains, and leave the issue of “mind” to those who understand things spiritual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;can-brains-evolve-to-get-smarter-more-conscious&quot;&gt;Can brains evolve to get smarter? More conscious?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can brains get better at thinking?  They certainly vary from species to species in the ability to think.  In their simplest forms they can’t do very much thinking.   That’s where the image at the start of this article becomes relevant.  It shows &lt;em&gt;Nuucichthys&lt;/em&gt;, a recently-discovered early vertebrate, from the early Cambrian.  It has eyes near its front, and it is quite a good assumption that they connect to a primitive brain.  Given that bigger brains are needed to have more intelligent behavior, there is really no reason to imagine a barrier to the evolution of more intelligence by ordinary evolutionary processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what about consciousness?  We usually think about consciousness in terms of conscious behavior of humans, contemplating beauty, morality, and mortality.  All very lofty and difficult.  But if we take an evolutionary view of it, 
we can ask whether much earlier species could show the basics of consciousness.  If a mouse is looking at its surroundings and is able to have some representation of them, a representation that includes itself, then if it can 
choose a route for itself to its burrow, that seems to me to be an early form of consciousness.  “Let’s see, 
if I am &lt;em&gt;there&lt;/em&gt; and the bush is &lt;em&gt;there&lt;/em&gt; and the log is &lt;em&gt;there&lt;/em&gt;, and my burrow is behind the tree, then I should go 
to the left of the bush, over log, and to the right of the tree, and there will be the burrow.”  The mouse is making a representation of its environment which includes a representation of itself, viewed from outside.  From there, more elaborate forms of consciousness could, I think, evolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there is, in fact, evidence of such a map of the surroundings in the brains of rats.   See, for example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hhmi.org/news/uncovering-the-neural-basis-for-hypothetical-thinking-in-rats&quot;&gt;this report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If any of this makes sense then there is no reason to suppose that there is some barrier to the evolution of conscious, intelligent brains.  In which case Eric Hedin’s argument boils down to simple incredulity, without any logical proof of a barrier to evolution by ordinary evolutionary processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is where Granville Sewell’s argument ended up, too.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">One of the intermediate steps that Granville Sewell does not mention, and which Eric Hedin sort-of-knows occur. (a), Reconstruction of a very early vertebrate, the fossil Nuucichthys, which lived 518 million years ago, with (b) its inferred position shown on the vertebrate phylogeny. From a paper by Rudy Lerosey-Aubril &amp;amp; Javier Ortega-Hernández, CC BY 4.0 From Wikimedia. &amp;nbsp; Physicist Eric Hedin has posted to the Discovery Institute site Evolution News on 27 November 2024 an argument that the processes of physics cannot account for intelligent life. As he is a well-trained physicist (whose Ph.D. degree was from my university), and who has done experimental work on plasma physics, we can expect a mathematically sophisticated argument which would give us all pause. Well, here’s the guts of his argument, from the Evolution News post: In fact, for making anything other than large-scale conglomerations of matter (such as stars and planets), nature has only one tool in its bag — the electromagnetic force. This tool primarily manifests as the electric force, causing opposite charges (such as electrons and protons) to attract, and like charges to repel. It is completely indiscriminate, and cannot select between multiple options, preferring one charge over another, except for the rule that the bigger the charges and the closer the distance between them the stronger the resulting force. Can you imagine such blind, brute forces pulling together countless atoms of specific elements into the necessary configurations to result in a functioning laptop computer? and The “boundaries of science” refers to the common-sense conclusion that nature is limited in what it can produce to outcomes consistent with the laws and forces of nature. Natural processes are sought and found to be sufficient for natural phenomena, such as star formation or precipitation. However, attempting to naturally explain the origin of some things found within our universe comes into conflict with the boundaries of science. Positing a natural explanation for the origin of the universe itself, the origin of the specific suite of physical parameters finely tuned to allow life, the origin of life itself, and the origin of conscious, intelligent minds, all defy what we have discovered about the limits of natural processes. And basically, that’s the argument. Evolutionary biology does not pretend to address the origin of the universe, or the issue of fine-tuning in physics, and even the origin of life is outside its scope, though adjacent. But somehow Hedin knows that physical forces cannot explain “the origin of conscious, intelligent minds”. I wonder how he knows that.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ellipes minuta</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/ellipes-minuta.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ellipes minuta" /><published>2024-12-09T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-12-09T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/ellipes-minuta</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/ellipes-minuta.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Mark Sturtevant&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Sturtevant.Pygmy_mole_cricket.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pygmy mole cricket&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bugguide.net/node/view/110363&quot;&gt;Ellipes minuta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; pygmy mole cricket.  Dr. Sturtevant notes, &quot;This insect is a small oddity. Despite its name, the diminutive pygmy mole crickets are not true mole crickets, or even crickets for that matter. They are classified as belonging in the same sub-order as grasshoppers.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Mark Sturtevant. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Ellipes minuta &amp;ndash; pygmy mole cricket. Dr. Sturtevant notes, &quot;This insect is a small oddity. Despite its name, the diminutive pygmy mole crickets are not true mole crickets, or even crickets for that matter. They are classified as belonging in the same sub-order as grasshoppers.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Confidence in scientists rises</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/confidence-scientists.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Confidence in scientists rises" /><published>2024-11-26T10:34:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-11-26T10:34:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/confidence-scientists</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/confidence-scientists.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/AIP_Pew_Views_Of_Scientists_Fig_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Public's views of scientists.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Figure 1. Intelligent, but closed-minded. Not entirely flattering.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the Pew Research Center, confidence in scientists has ticked up slightly, though it remains lower than it was before the pandemic. That is one of the conclusions of a report, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/science/2024/11/14/public-trust-in-scientists-and-views-on-their-role-in-policymaking/&quot;&gt;Public Trust in Scientists and Views on Their Role in Policymaking&lt;/a&gt;, by Alec Tyson and Brian Kennedy. Pew surveyed nearly 10,000 US adults in October and discovered that Americans (mostly) perceive scientists as intelligent, honest, and focused on real-world problems. They see communication as a weak area and think that we are good at working in teams, though how they know about teamwork is a puzzle to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least they think we are reasonably bright; they also find us socially awkward, cold, superior, and closed-minded. Figure 1 shows how these perceptions break down according to political party: Democrats and their fellow travelers (whom I shall call Democrats) have a considerably more favorable view of scientists than Republicans and their fellow travelers (whom I shall call Republicans). I was somewhat bemused by the claim of roughly half of Republicans that scientists &quot;[d]on't pay attention to moral values of society,&quot; and wondered precisely what and whose moral values they have in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pew notes, somewhat to my surprise,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;In an era of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewtrusts.org/en/trend/archive/fall-2024/americans-deepening-mistrust-of-institutions&quot;&gt;low public trust in institutions&lt;/a&gt;, scientists continue to be held in higher regard than several other prominent groups we’ve asked about, including journalists, elected officials, business leaders and religious leaders. Confidence ratings for scientists are even slightly higher than those for public school principals and police officers – two groups that receive positive overall ratings. [I did not follow the preceding link.] &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pew also notes differences by race and ethnicity; you may find these by following the link in the first paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/AIP_Pew_Role_In_Policy_Fig_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Scientists' role in public policy.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Figure 2. Approximately half of those surveyed think that scientists should be active in policy debates.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding science policy, I would wager, assuming it is legal to do so, that a very significant fraction of those reading this article would privilege scientists over laypersons when it came to setting science policy. Figure 2 shows that almost exactly half of the respondents to the Pew survey disagree with that contention and think that scientists should stay out of policy. Only about one-third of Republicans think that scientists should &quot;[t]ake an active role in public policy debates about scientific issues,&quot; as opposed to two-thirds of Democrats. Only 7&amp;nbsp;% of Democrats think that scientists have too much influence in public policy debates. One important question, of course, is whether laypersons who weigh in on scientific issues have informed opinions, and another is whether scientists who weigh in on issues outside their own fields have opinions that are more informed than anyone else's.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A science policy bulletin from the American Institute of Physics, &lt;a href=&quot;https://us17.campaign-archive.com/?e=480f65d998&amp;amp;u=be8b78d2ef406eb6026a6ba21&amp;amp;id=539a20766c&quot;&gt;Public Opinion Divided over Role of Scientists in Policymaking&lt;/a&gt;, by Lindsay McKenzie, synopsized the Pew article and stated,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Perceptions that scientists are poor communicators and feel superior to others “pain me to my core,” said Sudip Parikh, CEO of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, during [an] event discussing the survey results. “Humility is an absolute requirement for science communication,” said Parikh. “If you can’t be humbled about the fact that science is done by humans and we are all subject to all the fallibility and all the extraordinary talents that humans have, then you can’t relate.” &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;i&gt;Times&lt;/i&gt; article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2024/11/14/health/trust-science-americans.html&quot;&gt;Americans Have Regained Modest Trust in Scientists, Survey Finds&lt;/a&gt;, by Teddy Rosenbluth, incidentally, speculates,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Recent high-profile medical and scientific advancements — like the new gene therapy for sickle cell and ambitious space exploration missions — have done the most to rebuild confidence in scientific institutions, [Parikh] added.&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Figure 1. Intelligent, but closed-minded. Not entirely flattering. According to the Pew Research Center, confidence in scientists has ticked up slightly, though it remains lower than it was before the pandemic. That is one of the conclusions of a report, Public Trust in Scientists and Views on Their Role in Policymaking, by Alec Tyson and Brian Kennedy. Pew surveyed nearly 10,000 US adults in October and discovered that Americans (mostly) perceive scientists as intelligent, honest, and focused on real-world problems. They see communication as a weak area and think that we are good at working in teams, though how they know about teamwork is a puzzle to me. At least they think we are reasonably bright; they also find us socially awkward, cold, superior, and closed-minded. Figure 1 shows how these perceptions break down according to political party: Democrats and their fellow travelers (whom I shall call Democrats) have a considerably more favorable view of scientists than Republicans and their fellow travelers (whom I shall call Republicans). I was somewhat bemused by the claim of roughly half of Republicans that scientists &quot;[d]on't pay attention to moral values of society,&quot; and wondered precisely what and whose moral values they have in mind. Pew notes, somewhat to my surprise,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bombus mixtus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/bombus-mixtus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bombus mixtus" /><published>2024-11-25T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-11-25T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/bombus-mixtus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/bombus-mixtus.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Ken Phelps&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Phelps_Bombus_mixtus_Spring_Rain.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bumblebee&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bombus_mixtus&quot;&gt;Bombus mixtus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; bumblebee, photographed on a thistle immediately after a spring shower. The hairs on the abdomen are wetted where a raindrop hit. Located Nanaimo Lakes, Vancouver Island. Canon 20D, 100&amp;nbsp;mm macro.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Ken Phelps. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Bombus mixtus &amp;ndash; bumblebee, photographed on a thistle immediately after a spring shower. The hairs on the abdomen are wetted where a raindrop hit. Located Nanaimo Lakes, Vancouver Island. Canon 20D, 100&amp;nbsp;mm macro. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Every Living Thing: book report</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/every-living-thing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Every Living Thing: book report" /><published>2024-11-12T19:15:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-11-12T19:15:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/every-living-thing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/every-living-thing.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Roberts_Every_Living_Thing_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The cover is kind of &quot;busy,&quot; but I shall try not to judge the book by its cover.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0C7TNQHKK/&quot;&gt;Every Living Thing&lt;/a&gt;, The Great and Deadly Race to Know All Life&lt;/i&gt;, by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jason_Roberts_(author)&quot;&gt;Jason Roberts&lt;/a&gt;. It is sort of a double biography of Carl Linnaeus (1707-1778) and Georges-Louis Leclerc, Comte de Buffon (1707-1788), but it continues to follow their legacies well beyond their lifetimes to the present. I cannot recommend it more highly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not know what impression Mr. Roberts intended, but if you thought Linnaeus was a young man on the make, something of a scoundrel who might say anything in the interests of self-promotion, you might not be too far from the truth. The hero of this book is not Linnaeus but rather his sometime rival, Buffon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let us deal with Linnaeus first. Linnaeus obtained a phony doctor’s degree from what we would now call a diploma mill. He anointed 14 (or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ikfoundation.org/books-and-art/linnaeus-apostles-full-set/&quot;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;
 of what he called his “apostles” (!), sent them on long journeys from which many never returned, and completely abandoned one who returned with no specimens. He has been criticized for not allowing his daughters their educations, to a degree, says Roberts, that was extreme even for the time (but he supported his daughter Elisabeth in her interest in botany. She wrote a paper devoted to what is now known as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nybg.org/blogs/science-talk/2013/12/flashes-in-the-twilight/&quot;&gt;Elizabeth Linnaeus phenomenon&lt;/a&gt;). Linnaeus also believed in the fixity of species, not to mention some very bizarre creatures, but in that he was probably not alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linnaeus developed a taxonomy that is largely in use today; that is a major accomplishment, to say the least. After defining and then apparently rejecting some ridiculous species within the genus &lt;i&gt;Homo&lt;/i&gt;, he divided &lt;i&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/i&gt; into four subspecies: in essence, European, African, indigenous American, and Asian. Europeans, to Linnaeus, were governed by laws, whereas Africans were governed by whim, Americans by customs, and Asians by opinions. Roberts notes that “apologists have attempted to absolve Linnaeus of racism,” but he insists that claiming that Europeans alone were governed by laws is a clear statement of superiority. He cannot forgive Linnaeus, who stood by these characterizations for the rest of his life. I do not know whether Roberts is engaging in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Presentism_(historical_analysis)&quot;&gt;presentism&lt;/a&gt;, but I suspect not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linnaeus occasionally defined species on the basis of scant evidence and sometimes published reviews of his own work using a pseudonym. Roberts accuses him of drawing “unmoored conclusions” in “an act of ignorance masquerading as savantry.” Buffon was the real thing; he would have been called a scientist, but the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/scientist&quot;&gt;first known use of the word&lt;/a&gt; was in 1834. Where Linnaeus required scant evidence, Buffon studied his “private menagerie” for years and concluded, in Roberts’s words, “The essence of species lay in reproduction, the ability of one generation to propagate another.” On the basis of what is essentially this definition, Buffon further concluded that there was only one human species, which “underwent diverse changes from the influence of the climate, food, mode of living, epidemical distempers, and the intermixture of individuals[.]” Charles Darwin, a century or so later, thought that Buffon’s theories were “laughably like mine.” Like Darwin, Buffon opposed slavery, and he did not care for the slave-owner Jefferson. Roberts does not discuss Linnaeus’s views on slavery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buffon ultimately published 35 volumes of his encyclopedia, &lt;i&gt;Histoire naturelle&lt;/i&gt;. According to the author, he outsold Rousseau, Voltaire, and Montesquieu, and his work continued in print for over 150 years. Roberts says it is the longest nonfiction work written by a single author and rivals encyclopedias written by many authors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides evolution, Buffon developed what Roberts calls “the first rough sketch of a working theory of reproduction,” which included an “internal matrix” that sort of resembles DNA. Where Linnaeus insisted on the fixity of species, Buffon studied fossil remains and concluded that some species had gone extinct and others had been born. Species, he thought, changed by adaptation to the environment, and later species were demarcated from their ancestors when they could no longer interbreed (cf. the modern &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution.berkeley.edu/biological-species-concept/&quot;&gt;biological species concept&lt;/a&gt;). He thought that related families may have a common ancestor and indeed that all life could be further traced to a yet earlier common ancestor. Buffon realized that these were dangerous thoughts in the mid-1700’s; he wrote to a friend, “One can slip ideas into a quarto volume which would cause a public outcry if they appeared in a pamphlet.” In consequence, he was very careful and penned a disclaimer any time he drew a conclusion that might offend the religious hierarchy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buffon also suggested that single-celled organisms may not all be animals or plants but rather “indeterminate species and in-between objects which we do not know where to place…” and suggested that living organisms might consist of building blocks now known as cells. On a less biological note, he opened an ironworks, which Roberts calls “a template for factories to come.” A gazebo that he had cast was the “first all-iron structure in Paris.” Its roof is a lattice shaped as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperboloid&quot;&gt;one-sheeted hyperboloid&lt;/a&gt; (a hyperboloid of revolution), which did not appear in architecture until the 20th century. According to Wikipedia, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buffon%27s_needle_problem&quot;&gt;Buffon’s needle&lt;/a&gt; was the first solved problem in geometric probability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buffon deduced that the earth was much older than a few thousand years and divided its history into seven “epochs.” Apart from not knowing the duration of any epoch, he got their chronology about right. (In fact, he used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.geolsoc.org.uk/Geoscientist/Archive/April-2018/Buffon-the-geologist&quot;&gt;cannonballs&lt;/a&gt; to estimate the rate of cooling of the earth and concluded that its age was around 75,000 years.) Roberts calls his work a deliberate provocation and an attack on the fixity of species. For his pains he was denounced by the Sorbonne and required to sign a retraction, which he promptly ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buffon speculated – &lt;i&gt;very&lt;/i&gt; carefully – as to whether nonhuman animals had souls, for which transgression apparently Madame Pompadour smacked him in the face with a fan. He recognized, nearly 300 years ago, that humans could “despoil and impoverish” the earth by out-producing its capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;History was kinder to Linnaeus than to Buffon. Buffon’s star began to fade during the French Revolution, when the Société de Linné took advantage of the turmoil to promote Linnaeus and minimize Buffon. By the 1860’s in England, Buffon’s &lt;i&gt;Natural History&lt;/i&gt; was sold in badly abridged, perhaps caricatured form alongside &lt;i&gt;Aesop’s Fables&lt;/i&gt;. Shaw remembers as a child hearing Buffon called “Buffoon” and says that within 10 years he was forgotten. Perhaps this book will succeed in &lt;strike&gt;reviving&lt;/strike&gt; enhancing his legacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I liked the writing very well and noticed only four editorial mistakes: seraphim for seraph, &lt;i&gt;Camillia sinsesis&lt;/i&gt; for &lt;i&gt;Camellia sinensis&lt;/i&gt;, counsel for consul, and Ernest Haeckel for Ernst Haeckel. Well, maybe one more: Rosalind Franklin arguably did not win a Nobel Prize because she had died before the prize was awarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgment. &lt;/strong&gt;Thanks to Ron Wittmann for discussing taxonomy and other topics with me. Deanna Young read a draft and offered several useful comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">The cover is kind of &quot;busy,&quot; but I shall try not to judge the book by its cover. The book is Every Living Thing, The Great and Deadly Race to Know All Life, by Jason Roberts. It is sort of a double biography of Carl Linnaeus (1707-1778) and Georges-Louis Leclerc, Comte de Buffon (1707-1788), but it continues to follow their legacies well beyond their lifetimes to the present. I cannot recommend it more highly. I do not know what impression Mr. Roberts intended, but if you thought Linnaeus was a young man on the make, something of a scoundrel who might say anything in the interests of self-promotion, you might not be too far from the truth. The hero of this book is not Linnaeus but rather his sometime rival, Buffon. But let us deal with Linnaeus first. Linnaeus obtained a phony doctor’s degree from what we would now call a diploma mill. He anointed 14 (or 17 of what he called his “apostles” (!), sent them on long journeys from which many never returned, and completely abandoned one who returned with no specimens. He has been criticized for not allowing his daughters their educations, to a degree, says Roberts, that was extreme even for the time (but he supported his daughter Elisabeth in her interest in botany. She wrote a paper devoted to what is now known as the Elizabeth Linnaeus phenomenon). Linnaeus also believed in the fixity of species, not to mention some very bizarre creatures, but in that he was probably not alone. Linnaeus developed a taxonomy that is largely in use today; that is a major accomplishment, to say the least. After defining and then apparently rejecting some ridiculous species within the genus Homo, he divided Homo sapiens into four subspecies: in essence, European, African, indigenous American, and Asian. Europeans, to Linnaeus, were governed by laws, whereas Africans were governed by whim, Americans by customs, and Asians by opinions. Roberts notes that “apologists have attempted to absolve Linnaeus of racism,” but he insists that claiming that Europeans alone were governed by laws is a clear statement of superiority. He cannot forgive Linnaeus, who stood by these characterizations for the rest of his life. I do not know whether Roberts is engaging in presentism, but I suspect not.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Butorides virescens</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/butorides-virescens.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Butorides virescens" /><published>2024-11-11T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-11-11T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/butorides-virescens</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/butorides-virescens.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Denelsbeck_Butorides_virescens.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Green heron&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Green_Heron/overview&quot;&gt;Butorides virescens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; green heron. Mr. Denelsbeck blogs at &lt;a href=&quot;https://wading-in.net/&quot;&gt;Wading-In Photography&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Al Denelsbeck. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Butorides virescens &amp;ndash; green heron. Mr. Denelsbeck blogs at Wading-In Photography. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dembski and Ewert wish upon a star</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/dembskiewert2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dembski and Ewert wish upon a star" /><published>2024-11-10T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-11-10T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/-dembskiewert2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/dembskiewert2.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;600px&quot; src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Six_Grandfathers.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Six grandfathers image]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;The mountain called &lt;em&gt;Six Grandfathers&lt;/em&gt; by the 
Lakota people before it was renamed Mount&lt;br /&gt; Rushmore. An image of Mount Rushmore adorns the cover of Dembski and 
  Ewert's book,&lt;br /&gt; as an example of a design inference we make. Does the Lakota name&lt;br /&gt; reflect 
a design inference? &lt;em&gt;Wikimedia, public domain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/dembskiewert1.html&quot;&gt;post of 12 June&lt;/a&gt;, I commented on the first part of William 
Dembski and Winston Ewert’s new book, the second edition of Dembski’s 
1998 book &lt;em&gt;The Design Inference: Eliminating Chance 
Through Small Probabilities&lt;/em&gt;.   I noted that to make the argument 
for a Design Inference they had set aside Dembski’s previous criterion 
of Complex Specified Information, and instead replaced it by 
Algorithmic Specified Complexity (ASC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a measure of the difference between the length of a bitstring and the length of a bitstring that describes it. 
It originates from the mathematical work on “randomness deficiciency”, where the bitstring is a binary number, and the smaller bitstring is a computer program that computes it.  In that field, numbers that are considered truly random are those generated by programs that are almost as long as the number.  A number that can be generated by a short program is not considered random.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dembski and Ewert intend to apply this to biology.  The longer number somehow specifies a phenotype (or maybe a 
genotype), while the shorter number “describes” it.  In my previous review, I had reached Chapter 7, “Evolutionary Biology”.  Here, let’s consider how they argue the ASC criterion can be applied to biological adaptations.  (Spoiler – we’re going to be disappointed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was full of expectations when I started reading Chapter 7.  I had a number of questions in mind, ones I have 
asked before in posts and comments about their ASC criterion for design inference (for example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/12/Is-Algorithmic-Specified-Complexity-Useless-for-Analyzing-Evolution.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Any-new-arguments.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/worst-of-2021.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What did the bitstring represent? A genotype?  A phenotype?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Was the “description” string a program for computing the larger string?  Was it perhaps some genetic encoding of developmental instructions?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the difference between the lengths of the two is large enough, this is supposed to be astronomically improbable.  Under what distribution?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the probability somehow able to take into account the possibility of natural selection building up such
large difference step by step?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 7 has a number of sections.  Let me describe briefly what each covers, and what it accomplishes.  I will summarize their arguments.  I will add comments of my own, in parentheses, or otherwise explicitly identified:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;insulating-evolution-against-small-probabilities-pages-321-326&quot;&gt;Insulating Evolution against Small Probabilities (pages 321-326)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dembski and Ewert describe the success and wide acceptance of their design inference in evolutionary biology.  They then say “And now back to the real world”.  The success and acceptance, they accept, has not happened in reality.  This is because evolutionary biologists have been resistant to accepting that evolution of biological systems involves 
probabilities that small.  The evolutionary biologists have done so by invoking mechanisms of cumulative selection.  As an example Dembski and Ewert describe Richard Dawkins’s teaching example of a simple form of simulated natural selection starting with a random 28-letter sequence of letters and spaces, and reaching the target phrase “METHINKS IT IS LIKE A WEASEL” in hundreds or thousands of steps, instead of the 10&lt;sup&gt;40&lt;/sup&gt; steps it would take if one simply drew new 28-letter sequences at random.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;variations-on-the-weasel-pages-326-330&quot;&gt;Variations on the WEASEL (pages 326-330)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evolutionary biologists are obsessed by the Weasel example (I would say it is creationists and advocates of Design that 
are actually the ones obsessed with it). “Perhaps design theorists should shift focus to the origin of life”.  (The infamous OTOOL diversion – Off To the Origin Of Life).  There cumulative selection cannot play a role, they argue.  Simulations like the Weasel are declared to be “suggestive but misleading, so removed from biological reality that they cannot decide the matter”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;resetting-darwinian-evolutions-bayesian-prior-pages-331-336&quot;&gt;Resetting Darwinian Evolution’s Bayesian Prior (pages 331-336)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering the choice between design and natural selection as a Bayesian Inference, it is important what prior probabilities one assigns these two hypotheses.  If one gives design a low enough prior probability, it cannot have any reasonably high posterior probability.  A design inference can be used to “sweep the field clear of all relevant chance hypotheses”. (Actually they could only do that if they could show that the probability of the data, given natural selection, was zero, but Demsbki and Ewert don’t quite mean that, they mean showing that the data is astronomically improbable).  Biologists argue that there may be many other “chance hypotheses”, but this is an argument by mere possibility as the biologists do not produce these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;who-is-arguing-from-ignorance-pages-337-339&quot;&gt;Who Is Arguing from Ignorance? (pages 337-339)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biologists are, since they essentially never produce the exact sequence of events needed to evolve these biological systems.  However, the biologists accuse the design theorists of arguing from ignorance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;john-stuart-mills-method-of-difference-pages-340-345&quot;&gt;John Stuart Mill’s Method of Difference (pages 340-345)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mill argued that if two situations differ in only one circumstance and a phenomenon occurs in one and not in the other, this circumstance is the effect, or cause.   Biologists such as Kenneth Miller say that all that is needed for natural selection to work is the presence of selection, replication, and mutation.  But these do not automatically lead to “complexity” or something “interesting”.  The evolution experiments of Sol Spiegelman and of Richard Lenski do not show those, but have genomes that rapidly decay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-challenge-of-multiple-simultaneous-mutations-pages-345-352&quot;&gt;The Challenge of Multiple Simultaneous Mutations (pages 345-352)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is basically a discussion of Michael Behe’s argument that major innovations require multiple mutations, each of which is individually disadvantageous, with an advantage only when they get together.  It is extremely improbable that these can be brought together by natural selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-to-make-of-bad-design-pages-353-to-368&quot;&gt;What to Make of Bad Design? (pages 353 to 368)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bad design arguments are not plausible for a number of reasons.  Quotes from “some naturalistic thinkers” who do not think there is actual design but are impressed with the design of the  cell.  These include James Shapiro.  Discussion of whether there is junk DNA, giving great credit to the 2012 (supposed) refutation of junk DNA by the ENCODE Consortium.  Dembski and Ewert cite an embarrassing quote by Richard Dawkins in 2012 accepting the ENCODE result and arguing that it is compatible with his views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;doing-the-calculation-pages-368-378&quot;&gt;Doing the Calculation (pages 368-378)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(At last, are we to be shown how?  Well, partly.)  Calculates the probability of a “biological system”, using protein folds as one example, invoking Douglas Axe’s experiments which that only one in 10&lt;sup&gt;-77&lt;/sup&gt; randomly constructed proteins would have enough of the proper structure and sequence 
to make a minimally functional β-lactamase enzyme.  Axe’s paper was in &lt;em&gt;Journal of Molecular Biology&lt;/em&gt;, volume 341, issue 5, page 1295 in 2004. The argument is based on the view that to get started evolving a β-lactamase enzyme one must have random assembly of such a protein, before natural selection can act. The example uses the protein sequence, with a 20-letter alphabet, as the string, equivalent to about a 648-bit string.  Dembski and 
Ewert do not try to quantitate the length of the “description” needed.  They acknowledge that evolutionary biologistss would argue that there might be other paths to the same functionality, without using these specific structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-breakdown-of-evolvability-pages-378-381&quot;&gt;The Breakdown of Evolvability (pages 378-381)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“whence the confidence that Darwinian evolution should allow untrammeled interconnectivity from any one living form to any other, whether by direct evolution or by indirect evolution from a common evolutionary precursor?”  They talk about protein alphabets, then uses a word game of changing a letter in a word, or deleting it, or adding a letter to change to another English word.  Argues that one cannot go from any word to any other this way.  Therefore although we have not proven that such interconnectedness in biological organisms cannot exist, we have shown it may not exist.  Therefore “there are indeed good reasons to think that a gradualist Darwinian form of evolution is very limited in what it can accomplish in biology, and that some features of biological systems not only resist Darwinian explanations but also invite design inferences”.  (This last part, the “some features” part, does not follow).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;where-to-look-for-small-probabilities-in-biology-pages-382-394&quot;&gt;Where to Look for Small Probabilities in Biology? (pages 382-394)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, the last section in Chapter 7, talks about Michael Behe’s arguments about Irreducible Complexity.  Lots of discussion of how the bacterial flagellum could or could not have arisen.  Evolutionary biologists never seem to come up with a detailed series of steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-have-dembski-and-ewert-accomplished&quot;&gt;What have Dembski and Ewert accomplished?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the questions I asked above, they have not answered most of them.   The one example that they give that involves a sequence of digital symbols 
asks about the probability of a particular protein sequence arising from random sequences of amino acids.  What they give is really not an Algorithmically 
Specified Complexity agument, but a much older argument.   Usually that argument takes the lengths of modern proteins as a necessary requirement for protein function, and does not take into account that many random protein sequences (and random RNA sequences) show a variety of weak enzymatic function.  And small changes in those sequences often lead to similar amounts of function.  It is therefore not impossible for evolution to follow steps uphill on a fitness surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difficulty with Dembski and Ewert’s definition of Algorithmically Specified Complexity is that when the quantity is large, it means that there is a long sequence (of something) which is “described” by a short sequence.  And there is simply no point in their argument that explains why (a) natural selection cannot achieve that, step by step, or (b) why achieving that is needed to result in any adaptation.  The matter is left without discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a large difference between the new argument and the previous specified complexity arguments.  As I noted in the first section of this review (12 June), the new concept is not a Functional Information argument.  The “probability” is not the probability that a random sequence has this much &lt;em&gt;or more&lt;/em&gt; of the desired trait.  It is just the probability of this sequence.  There is simply no discussion of how to compute a tail probability in some relevant distribution.  Or even in some nonrelevant distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are left with the questions I asked, and re-asked, above.  How does this argument work?  What are the relevant distributions?  What is the “sequence”?  How does the “description” relate to some relevant probability?  Is it a tail probability under some relevant null distribution?  Is it a probability that ordinary evolutionary processes could achieve something?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-burden-of-proof&quot;&gt;A burden of proof&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By not explaining how their arguments work, in spite of 400+ pages of explanation, Dembski and Ewert are engaged in wish-fulfillment.  They have “wished upon a star”.  But it is not true that, as the song claims, that if you do, “your dreams come true”.  Dembski and Ewert do not fill in the blanks, not even close.  They do go off sideways into irreducible complexity arguments, and they do repeatedly claim that evolutionary biologists argue that natural selection will always succeed in meeting challenges.  Ask the passenger pigeon about that, or the Great Auk, or the Dodo, or the Carolina Paroquet, or the mammoth.  Or the trilobites, or the seed ferns. or the ammonites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is still possible for them to answer my objections by filling in the blanks.  Saying that this is unfair, because biologists have not outlined every last step of the evolution of a complicated biological adaptation is no excuse.   I’ll be happy to hear from them how their arguments actually work.  We’re waiting …&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">The mountain called Six Grandfathers by the Lakota people before it was renamed Mount Rushmore. An image of Mount Rushmore adorns the cover of Dembski and Ewert's book, as an example of a design inference we make. Does the Lakota name reflect a design inference? Wikimedia, public domain &amp;nbsp; In my post of 12 June, I commented on the first part of William Dembski and Winston Ewert’s new book, the second edition of Dembski’s 1998 book The Design Inference: Eliminating Chance Through Small Probabilities. I noted that to make the argument for a Design Inference they had set aside Dembski’s previous criterion of Complex Specified Information, and instead replaced it by Algorithmic Specified Complexity (ASC). This is a measure of the difference between the length of a bitstring and the length of a bitstring that describes it. It originates from the mathematical work on “randomness deficiciency”, where the bitstring is a binary number, and the smaller bitstring is a computer program that computes it. In that field, numbers that are considered truly random are those generated by programs that are almost as long as the number. A number that can be generated by a short program is not considered random. Dembski and Ewert intend to apply this to biology. The longer number somehow specifies a phenotype (or maybe a genotype), while the shorter number “describes” it. In my previous review, I had reached Chapter 7, “Evolutionary Biology”. Here, let’s consider how they argue the ASC criterion can be applied to biological adaptations. (Spoiler – we’re going to be disappointed).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Philosopher Michael Ruse dies</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/philosopher-michael-ruse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Philosopher Michael Ruse dies" /><published>2024-11-07T09:47:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-11-07T09:47:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/philosopher-michael-ruse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/philosopher-michael-ruse.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The following &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/michael-ruse-influential-historian-and-philosopher-biology-dies-84&quot;&gt;obituary&lt;/a&gt; by Glenn Branch is reproduced with permission from the National Center for Science Education. In addition, you may read over a dozen &lt;/i&gt;very&lt;i&gt; nice remembrances on Leiter Reports, &lt;a href=&quot;https://leiterreports.typepad.com/blog/2024/11/in-memoriam-michael-ruse-1940-2024.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Leiter Reports describes itself as “[t]he world’s most popular philosophy blog, since 2003.” Thanks to Nick Matzke for providing the link.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Michael Ruse, influential historian and philosopher of biology, dies at 84&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Ruse_Obit_Pic_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Michael Ruse with his pet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;Michael Ruse with his pet, McGruff, in 2020. &lt;small&gt;By Lizzie Ruse, CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The influential historian and philosopher of biology Michael Ruse died on November 1, 2024, at the age of 84, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.legacy.com/ca/obituaries/theglobeandmail/name/michael-ruse-obituary?id=56689886&quot;&gt;according&lt;/a&gt; to the obituary in &lt;i&gt;The Globe and Mail&lt;/i&gt; (November 4, 2024). Ruse was one of the founders of the field of philosophy of biology: the first of his more than 70 books was the seminal &lt;i&gt;The Philosophy of Biology&lt;/i&gt; (1970) and he founded the field’s first journal, &lt;i&gt;Biology and Philosophy&lt;/i&gt;. He was especially interested in evolutionary biology, which he discussed in books such as &lt;i&gt;The Darwinian Revolution&lt;/i&gt; (1979, second edition 1999), &lt;i&gt;Darwinism Defended&lt;/i&gt; (1982), &lt;i&gt;Taking Darwin Seriously&lt;/i&gt; (1986), &lt;i&gt;Monad to Man: The Concept of Progress in Evolutionary Biology &lt;/i&gt;(1996), and &lt;i&gt;Darwin and Design&lt;/i&gt; (2003), among others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Owing to his scholarly interest in evolutionary biology, Ruse was recruited by the plaintiffs in &lt;i&gt;McLean v. Arkansas&lt;/i&gt;, a legal case challenging the constitutionality of Arkansas’s 1981 equal time for creation science law. His testimony that creation science failed to qualify as scientific was central to the favorable ruling, although it excited considerable controversy among his fellow philosophers. Ruse continued to discuss and criticize creationism, editing a collection of essays related to &lt;i&gt;McLean&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;But Is It Science?&lt;/i&gt; (1988, second edition coedited with Robert T. Pennock 2008) as well as writing &lt;i&gt;The Evolution War &lt;/i&gt; (2000), and &lt;i&gt;The Evolution/Creation Struggle&lt;/i&gt; (2005). Raised as a Quaker, Ruse was not a believer, but he sought to promote peaceful coexistence of science and religion, articulating his views in books such as &lt;i&gt;Can a Darwinian Be a Christian?&lt;/i&gt; (2001) and &lt;i&gt;Science and Spirituality&lt;/i&gt; (2010). Despite his differences with his intellectual foes, Ruse was famed for his friendliness and conviviality. Kenneth R. Miller of Brown University, president of NCSE’s board of directors, commented, “I respected him as a philosopher who genuinely understood science and more importantly loved him as a friend.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ruse was born in Birmingham, England, on June 21, 1940. He earned his B.A. in philosophy and mathematics from the University of Bristol in 1962, his M.A. in philosophy from McMaster University in 1964, and his Ph.D. in philosophy from the University of Bristol in 1970. He spent his career at the University of Guelph from 1965 to 2000 and then at Florida State University, where he was the Lucyle T. Werkmeister Professor of Philosophy from 2000 onward. He was a Fellow of the Royal Society of Canada and of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, one of the Gifford Lecturers in Natural Theology for 2001, and the recipient of at least four honorary doctoral degrees.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">The following obituary by Glenn Branch is reproduced with permission from the National Center for Science Education. In addition, you may read over a dozen very nice remembrances on Leiter Reports, here. Leiter Reports describes itself as “[t]he world’s most popular philosophy blog, since 2003.” Thanks to Nick Matzke for providing the link. Michael Ruse, influential historian and philosopher of biology, dies at 84 Michael Ruse with his pet, McGruff, in 2020. By Lizzie Ruse, CC BY-SA 4.0. The influential historian and philosopher of biology Michael Ruse died on November 1, 2024, at the age of 84, according to the obituary in The Globe and Mail (November 4, 2024). Ruse was one of the founders of the field of philosophy of biology: the first of his more than 70 books was the seminal The Philosophy of Biology (1970) and he founded the field’s first journal, Biology and Philosophy. He was especially interested in evolutionary biology, which he discussed in books such as The Darwinian Revolution (1979, second edition 1999), Darwinism Defended (1982), Taking Darwin Seriously (1986), Monad to Man: The Concept of Progress in Evolutionary Biology (1996), and Darwin and Design (2003), among others. Owing to his scholarly interest in evolutionary biology, Ruse was recruited by the plaintiffs in McLean v. Arkansas, a legal case challenging the constitutionality of Arkansas’s 1981 equal time for creation science law. His testimony that creation science failed to qualify as scientific was central to the favorable ruling, although it excited considerable controversy among his fellow philosophers. Ruse continued to discuss and criticize creationism, editing a collection of essays related to McLean, But Is It Science? (1988, second edition coedited with Robert T. Pennock 2008) as well as writing The Evolution War (2000), and The Evolution/Creation Struggle (2005). Raised as a Quaker, Ruse was not a believer, but he sought to promote peaceful coexistence of science and religion, articulating his views in books such as Can a Darwinian Be a Christian? (2001) and Science and Spirituality (2010). Despite his differences with his intellectual foes, Ruse was famed for his friendliness and conviviality. Kenneth R. Miller of Brown University, president of NCSE’s board of directors, commented, “I respected him as a philosopher who genuinely understood science and more importantly loved him as a friend.” Ruse was born in Birmingham, England, on June 21, 1940. He earned his B.A. in philosophy and mathematics from the University of Bristol in 1962, his M.A. in philosophy from McMaster University in 1964, and his Ph.D. in philosophy from the University of Bristol in 1970. He spent his career at the University of Guelph from 1965 to 2000 and then at Florida State University, where he was the Lucyle T. Werkmeister Professor of Philosophy from 2000 onward. He was a Fellow of the Royal Society of Canada and of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, one of the Gifford Lecturers in Natural Theology for 2001, and the recipient of at least four honorary doctoral degrees.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Climate Change Denial for Creationist Kids</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/climate-change-denial.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Climate Change Denial for Creationist Kids" /><published>2024-11-06T09:22:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-11-06T09:22:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/climate-change-denial</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/climate-change-denial.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Branch_Climate_Change_Kids_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Screenshot image of Ken Ham and Jessica DeFord’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.masterbooks.com/climate-change-for-kids-and-parents-too&quot;&gt; &lt;i&gt;Climate Change for Kids…and Parents Too!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Originally posted in &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/climate-change-denial-for-creationist-kids/&quot;&gt;Righting America&lt;/a&gt;, October 29, 2024, and reprinted with permission. Glenn Branch is deputy director of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/&quot;&gt;National Center for Science Education&lt;/a&gt;, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as &lt;/i&gt;Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher, &lt;i&gt;and the &lt;/i&gt;Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics, &lt;i&gt;and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of &lt;/i&gt;Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools&lt;i&gt; (2006). He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.masterbooks.com/climate-change-for-kids-and-parents-too&quot;&gt; &lt;i&gt;Climate Change for Kids…and Parents Too!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the latest entry in a spate of climate change denial books aimed at a young audience, invites the reader to “[d]elve into the science of climate change and discover how science, removed from assumption and speculation, reflects the history and truth found in God’s Word” (in the words of the back cover). The reference to God’s Word is distinctive: the propaganda efforts in the same vein from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/climate-environment/2023/04/11/CO&amp;lt;sub&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;/sub&amp;gt;-coalition-climate-denial/&quot;&gt;the CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; Coalition&lt;/a&gt;, Mike Huckabee’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://insideclimatenews.org/news/31072023/huckabees-kids-guide-to-climate/&quot;&gt;EverBright Kids&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eenews.net/articles/in-desantis-fla-schools-get-ok-for-climate-denial-videos/&quot;&gt;PragerU&lt;/a&gt; are ostensibly secular. But the authors of &lt;i&gt;Climate Change for Kids&lt;/i&gt; are Ken Ham, the founder of the young-earth creationist ministry Answers in Genesis, and Jessica DeFord, who, armed with a master of science degree in wildlife ecology, works for the same organization. In consequence, their book is a mix of error and fantasy, with the errors resembling those of secular climate change deniers and the fantasies emanating from their own reading of — and creative additions to — the Bible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fair amount of the eighty-page book purports to address the evidence for climate change and for anthropogenic climate change from the historical record. It would be tedious to describe all of its errors, but a central misunderstanding deserves attention. Acknowledging that “[t]he observational data shows [&lt;i&gt;sic&lt;/i&gt;] that the global surface temperature of the earth has been warming over the past 100 years or so since it has been recorded” and reporting that the amount of warming is estimated to be about 1.5–1.8 °C, Ham and DeFord then caution, “But this warming estimate didn’t come solely from the observational data collected at weather stations and by satellites. It’s based on computer models. What you input into these models will decide what predications [&lt;i&gt;sic&lt;/i&gt;] the computer model provides” (p. 18). A footnote offers a 2022 paper by meteorologist Roy W. Spencer and climatologist John R. Christy, both at the University of Alabama in Huntsville, as evidence for the middle sentence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s the problem? Well, the cited paper, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchsquare.com/article/rs-2162757/v1&quot;&gt;Dependence of Climate Sensitivity Estimates on Internal Climate Variability During 1880–2020 &lt;/a&gt;,” is prominently labeled “This is a preprint; it has not been peer reviewed by a journal.” So Ham and DeFord have no business citing it. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00704-023-04634-7&quot;&gt;version&lt;/a&gt; of the paper was later published in the journal &lt;i&gt;Theoretical and Applied Climatology&lt;/i&gt;, although it seems not to have attracted significant scientific attention. More importantly, though, in neither version of their paper do Spencer and Christy claim that the warming estimate is based on computer models. And that is simply because the warming estimate is not based on predictive computer models! Rather, it is based on observational data, namely, measurements taken by surface and satellite thermometers. True, both data sets require adjustment and correction in light of factors that introduce biases. But their close agreement, unmentioned by Ham and DeFord, is strong confirmation that the climate is warming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ham and DeFord conclude, “So the predictions don’t necessarily reflect the real-world, observational data” (p. 18) — which is odd, since no predictions are under discussion. They add, “And one study that compared computer climate models to the observational data found every single climate model they studied overpredicted warming,” citing a 2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdfdirect/10.1029/2020EA001281&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; by Ross McKitrick, a professor of economics at the University of Guelph, and Christy. But the paper focuses on the ability of a certain class of models, not all models, to predict tropospheric, not surface, temperatures. (It is a robust scientific finding that we live on the surface of the planet.) A comprehensive analysis of climate models published between 1970 and 2007 &lt;a href=&quot;https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1029/2019GL085378&quot;&gt;found&lt;/a&gt; them to be “skillful in predicting subsequent GMST [global mean surface temperature] changes, with most models examined showing warming consistent with observations, particularly when mismatches between model-projected and observationally estimated forcings were taken into account.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Illustrated here is Ham and DeFord’s general approach to handling the scientific literature on climate change: cite a single source that seems to offer evidence for the necessary point without worrying about whether it is legitimate, relevant, or confirmed by the bulk of scientific research. Sometimes, however, they abandon the approach in favor of bald assertion. Continuing, Ham and DeFord assert, with dubious coherence, “Climate researchers generally assume Earth maintains a constant average temperature and that our atmosphere traps more heat from the sun than what is returned to outer space” (p. 19), but they provide no examples of any researcher making such assumptions. Similarly, they claim that there is evidence that both of these “assumptions” are wrong, thus invalidating any models incorporating them, but they provide no references to such evidence. In any case, the views of climate scientists on these questions are not a matter of assumption but of evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite their view that there’s no telling how much Earth has warmed since the 1880s, Ham and DeFord are apparently willing to concede that recent global warming is real. But they misrepresent the argument for its anthropogenic nature, writing, “Since humans burn fossil fuels and burning fossil fuels produces CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; traps heat … we must be responsible for any warming … right?” (p. 20, ellipses in original). In fact, climate scientists have not jumped to their conclusion as &lt;i&gt;Climate Change for Kids&lt;/i&gt; suggests; rather, they have meticulously examined all of the known mechanisms capable of changing the climate and have concluded that greenhouse gases released by human activities are responsible for recent global warming. Popular explanations of the way in which they reached their conclusion are easy to find. For Ham and DeFord to misrepresent the argument so badly suggests at best that they are incompetent to write a book about climate science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paleoclimatology is dismissed on the grounds of a general skepticism about scientific knowledge of the past: “You can’t directly test, observe, or repeat the past!” (p. 33). “Scientists cannot 100% accurately describe past events if they were not there to directly observe them,” Ham and DeFord assert (p. 33), ignoring the fact that, far from claiming 100% accuracy, scientists typically report their findings with error bars. From a secular point of view, their emphasis on dismissing paleoclimatology is odd: until recently, paleoclimatological data (as well as historical data) were not considered to be as reliable as data from climate models, so the best evidence for the anthropogenic nature of climate change was from climate models — which are, of course, rooted in basic physics as applied to observational data. But Answers in Genesis, as a young-earth creationist ministry, is heavily invested in disputing the possibility of scientific knowledge of the past, and Ham and DeFord evidently want to put the investment to work here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus &lt;i&gt;Climate Change for Kids&lt;/i&gt; insists, “God and His Word is the ultimate authority by which we must discern all climate and weather information” (p. 53), and Ham — who nominally takes over the narration from p. 54 onward — explains, “As I’ve read the Bible to understand ‘climate change’ events that affect us to this day, God has revealed 7 climate ages divided into the history in the Bible” (p. 58). There are seven of these ages, presumably to rhyme with the seven days of creation; Answers in Genesis similarly discerns &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/bible-history/seven-cs-of-history/&quot;&gt;seven eras of history&lt;/a&gt;: Creation, Corruption, Catastrophe, Confusion, Christ, Cross, and Consummation. The alliterative muse apparently having deserted him, and no explicit nomenclature to be found in the Bible, Ham calls the seven climate ages Perfect, Groaning (i.e., postlapsarian, the label referring to Romans 8:22: “For we know that the whole creation has been groaning together in the pains of childbirth until now” [ESV]), Flooding, Icy, Shifting, Fiery, and Heavenly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the displays at Answers in Genesis’s attractions, the Creation Museum and Ark Encounter, the discussion of the seven climate ages (sprawled from p. 60 to p. 77) presents a reading of the Bible that both confabulates details that aren’t visible in the text (starting with the seven climate ages themselves) and fails to acknowledge a diversity of opinion among Bible-believing Christians. (On the attractions, see, for example, Susan L. Trollinger and William Vance Trollinger Jr.’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.press.jhu.edu/books/title/10885/righting-america-creation-museum&quot;&gt; &lt;i&gt;Righting America at the Creation Museum&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and James S. Bielo’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://nyupress.org/9781479843244/ark-encounter/&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Ark Encounter&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;; for organizations of evangelical Christians who accept climate change, see, for example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://yecaction.org/&quot;&gt;Young Evangelicals for Climate Action&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://creationcare.org/&quot;&gt;Evangelical Environmental Network&lt;/a&gt;.) Puzzlingly, the Groaning climate age is described as “continuing to this day, because God has not yet made a new heavens and earth to restore perfection” (p. 65); what’s the point of distinguishing among seven climate ages if there’s going to be overlap among them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Climate Change for Kids&lt;/i&gt; is purportedly aimed at readers nine years and older, and there are features, beyond the color illustrations on every page, clearly aimed at a young audience, such as boxes headed “Let’s ask” and “Why then?” and “From God’s Word” (with highlighted and annotated verses from the Bible). Still, having a four-page introduction from a septuagenarian Australian complaining about the secularism infecting his college education in the early 1970s seems like not the best way to attract the intended readership. Similarly, a fourth-grader might gaze upon the admonition “When climate change panic is induced and alarms are sounded in the media or in the halls of academia, we must exercise discernment” (p. 11) with a degree of puzzlement. Many of the cited sources (with details crammed, in tiny text, on p. 80) would certainly be beyond the ability of a young audience even to comprehend, let alone assess for scientific credibility. (A number of those works are in fact not scientifically credible.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But probably none of its readers are going to exercise discernment while poring over the arguments of the book. A five-star review posted at its publisher’s website comments, “I have it sitting on our coffee table in the living room (strategically placed!) and the kids have all flipped through it and learned so much!” “Flipped through” rings true. Rather, &lt;i&gt;Climate Change for Kids&lt;/i&gt; is geared for a readership that expects Answers in Genesis to have answers — so to speak — to all questions of importance to the Bible-believing Christian and so is less concerned about the quality than about the existence of the answers. Owning a copy of the book, and thus manifesting solidarity with Answers in Genesis, is what matters. Unfortunately, the same attitude is likely to bolster continuing efforts to derail, delay, and degrade action on the very real disruptions caused by anthropogenic global warming that are already afflicting people, including Ken Ham’s base, around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgments.&lt;/strong&gt;
Thanks to Paul Braterman for useful discussion and to Barry Bickmore, Andrew Dessler, and Spencer Weart for discussion of the climate change literature.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Glenn Branch</name></author><summary type="html">Screenshot image of Ken Ham and Jessica DeFord’s Climate Change for Kids…and Parents Too! Originally posted in Righting America, October 29, 2024, and reprinted with permission. Glenn Branch is deputy director of the National Center for Science Education, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher, and the Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics, and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools (2006). He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers. Climate Change for Kids…and Parents Too!, the latest entry in a spate of climate change denial books aimed at a young audience, invites the reader to “[d]elve into the science of climate change and discover how science, removed from assumption and speculation, reflects the history and truth found in God’s Word” (in the words of the back cover). The reference to God’s Word is distinctive: the propaganda efforts in the same vein from the CO2 Coalition, Mike Huckabee’s EverBright Kids, and PragerU are ostensibly secular. But the authors of Climate Change for Kids are Ken Ham, the founder of the young-earth creationist ministry Answers in Genesis, and Jessica DeFord, who, armed with a master of science degree in wildlife ecology, works for the same organization. In consequence, their book is a mix of error and fantasy, with the errors resembling those of secular climate change deniers and the fantasies emanating from their own reading of — and creative additions to — the Bible. A fair amount of the eighty-page book purports to address the evidence for climate change and for anthropogenic climate change from the historical record. It would be tedious to describe all of its errors, but a central misunderstanding deserves attention. Acknowledging that “[t]he observational data shows [sic] that the global surface temperature of the earth has been warming over the past 100 years or so since it has been recorded” and reporting that the amount of warming is estimated to be about 1.5–1.8 °C, Ham and DeFord then caution, “But this warming estimate didn’t come solely from the observational data collected at weather stations and by satellites. It’s based on computer models. What you input into these models will decide what predications [sic] the computer model provides” (p. 18). A footnote offers a 2022 paper by meteorologist Roy W. Spencer and climatologist John R. Christy, both at the University of Alabama in Huntsville, as evidence for the middle sentence.</summary></entry></feed>