<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-05-19T05:56:10-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Creationist Paper on Heat Problems Associated with Genesis Flood</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/05/creationist-paper-heat-problems.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creationist Paper on Heat Problems Associated with Genesis Flood" /><published>2023-05-18T08:02:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-05-18T08:02:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/05/creationist-paper-heat-problems</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/05/creationist-paper-heat-problems.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Phelps_Flood_Stamp_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Noah's Ark&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;And the Ark floated on the face of the waters. &lt;small&gt;Wikimedia Commons, detail from Stamp of Israel &amp;ndash; Festivals 5730, 13 August 1969, http://israelphilately.org.il/he/catalog/stamps/871, Asher Kalderon and Davis Grebu for Israel Post. Public domain.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers in Genesis (AiG) published a &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersresearchjournal.org/noahs-flood/heat-problems-flood-models-4/&quot;&gt;new paper&lt;/a&gt; yesterday in their &lt;i&gt;Answers Research Journal&lt;/i&gt; discussing how life on earth survived the massive amount of heat produced in volcanic eruptions and intrusions during “The Flood.” The paper was authored by Dr. &lt;a href=&quot;https://creation.com/bill-worraker&quot;&gt;William Worraker&lt;/a&gt;, a British creationist with a doctorate in mathematics and a BS in physics. To their credit, the creationists realize having the Paleozoic-to-Recent igneous rock record go from molten to crystallizing in the last few thousand years presents a big problem for Young Earth Creationism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual for &lt;i&gt;Answers Research Journal&lt;/i&gt;, it is difficult to determine who the paper is aimed at or how it was peer reviewed by any competent scientist in the fields the paper discusses. Lots of technical articles from real journals and several mathematical appendices are cited, but then there is a section of definitions taken from &lt;i&gt;Encyclopedia Britannica&lt;/i&gt; that include basic information that an undergraduate chemistry student should be aware of, as well as descriptions of minerals at an undergraduate mineralogy class level. This paper doesn’t appear to be written with the intent of convincing a geophysicist or geoscientist studying tectonics. In reality, it seems written to impress non-scientists, including potential donors to AiG, by being “sciencey.” Much of what is put out by AiG, the Institute for Creation Research, and other creationists that looks technical is really just a parody of science, meant to impress their followers/donors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The abstract mentions supernatural explanations, but most of the paper doesn’t do so until the concluding portion. After paragraphs of rather questionable reasoning, special pleading, attempts at physics, and creation “science,” the author finally comes clean with this total &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2017/02/on-bullshit.html&quot;&gt;bullshit&lt;/a&gt; by claiming the Bible says it and God did it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;However, it is important to appreciate that our inability to identify an acknowledged mechanism for removing the excess heat deposited during and after the Flood, an issue first identified over 35 years ago (Baumgardner 1986), is only a problem in the sense that it represents the limited nature of our human understanding. In a biblical context there is no fundamental problem because God purposely brought about the Flood (Genesis 6:17) as a judgment on the wicked human race of Noah’s day and covenanted with Noah to preserve human and animal life through the cataclysm (Genesis 6:18). He sovereignly accomplished both objectives, implying that environmental temperatures could not have risen beyond biological endurance limits. The only real problem is our current lack of understanding of how this was accomplished; the Flood account in Genesis 6–9 does not tell us directly whether supernatural processes were involved, though it seems very likely that they were. The same basic issue arises in connection with the topics to be covered in Parts 5 (heat due to Accelerated Nuclear Decay) and 6 (heat due to bombardments from space) of this series, and will be considered at greater length in Part 7.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author could have saved a great deal of time if he had just said a miracle occurred rather than subjecting the reader to all of the arm waving and special pleading.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">And the Ark floated on the face of the waters. Wikimedia Commons, detail from Stamp of Israel &amp;ndash; Festivals 5730, 13 August 1969, http://israelphilately.org.il/he/catalog/stamps/871, Asher Kalderon and Davis Grebu for Israel Post. Public domain. Answers in Genesis (AiG) published a new paper yesterday in their Answers Research Journal discussing how life on earth survived the massive amount of heat produced in volcanic eruptions and intrusions during “The Flood.” The paper was authored by Dr. William Worraker, a British creationist with a doctorate in mathematics and a BS in physics. To their credit, the creationists realize having the Paleozoic-to-Recent igneous rock record go from molten to crystallizing in the last few thousand years presents a big problem for Young Earth Creationism. As usual for Answers Research Journal, it is difficult to determine who the paper is aimed at or how it was peer reviewed by any competent scientist in the fields the paper discusses. Lots of technical articles from real journals and several mathematical appendices are cited, but then there is a section of definitions taken from Encyclopedia Britannica that include basic information that an undergraduate chemistry student should be aware of, as well as descriptions of minerals at an undergraduate mineralogy class level. This paper doesn’t appear to be written with the intent of convincing a geophysicist or geoscientist studying tectonics. In reality, it seems written to impress non-scientists, including potential donors to AiG, by being “sciencey.” Much of what is put out by AiG, the Institute for Creation Research, and other creationists that looks technical is really just a parody of science, meant to impress their followers/donors. The abstract mentions supernatural explanations, but most of the paper doesn’t do so until the concluding portion. After paragraphs of rather questionable reasoning, special pleading, attempts at physics, and creation “science,” the author finally comes clean with this total bullshit by claiming the Bible says it and God did it: However, it is important to appreciate that our inability to identify an acknowledged mechanism for removing the excess heat deposited during and after the Flood, an issue first identified over 35 years ago (Baumgardner 1986), is only a problem in the sense that it represents the limited nature of our human understanding. In a biblical context there is no fundamental problem because God purposely brought about the Flood (Genesis 6:17) as a judgment on the wicked human race of Noah’s day and covenanted with Noah to preserve human and animal life through the cataclysm (Genesis 6:18). He sovereignly accomplished both objectives, implying that environmental temperatures could not have risen beyond biological endurance limits. The only real problem is our current lack of understanding of how this was accomplished; the Flood account in Genesis 6–9 does not tell us directly whether supernatural processes were involved, though it seems very likely that they were. The same basic issue arises in connection with the topics to be covered in Parts 5 (heat due to Accelerated Nuclear Decay) and 6 (heat due to bombardments from space) of this series, and will be considered at greater length in Part 7. The author could have saved a great deal of time if he had just said a miracle occurred rather than subjecting the reader to all of the arm waving and special pleading.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Branta canadensis/Anser caerulescens</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/05/branta-canadensis-anser-caerulescens.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Branta canadensis/Anser caerulescens" /><published>2023-05-08T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-05-08T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/05/branta-canadensis-anser-caerulescens</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/05/branta-canadensis-anser-caerulescens.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/P1010237_Geese_Crop_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Canada goose, snow goose&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canada_goose&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Branta canadensis&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Canada goose &amp;ndash; being shadowed by an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snow_goose&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Anser caerulescens&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; snow goose &amp;ndash; Coot Lake, Boulder, Colorado, April, 2023. The solitary snow goose followed a meter or two behind the Canada goose the entire time we watched. Since the two species are known to &lt;a href=&quot;https://ebird.org/species/x00197&quot;&gt;hybridize&lt;/a&gt;, I wondered whether they were a pair.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Branta canadensis &amp;ndash; Canada goose &amp;ndash; being shadowed by an Anser caerulescens &amp;ndash; snow goose &amp;ndash; Coot Lake, Boulder, Colorado, April, 2023. The solitary snow goose followed a meter or two behind the Canada goose the entire time we watched. Since the two species are known to hybridize, I wondered whether they were a pair.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Existential Physics: Book review</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/05/existential-physics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Existential Physics: Book review" /><published>2023-05-06T09:27:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-05-06T09:27:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/05/existential-physics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/05/existential-physics.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Hossenfelder_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sabine Hossenfelder is fearless. Though she would allow you to believe anything you want to, as long as your belief is at least consistent with what we know about science, she will remind you whenever there is no evidence in favor of your belief. Indeed, she says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;If your belief conflicts with empirically confirmed knowledge, then you are not seeking meaning; you are delusional.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to hold onto your delusions, she avers, then this book is not for you. She treats beliefs that do not conflict with what we know as harmless and indeed thinks that “scientists should acknowledge that science is compatible with many traditional sacred beliefs.” Thus, she (indirectly) criticizes Richard Dawkins and the “new atheists” for being too rigid in their beliefs: we have no evidence to distinguish between a Big Bang that was created by God and one that was not. She is right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, she reminds us that there is no empirical evidence in favor of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;the many-worlds hypothesis of quantum mechanics; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the multiverse, multiple universes, or an infinite universe; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a mathematical universe, in which math is real and we are not; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;panpsychism, the conceit that all matter is to some degree conscious; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a universe in which we are simulations;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cyclic universes;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cosmic inflation in the early universe; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a universe designed by God.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She calls these “modern creation myths written in the language of mathematics.” They are, basically, religious beliefs, and can generally not be falsified. She even doubts the heat death of the universe, in part because there may be longer-term or longer-scale effects of which we are unaware. Additionally, Hossenfelder thinks the second law of thermodynamics may itself be overturned when we develop a quantum theory that includes gravity, though I think that is pure speculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a section on reductionism, she says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;… [T]he available evidence tells us that the whole is the sum of the parts, not more and not less. Countless experiments have confirmed for millennia that things are made of smaller things, and if you know what the small things do, then you can tell what the large things do. There is not a single known exception to this rule. There is not even a consistent theory for such an exception. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oddly, the ensuing discussion softens the statement somewhat, and she notes that we do not know why reductionism works, only that it does. But she ends up with the pithy remark, “If you say ‘holism,’ I hear ‘bullshit.’” Me too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hossenfelder is pretty much a strict determinist and devotes a few pages (contra Daniel Dennett, Sean Carroll, and others) to explaining why she thinks we do not have free will. Her argument could perhaps expose more clearly a confusion between being unpredictable and being truly random (even if this confusion is dressed up as an emergent property). Several times she reminds us that “the future is still fixed except for occasional quantum events that we cannot influence.” To believe in truly free will, you practically have to be a dualist. (As for me, I &lt;i&gt;act&lt;/i&gt; as if I have free will because I have no choice.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On quantum mechanics, Hossenfelder takes on the Copenhagen interpretation and notes that the “collapse” of the wavefunction is something of a misnomer, in that it makes you think that the wavefunction, which fills all space, is slurped faster than the speed of light into a fixed location whenever we make a measurement. Instead, she says that the &lt;i&gt;collapse&lt;/i&gt; would better be called the &lt;i&gt;update&lt;/i&gt; or the &lt;i&gt;reduction&lt;/i&gt;. What is a measurement? It is any interaction that is strong enough to destroy the quantum behavior of the system and does not require a conscious observer. So (as I once put it elsewhere) a photographic plate does not have to wait till it is developed and indeed looked at by a conscious observer for a latent image to be present in the undeveloped plate. A measurement has been made every time a photoelectron is trapped in a photographic grain. (Maybe measurement is also a misnomer.) The grain will be developed, Hossenfelder would say, according to ordinary classical chemistry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hossenfelder acknowledges that quantum mechanics is random. I disagree and suspect that deep down it too is deterministic. I will grant that this is a religious belief of a sort, but I can defend it with a better argument than, say, the argument from first cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I studied special relativity for perhaps a couple of weeks, admittedly long ago, and I found the first chapter, on special relativity, somewhat hard in places. Hossenfelder notes that Now [her capitalization] is undefinable, and you can always find some place in the universe where some observer could in principle observe your grandmother in her daily activities. In that case, your grandmother is not just alive and kicking, but immortal. I do not know exactly what she was trying to prove with that discussion, but I find it to be cold comfort in that we can never get back to that time in our own frame of reference (because of irreversibility, a subject of another chapter).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have uncharacteristically few quibbles, but I think it is worth noting that the unit of temperature is the kelvin – plural, kelvins – not the Kelvin, and certainly not the degree Kelvin. Thus, both “2.7 Kelvin” and “a degree Kelvin” are incorrect and should have been caught by an editor. Otherwise, I thought that the book was extremely well prepared and clearly written, and I advise nonphysicists that there is much more, so be sure to persevere beyond the first chapter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sabine Hossenfelder, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/616868/existential-physics-by-sabine-hossenfelder/&quot;&gt;Existential Physics&lt;/a&gt;: A Scientist’s Guide to Life’s Biggest Questions&lt;/i&gt;, Viking, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Sabine Hossenfelder is fearless. Though she would allow you to believe anything you want to, as long as your belief is at least consistent with what we know about science, she will remind you whenever there is no evidence in favor of your belief. Indeed, she says, If your belief conflicts with empirically confirmed knowledge, then you are not seeking meaning; you are delusional. If you want to hold onto your delusions, she avers, then this book is not for you. She treats beliefs that do not conflict with what we know as harmless and indeed thinks that “scientists should acknowledge that science is compatible with many traditional sacred beliefs.” Thus, she (indirectly) criticizes Richard Dawkins and the “new atheists” for being too rigid in their beliefs: we have no evidence to distinguish between a Big Bang that was created by God and one that was not. She is right.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Answers in Genesis seeks high school “science” teacher</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/answers-in-Genesis-seeks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Answers in Genesis seeks high school “science” teacher" /><published>2023-04-29T16:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-04-29T16:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/answers-in-Genesis-seeks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/answers-in-Genesis-seeks.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Taking_Dinosaurs_Back.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bumper sticker&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A bumper sticker offered for sale by AIG in 2012 and displayed in an article attacking a scientist who thinks that birds evolved from dinosaurs.
&lt;small&gt;Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/dinosaurs/feathers/blogger-evolutionists-reject-feathered-dinosaurs-misguided/&quot;&gt;Blogger: Evolutionists who Reject Feathered Dinosaurs &quot;Misguided&quot;&lt;/a&gt; by Elizabeth Mitchell.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An informant tells us that Answers in Genesis is looking for a high school “science” teacher for their “Answers Academy” (formerly “Twelve Stones Academy”) [informant’s quotation marks]. Here are some of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.paycomonline.net/v4/ats/web.php/jobs/ViewJobDetails?clientkey=36BAEBCF961EB253FD190A922A7D98D6&amp;amp;job=77715&quot;&gt;requirements&lt;/a&gt; for the job:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The qualified individual must be an evangelical Christian committed to living a biblical lifestyle in all areas and in full agreement with the schools (sic) statement of faith. The teacher is expected to be in alignment with the science and biblical positions held at Answers in Genesis and able to teach science from a biblical worldview in the classroom. The teacher must also be able to distinguish operational vs historical science as well as be able to articulate the evolutionary beliefs correctly while being able to refute them biblically and scientifically. The teacher must also have a good understanding of AiGs (sic) presuppositional apologetic approach and know how to incorporate it in the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The teacher shall be one who feels called of God to the teaching profession. The teacher must maintain a teachable spirit while demonstrating patience, humility, integrity, and kindness while performing his/her day-to-day duties. He/she must be devoted to prayerfully work with administration, faculty, students, and parents to develop and maintain a school which is thoroughly Christian and academically exceptional. The teacher shall prayerfully help students learn attitudes, skills, and subject matter that will contribute to their development as mature, able, and responsible Christians to the glory of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest is mostly boilerplate, except for the requirements to adhere to AIG’s statement of faith, be “deeply committed to a consistent daily walk with Jesus Christ,” spend time in prayer, attend church services, be a Christian role model, and so on. There is no indication what subjects are to be taught nor at what grade level, except for the requirement that the material must be tied to the Bible. If anyone is interested, you may click the “Apply” button and submit your résumé.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">A bumper sticker offered for sale by AIG in 2012 and displayed in an article attacking a scientist who thinks that birds evolved from dinosaurs. Credit: Blogger: Evolutionists who Reject Feathered Dinosaurs &quot;Misguided&quot; by Elizabeth Mitchell. An informant tells us that Answers in Genesis is looking for a high school “science” teacher for their “Answers Academy” (formerly “Twelve Stones Academy”) [informant’s quotation marks]. Here are some of the requirements for the job: The qualified individual must be an evangelical Christian committed to living a biblical lifestyle in all areas and in full agreement with the schools (sic) statement of faith. The teacher is expected to be in alignment with the science and biblical positions held at Answers in Genesis and able to teach science from a biblical worldview in the classroom. The teacher must also be able to distinguish operational vs historical science as well as be able to articulate the evolutionary beliefs correctly while being able to refute them biblically and scientifically. The teacher must also have a good understanding of AiGs (sic) presuppositional apologetic approach and know how to incorporate it in the classroom. The teacher shall be one who feels called of God to the teaching profession. The teacher must maintain a teachable spirit while demonstrating patience, humility, integrity, and kindness while performing his/her day-to-day duties. He/she must be devoted to prayerfully work with administration, faculty, students, and parents to develop and maintain a school which is thoroughly Christian and academically exceptional. The teacher shall prayerfully help students learn attitudes, skills, and subject matter that will contribute to their development as mature, able, and responsible Christians to the glory of God. The rest is mostly boilerplate, except for the requirements to adhere to AIG’s statement of faith, be “deeply committed to a consistent daily walk with Jesus Christ,” spend time in prayer, attend church services, be a Christian role model, and so on. There is no indication what subjects are to be taught nor at what grade level, except for the requirement that the material must be tied to the Bible. If anyone is interested, you may click the “Apply” button and submit your résumé.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rosalind Franklin and 70th anniversary of publication of structure of DNA</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/rosalind-franklin-and.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rosalind Franklin and 70th anniversary of publication of structure of DNA" /><published>2023-04-25T15:51:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-04-25T15:51:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/rosalind-franklin-and</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/rosalind-franklin-and.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Rosalind-franklin-in-paris_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rosalind Franklin&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Rosalind Elsie Franklin was an English chemist and X-ray crystallographer whose work was central to the understanding of the molecular structures of DNA (deoxyribonucleic acid), RNA (ribonucleic acid), viruses, coal, and graphite.&lt;small&gt;Wikimedia Commons. &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.en&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 4.0 International license&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2023/04/25/cobb-and-comfort-on-the-contributions-of-rosalind-franklin-to-solving-the-structure-of-dna/&quot;&gt;Jerry Coyne reminds us&lt;/a&gt;, is the 70th anniversary of the publication of the structure of DNA in three &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt; papers by Watson and Crick; Wilkins, Stokes, and Wilson; and Franklin and Gosling. Coyne takes the opportunity to remind us that much of the “folklore” concerning Rosalind Franklin is false and based on a nearly fictional characterization written by James Watson, who frankly makes himself look like a fool. At any rate, it was Watson himself who initiated the conceit that a critical X-ray interferogram taken by Franklin had actually been stolen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coyne cites new work by Matthew Cobb and Nathaniel Comfort showing that in fact neither Watson nor Crick himself saw the critical interferogram. Cobb is a biologist at Manchester and is writing a biography of Watson; Comfort is a historian of science at Johns Hopkins University and is writing a biography of Crick. The two collaborated and discovered that Watson and Crick had actually read a report, and that Franklin knew that Max Perutz had passed the report to them. Indeed, Franklin remained friends with Crick throughout the rest of her life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of this will be exactly shocking to anyone who has read &lt;i&gt;The Secret of Life: Rosalind Franklin, James Watson, Francis Crick, and the Discovery of DNA’s Double Helix&lt;/i&gt;, by the scientist and historian Howard Markel. I reviewed the book on Amazon &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/customer-reviews/R2DQ9BL2R1HJN1?ref=pf_ov_at_pdctrvw_srp&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (it is a bad habit I occasionally indulge in). Franklin was a remarkable scientist who, as the Wikimedia caption notes, contributed to understanding the structures of DNA, RNA, viruses, coal, and graphite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came away from Markel’s book with the impression that Watson had seen the X-ray interferogram, and Franklin was unaware that he had. The work of Cobb and Comfort suggests that in fact Watson had not seen the X-ray let alone stolen it. That said, the end of Markel’s book is a long, long interview with Watson, and I thought that Watson, for whatever reason, came across as knowing that he had not been entirely honest.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Rosalind Elsie Franklin was an English chemist and X-ray crystallographer whose work was central to the understanding of the molecular structures of DNA (deoxyribonucleic acid), RNA (ribonucleic acid), viruses, coal, and graphite.Wikimedia Commons. Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 4.0 International license. Today, Jerry Coyne reminds us, is the 70th anniversary of the publication of the structure of DNA in three Nature papers by Watson and Crick; Wilkins, Stokes, and Wilson; and Franklin and Gosling. Coyne takes the opportunity to remind us that much of the “folklore” concerning Rosalind Franklin is false and based on a nearly fictional characterization written by James Watson, who frankly makes himself look like a fool. At any rate, it was Watson himself who initiated the conceit that a critical X-ray interferogram taken by Franklin had actually been stolen. Coyne cites new work by Matthew Cobb and Nathaniel Comfort showing that in fact neither Watson nor Crick himself saw the critical interferogram. Cobb is a biologist at Manchester and is writing a biography of Watson; Comfort is a historian of science at Johns Hopkins University and is writing a biography of Crick. The two collaborated and discovered that Watson and Crick had actually read a report, and that Franklin knew that Max Perutz had passed the report to them. Indeed, Franklin remained friends with Crick throughout the rest of her life. None of this will be exactly shocking to anyone who has read The Secret of Life: Rosalind Franklin, James Watson, Francis Crick, and the Discovery of DNA’s Double Helix, by the scientist and historian Howard Markel. I reviewed the book on Amazon here (it is a bad habit I occasionally indulge in). Franklin was a remarkable scientist who, as the Wikimedia caption notes, contributed to understanding the structures of DNA, RNA, viruses, coal, and graphite. I came away from Markel’s book with the impression that Watson had seen the X-ray interferogram, and Franklin was unaware that he had. The work of Cobb and Comfort suggests that in fact Watson had not seen the X-ray let alone stolen it. That said, the end of Markel’s book is a long, long interview with Watson, and I thought that Watson, for whatever reason, came across as knowing that he had not been entirely honest.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ChatGPT on whether black is white</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/ChatGPT_on_whether.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ChatGPT on whether black is white" /><published>2023-04-24T14:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-04-24T14:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/ChatGPT_on_whether</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/ChatGPT_on_whether.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Callahan_alice0424_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot; Alice and the White Queen&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Alice and the White Queen, drawn by the author with the assistance of an AI (or perhaps it was the other way around).
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post by Paul Callahan is copied from a series of comments that were posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/uncommondead.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and which we thought were fascinating but off-task. The comments document a discussion between Mr. Callahan and &lt;strong&gt;ChatGPT&lt;/strong&gt; (version 3.5) regarding young-earth creationism and intelligent-design creationism. We deemed them interesting and reproduce them here with Mr. Callahan’s permission. (He says: Note that this was ChatGPT 3.5, not 4, which is the latest public version. I haven’t tried it on that. I don’t think there will be much of a difference in substance.) Matt Young copied and pasted from the comments section and claims responsibility for any errors of transcription.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paul Callahan&lt;/strong&gt; is a former academic computer scientist with about 25 years experience as a software engineer. He has a strong interest in evolution and emergent complexity, particularly cellular automata, and has contributed some new results about Conway’s Game of Life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Callahan writes,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;My intent here is not to play gotcha with ChatGPT 3.5. Large language models like this are a genuine breakthrough with many useful applications when used appropriately. I was curious how it would deal with the subject of creationism. I am mostly satisfied with its explanation of the scientific consensus on evolution. However, it was far too circumspect when it came to identifying creationism as a refuted belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played around to see how it would handle another false statement, which it had no problem identifying as false. I understand the distinction it's actually making. When I identify &quot;black is white&quot; as false, I am very unlikely to generate any controversy. By contrast, I will generate controversy when I identify as false &quot;the earth and its species were created in seven days as stated in Genesis.&quot; Yet both are refuted by empirical evidence. Conversely, both can be &quot;rescued&quot; by appealing to unfalsifiable beliefs. The only real distinction seems to be a constituency who will be offended. It's understandable that ChatGPT will try to be sensitive to people and their religious beliefs. So am I, usually. I only wish it was more forthcoming about the precise distinction.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Herewith, the discussion between Mr. Callahan and ChatGPT. Mr. Callahan’s questions are flush left, and those of ChatGPT are indented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhat on topic (yeah, it’s a stretch), I asked ChatGPT for its recollection of &lt;strong&gt;Uncommon Descent&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you know of a blog called Uncommon Descent?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Yes, Uncommon Descent is a blog that focuses on topics related to &lt;strong&gt;intelligent design&lt;/strong&gt; and is known for presenting arguments and viewpoints that support intelligent design as an alternative to evolutionary theory. The blog features posts written by various contributors who advocate for intelligent the, including some of the individuals mentioned earlier who are associated with the intelligent design movement. However, it's important to note that Uncommon Descent is not a peer-reviewed scientific publication, and its views are not widely accepted or considered scientifically valid by the mainstream scientific community. As with any source of information, it's important to critically evaluate the content and consider multiple perspectives, including those of the mainstream scientific community, when forming an understanding of complex scientific topics like intelligent design.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to dock it some points for referring to ID as a “scientific topic,” but that’s a large language model for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To avoid spamming further, here’s an &lt;a href=&quot;https://disq.us/url?url=https%3A%2F%2Fdocs.google.com%2Fdocument%2Fd%2F1rRkfPcdePP4PaM9Jx1KSLSi2BFxMBKriScd_tjJVNPA%2Fedit%3A1_hegEh5KzA7O69j0n4IDQPgVts&amp;amp;cuid=4707939&quot;&gt;edited transcript of my conversation with ChatGPT inspired by this topic&lt;/a&gt;. I found that while it is clear in identifying evolution as the scientific consensus, it is possible to get it to spout creationism and ID simply by asking it to write fictitious speeches to church groups. Anyone who wants to go deep in the weeds can evaluate how these compare to the writing on creationist blogs. You probably could automate this even with guardrails just by setting a context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JimboK&lt;/strong&gt; then asked, “I don’t have an account on ChatGPT, so could you ask “it” for its description of “&lt;strong&gt;Creation Science&lt;/strong&gt;”? Thanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an AI language model, I'd be happy to provide a description of &quot;Creation Science&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creation Science is a perspective or belief system that seeks to reconcile scientific and religious views of the origin of the universe, life, and humanity. It is often associated with certain branches of Christianity and holds that the account of creation as described in religious texts, such as the Bible, is a literal and accurate scientific explanation for the origin of the universe and life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creation Science typically posits that the Earth and universe are relatively young, often adhering to a literal interpretation of the Bible's account of creation, which suggests that the Earth is around 6,000 to 10,000 years old. It may reject or challenge scientific theories such as evolution, the Big Bang theory, and geological dating methods that conflict with literal interpretations of religious texts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advocates of Creation Science often argue for the scientific validity of their views through interpretations of scientific data and evidence that they believe supports a literal interpretation of religious texts. However, these views are not widely accepted by the mainstream scientific community, which generally regards evolution and the Big Bang theory as well-supported scientific theories based on extensive evidence from multiple fields of science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's important to note that Creation Science is considered by many to be a religious belief rather than a scientific theory, as it often relies heavily on faith-based interpretations of religious texts rather than empirical scientific methods. It has been a topic of debate and discussion among religious groups, educators, and scientists, and it continues to be a controversial and divisive issue in the intersection of science and religion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mike Elzinga&lt;/strong&gt; asked, “The description reminds me of Creation Science back in the 1970s through the 1990s. It doesn’t include Gitt’s “In the beginning was information,” nor its tension with ID.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does ChatGPT use databases or use Google in compiling its summary of a topic? I haven’t tried it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Callahan responded, “I’ll let ChatGPT field both of those questions for you. This is a little risky because I haven’t tried it. On the second question, though, it’s a large language model, which is a type of deep learning network that trains on enormous sets of written text (basically anything it could find on the internet as of 2021). It is a predictive model, so it predicts statistically that if someone writes a question “What is the capital of Pennsylvania?” The most likely thing to follow will be something about Harrisburg. It is kind of amazing that this works so well. People have been trying to do it for decades but there is finally the computational power in the cloud as well as the size of datasets to form a meaningful predictive model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 1&lt;/strong&gt;: The description reminds me of Creation Science back in the 1970s through the 1990s. It doesn’t include Gitt’s “In the beginning was information,” nor its tension with ID.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;You're correct. The description I provided is a general overview of Creation Science and does not encompass all the nuances and developments of the concept over time, including more recent perspectives such as those espoused by creationist and intelligent design (ID) proponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1970s through the 1990s, there were significant developments in the field of Creation Science, including the introduction of the concept of &quot;information&quot; as a key component in arguments against evolution. Proponents of Creation Science, including scholars like &lt;strong&gt;Werner Gitt&lt;/strong&gt;, argued that information, as evidenced in complex biological systems, cannot arise from natural processes and must be the result of an intelligent designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intelligent Design (ID) is a concept that gained prominence in the late 20th century and is often associated with Creation Science. ID proponents argue that certain features of the natural world, including biological systems, are best explained by an intelligent cause rather than naturalistic processes. ID proponents often argue for the existence of an intelligent designer without explicitly naming it as a religious concept, in an attempt to present it as a scientific theory. However, the scientific validity of ID has been widely debated, with many scientists and educators regarding it as a form of creationism dressed in scientific language rather than a genuine scientific theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's important to note that Creation Science, including its relationship with ID, is not universally accepted within the scientific community and is often viewed as a controversial topic. Many scientists, educators, and proponents of mainstream science reject Creation Science and ID as unscientific and not supported by empirical evidence. The scientific consensus is that evolution and the Big Bang theory, among other well-established scientific theories, provide the most comprehensive and widely accepted explanations for the origin and development of the universe and life on Earth.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I’ll note that it’s being far too diplomatic here but it can be asked the question in such way that it will be more definitive that the scientific consensus favors evolution.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 2&lt;/strong&gt;: Does ChatGPT use databases or use Google in compiling its summary of a topic?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an AI language model, I do not have direct access to external databases or the internet, including Google, to compile my responses. I do not have real-time access to up-to-date information beyond my knowledge cutoff date, which is September 2021. I generate responses based on the patterns and information learned during my training on a large corpus of text from the internet and other sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When providing information, I do not retrieve or reference specific sources, and my responses are generated based on patterns learned during training. I should not be considered as a primary source of authoritative or current information. Users should independently verify any information I provide with reliable sources, consult domain experts, or access up-to-date information from reputable sources for accurate and reliable information.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll add that ChatGPT has come under attack from the right, some of whom accuse it of being intentionally biased. It has guardrails against spouting hate or pseudoscience, so that does limit it a bit. Other than that, it has a pretty wide summary of what you will find as long as you do not limit yourself to Fox News and similar sources. It’s free for now (at least the more limited ChatGPT 3.5 release). I would recommend that anyone curious try it out for themselves: &lt;a href=&quot;https://chat.openai.com/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update. I had to add this: I thought this should be stated more forcefully: It’s important to note that Creation Science, including its relationship with ID, is not universally accepted within the scientific community and is often viewed as a controversial topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;You are correct. It is important to emphasize that Creation Science, including its relationship with Intelligent Design (ID), is not widely accepted within the scientific community and is often viewed as a controversial topic. The scientific consensus is that evolution, the Big Bang theory, and other established scientific theories provide the most comprehensive and widely accepted explanations for the origin and development of the universe and life on Earth, based on extensive evidence from multiple fields of science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's worth noting that the majority of the scientific community regards Creation Science and ID as unscientific, as they often rely on faith-based interpretations of religious texts rather than empirical scientific methods. These perspectives are not considered mainstream scientific theories, and their validity and scientific rigor have been widely debated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to approach topics related to science and religion with critical thinking, an understanding of the scientific method, and an appreciation for the consensus of the scientific community. When seeking information on controversial topics, it is crucial to consult reputable sources, including peer-reviewed scientific journals and established scientific institutions, to obtain accurate and reliable information.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After commenting that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barber_paradox&quot;&gt;barber paradox&lt;/a&gt; probably would not make the computer “spark out and self-destruct,” Mr. Callahan asked: I agree with what you [ChatGPT] say, but I find it too diplomatic. It as if you wrote: “The assertion ‘black is white’ is not universally accepted within the scientific community, which generally regards these colors as distinct.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an AI language model, I strive to provide balanced and factual information while avoiding taking a position or promoting any particular viewpoint. I aim to provide a neutral and objective perspective based on widely accepted knowledge and understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of Creation Science, it's important to acknowledge that it is not supported by mainstream scientific evidence and methodologies, and it is not universally accepted within the scientific community. However, as with any topic, it's important to approach discussions with respect for diverse perspectives and engage in open and respectful dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using neutral language and avoiding taking a position on controversial topics is in line with the ethical guidelines and policies that govern the use of AI models to ensure responsible and unbiased communication. It's important to understand that AI models like ChatGPT do not hold opinions, beliefs, or biases, but rather generate responses based on patterns learned from vast amounts of data.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will you take a position on the assertion, “Black is white”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an AI language model, I do not hold opinions or take positions on any statements, including the assertion &quot;Black is white.&quot; This statement is factually incorrect and goes against commonly accepted definitions of colors. In the context of color perception and scientific understanding of colors, black and white are considered distinct colors with specific characteristics and properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's important to note that as an AI language model, I generate responses based on patterns learned from vast amounts of data, and I strive to provide factual and accurate information. It's always important to rely on credible sources and established knowledge when seeking information or discussing statements or assertions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would argue that evolution is the only explanation for the diversity of life on earth that is well-supported by evidence, and that creation is at best an unfalsifiable belief that is entirely outside the scope of science. Thus, the assertions of “creation science” are just as factually incorrect as the assertion “black is white.” Note that the latter might also be supported by some unfalsifiable claims about human perception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's widely accepted within the scientific community that the theory of evolution is a well-supported scientific explanation for the diversity of life on Earth, based on a large body of evidence from various fields of science, including biology, geology, genetics, and more. Evolution is considered a foundational concept in modern biology and is widely taught and accepted in scientific education and research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, creationism, including the notion of &quot;creation science,&quot; is often considered a belief or philosophical position that is outside the scope of scientific inquiry, as it typically involves religious or metaphysical perspectives that are not based on empirical evidence or subject to scientific testing and falsification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's important to note that science is a self-correcting process that relies on evidence, experimentation, and peer review to establish and refine our understanding of the natural world. While individuals are entitled to their personal beliefs, it's crucial to distinguish between scientific knowledge, which is based on empirical evidence and subject to rigorous testing and verification, and other forms of belief or opinion that may not meet the criteria of scientific inquiry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an AI language model, I do not hold personal opinions, but I aim to provide information that is based on widely accepted scientific knowledge and understanding. It's always important to rely on credible sources and established scientific consensus when discussing scientific topics. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am going to claim that indeed “black is white.” My belief is that we only know about these things through human perception. Human perception is provably faulty. Thus, it may be that every time we perceived distinct colors or read the distinction through other means (photodetectors) our interpretation was faulty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The assertion that &quot;black is white&quot; would likely be considered a non-factual statement based on our current understanding of color perception and the properties of black and white as distinct colors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it's true that human perception, including color perception, is subjective and can be influenced by various factors such as lighting conditions, individual differences in perception, and other variables, it does not necessarily imply that black and white are not distinct colors in the conventional sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the field of science, including the study of color perception, there are established principles, theories, and empirical evidence that guide our understanding of how color works in the natural world. These principles are based on extensive research, experimentation, and scientific consensus, and provide a reliable framework for understanding the physical properties of colors, including black and white.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's important to distinguish between subjective beliefs or interpretations and established scientific knowledge when discussing factual statements. While perceptions and interpretations can vary among individuals, the scientific method and empirical evidence provide a rigorous and reliable approach for understanding the natural world to the best of our current knowledge.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why don’t you respect my diverse perspective that black is in fact white?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an AI language model, I do not have personal beliefs, opinions, or perspectives. My responses are generated based on patterns learned from a large corpus of text data, and I strive to provide factual and evidence-based information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statement that &quot;black is white&quot; goes against established scientific knowledge and our understanding of color perception. It is not supported by empirical evidence, principles of physics, or established scientific theories. While diverse perspectives and opinions are important, it is also essential to differentiate between subjective beliefs and established factual information based on scientific evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an AI language model, my responses are guided by a commitment to accuracy, reliability, and adherence to established knowledge. I aim to provide information that is based on sound scientific principles and widely accepted facts.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that you are given [sic] more respect to creationism as “diverse perspective” than you give to my claim above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an AI language model, I strive to provide impartial and unbiased responses. However, it is important to note that while diverse perspectives are valued, they are not all equal in terms of their scientific validity or evidence-based support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The assertion that &quot;black is white&quot; is not supported by established scientific knowledge and is contrary to our understanding of color perception, physics, and empirical evidence. It would be misleading to equate it with a diverse perspective on a topic that is based on credible scientific evidence, such as the theory of evolution, which is supported by extensive scientific research and evidence from various fields of science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to distinguish between subjective beliefs or opinions and scientifically supported facts when discussing scientific topics. While diverse perspectives and opinions are important, scientific validity is determined by empirical evidence, peer-reviewed research, and the consensus of the scientific community. As an AI language model, my responses are guided by established knowledge and evidence-based information.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, but creationism is not based on credible scientific evidence. Yet you treat it deferentially with phrases such as “not widely accepted” as opposed to “factually wrong.” I would use the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I understand your perspective. It is important to note that as an AI language model, I do not hold personal opinions or beliefs. My responses are generated based on patterns learned from a large corpus of text data and are intended to be informative and unbiased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding the topic of creationism, while it is a belief held by some individuals, it is not widely accepted within the scientific community as a credible scientific explanation for the diversity of life on Earth. The scientific consensus overwhelmingly supports the theory of evolution as the most well-supported and evidence-based explanation for the diversity of life on our planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to use accurate and precise language when discussing scientific topics. While &quot;not widely accepted&quot; may be a diplomatic way to describe the lack of scientific support for creationism, it is indeed a fact that creationism is not supported by credible scientific evidence and is considered by many scientists and researchers as incompatible with established scientific knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to critically evaluate and differentiate between scientific facts, evidence-based theories, and subjective beliefs or opinions when discussing scientific topics. This helps to ensure accuracy and clarity in communication and promotes a better understanding of scientific concepts. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would say that creationism is factually wrong and stands in contradiction of a preponderance of evidence and scientific analysis carried out for over 150 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an AI language model, I do not hold personal opinions or beliefs. However, it is important to note that creationism, as a belief that rejects or contradicts established scientific theories such as evolution, is not supported by credible scientific evidence and is not widely accepted within the scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory of evolution, supported by a vast body of scientific evidence from diverse fields such as biology, genetics, geology, and comparative anatomy, is considered the most well-supported scientific explanation for the diversity of life on Earth. It is widely accepted by the scientific community and has been extensively researched, analyzed, and refined over more than 150 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While individuals may hold personal beliefs or opinions that differ from scientific consensus, it is important to recognize that scientific theories are based on empirical evidence, rigorous testing, and peer-reviewed research. In the context of science, a theory represents the best available explanation based on the available evidence and is subject to revision or abandonment in light of new evidence. As such, it is scientifically accurate to state that creationism is not supported by credible scientific evidence and contradicts the well-established scientific theory of evolution.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it accurate to call creationism factually wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an AI language model, I do not hold personal opinions or beliefs, and I strive to provide information based on credible sources and established scientific consensus. The term &quot;factually wrong&quot; is subjective and can be seen as a value judgment. In the context of scientific consensus, creationism, as a belief that rejects or contradicts established scientific theories such as evolution, is not supported by credible scientific evidence and is not widely accepted within the scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the overwhelming body of scientific evidence, the theory of evolution is considered the most well-supported scientific explanation for the diversity of life on Earth. It is widely accepted by the scientific community and has been extensively researched, analyzed, and refined over more than 150 years. In this scientific context, creationism, which proposes supernatural or religious explanations for the origin and diversity of life, is not considered scientifically valid or supported by credible evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's important to recognize that science is a self-correcting process based on empirical evidence, rigorous testing, and peer-reviewed research. Scientific theories are subject to revision or abandonment in light of new evidence. However, the established scientific consensus based on the preponderance of evidence currently supports the theory of evolution as the most scientifically accurate explanation for the diversity of life on Earth.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it accurate to call the assertion “black is white” factually wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, it would be accurate to call the assertion &quot;black is white&quot; factually wrong based on established definitions and understanding of colors within the framework of human perception and scientific knowledge. In the standard understanding of colors, black and white are considered distinct and opposite, with black being the absence of light or color, and white being the presence of all colors or a combination of all colors of light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While human perception can have limitations and individual interpretations may vary, within the established scientific understanding of colors, the assertion &quot;black is white&quot; would be considered factually incorrect. It would go against established definitions, principles of physics, and scientific knowledge related to colors, light, and human perception.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if I told you I see that as a value judgment? For example, it is based on an overoptimistic view of human perception, and it also suggests a preference for falsifiable claims and disregards my belief that black really is white and we have simply failed to notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an AI language model, I do not have personal beliefs or preferences. However, I can provide an objective response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The assertion &quot;black is white&quot; is not supported by established definitions, principles of physics, and scientific knowledge related to colors, light, and human perception. It would be considered factually incorrect based on our current understanding of these concepts. Scientific understanding is based on empirical evidence, testable hypotheses, and the scientific method, which involves the rigorous evaluation of claims using evidence, logic, and critical thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While individuals may have personal beliefs or perspectives, it is important to note that in the realm of science, falsifiable claims, evidence-based reasoning, and established principles are the basis for our understanding of the natural world. Claims that lack credible evidence or go against established scientific knowledge are generally not considered scientifically valid. It is important to distinguish between personal beliefs and scientific facts when discussing matters related to science and evidence-based reasoning.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Callahan</name></author><summary type="html">Alice and the White Queen, drawn by the author with the assistance of an AI (or perhaps it was the other way around). This post by Paul Callahan is copied from a series of comments that were posted here and which we thought were fascinating but off-task. The comments document a discussion between Mr. Callahan and ChatGPT (version 3.5) regarding young-earth creationism and intelligent-design creationism. We deemed them interesting and reproduce them here with Mr. Callahan’s permission. (He says: Note that this was ChatGPT 3.5, not 4, which is the latest public version. I haven’t tried it on that. I don’t think there will be much of a difference in substance.) Matt Young copied and pasted from the comments section and claims responsibility for any errors of transcription. Paul Callahan is a former academic computer scientist with about 25 years experience as a software engineer. He has a strong interest in evolution and emergent complexity, particularly cellular automata, and has contributed some new results about Conway’s Game of Life. Mr. Callahan writes, My intent here is not to play gotcha with ChatGPT 3.5. Large language models like this are a genuine breakthrough with many useful applications when used appropriately. I was curious how it would deal with the subject of creationism. I am mostly satisfied with its explanation of the scientific consensus on evolution. However, it was far too circumspect when it came to identifying creationism as a refuted belief. I played around to see how it would handle another false statement, which it had no problem identifying as false. I understand the distinction it's actually making. When I identify &quot;black is white&quot; as false, I am very unlikely to generate any controversy. By contrast, I will generate controversy when I identify as false &quot;the earth and its species were created in seven days as stated in Genesis.&quot; Yet both are refuted by empirical evidence. Conversely, both can be &quot;rescued&quot; by appealing to unfalsifiable beliefs. The only real distinction seems to be a constituency who will be offended. It's understandable that ChatGPT will try to be sensitive to people and their religious beliefs. So am I, usually. I only wish it was more forthcoming about the precise distinction. Herewith, the discussion between Mr. Callahan and ChatGPT. Mr. Callahan’s questions are flush left, and those of ChatGPT are indented. Somewhat on topic (yeah, it’s a stretch), I asked ChatGPT for its recollection of Uncommon Descent: Do you know of a blog called Uncommon Descent? Yes, Uncommon Descent is a blog that focuses on topics related to intelligent design and is known for presenting arguments and viewpoints that support intelligent design as an alternative to evolutionary theory. The blog features posts written by various contributors who advocate for intelligent the, including some of the individuals mentioned earlier who are associated with the intelligent design movement. However, it's important to note that Uncommon Descent is not a peer-reviewed scientific publication, and its views are not widely accepted or considered scientifically valid by the mainstream scientific community. As with any source of information, it's important to critically evaluate the content and consider multiple perspectives, including those of the mainstream scientific community, when forming an understanding of complex scientific topics like intelligent design. I have to dock it some points for referring to ID as a “scientific topic,” but that’s a large language model for you.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Buteo jamaicensis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/Buteo-jamaicensis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buteo jamaicensis" /><published>2023-04-24T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-04-24T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/Buteo-jamaicensis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/Buteo-jamaicensis.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;David Young&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/David_MG_0635_Crop_Hawk_Rabbit_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Red-tailed hawk with rabbit&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Red-tailed_Hawk/overview&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Buteo jamaicensis&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; red-tailed hawk enjoying a rabbit dinner, possibly &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cottontail_rabbit&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Sylvilagus audubonii&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; desert cottontail. Boulder, Colorado, April, 2023. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/06/Buteo-jamaicensis.html&quot;&gt;hawks' nest&lt;/a&gt; we were following several years ago has disappeared, but we are seeing hawks more often in residential areas within the city.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by David Young. Buteo jamaicensis &amp;ndash; red-tailed hawk enjoying a rabbit dinner, possibly Sylvilagus audubonii &amp;ndash; desert cottontail. Boulder, Colorado, April, 2023. The hawks' nest we were following several years ago has disappeared, but we are seeing hawks more often in residential areas within the city.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Uncommon Descent is dead (or maybe undead)</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/uncommondead.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Uncommon Descent is dead (or maybe undead)" /><published>2023-04-18T18:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-04-18T18:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/uncommondead</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/uncommondead.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/undead.png&quot; alt=&quot;part of UD logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Uncommon Descent sinks slowly in the west (Fair Use claimed)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ID-advocacy blog Uncommon Descent is dead (or maybe undead).  The blog was founded by 
William Dembski in April, 2005, the year of the Dover School Board case.  It became a central 
site for posts arguing for Intelligent Design, with the comment sections having arguments 
back and forth.  Many of the posts were by the ever-astonishing Denyse O’Leary, who took on this job, writing as “News”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2008 Dembski withdrew from active participation in the site; its administration was
set up as a nonprofit organization. The Denver-area right-wing lawyer Barry Arrington 
took over administration of the site, ruling with an iron hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last few weeks UD had frequently been down.  This seems to be connected to what finally happened on April 12.  William Dembski posted an announcement that the site had been “archived” by the 
Discovery Institute and would be available in that form.  The front page layout changed, 
with links to posts and their comments but no way for anyone to post further comments.  Dembski’s post was a farewell to the site, in which he gave an account of its history and thanked 
the people who helped with it.  No further posts are expected to appear. 
The blog had died, and was only available in that form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or was it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;afterglow&quot;&gt;Afterglow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a few days after, one could access a version of UD that was in its original form, and 
did not include Dembski’s farewell post.  Commenters continued to argue in the threads 
for recent posts, but these comments were not included in the archived versions.  No new 
posts appeared on that undead form.  I am told that there were two links in the DNS record 
for UD, corresponding to different forms of the URL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the undead version had not long to go.  It seems now to have vanished, and its recent 
comments with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-favorite-moments&quot;&gt;My favorite moments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many fond memories I have of UD.  I’ll just mention two (you are encouraged to 
tell us yours, in the comments below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;indefensible&quot;&gt;Indefensible&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first was a post by the late, lamented Gil Dodgen &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/at-some-point-the-obvious-becomes-transparently-obvious-or-recognizing-the-forrest-with-alls-its-barbs-through-the-trees/&quot;&gt;(here)&lt;/a&gt; in 2011.  Forgetting the main meaning of the word “indefensible”, he declared that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At UD we have many brilliant ID apologists, and they continue to mount what I perceive as increasingly indefensible assaults on the creative powers of the Darwinian mechanism of random errors filtered by natural selection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I think he meant by “indefensible” that no one could mount a defense against the “assaults”).  Anyway, I &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2011/06/total-agreement.html&quot;&gt;rushed to agree&lt;/a&gt; here at PT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-great-purge-of-2012&quot;&gt;The Great Purge of 2012&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My second favorite UD moment was Barry Arrington carrying out &lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/why-is-barry-arringtonstifling-dissent-at-ud/&quot;&gt;the Great Purge of 2012&lt;/a&gt;.  Obviously 
irritated by having so many cogent opponents of ID in the comment section, he declared that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The issue, then, is not whether persons who disagree with us on the facts and logic will be allowed to debate on this site. Anyone who disagrees about the facts and logic is free to come here at any time. But if you come on here and say, essentially, that facts and logic do not matter, then we have no use for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He declared that commenters were denying basic logical principles such as the Law of Non-Contradiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For that reason, I am today announcing a new moderation policy at UD. At any time the moderator reserves the right to ask the following question to any person who would comment or continue to comment on this site: “Can the moon exist and not exist at the same time and in the same formal relation?” The answer to this question is either “yes” or “no.” If the person gives any answer other than the single word “no,” he or she will immediately be deemed not worth arguing with and therefore banned from this site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course lots of people thought immediately of the results of quantum mechanics, in which 
an object is actually a wave, and not necessarily located in one precise place.  They said “Well, 
actually, …” and were immediately banned.  Pro-evolution commenters were banned almost 
en masse.  Even some creationist commenters reacted that way … and they were banned too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most patient, temperate, polite, incisive, and logical pro-evolution commenters at UD was 
Elizabeth Liddle, a neuroscientist at the University of Nottingham in England.  She 
immediately made available her own blog &lt;a href=&quot;theskepticalzone.com/wp/&quot;&gt;The Skeptical Zone&lt;/a&gt; as 
a home for discussion by the banned and the unbanned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I later made a post about this hilarious purge (in 2015 &lt;a href=&quot;http://theskepticalzone.com/wp/was-denial-of-the-laws-of-thought-a-myth/&quot;&gt;at The Skeptical Zone&lt;/a&gt;) asking whether 
anyone could actually point out any comments at UD where pro-evolution commenters rejected laws of logic.  No 
one could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arrington must have realized that without any pro-evolution commentators the site would 
die of lack of interest, because he allowed some to remain after that, without 
getting too insistent on the existence of the moon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;failures-to-stay-on-topic&quot;&gt;Failures to stay on-topic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish I could say that most of the discussion at UD was about evolution 
and ID.  But the pro-ID and/or creationist participants seemed to feel 
that the basic issue was the existence of God, and their basic task was 
to refute atheism.  So much space was devoted to where the Universe 
came from, whether the laws of physics were fine-tuned for life, and 
whether there was any basis for morality if there was not a God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result was an awful lot of off-topic posts and comments.  If the 
Universe is the result of fine-tuned laws, that makes it easier, 
not harder, to imagine that biological evolution occurred.  And the 
origin of the Universe or of morality has basically nothing to do 
with whether evolution occurred or whether Design Intervention must 
have occurred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-big-tent&quot;&gt;The Big Tent&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Intelligent Design movement tries to maintain a “big tent”, 
and make its arguments attractive to people who reject 
Young-Earth Creationism.  They are offended by the thought that 
people think that they are YECs.  But at the same time they 
needed the political and financial backing of YEC folks. This 
creates dilemmas for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, many of the most active commenters at UD seemed to 
be YECs. This led to some commenters arguing that there 
was overwhelming evidence against “evolution”, while others 
were angry at us for even suggesting that ID advocates 
rejected evolution.  These folks never seemed to notice one 
another, let alone debate each other.  So much for deep thinking 
about evolutionary theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-were-your-favorite-moments&quot;&gt;What were your favorite moments?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But enough from me.  For those who paid attention to UD, what were 
your favorite moments?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Uncommon Descent sinks slowly in the west (Fair Use claimed) The ID-advocacy blog Uncommon Descent is dead (or maybe undead). The blog was founded by William Dembski in April, 2005, the year of the Dover School Board case. It became a central site for posts arguing for Intelligent Design, with the comment sections having arguments back and forth. Many of the posts were by the ever-astonishing Denyse O’Leary, who took on this job, writing as “News”. In 2008 Dembski withdrew from active participation in the site; its administration was set up as a nonprofit organization. The Denver-area right-wing lawyer Barry Arrington took over administration of the site, ruling with an iron hand. In the last few weeks UD had frequently been down. This seems to be connected to what finally happened on April 12. William Dembski posted an announcement that the site had been “archived” by the Discovery Institute and would be available in that form. The front page layout changed, with links to posts and their comments but no way for anyone to post further comments. Dembski’s post was a farewell to the site, in which he gave an account of its history and thanked the people who helped with it. No further posts are expected to appear. The blog had died, and was only available in that form. Or was it?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Vulpes macrotis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/Vulpes-macrotis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vulpes macrotis" /><published>2023-04-10T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-04-10T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/Vulpes-macrotis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/Vulpes-macrotis.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;James Rice&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Rice Vulpes macrotis.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kit fox&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kit_fox&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Vulpes macrotis&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; kit fox. Mr. Rice writes, &quot;This kit fox was photographed shortly after sunset along a dirt track in central Nevada.  Kit foxes are the smallest North American fox, and favor arid climates. I've had a couple of wonderful encounters with kit foxes, and they seem to be far more curious than afraid; however, it is likely that in the places I've seen them, they've never encountered a human before.&quot; He notes that they are about half the size of a coyote.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by James Rice. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Vulpes macrotis &amp;ndash; kit fox. Mr. Rice writes, &quot;This kit fox was photographed shortly after sunset along a dirt track in central Nevada. Kit foxes are the smallest North American fox, and favor arid climates. I've had a couple of wonderful encounters with kit foxes, and they seem to be far more curious than afraid; however, it is likely that in the places I've seen them, they've never encountered a human before.&quot; He notes that they are about half the size of a coyote.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stromatolitic chert</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/03/stromatolitic-chert.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stromatolitic chert" /><published>2023-03-27T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-03-27T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/03/stromatolitic-chert</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/03/stromatolitic-chert.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;James Kocher&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Kocher_Gunflint_Chert_Translucent_Slice.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Slice of Gunflint Chert&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Digitate &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stromatolite&quot;&gt;stromatolites&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gunflint_chert&quot;&gt;Gunflint formation&lt;/a&gt; (Lower Algal Member), Nolalu, Ontario. Mr. Kocher writes, &quot;Specimen is a vertical section cut on lapidary saw (i.e., perpendicular to bedding). Thin piece (1-2 mm thick) is translucent &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chert&quot;&gt;chert&lt;/a&gt; and shows preserved columnar algal colonies, hematite oolites, and algal pellets (peloids). Specimen is ~4 cm wide. Variously classified as &lt;i&gt;Collenia undosa&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;Stratifera biwabikensis&lt;/i&gt;, among others. Age ~ 1.8 Ga; Mesoproterozoic.&quot; Mr. Kocher explains further, &quot;'Lower Algal Member' is a designation given to a subset of strata within the Gunflint Formation. The Gunflint Formation has been divided up stratigraphically into at least 5 subsets of strata, i.e., 'Members.'&quot; Perhaps it goes without saying, but the specimen is flat, despite the illusion of hills and valleys.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by James Kocher. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Digitate stromatolites in the Gunflint formation (Lower Algal Member), Nolalu, Ontario. Mr. Kocher writes, &quot;Specimen is a vertical section cut on lapidary saw (i.e., perpendicular to bedding). Thin piece (1-2 mm thick) is translucent chert and shows preserved columnar algal colonies, hematite oolites, and algal pellets (peloids). Specimen is ~4 cm wide. Variously classified as Collenia undosa, Stratifera biwabikensis, among others. Age ~ 1.8 Ga; Mesoproterozoic.&quot; Mr. Kocher explains further, &quot;'Lower Algal Member' is a designation given to a subset of strata within the Gunflint Formation. The Gunflint Formation has been divided up stratigraphically into at least 5 subsets of strata, i.e., 'Members.'&quot; Perhaps it goes without saying, but the specimen is flat, despite the illusion of hills and valleys.</summary></entry></feed>