<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-10-28T16:03:39-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Pheucticus melanocephalus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/Pheucticus-melanocephalus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pheucticus melanocephalus" /><published>2020-10-26T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-26T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/Pheucticus-melanocephalus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/Pheucticus-melanocephalus.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Mark Lee&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Lee_BlackheadedGrosbeak.JPEG&quot; alt=&quot;Grosbeak&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Black-headed_Grosbeak/id&quot;&gt;Pheucticus melanocephalus&lt;/a&gt;, black-headed grosbeak, Palo Duro Canyon State Park, Texas.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Mark Lee. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Pheucticus melanocephalus, black-headed grosbeak, Palo Duro Canyon State Park, Texas.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Does approach to higher probability block natural selection?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/does-approach-toward-higher-probability.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does approach to higher probability block natural selection?" /><published>2020-10-25T00:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-25T00:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/does-approach-toward-higher-probability</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/does-approach-toward-higher-probability.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/gf.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his video, which we have discussed &lt;em&gt;ad nauseam&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/are-evolutionary-biologists-ignoring-science.html&quot;&gt;our
extremely long recent thread&lt;/a&gt; Mark Champneys claims that
scientists are ignoring science when they claim that natural selection can
result in functional information increasing in the genome.  In the subsequent
discussion, Champneys insisted that there was a generalized form of the Second
Law which made such increase impossible, insisted that it applied not just to
isolated systems but to non-isolated populations of organisms, and that it
did prevent natural selection from achieving long-term improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In this post, I hope to show a very simple example, and to get away from
the issue of whether this has anything to do with the Second Law.  If we
can focus on discussing whether the approach of a stochastic process to its
equilibrium prevents natural selection from having effect, maybe we
can avoid having 1,600-plus comments and actually discuss the matter at hand.
&lt;p&gt;
Let's try for that focus and relevance.  Surely someone who wants scientists
to actually grapple with the science must agree with that goal.  Right?  Let's
see ...
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;The example&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My simple example will be a large population of organisms, haploid ones, for
simplicity.  We will follow 100 sites in their DNA.  At each site there are
four possible bases, A, C, G and T.  There will be a simple mutational
process which changes symmetrically among the four possible bases
(technically, a Jukes-Cantor model of change).  Each base has the same
probability of mutating, and when it mutates it changes to one of the other
three bases, chosen at random.  We'll take the probability of mutation to be
0.0001 per base per generation, a fairly high value.
&lt;o&gt;
No matter what the population of sequences is, as mutations accumulate,
the population proceeds towards its equilibrium.  Each site becomes
equally likely to have all four bases, and this happens independently
at all 100 sites.  The equilibrium has all 4^(100) possible sequences,
equally frequent.  If we were to follow only how many copies of one of the
four bases, say C, the sequence has, each site has a 25% chance of having a
C.  So on average there will be 25 Cs.  It will be like coin tosses of a
biased coin, with 100 tosses, on average 25% of which are Heads.  This is a
binomial distribution.  In the figure above, it is the orange histogram,
which varies around 25.  If having lots of Cs were somehow desirable, with
only mutation, the sequences are stuck in the vicinity of 25, forever.
&lt;p&gt;
The process of change of these sequences is a random process (a stochastic
process), and it has a single equilibrium distribution toward which it
proceeds.  In technical terminology, this is an ergodic process.
So far things look as if they follow Mark Champneys' rules.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;With natural selection&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But notice what is left out -- natural selection.  So let's consider
another case, which puts it in.  Suppose that at a site, having a C
improves the fitness of the individual by 0.005, which is one part
in 200, or 0.5%.  And suppose that this happens at all the sites.
For simplicity we'll suppose that the higher fitness is always
for C, with all three other bases having the equal, slightly lower fitness.
The fitnesses at the different sites combine by multiplying.  So
The fitness of a 100-base genotype is 1.005, raised to the power
of the number of Cs in those sites.
&lt;p&gt;
It will not be a big surprise that Cs increase at each of the
sites.  I'll leave out the algebra, but can supply it on request.
Starting out with a population gene frequency of 0.25 at all 100
sites, the gene frequencies are always the same at all of the sites,
but they rise gradually.  After about 5,000 generations. they
rise almost to 1, settling in to an equilibrium gene frequency
of 0.9801332.  They don't get all the way to 1, because mutation
has continued, and Cs keep mutating away from C as well as being
selected towards it.
&lt;p&gt;
In the figure, the result is the green histogram.  There are an
average of 98.01332 Cs in these 100 sites.  The number varies around that
from genome to genome, just as tosses of 100 coins would that have a Heads
probability of 0.9801332.  It is possible to show that the average
fitness of genomes in that equilibrium distribution is 1.630472.
Natural selection shifts the equilibrium distribution dramatically
to the right.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Mark Champneys is right (and also wrong)&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yes, in both of these cases the random process results in an equilibrium
distribution, toward which the process moves.  But note -- &lt;em&gt;they
aren't the same distribution in the two cases.&lt;/em&gt;  Natural
selection has a dramatic effect on what the equilibrium
distribution is.  So the movement towards an equilibrium does
not mean that natural selection is ineffective.
&lt;p&gt;
I will be interested in seeing whether Mark Champneys agrees with
this.  His video gives the distinct impression that
both cases are expected to have the same equilibrium distribution,
with natural selection therefore being ineffective.  That would
seem to require some changes in the video, and some acknowledgement
that maybe evolutionary biologists are not quite as ignorant
of science as Mark Champneys said they were.


&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/o&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">In his video, which we have discussed ad nauseam in our extremely long recent thread Mark Champneys claims that scientists are ignoring science when they claim that natural selection can result in functional information increasing in the genome. In the subsequent discussion, Champneys insisted that there was a generalized form of the Second Law which made such increase impossible, insisted that it applied not just to isolated systems but to non-isolated populations of organisms, and that it did prevent natural selection from achieving long-term improvement. In this post, I hope to show a very simple example, and to get away from the issue of whether this has anything to do with the Second Law. If we can focus on discussing whether the approach of a stochastic process to its equilibrium prevents natural selection from having effect, maybe we can avoid having 1,600-plus comments and actually discuss the matter at hand. Let's try for that focus and relevance. Surely someone who wants scientists to actually grapple with the science must agree with that goal. Right? Let's see ...</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gold of the gaps</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/gold-of-the-gaps.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gold of the gaps" /><published>2020-10-16T09:43:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-16T09:43:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/gold-of-the-gaps</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/gold-of-the-gaps.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2020/10/does-gold-have-a-purpose-science-hints-at-answers/&quot;&gt;Does gold have a purpose?&lt;/a&gt; asks an unnamed author in &lt;em&gt;Evolution News &amp;amp; Science Today&lt;/em&gt;. The author goes on to observe that there is more gold on earth than astrophysicists can account for and also that gold has risen to the surface of the earth faster than might be expected. They go on to note the “availability of many essential elements at the surface of the earth …” and also discuss the use of gold in medicine. They are somewhat breathless at the discovery that the body can metabolize gold:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Gold nanoparticles, which are &lt;strong&gt;supposed to be stable&lt;/strong&gt; in biological environments, &lt;strong&gt;can be degraded inside cells&lt;/strong&gt;, [boldface in original]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;even though, as they note, gold salts have been used for decades in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At any rate, the article stresses the “mystery of biological gold” and claims several hints why gold may have a purpose: its abundance and seemingly unlikely transport to the surface of the earth, the ability of cells to “metabolize” [sic] gold, the fact that gold persists in the body, and the usefulness of gold for therapeutics. The conclusion of the article is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since ID advocates are better equipped to think outside the box than are the paradigm-locked materialist scientists, they are more free to consider a positive answer — showing once again that intelligent design is not a “science stopper” but a fruitful way to pursue interesting questions. If the answer is “Yes, gold has a purpose,” the applications could be profound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Au boy! The author seems a little Au-struck by what seem to me relatively unrelated scientific discoveries and is trying Au-fully hard to weave them together into a fine-tuning argument. Here is my translation of the conclusion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since intelligent-design creationists are desperately searching for “hints” of design, they are more likely than empirically based scientists to come up with a positive answer — showing once again that intelligent-design creationists can pretend that any unanticipated scientific discovery leads to “interesting questions.” If the answer is, “Yes, gold has a purpose,” no practical applications will result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, the answer to the question is, “Yes, gold, like anything else, has whatever purposes we assign to it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Glenn Branch, who apparently reads Evolution News, so I generally do not have to.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Does gold have a purpose? asks an unnamed author in Evolution News &amp;amp; Science Today. The author goes on to observe that there is more gold on earth than astrophysicists can account for and also that gold has risen to the surface of the earth faster than might be expected. They go on to note the “availability of many essential elements at the surface of the earth …” and also discuss the use of gold in medicine. They are somewhat breathless at the discovery that the body can metabolize gold: Gold nanoparticles, which are supposed to be stable in biological environments, can be degraded inside cells, [boldface in original] even though, as they note, gold salts have been used for decades in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. At any rate, the article stresses the “mystery of biological gold” and claims several hints why gold may have a purpose: its abundance and seemingly unlikely transport to the surface of the earth, the ability of cells to “metabolize” [sic] gold, the fact that gold persists in the body, and the usefulness of gold for therapeutics. The conclusion of the article is Since ID advocates are better equipped to think outside the box than are the paradigm-locked materialist scientists, they are more free to consider a positive answer — showing once again that intelligent design is not a “science stopper” but a fruitful way to pursue interesting questions. If the answer is “Yes, gold has a purpose,” the applications could be profound. Au boy! The author seems a little Au-struck by what seem to me relatively unrelated scientific discoveries and is trying Au-fully hard to weave them together into a fine-tuning argument. Here is my translation of the conclusion: Since intelligent-design creationists are desperately searching for “hints” of design, they are more likely than empirically based scientists to come up with a positive answer — showing once again that intelligent-design creationists can pretend that any unanticipated scientific discovery leads to “interesting questions.” If the answer is, “Yes, gold has a purpose,” no practical applications will result. Actually, the answer to the question is, “Yes, gold, like anything else, has whatever purposes we assign to it.” Thanks to Glenn Branch, who apparently reads Evolution News, so I generally do not have to.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Platalea ajaja L.</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/Platalea-ajaja.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Platalea ajaja L." /><published>2020-10-12T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-12T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/Platalea-ajaja</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/Platalea-ajaja.html">&lt;p&gt;Roseate spoonbill, by &lt;strong&gt;C. Joseph Long&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Long_roseate_spoonbill.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Roseate spoonbill&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roseate_spoonbill&quot;&gt;Platalea ajaja L.&lt;/a&gt;, roseate spoonbill, with young. The photographer writes, &quot;This shot was taken at the Alligator Farm in St. Augustine, Florida.  This is a popular place (among the birds, as well as humans) because, while nestlings that fall to the surface are lost, the nests are safe from such predators as raccoons, bobcats, and snakes due to the inaccessibility of the trees’ bases.  The color is due, as in flamingos, to carotenoids in the diet.  According to Wikipedia, the roseate’s closest relative is the yellow-billed spoonbill, which is found in southeast Australia.  They do get around.&quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Roseate spoonbill, by C. Joseph Long. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Platalea ajaja L., roseate spoonbill, with young. The photographer writes, &quot;This shot was taken at the Alligator Farm in St. Augustine, Florida. This is a popular place (among the birds, as well as humans) because, while nestlings that fall to the surface are lost, the nests are safe from such predators as raccoons, bobcats, and snakes due to the inaccessibility of the trees’ bases. The color is due, as in flamingos, to carotenoids in the diet. According to Wikipedia, the roseate’s closest relative is the yellow-billed spoonbill, which is found in southeast Australia. They do get around.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Protein chimeras are evidence against ID claims!</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/protein-chimeras.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Protein chimeras are evidence against ID claims!" /><published>2020-10-11T12:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-11T12:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/protein-chimeras</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/protein-chimeras.html">&lt;p&gt;Where do novel functional proteins come from? It has become something of a staple of the ID-creationism movement that proteins with novel functions and structures are practically impossible to evolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? In part because functional protein sequences, that is, protein sequences &lt;em&gt;with functions that are useful to living organisms&lt;/em&gt; (such as protecting DNA from damage or promoting essential chemical reactions), are supposedly hyper-astronomically rare among all &lt;em&gt;possible&lt;/em&gt; protein sequences. So rare, ID-creationists argue, that even with unrealistically huge population sizes and rates of mutation, not a single functional protein sequence could be expected to evolve in the entire history of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The intended message is, of course, that since we know of millions of functional protein sequences within the diversity of life on Earth, and since supposedly none of them could have evolved, Intelligent Design becomes the only other plausible explanation for why they exist. And so, you know, evolution must be false and there must be an Intelligent Designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main champions of this claim is ID-creationist and researcher Douglas Axe, who is one among few ID-creationists with actual qualifications in biochemistry. Back in 2004 he &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2004.06.058&quot;&gt;published a paper&lt;/a&gt; in the journal Molecular Biology and Evolution detailing some experiments he did on a protein enzyme 150 amino acids in length. In this paper he concludes that functional protein enzyme sequences of a similar size (150 amino acids) are so rare among all possible proteins, that they are found at the astonishingly low frequency of approximately 1 in 10&lt;sup&gt;77&lt;/sup&gt;. This number is frequently cited in the ID literature, ranging from Stephen Meyer’s book &lt;em&gt;Darwin’s Doubt&lt;/em&gt;, through &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2016/10/imagine_60_mill/&quot;&gt;being bandied about&lt;/a&gt; on the Discovery Institute’s pro-ID blog Evolution News &amp;amp; Science Today, to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519320302071?via%3Dihub&quot;&gt;recent pro-ID paper&lt;/a&gt; published in the Journal of Theoretical Biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now 1 in 10&lt;sup&gt;77&lt;/sup&gt; is certainly a very low frequency, and all the way back in January of 2007, Panda’s Thumb contributor Arthur Hunt wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2007/01/92-second-st-fa.html&quot;&gt;a post detailing good reasons&lt;/a&gt; why Axe’s work is incapable of supporting this 10&lt;sup&gt;-77&lt;/sup&gt; frequency. And while I will not reiterate those reasons here, in a future post I intend to revisit some of the conclusions ID-creationists draw from Axe’s work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather, given that Axe’s work is once again being cited and is doing the rounds in ID-creationist circles, I thought this would be as good a time as any to visit some work in experimental molecular biology that massively contradicts Axe’s number. And to not beat around the bush too much, we’re talking &lt;em&gt;a 72 order-of-magnitude discrepancy&lt;/em&gt; between Axe’s frequency of 1 in 10&lt;sup&gt;77&lt;/sup&gt; and what other experiments in probing protein sequence space reveal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will give an account of experiments done to probe a particular process of novel protein evolution, called gene fusion, which turned out to be able to find functional proteins at a rate of 1 in 3.3×10&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;. To put the magnitude of the discrepancy into context, it’s 1 followed by 72 zeroes, which is a number that seems to fit in the arena concerning things like the number of atoms in the observable universe (estimated at ~10&lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;). Quite a margin of error!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question of how novel protein-coding genes have arisen by evolutionary processes throughout life’s history has many possible answers, ranging from processes such as mutational divergence of duplicate genes, through emergence by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frameshift_mutation&quot;&gt;frameshift mutation&lt;/a&gt;, to proteins evolving &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; from non-coding DNA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another idea is that novel protein-coding genes can arise by recombination of smaller fragments of already existing genes, resulting in chimeric sequences with the potential for new functions. An example of how such a chimeric gene can arise is depicted in Figure 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Rasmussen_Fig1_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Origin of chimeric gene&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt;: Overview of a step-wise process by which a chimeric gene can arise by what is in essence analogous to a copy-and-paste mechanism operating on DNA sequences. A piece of an organism’s chromosome is depicted with intergenic DNA represented by black horizontal lines, separated by colored bars representing the protein-coding genes A and B. (1) A small segment of chromosomal DNA is copied. (2) This copy is inserted back into the chromosome, this time inside the functional gene B. (3) This insertion results in a novel hybrid gene A/B. (4) All three genes A, B, and hybrid gene A/B, are expressed within the cell.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put very succinctly, take two (or more) pieces of already existing genes and combine them into a new gene which is a hybrid of the two. Since for the purposes of this post I am defining a gene as a piece of DNA that encodes a protein, the resulting hybrid protein consists of fragments of other existing proteins, and potentially has novel and useful biological functions, possibly facilitated by folding into a novel 3-dimensional structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve come across an interesting PhD thesis, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ourarchive.otago.ac.nz/handle/10523/9772&quot;&gt;Exploring the protein universe: a study of subdomain driven evolution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, by Gabriel Rawcliffe, detailing experiments to explore the evolution of novel functional proteins, by a version of this process of combining pieces of different genes, which the author calls “subdomain driven evolution.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rawcliffe sought to determine whether this process of generating hybrid genes by combining pieces of existing genes was capable of finding novel functional proteins. To do so, Rawcliffe performed his experiments using 107 different genetically engineered &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auxotrophy&quot;&gt;auxotrophic strains&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; bacteria. Each strain had only one of 107 different genes rendered nonfunctional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get some terminology down, an auxotrophic organism is a mutant variant of the same species that has lost the ability to biosynthesize a key organic compound that is essential for growth. Think of how we as humans have lost the ability to synthesize our own vitamin C, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pseudogene&quot;&gt;due to the pseudogenization&lt;/a&gt; (mutations have rendered a gene nonfunctional, turning into a so-called pseudogene) of a key gene in the vitamin C biosynthesis pathway. This means we need vitamin C in our diet to survive since we can’t make it within our own bodies. The particular gene that has mutated and become nonfunctional is found in humans and many of our close primate cousins and is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L-gulonolactone_oxidase&quot;&gt;known as GULOP&lt;/a&gt; (we inherited this nonfunctional gene from a distant primate common ancestor).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar principle goes for the &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; bacteria used in Rawcliffe’s experiments. He used 107 different auxotrophic strains, that is, 107 variants of &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt;, each of which carried a single genetically engineered mutation that made that strain unable to biosynthesize one of 107 different organic compounds the bacteria need to grow and divide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This compound could be anything from a particular sugar or amino acid, to lipids used in the cell membrane, or other essential constituents of &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt;. Experiments of this nature are also known as “knock-out” experiments, denoting that the experiment is performed with an organism carrying a gene that has been “knocked out” of function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rawcliffe’s strategy was then to find out whether it was possible to find a novel hybrid gene that was capable of performing a function that compensated for any one of the 107 different knocked out genes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He went on to screen a library of 1.65 million different hybrid genes created (using a molecular biology protocol called &lt;a href=&quot;https://experiments.springernature.com/articles/10.1007/978-1-4939-1053-3_16&quot;&gt;ITCHY&lt;/a&gt;) from what was essentially random fragments of existing genes, to see whether one of these millions of new hybrid genes could perform a function that could compensate for one of the 107 different dysfunctional mutant genes. It’s important to note here that the novel hybrid gene might not perform &lt;em&gt;the same&lt;/em&gt; function as the gene that was knocked out, but it is still able to rescue the strain by performing some other compensating function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The protocol he employed to detect whether such a function existed among his millions of random chimeric genes is depicted in this Figure 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Rasmussen_Fig2_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Plasmids carrying hybrid genes&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt;: On the right: circles with colored segments represent DNA &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plasmid&quot;&gt;plasmids&lt;/a&gt; carrying hybrid genes (created using the ITCHY protocol). These plasmids are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transformation_(genetics)&quot;&gt;transformed&lt;/a&gt; (a process by which bacteria can take in and use foreign DNA) into auxotrophic *E. coli* bacteria, and the transformed bacteria are then transferred to a Petri dish to see if they are able to grow and divide by employing the hybrid gene. If they can, a bacterial colony will become visible on the Petri dish, which can then be isolated and analyzed. On the left: Same strains of bacteria are used, but without the plasmid DNA carrying the hybrid genes. &lt;small&gt;Image credit: Figure 4.10 of Rawcliffe, G. (2019). Exploring the protein universe: a study of subdomain driven evolution. Reproduced with permission. &lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To elaborate a bit, what Rawcliffe does is first and foremost to use some rather technical molecular biology methods (the &lt;a href=&quot;https://experiments.springernature.com/articles/10.1007/978-1-4939-1053-3_16&quot;&gt;ITCHY protocol&lt;/a&gt;) to generate a huge library of random gene hybrids. Due to various technical limitations, his hybrid genes are restricted to consist of only two fragments at most, each derived from a different gene (essentially similar to that A/B hybrid depicted in Figure 1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rawcliffe generated a library of ~1.65 million different such hybrid genes that met the specifications for his experimental protocol. Rawcliffe then went on to use this library of ~1.65 million hybrid genes in a process called bacterial transformation, which basically means he gets his 107 different auxotrophic strains of &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; to transport the DNA encoding the novel hybrid genes inside themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the DNA is inside the bacterial cells, these same bacteria can now “read and decode” the DNA and thereby produce the novel hybrid gene. And here comes the crucial part: if by chance this novel hybrid gene can perform a function that compensates for the “knocked out” gene, the bacteria will be able to grow in a Petri dish on agar that otherwise lacks the essential nutrient. If any of Rawcliffe’s auxotrophic strains can grow and form a colony on a Petri dish, it is known as a rescue clone (because the inserted DNA “rescued” its ability to grow despite having a gene knocked out).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, having a negative control is important if we are to conclude that the bacteria grow &lt;em&gt;because they received a novel hybrid gene&lt;/em&gt; (instead of gaining this ability through some other spontaneous mutation, or perhaps having his culture cross-contaminated with bacteria that do not carry “knock out” mutations), so, crucially, Rawcliffe also tested his auxotrophic bacteria &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; giving them any of the DNA containing novel hybrid genes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so what did Rawcliffe find? He has this table summarizing his findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Rasmussen_Table1_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Table of results&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Table 4.2 from Rawcliffe, G. 2019. Ibid.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically what Rawcliffe found was that among his ~1.65 million hybrids, there were six different genes capable of performing a function that rescued one of his 107 auxotrophic strains (listed under the Hybrid column). Reading the table we see, for example, the hybrid gene Sgbe147/MioC82, being derived from a fusion of fragments from the genes Sgbe147 and MioC82, rescued a strain of &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; having the gene cysN knocked out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rawcliffe goes into more detail in his thesis, analyzing the particular strains that were rescued, what function was initially knocked out, and from which genes the fragments that constitute the rescuing hybrid gene was derived. One of his six rescue clones turned out to be a case of “self-rescue,” which means that a piece of the gene that was originally knocked out was also found as part of the hybrid gene that performed the rescue function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly the self-rescue is not a fully intact version of the original knocked out gene, being partially constituted of a smaller fragment from it, but is nevertheless able to carry out its function, at least while fused to a fragment of another gene. Rawcliffe writes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4.3.2.4 Rescue of E. coli ΔguaB&lt;/strong&gt;
The rescue of &lt;em&gt;E. coli ΔguaB&lt;/em&gt; represents a partial self-rescue; it was rescued by the hybrid YdjO257/GuaB283, a combination of 257 amino acids of YdjO and 283 amino acids of GuaB. The full length GuaB is 488 amino acids, meaning that ~60% of GuaB, fused to an almost full length YdjO (267 amino acids), seemingly performed the function of GuaB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of this post we can discount a partial self-rescue. What we need to know here is only that among Rawcliffe’s original ~1.65 million hybrid genes, there were 5 novel ones capable of performing a function essential for life in a real living organism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means we now have a number to compare to the number that gets bandied about in the ID-creationist literature, that functional proteins are found at the hyper astronomically low frequency of about 1 in 10&lt;sup&gt;77&lt;/sup&gt;. The number we have is ~1.65 million divided by 5 = ~330 000. So we have a frequency of functional proteins of 1 in 330 thousand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rawcliffe didn’t have to search through 10&lt;sup&gt;77&lt;/sup&gt; random combinations to find a new functional protein, and apparently truncated fragments of already existing protein sequences, when fused together, were capable of performing other functions. Thus, Axe’s estimate is in error, as noted above, by something on the order of &lt;em&gt;72 orders of magnitude&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Axe DD. Estimating the prevalence of protein sequences adopting functional enzyme folds. J Mol Biol. 2004;341(5):1295-1315. doi:10.1016/j.jmb.2004.06.058&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rawcliffe, G. (2019). Exploring the protein universe: a study of subdomain driven evolution (Thesis, Doctor of Philosophy). University of Otago. Retrieved from http://hdl.handle.net/10523/9772&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mikkel Nif Rasmussen</name></author><summary type="html">Where do novel functional proteins come from? It has become something of a staple of the ID-creationism movement that proteins with novel functions and structures are practically impossible to evolve. Why? In part because functional protein sequences, that is, protein sequences with functions that are useful to living organisms (such as protecting DNA from damage or promoting essential chemical reactions), are supposedly hyper-astronomically rare among all possible protein sequences. So rare, ID-creationists argue, that even with unrealistically huge population sizes and rates of mutation, not a single functional protein sequence could be expected to evolve in the entire history of the universe. The intended message is, of course, that since we know of millions of functional protein sequences within the diversity of life on Earth, and since supposedly none of them could have evolved, Intelligent Design becomes the only other plausible explanation for why they exist. And so, you know, evolution must be false and there must be an Intelligent Designer.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Biology Journal Gets Conned</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/biology-journal-gets-conned.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Biology Journal Gets Conned" /><published>2020-10-06T15:02:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-06T15:02:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/biology-journal-gets-conned</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/biology-journal-gets-conned.html">&lt;p&gt;In 1977, the &lt;em&gt;Journal of Theoretical Biology&lt;/em&gt; (JTB) published a paper by Hubert Yockey called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/0022519377900443&quot;&gt;A calculation of the probability of spontaneous biogenesis by information theory&lt;/a&gt;.  The paper became something of an embarrassment for the journal, since Yockey’s calculations, which purported to show that a naturalistic origin of life was effectively impossible, were both biologically and mathematically ridiculous.  Of course, this didn’t stop the creationists from crowing about the paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JTB is normally a well-respected journal, but history has now repeated itself.  The journal has just published a paper by Steinar Thorvaldsen and Ola Hössjer called &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtbi.2020.110352&quot;&gt;Using statistical methods to model the fine-tuning of molecular machines and systems&lt;/a&gt;.  Once again, the creationists are crowing about having slipped some of their dreck into a respectable venue.  But as with Yockey’s paper, the authors’ mathematics is naïve to the point of being silly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors characterize fine-tuning in physics like this: “The finely-tuned universe is like a panel that controls the parameters of the universe with about 100 knobs that can be set to certain values.  … If you turn any knob just a little to the right or to the left, the result is either a universe that is inhospitable to life or no universe at all.”  However, whether this constitutes fine-tuning, by some reasonable definition of that term, is going to depend on a lot more than just the number of knobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tell me more about those “certain values.”  Can the knobs be rotated all the way around, or can they only be rotated a few degrees?  Are all the hash marks on the knobs equally likely to occur, or are there physical reasons that some values are far more likely than others?  Can all the knobs be turned independently (which is the usual assumption made in thought experiments along these lines), or does turning one knob automatically force another knob to be turned?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need good answers to these questions if we are going to turn casual claims of fine-tuning (gosh, isn’t it interesting that small changes in the values of fundamental constants can lead to big changes in the stability of the universe!), into scientifically rigorous arguments useful for drawing grand, metaphysical conclusions (which only intelligent design can explain).  But the simple fact is that we have essentially no idea at all how to answer these questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors acknowledge this, writing, “A probabilistic argument presumes adequate knowledge of (the limits on) the space of possibility. … [T]here is no way of assigning a probability distribution as reference associated with the universe in that early stage.”  That’s the wisest thing they say in the whole paper!  They nonetheless quickly ignore this point, preferring instead to claim, groundlessly, that inferring design is the best explanation for cosmic fine-tuning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The situation only gets worse when they turn to biology.  Here their primary example of fine-tuning comes from so-called “irreducibly complex” systems in biology.  They even coin the term “Behe-system” after biochemist Michael Behe, who developed the idea in its modern form.  The authors write, “[William] Dembski applies the term ‘Discrete Combinatorial Object’ to any of the biomolecular systems which have been defined by Behe as having ‘irreducible complexity’.”  Mimicking the approach taken by Dembski in his book &lt;em&gt;No Free Lunch&lt;/em&gt;, they go on to write, “Then the probability of a protein complex is the multiplicative product of the probabilities of the origination of its constituent parts, the localization of those parts in one place, and the configuration of those parts into the resulting system (contact topology).”  There then follows a bona fide equation, complete with Greek letters, subscripts, and even a big pi to indicate a product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the point where a legitimate peer-reviewer would have thrown the paper aside, refusing to read any further, because every word is nonsense.  Complex systems do not evolve through three distinct phases of origination, localization, and configuration, for heaven’s sake.  But let’s leave that aside and play along for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the sake of argument, let’s assume the constituent parts are proteins.  When you speak of the probability of origination, do you mean the probability that the protein originates at random from an ocean of randomly colliding amino acids, or do you mean the probability that the protein originates as a slight variation on an already-existing protein?  When you refer to the probability of localization, are you imagining that the organism’s body is partitioned into discrete locations from which we choose uniformly and at random, or are you thinking in the context of slightly modifying a genetic program that already sends everything to specific locations?  And when you speak of the probability of configuration, are you imagining this probability simply as a permutation so that the number of configurations is just the factorial of the number of parts, or are you imagining the correct configuration arising gradually through a sequence of less effective systems until the modern form appears?  And why, exactly, are you treating origination, localization, and configuration as independent events, which they would have to be, to justify multiplying these probabilities together?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;No Free Lunch&lt;/em&gt;, William Dembski effectively chose the former option in each of these questions, which is why everyone laughed at him.  But we obviously need to consider the latter, and we equally obviously have no hope of assigning numbers to any of the relevant variables.   Incredibly, the authors even acknowledge &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; point, writing, “Modeling the formation of structures like protein complexes via this three-part process … is of course problematic because the parameters in the model are very difficult to estimate.”  But having just admitted to wasting the reader’s time developing a useless equation, they claim nonetheless that it has heuristic value.  It does not, because this three-fold process has precisely zero connection to any real biological process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a rule of thumb for you: If an author says he will address the question of whether a complex system could have arisen through evolution by natural selection, and then later says he will use probability theory to address the issue, then you can stop reading right there, because everything that comes next will be nonsense.  Probability theory is just flatly the wrong tool for this job because there is no hope of defining a proper probability space within which to carry out a calculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asked to explain their confidence that complex adaptations have evolved gradually, scientists generally note first that such systems always show what Stephen Jay Gould referred to as the “senseless signs of history,” meaning odd arrangements and strange kludges that make no sense when viewed as the product of human engineering, but make perfect sense when the history of the system is taken into consideration.  They then point to comparative anatomy in the present, to show that variant, and often simpler, systems exist in the present, thereby establishing the existence of plausible, functional, stepping-stones.  And for many specific systems they then go on to point to strong evidence from genetics, embryology, and paleontology that indicate precisely how the system evolved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, creationist arguments based on “irreducible complexity” just completely backfire.  We could as easily have used the term “easily broken” in place of “irreducibly complex,” and human engineers, at least, don’t usually brag about designing easily broken systems.  Engineers don’t design complex systems so that they fail catastrophically when a single part breaks, but natural selection, as has been pointed out many times, does this all but automatically.  In other words, the prevalence of “Behe-systems,” to use the authors’ term, is strong evidence of evolution.  When you find resilient systems with fail-safes, backups, and redundancies, then we can talk about intelligent design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desirous of keeping this post to a reasonable length, I have focused on what I take to be the absolutely fatal flaw of this paper.  The authors claim to have used probability theory to establish a scientifically rigorous and useful notion of “fine-tuning,” but they have failed because we have nothing like the information we would need to carry out meaningful probability calculations.  Done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I don’t think I’ve adequately communicated just how bad this paper is.  The authors are constantly tossing out bits of mathematical jargon and notation, but then they do nothing with them.  There is a frustrating lack of precision, as when they variously describe fine-tuning as an object, an entity, a method, and an attribute of a system, all on the first page of the paper.  They constantly cite creationist references, with only the most glancing mention that any of this work has been strongly and cogently criticized.  They say we should give fair consideration to a “design model” for the origination of complex structures, but they give not the beginning of a clue as to what such a model entails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, it’s hard to believe this paper could have gotten through an honest peer-review process (as opposed to one in which ideology played a big role).  Whatever happened behind the scenes, it’s a huge black eye for the journal.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jason Rosenhouse</name></author><summary type="html">In 1977, the Journal of Theoretical Biology (JTB) published a paper by Hubert Yockey called A calculation of the probability of spontaneous biogenesis by information theory. The paper became something of an embarrassment for the journal, since Yockey’s calculations, which purported to show that a naturalistic origin of life was effectively impossible, were both biologically and mathematically ridiculous. Of course, this didn’t stop the creationists from crowing about the paper. JTB is normally a well-respected journal, but history has now repeated itself. The journal has just published a paper by Steinar Thorvaldsen and Ola Hössjer called Using statistical methods to model the fine-tuning of molecular machines and systems. Once again, the creationists are crowing about having slipped some of their dreck into a respectable venue. But as with Yockey’s paper, the authors’ mathematics is naïve to the point of being silly. The authors characterize fine-tuning in physics like this: “The finely-tuned universe is like a panel that controls the parameters of the universe with about 100 knobs that can be set to certain values. … If you turn any knob just a little to the right or to the left, the result is either a universe that is inhospitable to life or no universe at all.” However, whether this constitutes fine-tuning, by some reasonable definition of that term, is going to depend on a lot more than just the number of knobs.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ID article in the Journal of Theoretical Biology</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/id-article-in-journal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ID article in the Journal of Theoretical Biology" /><published>2020-10-05T07:55:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-05T07:55:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/id-article-in-journal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/id-article-in-journal.html">&lt;p&gt;The Journal of Theoretical Biology appears to have published an article on intelligent-design creationism. Specifically, Steinar Thorvaldsen of the Department of Education, University of Tromsø, Norway; and Ola Hössjer of the Department of Mathematics, Stockholm University, Sweden, recently published a paper, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtbi.2020.110352&quot;&gt;Using statistical methods to model the fine-tuning of molecular machines and systems&lt;/a&gt;, which attempts to apply fine-tuning arguments to biology. I read the paper comparatively cursorily and did not fully understand it, not because it is above my pay grade, but because it is in a different department. It appears, though, to be applying arguments that reiterate William Dembski’s specified complexity and Michael Behe’s irreducible complexity, and repurposing them as a fine-tuning argument for biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And sure enough, within days, three biologists from Georgia Tech, Joseph Lachance, Corinne N. Simonti, and Joshua S. Weitz, submitted a rebuttal, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtbi.2020.110457&quot;&gt;Large sample spaces do not imply biological systems are ‘fine-tuned’&lt;/a&gt;, which has apparently already been accepted for the December 7 issue of the journal. Both the original article and the rebuttal are open access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The editors of the journal, Denise Kirschner, Mark Chaplain, and Akira Sasaki, jointly penned a &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtbi.2020.110456&quot;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/a&gt;, also for the December 7 issue. Unlike the original article and the letter to the editor, the disclaimer is, oddly, behind a paywall, even though the original article now displays a prominent link to that disclaimer. At any rate, the disclaimer is only one paragraph and &lt;a href=&quot;https://discourse.peacefulscience.org/t/hossjer-using-statistical-methods-to-model-the-fine-tuning-of-molecular-machines-and-systems/12009?u=swamidass&quot;&gt;was posted in Peaceful Science&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Journal of Theoretical Biology and its co-Chief Editors do not endorse in any way the ideology of nor reasoning behind the concept of intelligent design. Since the publication of the paper it has now become evident that the authors are connected to a creationist group (although their addresses are given on the paper as departments in bona fide universities). We were unaware of this fact while the paper was being reviewed. Moreover, the keywords “intelligent design” were added by the authors after the review process during the proofing stage and we were unaware of this action by the authors. We have removed these from the online version of this paper. We believe that intelligent design is not in any way a suitable topic for the Journal of Theoretical Biology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appears that the article has slipped past the editors, and they are trying to do damage control. I cannot fault the editors: the authors had legitimate university affiliations, and they have no obligation to state all the organizations they belong to, unless they perceive a conflict of interest. I doubt that the editor-in-chief of any journal reads all the articles in their entirety. I wonder, however, about the reviewing process and specifically about the reviewers: how were they chosen, and were they all suggested by the authors of the paper? Even more, I wonder whether the authors deliberately withheld the key word &lt;em&gt;intelligent design&lt;/em&gt; until the paper was in print and outside the purview of the editors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Joshua Swamidass for alerting us to the original article and the disclaimer at Peaceful Science, and also for commenting on and improving this article.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">The Journal of Theoretical Biology appears to have published an article on intelligent-design creationism. Specifically, Steinar Thorvaldsen of the Department of Education, University of Tromsø, Norway; and Ola Hössjer of the Department of Mathematics, Stockholm University, Sweden, recently published a paper, Using statistical methods to model the fine-tuning of molecular machines and systems, which attempts to apply fine-tuning arguments to biology. I read the paper comparatively cursorily and did not fully understand it, not because it is above my pay grade, but because it is in a different department. It appears, though, to be applying arguments that reiterate William Dembski’s specified complexity and Michael Behe’s irreducible complexity, and repurposing them as a fine-tuning argument for biology. And sure enough, within days, three biologists from Georgia Tech, Joseph Lachance, Corinne N. Simonti, and Joshua S. Weitz, submitted a rebuttal, Large sample spaces do not imply biological systems are ‘fine-tuned’, which has apparently already been accepted for the December 7 issue of the journal. Both the original article and the rebuttal are open access. The editors of the journal, Denise Kirschner, Mark Chaplain, and Akira Sasaki, jointly penned a Disclaimer, also for the December 7 issue. Unlike the original article and the letter to the editor, the disclaimer is, oddly, behind a paywall, even though the original article now displays a prominent link to that disclaimer. At any rate, the disclaimer is only one paragraph and was posted in Peaceful Science: The Journal of Theoretical Biology and its co-Chief Editors do not endorse in any way the ideology of nor reasoning behind the concept of intelligent design. Since the publication of the paper it has now become evident that the authors are connected to a creationist group (although their addresses are given on the paper as departments in bona fide universities). We were unaware of this fact while the paper was being reviewed. Moreover, the keywords “intelligent design” were added by the authors after the review process during the proofing stage and we were unaware of this action by the authors. We have removed these from the online version of this paper. We believe that intelligent design is not in any way a suitable topic for the Journal of Theoretical Biology. It appears that the article has slipped past the editors, and they are trying to do damage control. I cannot fault the editors: the authors had legitimate university affiliations, and they have no obligation to state all the organizations they belong to, unless they perceive a conflict of interest. I doubt that the editor-in-chief of any journal reads all the articles in their entirety. I wonder, however, about the reviewing process and specifically about the reviewers: how were they chosen, and were they all suggested by the authors of the paper? Even more, I wonder whether the authors deliberately withheld the key word intelligent design until the paper was in print and outside the purview of the editors. Thanks to Joshua Swamidass for alerting us to the original article and the disclaimer at Peaceful Science, and also for commenting on and improving this article.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Anavitrinella pampinaria</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/anavitrinella-pampinaria.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Anavitrinella pampinaria" /><published>2020-09-28T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-28T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/anavitrinella-pampinaria</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/anavitrinella-pampinaria.html">&lt;p&gt;Common gray moth, by &lt;strong&gt;James Kocher&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Kocher_CommonGrayMoth1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Common gray moth&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anavitrinella_pampinaria&quot;&gt;Anavitrinella pampinaria&lt;/a&gt;, common gray moth, resting on block of limestone masonry &amp;ndash; &quot;a nice example of camouflage (cryptic) coloration, St. Louis, Missouri.&quot; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Common gray moth, by James Kocher. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Anavitrinella pampinaria, common gray moth, resting on block of limestone masonry &amp;ndash; &quot;a nice example of camouflage (cryptic) coloration, St. Louis, Missouri.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Science on the Ballot</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/science-presents.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science on the Ballot" /><published>2020-09-21T11:35:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-21T11:35:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/science-presents</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/science-presents.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Science_Presents.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Poster&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry for the short notice, but I received this invitation from March for Science just this morning. Here is their e-mail in full:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;March For Science is partnering with &lt;a href=&quot;https://marchforscience.us20.list-manage.com/track/click?u=411a4f036b04a4b0a416702e2&amp;amp;id=53a573c7bf&amp;amp;e=515ccd05e3&quot;&gt;Science! The Show&lt;/a&gt; to bring you a night all about the science-related policies that are at stake this November. &lt;a href=&quot;https://marchforscience.us20.list-manage.com/track/click?u=411a4f036b04a4b0a416702e2&amp;amp;id=a979bc80f8&amp;amp;e=515ccd05e3&quot;&gt;Reserve your tickets&lt;/a&gt; to watch live on Twitch!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This Wednesday, at 6:00 p.m. PT, join us for a night of comedy and science advocacy with &lt;a href=&quot;https://marchforscience.us20.list-manage.com/track/click?u=411a4f036b04a4b0a416702e2&amp;amp;id=61acc9e838&amp;amp;e=515ccd05e3&quot;&gt;Dr. Gretchen Goldman&lt;/a&gt;, a research director for the Center for Science and Democracy at the Union of Concerned Scientists. Dr. Goldman leads research efforts on the role of science in public policy, focusing on topics ranging from scientific integrity in government decision-making, to political interference in science-based standards on hydraulic fracturing, climate change, and chemicals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;She will be joined by the talented &lt;a href=&quot;https://marchforscience.us20.list-manage.com/track/click?u=411a4f036b04a4b0a416702e2&amp;amp;id=21b75ce69c&amp;amp;e=515ccd05e3&quot;&gt;Cristela Alonzo&lt;/a&gt;, who created and starred in eponymous ABC sitcom ‘Cristela‘, making her the first Latinx woman to write and star in her own prime time comedy. Together with policy expert &lt;a href=&quot;https://marchforscience.us20.list-manage.com/track/click?u=411a4f036b04a4b0a416702e2&amp;amp;id=3fc096234a&amp;amp;e=515ccd05e3&quot;&gt;Rania Batrice&lt;/a&gt;, March For Science’s very own Senior Advisor, these three guests will help illuminate what will be on the ballot this election with the Science! The Show team for a night of conversation and laughs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We hope to see you there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so do I!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Sorry for the short notice, but I received this invitation from March for Science just this morning. Here is their e-mail in full: March For Science is partnering with Science! The Show to bring you a night all about the science-related policies that are at stake this November. Reserve your tickets to watch live on Twitch! This Wednesday, at 6:00 p.m. PT, join us for a night of comedy and science advocacy with Dr. Gretchen Goldman, a research director for the Center for Science and Democracy at the Union of Concerned Scientists. Dr. Goldman leads research efforts on the role of science in public policy, focusing on topics ranging from scientific integrity in government decision-making, to political interference in science-based standards on hydraulic fracturing, climate change, and chemicals.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Are Evolutionary Biologists Ignoring Science?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/are-evolutionary-biologists-ignoring-science.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are Evolutionary Biologists Ignoring Science?" /><published>2020-09-17T00:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-17T00:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/are-evolutionary-biologists-ignoring-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/are-evolutionary-biologists-ignoring-science.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/champneysscientists.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;From Champneys' video. Evolutionary biologists ignoring the Second Law
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Uncommon Descent in April, Granville Sewell has called attention to a new video by
Mark Champneys, “The Second Law of Thermodynamics: When Scientists Ignore Science”.
Sewell’s post will be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/when-scientists-ignore-science-by-mark-champney/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
Recall that Sewell’s own videos and books feature a refutation of evolution
by invoking something like the Second Law.  The Discovery Institute often praises Sewell, who is
one of their Fellows, and Sewell and Champneys say nice things about each
other.  So they all think that these arguments are good science, and that
what evolutionary biologists say is most definitely not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Champneys has shown up here once before: in 
2017 &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2017/04/Does-Granville-Sewells-entropy.html&quot;&gt;he made some comments on a 2011 post&lt;/a&gt; by me about Granville Sewell’s
arguments.  He and I had a brief, mild exchange in the comments section.  In those
days we had no Recent Comments widget to allow people to find comments on
older posts like that one, so no one else noticed this.  So I put up &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2017/04/Does-Granville-Sewells-entropy.html&quot;&gt;a new post about Champneys’ arguments&lt;/a&gt;
in the hope that he would join the discussion.  Alas, he did not show up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now Champneys has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/0oOt317kSro&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;new video&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which makes the shocking argument that when
scientists say that evolution occurs by natural selection acting on mutations
over time, they are ignoring the Second Law of Thermodynamics.  The new
video is 35 minutes long.  For a more extensive and discursive version of the
same argument, you could also consult a &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/8wLVBbqOGGA&quot;&gt;video of a lecture by Champneys&lt;/a&gt; where
he also explains how easily he has refuted scientists who fail to take into
account the Second Law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at what the new video says.  I do hope that Champneys will
come by and help us understand why he and Sewell think that we are ignoring
this fundamental law of science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As fodder for our discussion, let me just note some arguments he makes, and indicate
where I disagree with them, with quotes from the new Champneys video.  He says more on each
of these there.  Each quote is accompanied by the time in minutes and seconds
in his video where it will be found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Champneys describes evolutionary biologists as arguing that there are “loopholes”
and “exceptions” preventing the Second Law from working:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
(13:22) Sadly many brilliant scientists seek to dodge the law
with exactly such methods, suggesting that an open system
which lets sunlight in is not subject to this law of
science at all. Nothing can be further from the truth.
Increasing randomness and the principle driving the
law applies everywhere, to every part
of every system, open or isolated -- it just can't be
defined clearly for an open system, but the
principle does not go away just because
biologists want it to -- it is a principle, people, not
a loophole, and the principle driving the law works
everywhere without exception.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
(18:25) Their primary defense is to excuse their theory
by virtue of the fact that the earth is an open system. 
That's it, that's all they have.  Richard Dawkins has
stated that the Second Law can be disregarded simply
because of the sun.  The energy input of sunlight is
supposed to invalidate the application of the laws of
science to biology.  You can almost hear him shout 'loophole!
loophole!' Evolutionists claim that sunlight is the magical
ingredient that makes entropy decrease possible, but
it's simply not true -- sublight is actually very random,
and what's needed is the polar opposite of random,
which is specification. 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as I know that’s not what evolutionary biologists say: all the ones I have
heard say that evolution is completely consistent with the Second Law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Champneys seems to think that natural selection cannot put specified
information into the genome because it only destroys less fit individuals, and
does not preserve fit ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
(22:27) Then comes the evolutionists' last gasp
'but random mutations are not really random -- they
are directed by natural selection', so, they always say.
Oops again. I say, natural
selection is a constraint on random, but random
within constraints is still random.  Natural
selection kills and culls, it does not build
anything.  Killing the weak cannot reduce entropy,
only slow the increase in it.  Random begets random.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He argues that Darwin made a fundamental error in saying in the subtitle of his
book that natural selection “preserves” favored variations.  Actually, that
argument
is that variations of fitness lead to favored variations increasing in frequency
while less favored ones decrease in frequency.  With organisms competing for
limited resources, the one implies the other – culling less-favored variations
implies that more-favored ones are increasing.  They are not separate processes.
In a dense mat of dandelions in my yard, as a less favored genotype becomes
rarer, the more favored genotype is able to become more common and come to contain
more energy drawn from the sun.  This is an increase of specified information,
and affects the entropy calculation for the system.  But to Champneys,
this is not how information comes to be in the genome, he says clearly that
only intelligence can put it there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Champneys seems to miss the role in the thermodynamic bookkeeping
of energy flowing into living systems from
the sun (or from chemosynthesis) in allowing the growth of organisms and increases
in their adaptation and specified information.&lt;br /&gt;
He instead attributes the growth of organisms to “energy transfer mechanisms”,
“ETMs”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
(15:44) Consider photosynthesis. Sunlight alone would
dry up and destroy plants, but the photosynthesis ETM actually
builds them.  Plants use chlorophyll to harness very
random, even damaging sunlight to manufacture carbohydrates
and oxygen from carbon dioxide and water.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His “ETMs” are basically the complicated molecules of life which he thinks of as
basically exporting entropy.  These are simply the molecular
structures that capture energy, use it to maintain cells, retain it
and pass some of it on to offspring.  The proteins and RNAs of the cell.
That the incoming sunlight that arrives is at
a higher &lt;strike&gt;wavelength&lt;/strike&gt; frequency than its ultimate form as outgoing heat radiation seems
important, and affects entropy calculations, but that is
missing from Champneys’ argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Champneys keeps describing biologists as saying that it is mutation that puts
specified information into the genome.  He lampoons the way biologists
say that natural selection makes the mutation nonrandom, and makes
his “culling” argument to say that natural selection cannot add
specified information to the genome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
(21:24) Then after after a while comes the
only answer they can conjure up: 
'Mutations! Randoms mutations generated, and continue
to build the information sequences in DNA.'
Oops, I say, random is not an ETM.  Sorry, but it
is not, and never could be. Random is the
polar opposite of an ETM.  It does not make a
functional genome more probable, it makes it far less
probable.  Random is what ETMs are built to undo,
not to embrace.  Random mutations most certainly
degrade the genome, never sophisticate it. 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He seems not to see that changes in genotype frequencies have the effect
of choosing from among all variations the better-adapted ones.  Choosing a
relevant subset out of a larger set is the fundamental activity in
information theory.  If that subset is the better-adapted genotypes,
the information is also specified information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I hope that’s enough to lead to some discussion.  Watch the
video, and you will see the exact context of these quotes.  Look at
his longer video to get a more extensively and informally explained version.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">From Champneys' video. Evolutionary biologists ignoring the Second Law At Uncommon Descent in April, Granville Sewell has called attention to a new video by Mark Champneys, “The Second Law of Thermodynamics: When Scientists Ignore Science”. Sewell’s post will be found here Recall that Sewell’s own videos and books feature a refutation of evolution by invoking something like the Second Law. The Discovery Institute often praises Sewell, who is one of their Fellows, and Sewell and Champneys say nice things about each other. So they all think that these arguments are good science, and that what evolutionary biologists say is most definitely not. Champneys has shown up here once before: in 2017 he made some comments on a 2011 post by me about Granville Sewell’s arguments. He and I had a brief, mild exchange in the comments section. In those days we had no Recent Comments widget to allow people to find comments on older posts like that one, so no one else noticed this. So I put up a new post about Champneys’ arguments in the hope that he would join the discussion. Alas, he did not show up. Now Champneys has a new video, which makes the shocking argument that when scientists say that evolution occurs by natural selection acting on mutations over time, they are ignoring the Second Law of Thermodynamics. The new video is 35 minutes long. For a more extensive and discursive version of the same argument, you could also consult a video of a lecture by Champneys where he also explains how easily he has refuted scientists who fail to take into account the Second Law. Let’s take a look at what the new video says. I do hope that Champneys will come by and help us understand why he and Sewell think that we are ignoring this fundamental law of science.</summary></entry></feed>