<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-10-23T12:34:30-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Jason Rosenhouse and Phil Halper: creationist information theory</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/rosenhouse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jason Rosenhouse and Phil Halper: creationist information theory" /><published>2025-10-15T22:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2025-10-15T22:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/rosenhouse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/rosenhouse.html">&lt;div width=&quot;640px&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;390&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iJe_y4yXM7s&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
.embed-container {
  position: relative;
  padding-bottom: 56.25%;
  height: 0;
  overflow: hidden;
  max-width: 80%;
}
.embed-container iframe,
.embed-container object,
.embed-container embed {
  position: absolute;
  top: 0;
  left: 0;
  width: 100%;
  height: 100%;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Jason Rosenhouse is interviewed by Phil Halper on Halper's Youtube channel.  A demolition
of ID information theory.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;</content><author><name>Jason Rosenhouse</name></author><summary type="html">Jason Rosenhouse is interviewed by Phil Halper on Halper's Youtube channel. A demolition of ID information theory.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Aragonite Frostwork</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/aragonite-frostwork.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aragonite Frostwork" /><published>2025-10-13T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-10-13T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/aragonite-frostwork</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/aragonite-frostwork.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Alan Rice&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Rice-Alan_Aragonite Frostwork.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthodite&quot;&gt;Aragonite frostwork&lt;/a&gt;, taken in a cave in Nevada during field work. Mr. Rice writes, &quot;&lt;i&gt;Anthodites&lt;/i&gt; are speleothems (cave formations) composed of long needle-like crystals situated in clusters which radiate outward from a common base. Most anthodites are made of the mineral aragonite (a variety of calcium carbonate, CaCO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;), although some are composed of gypsum (CaSO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;·2H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O).  The &quot;needles&quot; may be quill-like or feathery.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Alan Rice. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Aragonite frostwork, taken in a cave in Nevada during field work. Mr. Rice writes, &quot;Anthodites are speleothems (cave formations) composed of long needle-like crystals situated in clusters which radiate outward from a common base. Most anthodites are made of the mineral aragonite (a variety of calcium carbonate, CaCO3), although some are composed of gypsum (CaSO4·2H2O). The &quot;needles&quot; may be quill-like or feathery.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building Bridges That Can Bear Scientific Scrutiny</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/building-bridges-that-can-bear.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building Bridges That Can Bear Scientific Scrutiny" /><published>2025-10-07T13:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-10-07T13:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/building-bridges-that%20can-bear</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/building-bridges-that-can-bear.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Jensen_Ark_IMG_2686_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Some of Jensen's team at the Ark.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Some of the team visiting the &quot;Ark.&quot; &lt;small&gt;Photograph by author.&lt;/small&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Jamie Jensen is a biologist and discipline-based education researcher at Brigham Young University, where she is a Professor of Biology. She has spent her career researching ways to help students and the public reconcile science with religious worldviews and has done work across the U.S., with the Smithsonian, and in other parts of the world including Qatar, South Africa, and Hungary.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently had the “opportunity” to visit the “Ark Encounter” and “Creation Museum” attractions in Kentucky while visiting Vanderbilt University for the Scopes Centennial Celebration. After participating in the academic meeting, I took a group of undergraduate students with me to these two attractions; these students work in my research lab investigating ways to communicate accurate evolutionary science across religious divides. We have had quite a bit of success in our efforts to increase evolution acceptance in the classroom without damaging students’ religious identities (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution-outreach.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12052-015-0051-6&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution-outreach.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12052-020-00133-9&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://online.ucpress.edu/abt/article-abstract/84/2/75/119835/Exploring-the-Relationship-between-Science?redirectedFrom=fulltext&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). However, with some of my more public-focused programming, I have met with varying levels of resistance (and sometimes hostility), even from members of my own Christian religious “in-group.” (Yes, I do belong to a conservative Christian religion. And I also fully embrace the modern science of evolution, in its entirety.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went to these two attractions seeking to better understand the viewpoints of those who stand in opposition to evolution, and to characterize the misconceptions and logical fallacies that may stand in the way of effective communication across the divide. We were astonished at the extent and sophistication of the attempts made to “create” science that supports alternative worldviews. This is not a case of trying to “sweep under the rug” the inconsistencies between a biblical account of creation and the physical evidence we see around us. It was, rather, an elaborate attempt to build a pseudoscientific “reality” that would satisfy a not unintelligent, but not scientifically well-versed patron of the attraction. But as I walked the halls of this misguided attraction, I got to thinking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;What occurred to me is that people &lt;i&gt;want&lt;/i&gt; a bridge. They &lt;i&gt;want&lt;/i&gt; the science and their faith to make sense. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gone are the days when parents could simply shield their kids from the science and hope they never encounter anything that questions their faith. Gone are the days when you could supply an alternative, completely non–science-based narrative and hope that your children never encounter the “real” story. With the advent of technology, social media, and information literally at our very fingertips, no one runs the risk of never being “exposed” to real science. And I think that those opposing evolution know this. They know that they can’t simply avoid the science. They can’t ask their patrons to rely on biblical writings alone. They can’t ask people to ignore the very real and very compelling evidence. They must invent a new science that is “close enough” to pass muster amongst their audience. They must build a bridge that, if crossed, maintains the integrity of their faith identity, and they understand that this bridge cannot utilize real science. But does this bridge have to be built on false scientific principles? I would argue that it does not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But &lt;strong&gt;first&lt;/strong&gt;: People &lt;i&gt;want&lt;/i&gt; a bridge. How do I know? I have been gathering empirical evidence that suggests it. In our research lab, we have been studying what we call the “Reconciliation Model” for years in various settings with a variety of religious affiliations. The Reconciliation Model involves discussing the nature and limitations of science, offering alternatives to literal biblical interpretations, and presenting evolutionary content in a way that is friendly to faith. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://biology.byu.edu/reconciling-evolution/curricular-materials&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for some example lesson plans, from a variety of faith traditions. We have found that we can increase students’ acceptance of evolutionary theory without reducing their religiosity (e.g., &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lifescied.org/doi/10.1187/cbe.19-04-0080&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution-outreach.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12052-021-00155-x&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. However, in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/jssr.70004&quot;&gt;recent study&lt;/a&gt;, we noticed an enigma that got us thinking about this increase in acceptance a little more. In this study, we measured the relationship between a literal interpretation of the Bible and acceptance of evolution. In a nationwide sample, we see an inverse relationship: the higher your literalism, the lower your acceptance. In our classroom study, utilizing the Reconciliation Model, we found that we could decrease biblical literalism and thereby directly predict increases in acceptance. However, what was puzzling to us was that students’ biblical literalism remained high, even though they were experiencing dramatic upward shifts in evolution acceptance (especially macro- and human evolution). This finding launched us into a second study, which has not yet been published. But I’ll give you a sneak preview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We re-surveyed students from among our highly religious student body and found students who were answering questions in a seemingly contradictory way. For example, they strongly agreed with both “Present animal diversity can be explained by the Great Flood” (a literal biblical interpretation) &lt;i&gt;and&lt;/i&gt; “I think all complex organisms evolved from single celled organisms” (an evolutionarily accurate statement). We wondered how a single student could strongly agree with both statements at the same time. Through thematic analysis using cultural border crossing and collateral learning theories (Aikenhead 1999) as our &lt;i&gt;a priori&lt;/i&gt; framework and then looking for emergent themes, we discovered two different lenses through which students were looking at these statements. Through an epistemological lens (i.e., “how do I know what I know?”), students felt certain that both science and religion are in harmony, that they could reconcile the two, that they could successfully build a bridge spanning the gap. For example, one student stated, “It doesn’t really feel important to me [to figure out how evolution and my religious beliefs fit together]. I just know that they do fit together. In whichever way it may be, I just know that they do.” Clearly, this student wants to believe that bridging the gap is possible – they &lt;i&gt;want&lt;/i&gt; a bridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, from a factual lens (i.e., “how does it actually work?”), students revealed a broad array of misconceptions, mental gymnastics, and uncertainty. When asked how the creation story in the Bible and evolution go together, this same student, who above was confident that both science and religion fit together, offered this explanation: “Just like… a lot of it like first starts off with the creation and all the species that were made and then when species start evolving and adapting to environments, that’s when more diversity happens,” indicating that all the “species” were created, and then they evolved to be more diverse. Another student, who stated from an epistemological standpoint, “I figured all truth is godly—whether it’s scientific or religious—they can be together,” then stated, when asked how the “Noah’s ark” story in the Bible and the evolution of modern diversity fit together, “I would have imagined that all of the land vertebrates that existed before the Ark would have died in the flood. So, the only ones that would survive would have been on the Ark…. But then there’s also that other part where maybe we’ve had some that have since come out of the water and they evolved that way.” Clearly, she holds misconceptions about the amount of modern diversity that exists, and about the time it takes to evolve from a water-dwelling organism to the diversity we see on land today (certainly more than the 4000 years or so since the flood supposedly occurred). We labeled these attempts to mesh a literal biblical interpretation and a scientific explanation together as “mental gymnastics,” which would be a new form of “dependent collateral learning” in collateral learning theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear, from our work, that students can appear to be epistemologically secured (i.e., they &lt;i&gt;want&lt;/i&gt; a bridge to be possible), when in reality, the bridge that they have built is full of factual holes and is likely to crumble as they obtain more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, &lt;strong&gt;second&lt;/strong&gt;: How do we help students build a bridge on a solid scientific foundation? And is it always possible? To answer the second part of the question first: in some cases, with extreme biblical literalist beliefs or specifically contradictory doctrine, a bridge may not be possible. However, in cases where this direct contradiction does not exist, I believe that it &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; possible to fortify their bridge. Here would be my advice: (a) Facilitate an accurate understanding of the nature and limitations of science. Research clearly shows that an understanding of the nature of science is one of the largest predictors of evolution acceptance (Dunk et al. 2019 provides a good overview). We have had large success in our courses when we emphasize the agnostic nature of science. Science can no more provide evidence &lt;i&gt;for&lt;/i&gt; God (a theistic perspective) as it can provide evidence &lt;i&gt;against&lt;/i&gt; the existence of a god (an atheistic perspective). Therefore, science is clearly agnostic and should not be a threat to anyone’s belief system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(b) Do not shy away from the facts. There is an emergingly clear relationship between the knowledge of evolution and its acceptance (again, see Dunk et al., 2019). A lack of the basics of evolution is often a struggle for students trying to build bridges. Some of those big ideas include that evolution is not a quest for perfection, that speciation takes a &lt;i&gt;really&lt;/i&gt; long time (longer than a human lifespan, usually), that organisms do not “choose” to adapt but that random mutations provide the variation upon which natural selection acts, that the process that leads to microevolution is the same process that leads to macroevolution, and that humans did not “come from” monkeys (i.e., an understanding of basic phylogeny principles).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would caution though, to always keep in mind that &lt;i&gt;only&lt;/i&gt; teaching the facts is not likely to overcome ideological barriers. Thus, (c) strive to use culturally competent strategies (or what is often now referred to as “conflict-reducing” strategies [Barnes and Brownell 2018]). Some of these strategies include acknowledging the potential for conflict, emphasizing the agnostic nature of science, providing religious role models who accept evolution, offering ways to reconcile science with religion, and practicing intellectual humility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is certainly a complex issue, and there is no one “silver bullet” way to solve these problems. Much of the conflict that exists today is the fruits of a long and troubled past involving historical events, impassioned publicity, and bad actors on both sides of the aisle. But we are not doomed to perpetuate the conflict. The understanding we have gained through rigorous research on pedagogy and communication can be used to launch us on a better trajectory to greater scientific literacy, more productive conversation, and more fortified bridges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aikenhead, G. S., and Jegede, O. J., 1999. &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/%28SICI%291098-2736%28199903%2936%3A3%3C269%3A%3AAID-TEA3%3E3.0.CO%3B2-T&quot;&gt;Cross-cultural science education: A cognitive explanation of a cultural phenomenon&lt;/a&gt;, Journal of Research in Science Teaching, 36, 269-287.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dunk, R. D. P., et al., 2019. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41559-019-0802-9&quot;&gt;Evolution education is a complex landscape&lt;/a&gt;. Nat. Ecol. Evol. 3(3):327-329. doi: 10.1038/s41559-019-0802-9. PMID: 30718854.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;M. Elizabeth Barnes and Sara E. Brownell, 2018. A Call to Use Cultural Competence When Teaching Evolution to Religious College Students: Introducing Religious Cultural Competence in Evolution Education (ReCCEE). Life sciences education, published online, https://doi.org/10.1187/cbe.17-04-0062&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jamie Jensen</name></author><summary type="html">Some of the team visiting the &quot;Ark.&quot; Photograph by author. Jamie Jensen is a biologist and discipline-based education researcher at Brigham Young University, where she is a Professor of Biology. She has spent her career researching ways to help students and the public reconcile science with religious worldviews and has done work across the U.S., with the Smithsonian, and in other parts of the world including Qatar, South Africa, and Hungary. I recently had the “opportunity” to visit the “Ark Encounter” and “Creation Museum” attractions in Kentucky while visiting Vanderbilt University for the Scopes Centennial Celebration. After participating in the academic meeting, I took a group of undergraduate students with me to these two attractions; these students work in my research lab investigating ways to communicate accurate evolutionary science across religious divides. We have had quite a bit of success in our efforts to increase evolution acceptance in the classroom without damaging students’ religious identities (see here, here, and here). However, with some of my more public-focused programming, I have met with varying levels of resistance (and sometimes hostility), even from members of my own Christian religious “in-group.” (Yes, I do belong to a conservative Christian religion. And I also fully embrace the modern science of evolution, in its entirety.) We went to these two attractions seeking to better understand the viewpoints of those who stand in opposition to evolution, and to characterize the misconceptions and logical fallacies that may stand in the way of effective communication across the divide. We were astonished at the extent and sophistication of the attempts made to “create” science that supports alternative worldviews. This is not a case of trying to “sweep under the rug” the inconsistencies between a biblical account of creation and the physical evidence we see around us. It was, rather, an elaborate attempt to build a pseudoscientific “reality” that would satisfy a not unintelligent, but not scientifically well-versed patron of the attraction. But as I walked the halls of this misguided attraction, I got to thinking:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ID education: coming soon nearby</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/idcourse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ID education: coming soon nearby" /><published>2025-10-04T21:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2025-10-04T21:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/idcourse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/idcourse.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;div halign=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/idcourse2a.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[question period at an earlier ID course]&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Students asking questions from the pews at an earlier version of the course in Spokane, Washington.  A speaker (Paul Nelson) seems to have been talking about how development can't anticipate function.&lt;br /&gt;From the announcement at Science &amp;amp; Culture (formerly Evolution News). Fair use claimed.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Discovery Institute’s Center for Science and Culture (formerly the Center for the Renewal of Science and Culture) has announced, at its blog &lt;a href=&quot;https://scienceandculture.com/2025/10/id-education-day-is-coming-to-tacoma-november-6/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; that it will run its ID Education Day for the fourth time, in Tacoma, Washington, on the 6th of November.  The theme will be “Creepy Crawly Complexity”.  I hadn’t been aware of this, but it was run most recently in Spokane, Washington in March, 
with nearly 500 students attending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For the past few years, we’ve held our most popular student event, ID Education Day, in Spokane, WA, and the excitement keeps growing! This past March, nearly 500 students from Central and Eastern Washington and North Idaho joined us, including one school that traveled nearly three hours to attend. To keep the momentum going and to serve the students of Western Washington, we’re excited to host our second “Creepy Crawly Complexity” ID Education Day in Tacoma on Thursday, November 6, from 9:30 am to 2:00 pm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a fantastic field trip opportunity for middle and high school students in homeschool and private school settings to interact directly with scientists and learn about the complexity and diversity of insects, spiders, and worms. Students will get to hear special presentations from philosopher of biology Paul Nelson on the miracle of butterfly metamorphosis and the complexity of the roundworm, biologist Pedro Moura on the phyla Arthropoda, Annelida, and Nematoda, and megadrilologist George Damoff on the elaborate design of the earthworm and its role in ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(A megadrilologist is not a specialist in very large mechanical drills, but in earthworm biology).
As we might expect&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The goal of the event will be to introduce students to the concept of intelligent design, to share updates from the field of zoology, and to think critically about the evidence (or lack thereof) for Darwinian evolution. In the panel Q&amp;amp;A, students will be encouraged to engage with our presenters to discuss the implications of their presentations for culture and worldview, helping them develop critical thinking skills and (in many cases) bolster their faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not know what the admission cost might be, or the requirements for one’s background. The link for the course is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discovery.org/e/idedday-fall-2025/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder whether the presentations and arguments will get beyond “gosh, aren’t these 
beasts amazingly complex? How could that happen except by Design Intervention?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Nelson’s argument apparently goes a bit beyond that, being an argument that 
development of embryos implies that the developmental process has foresight into what 
further-developed forms will need.  His argument is that this foresight could not be 
a property of natural selection, so Design Intervention is implied.  On &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.create.ab.ca/dr-paul-nelson-opened-our-minds/&quot;&gt;a creationist website&lt;/a&gt; he is quoted as saying that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you have a biological system which requires foresight [such as metamorphosis], you can be sure evolution did not do it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a similar argument in May at Evolution News (the previous name of Science &amp;amp; Culture) 
by David Klinghoffer (see my counterargument &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/05/platonic-nonsense.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), who has written a book publicizing the arguments of Richard Sternberg 
that when developmental processes seem to aim at an idealized form, that is impossible by 
normal evolutionary processes and implies that the development refers to a Platonic ideal 
form in an supernatural realm.  It completely ignores the possibility that there is 
genetic variability for developmental processes, and the individuals that succeed in 
achieving function leave more genes to their descendants.  Arguments like Sternberg’s and 
Nelson’s seem to be the new argument-du-jour of the DI.  See also Eric Hedin’s recent 
post at Science &amp;amp; Culture along similar lines (&lt;a href=&quot;https://scienceandculture.com/2025/02/fireweed-an-example-of-intelligent-latent-design/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nelson’s (and Sternberg’s) argument seems to be central to the new wave of “ID Education”.  Do the teachers mention the much simpler and more straightforward explanation using the ordinary processes of evolutionary biology?  Why do I suspect that they don’t?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that the Discovery Institute is working to spread their arguments among 
home school curricula and in private schools that dismiss evolution.  Should we suspect 
that they hope to spread their arguments into public schools?  In the past, when they 
were accused of that, they disclaimed any such intention.  For example, in 2005, they 
took the position, as Casey Luskin (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discovery.org/a/3000/&quot;&gt;posted at their website&lt;/a&gt;), that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s Constitutional But Not Smart to Teach Intelligent Design in Schools&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes since 2005 have largely been in a far-right federal government coming to power, the 
Supreme Court majority allowing many blatant violations of the separation of church and 
state, and states with right-wing governments feeling empowered to plaster public-school 
classrooms with their favorite religious icons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would not be surprised if the Discovery Institute changed its tune.  In which case, we 
will be seeing the new curriculum, coming soon to public-school classrooms near you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Students asking questions from the pews at an earlier version of the course in Spokane, Washington. A speaker (Paul Nelson) seems to have been talking about how development can't anticipate function.From the announcement at Science &amp;amp; Culture (formerly Evolution News). Fair use claimed.    The Discovery Institute’s Center for Science and Culture (formerly the Center for the Renewal of Science and Culture) has announced, at its blog here that it will run its ID Education Day for the fourth time, in Tacoma, Washington, on the 6th of November. The theme will be “Creepy Crawly Complexity”. I hadn’t been aware of this, but it was run most recently in Spokane, Washington in March, with nearly 500 students attending. For the past few years, we’ve held our most popular student event, ID Education Day, in Spokane, WA, and the excitement keeps growing! This past March, nearly 500 students from Central and Eastern Washington and North Idaho joined us, including one school that traveled nearly three hours to attend. To keep the momentum going and to serve the students of Western Washington, we’re excited to host our second “Creepy Crawly Complexity” ID Education Day in Tacoma on Thursday, November 6, from 9:30 am to 2:00 pm. Their description: This is a fantastic field trip opportunity for middle and high school students in homeschool and private school settings to interact directly with scientists and learn about the complexity and diversity of insects, spiders, and worms. Students will get to hear special presentations from philosopher of biology Paul Nelson on the miracle of butterfly metamorphosis and the complexity of the roundworm, biologist Pedro Moura on the phyla Arthropoda, Annelida, and Nematoda, and megadrilologist George Damoff on the elaborate design of the earthworm and its role in ecosystems. (A megadrilologist is not a specialist in very large mechanical drills, but in earthworm biology). As we might expect The goal of the event will be to introduce students to the concept of intelligent design, to share updates from the field of zoology, and to think critically about the evidence (or lack thereof) for Darwinian evolution. In the panel Q&amp;amp;A, students will be encouraged to engage with our presenters to discuss the implications of their presentations for culture and worldview, helping them develop critical thinking skills and (in many cases) bolster their faith. I do not know what the admission cost might be, or the requirements for one’s background. The link for the course is here. I wonder whether the presentations and arguments will get beyond “gosh, aren’t these beasts amazingly complex? How could that happen except by Design Intervention?”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sun dog</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/09/sun-dog.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sun dog" /><published>2025-09-29T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-09-29T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/09/sun-dog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/09/sun-dog.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Nicky Turner&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Nicky_Turner_Sun_Dog_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sun Dog over Tyrrhonian Sea, Italy.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sun_dog&quot;&gt;Sun dog&lt;/a&gt; (parhelion), overlooking the Tyrrhenian Sea, Castiligioncello, Livorno, Italy.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Nicky Turner. Sun dog (parhelion), overlooking the Tyrrhenian Sea, Castiligioncello, Livorno, Italy.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Antigone canadensis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/09/antigone-canadensis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Antigone canadensis" /><published>2025-09-15T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-09-15T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/09/antigone-canadensis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/09/antigone-canadensis.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;C. Joseph Long&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Long_Antigone_canadensis.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Caribou skull&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandhill_crane&quot;&gt;Antigone canadensis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; sandhill crane (formerly &lt;i&gt;Grus canadensis&lt;/i&gt;), &lt;a href=&quot;https://socorronm.org/location-activity/ladd-s-gordon-waterfowl-complex-bernardo-waterfowl-area/&quot;&gt;Bernardo State Wildlife Refuge&lt;/a&gt;, Rio Grande Valley, New Mexico. OM System, OM-1 Mark II.  300-mm lens with 2x teleconverter. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by C. Joseph Long. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Antigone canadensis &amp;ndash; sandhill crane (formerly Grus canadensis), Bernardo State Wildlife Refuge, Rio Grande Valley, New Mexico. OM System, OM-1 Mark II. 300-mm lens with 2x teleconverter.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Will LifeWise Academy Take Kentucky Students to the Ark and Creation Museum?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/09/will-lifewise-academy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Will LifeWise Academy Take Kentucky Students to the Ark and Creation Museum?" /><published>2025-09-09T10:53:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-09-09T10:53:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/09/will-lifewise-academy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/09/will-lifewise-academy.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_LifeWise_Academy_Frontispiece.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;LifeWise Academy van.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;LifeWise Academy is a religious instruction program that started in 2019 and now enrolls 50,000 students across 29 states. &lt;small&gt;Photo by Megan Henry, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ohiocapitaljournal.com/2025/09/04/lifewise-academy-will-be-in-nearly-half-of-ohios-school-districts-this-school-year/&quot;&gt;Ohio Capital Journal&lt;/a&gt;. Creative Commons license CC BY-NC-ND 4.0.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain Christian Nationalists, part of an organization known as LifeWise Academy, have found a way to get their religion into public schools in Ohio and are attempting to do the same here in Kentucky (and many other states). In Kentucky this could result in public school students visiting the Ark Encounter and Creation Museum in lieu of public school instruction. Below, I document Ohio students being taken to these fundamentalist Christian attractions with the cooperation of public schools. Kentucky students may also end up learning creationist nonsense during public school instruction time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, LifeWise Academy has been attempting to get a foothold in Kentucky’s 171 public school districts. &lt;a href=&quot;https://lifewise.org/&quot;&gt;LifeWise Academy&lt;/a&gt; is an Ohio-based ministry that has found a possible loophole to get Bible-based instruction into public school classrooms during school hours via “release time.” &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Released_time&quot;&gt;Release time laws&lt;/a&gt; in many places allow students to leave public school instruction for an hour a day, or in some places an hour a week, to receive religious instruction off-campus. However, LifeWise Academy has made release time into a major event where students get to leave school to receive numerous perks, such as pizza parties, while being evangelized and instructed in other ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students whose parents do not allow them to participate have to remain in school for classes or study hall. There have been many complaints in Ohio of students that do not participate being bullied and/or ostracized. Many of the LifeWise activities promote Christian Nationalism, fake history, and various right-wing political ideologies, which leads to more bullying of marginalized students who do not participate. This mistreatment of non-participants is well-documented in the Facebook Group (Secular Education Program, formerly Parents AGAINST LifeWise).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LifeWise organization is very well funded. Most LifeWise organizations in Ohio have their own bright red painted school buses. The ultra-conservative Heritage Foundation has given LifeWise Academy a portion of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.heritage.org/press/heritage-awards-over-1-million-conservative-organizations-2025-innovation-prizes&quot;&gt;million dollar award&lt;/a&gt; for their child evangelism. Here is an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/lifewise-academy-public-school-christian-church-rcna142172&quot;&gt;excellent news article&lt;/a&gt; about some of LifeWise’s activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early in 2025, the Kentucky General Assembly passed &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.legislature.ky.gov/record/25rs/sb19.html&quot;&gt;Senate Bill 19&lt;/a&gt;, which allows schools to let students receive “moral instruction” from outside groups. This legislation opened the door for LifeWise to request each of Kentucky’s 171 school districts to allow them access. (Kentucky has 120 county school systems plus a number of cities have systems separate from their county.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LifeWise was recently rejected by the Warren County Public Schools (near Bowling Green). However, this rejection  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kentucky.com/news/local/education/article312010654.html&quot;&gt;has been appealed&lt;/a&gt; with the help of the Family Foundation of Kentucky (more about them below). Presently, Oldham County Public Schools (the county east of Louisville) is considering allowing a LifeWise program to operate there. Apparently, proposals will be made in numerous other districts in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the effort to push LifeWise into Kentucky schools is due to their regional partnership with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kentuckyfamily.org/four-new-education-laws-to-know-before-school-starts/&quot;&gt;Family Foundation of Kentucky&lt;/a&gt;. The Family Foundation has provided legal representation to LifeWise at a Kentucky school board meeting (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/kBXaWD2YQzo?si=5d9iWW5kBTnQHT_6&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/live/e2QeZNoCf0s?si=B_AX7ZCX-96fW591&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Family Foundation of Kentucky almost derailed the implementation of the Next Generation Science Standards in 2013 and provided &lt;a href=&quot;http://theprincipal.blogspot.com/search?q=Dan+phelps&quot;&gt;anti-evolution inserts for church bulletins&lt;/a&gt; as part of their campaign. Apparently, the Family Foundation is including a &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.charityengine.net/2025KYFamilyForum?sm_guid=ODg1OTM5fDY1Mzc3MjUxfC0xfGVkcmlvYXN0ZXJvaWRAbXNuLmNvbXw4MTI2MjMxfHwwfDB8Mjc2NjY4MjgwfDEwNTR8MHwwfHw4ODIxNTB8MA2&quot;&gt;speaker from LifeWise&lt;/a&gt; at their annual “Family Forum” in late September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of my long-standing opposition to Answers in Genesis’s Ark Encounter and Creation Museum, I became interested in establishing whether these Kentucky “attractions” were being visited by LifeWise students from Ohio. Google searches and Facebook searches using the terms “LifeWise Ark Encounter” and “LifeWise Creation Museum” brought up numerous examples of LifeWise bringing students to both attractions. Many times these trips occurred during Spring and Fall breaks, but many times they were done during school time and using the school as a staging place for the red LifeWise bus to pick up and return the students. LifeWise Academy Ohio chapters apparently sent students from these towns and/or school districts: Adams County, Clark-Shawnee, Holgate, West-Cental, Continental, Antwerp, Wayne Trace, Central Local, Van Wert, Paulding Exempted, Tinora, Pandora-Gilboa, Continental Elementary, and Upper Arlington. There may be many more that did not post about their trip to Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of these groups went across state lines from Ohio to Kentucky multiple times over the last several years. At least one group, Continental Elementary departed and returned to the public school after an all-day trip to the Ark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_LifeWise_Academy_Figure_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Permission slip.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 1. Continental Elementary Ark trip &lt;a href=&quot;https://form.jotform.com/230754010641141?fbclid=IwZXh0bgNhZW0CMTEAAR5tSeAsXNacnStLbA2dk04S0MCPOIuiZ4V47IhzkdqKb2AgAOqWsGYGLajUpg_aem_uVofdGsk6amg93da6ZIwHQ&quot;&gt;permission slip&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 1 is part of the permission slip. Some of the trips are paid for by various fundraisers, including breakfasts and spaghetti dinners (see Figure 2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have visited both the Ark Encounter and the Creation Museum. My reviews can be found on The Panda’s Thumb &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2016/07/ark-park-on-ope.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, as well as &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/kentucky-gets-ark-shaped-second-creation-museum&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/anti-museum&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The contents of these ersatz “museums” are simply incredible in the most literal sense of the word. Both attractions are devoted to a crude biblical literalism, which has the earth and universe only approximately 6,000 years old, most geology being the result of Noah’s Flood in 2,348 BCE, dinosaurs being fire-breathing dragons, and other complete nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_LifeWise_Academy_Figure_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Poster.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 2. Fundraiser for Ark trip.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The words pseudoscience and anti-science are not adequate to describe the attacks on various fields of science by the Ark and Creation Museum including, but not limited to, geology, paleontology, biology, astronomy, paleoanthropology, climate science, archaeology, linguistics, and history. An adult with a reasonable education in any of these fields, or just with basic reasoning skills, may be amused or angered by the contents, but an elementary school kid is only going to be confused or seriously misinformed after a visit. Since many of the claims in these venues imply a conspiracy by actual scientists who study these fields, a student may feel discouraged from pursuing a career in science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_LifeWise_Academy_Figure_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Death match between humans, giants and a dinosaur.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 3. A pre-Flood death match between giants, humans, and a dinosaur in a pre-Flood arena o’death.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite absolutely cringeworthy example of an Ark-load of ignorant misinformation is in the Ark Encounter, where a well-crafted diorama depicts a three-way death match between giants, humans, and a &lt;i&gt;Carnotaurus&lt;/i&gt; dinosaur. This extra-Biblical fantasy occurs in a “pre-Flood” arena. Apparently, this “scientific” display is based on a series of three novels by an employee of Answers in Genesis, the ministry behind the Ark (see Figure 3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the political support LifeWise has from our far-right politicians and many members of the public, it may be extremely difficult to stop LifeWise from having student trips to the Answers in Genesis attractions, either on public school time or using public school resources. If the churches supporting LifeWise in Ohio are willing to send children across state lines for creationist indoctrination, then their Kentucky LifeWise supporters will have no compunction about sending children from distant parts of the state to the Ark and Creation Museum. Kentucky lacks an actual natural history museum, and many of our children are going to be instructed in fake science if LifeWise gets a foothold in Kentucky schools. I hope parents and educators speak out on this matter. Unfortunately, in many areas, this mixing of extremist religion and education will be ignored or even encouraged.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">LifeWise Academy is a religious instruction program that started in 2019 and now enrolls 50,000 students across 29 states. Photo by Megan Henry, Ohio Capital Journal. Creative Commons license CC BY-NC-ND 4.0. Certain Christian Nationalists, part of an organization known as LifeWise Academy, have found a way to get their religion into public schools in Ohio and are attempting to do the same here in Kentucky (and many other states). In Kentucky this could result in public school students visiting the Ark Encounter and Creation Museum in lieu of public school instruction. Below, I document Ohio students being taken to these fundamentalist Christian attractions with the cooperation of public schools. Kentucky students may also end up learning creationist nonsense during public school instruction time. Recently, LifeWise Academy has been attempting to get a foothold in Kentucky’s 171 public school districts. LifeWise Academy is an Ohio-based ministry that has found a possible loophole to get Bible-based instruction into public school classrooms during school hours via “release time.” Release time laws in many places allow students to leave public school instruction for an hour a day, or in some places an hour a week, to receive religious instruction off-campus. However, LifeWise Academy has made release time into a major event where students get to leave school to receive numerous perks, such as pizza parties, while being evangelized and instructed in other ways. Students whose parents do not allow them to participate have to remain in school for classes or study hall. There have been many complaints in Ohio of students that do not participate being bullied and/or ostracized. Many of the LifeWise activities promote Christian Nationalism, fake history, and various right-wing political ideologies, which leads to more bullying of marginalized students who do not participate. This mistreatment of non-participants is well-documented in the Facebook Group (Secular Education Program, formerly Parents AGAINST LifeWise).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rangifer tarandus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/09/rangifer-tarandus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rangifer tarandus" /><published>2025-09-01T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-09-01T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/09/rangifer-tarandus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/09/rangifer-tarandus.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Malcolm Schongalla&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Schongalla_Rangifer_tarandus_skull.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Caribou skull&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reindeer&quot;&gt;Rangifer tarandus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; caribou skull found near the Russell Glacier on the West Coast of Greenland, June, 2022. The photo was taken with a Pixel 4a.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Malcolm Schongalla. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Rangifer tarandus &amp;ndash; caribou skull found near the Russell Glacier on the West Coast of Greenland, June, 2022. The photo was taken with a Pixel 4a.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ginkgo biloba</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/ginkgo-biloba.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ginkgo biloba" /><published>2025-08-18T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-08-18T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/ginkgo-biloba</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/ginkgo-biloba.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Denelsbeck_Ginkgo_biloba.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ginkgo biloba showing water droplets&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ginkgo_biloba&quot;&gt; Ginkgo biloba&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; ginkgo leaf after a heavy rain. Mr. Denelsbeck notes, &quot;The leaves are quite water-repellent (hydrophobic) and cause the water to form almost-spherical drops under their own surface tension, which allows them to become lenses by themselves &amp;ndash; you can see them showing further drops behind themselves. Often called a &quot;living fossil,&quot; ginkgos are the last of their 300 my order, Ginkgoales, and easily distinguished by the leaf 'veins' which do not branch, but all originate from the base of the stem in a fanlike manner. This trait, along with the water-repellence, helps funnel water down to the trunk and thus to roots that would otherwise be blocked or redirected by the leaves. Canon 7D, Canon 18-135 STM at 135&amp;nbsp;mm, ISO 250, F/13, 1/200&amp;nbsp;s with custom softbox flash unit.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Al Denelsbeck. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Ginkgo biloba &amp;ndash; ginkgo leaf after a heavy rain. Mr. Denelsbeck notes, &quot;The leaves are quite water-repellent (hydrophobic) and cause the water to form almost-spherical drops under their own surface tension, which allows them to become lenses by themselves &amp;ndash; you can see them showing further drops behind themselves. Often called a &quot;living fossil,&quot; ginkgos are the last of their 300 my order, Ginkgoales, and easily distinguished by the leaf 'veins' which do not branch, but all originate from the base of the stem in a fanlike manner. This trait, along with the water-repellence, helps funnel water down to the trunk and thus to roots that would otherwise be blocked or redirected by the leaves. Canon 7D, Canon 18-135 STM at 135&amp;nbsp;mm, ISO 250, F/13, 1/200&amp;nbsp;s with custom softbox flash unit.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Knowing you are right, even when you are not</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/knowing-you-are-right.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Knowing you are right, even when you are not" /><published>2025-08-17T10:58:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-08-17T10:58:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/knowing-you-are-right</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/knowing-you-are-right.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/On_Being_Certain_Cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This little book, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B003J5UJHW/&quot;&gt; On Being Certain&lt;/a&gt;: Believing You Are Right Even When You’re Not&lt;/i&gt;, is not exactly about epistemology, that is, how we know what we know; rather, it is about how we think we know, even when potentially we do not. Indeed, it seems to me that it explains why the philosopher Lee McIntyre was by his own account singularly unsuccessful in convincing virtually any science denier about anything (see my article &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/how-to-talk-science-denier.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author of the present book, Robert Alan Burton, is a neurologist, not a philosopher. The book was originally published in 2009 and recently rereleased. It is well out of my area, so I have no way of knowing how much is dated. To oversimplify, Burton argues, somewhat apologetically, that there may be evolutionary advantage to having a module that quickly tells you, you are right. As he notes in the Preface,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Despite how certainty feels, it is neither a conscious choice nor even a thought process. Certainty and similar states of “knowing what we know” arise out of involuntary brain mechanisms that, like love or anger, function independently of reason.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He calls this sentence “[t]he revolutionary premise at the heart of this book….”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another oversimplification (mine, that is): Burton tells us that the brain is a neural network (or perhaps a network of neural networks) that can be characterized as having an input, an output, and between them a hidden layer that does all the processing. We know that the layer is hidden, in part because we can bring to the surface only one or two of our thought processes at a time. Other thought processes are clearly going on, as we know, for example, when we have a sudden realization of something that we did not consciously know we were thinking about. Suddenly, we just &lt;i&gt;know&lt;/i&gt; the solution to an important problem; we have what Burton calls a &lt;i&gt;feeling of knowing&lt;/i&gt;, and he considers this phrase so important that he italicizes it throughout the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This insight, that we have a &lt;i&gt;feeling of knowing&lt;/i&gt; whether we know or not, is important to discussions of pseudoscience. In my article on McIntyre’s book &lt;i&gt;On Being Certain&lt;/i&gt; (see link above), we met flat-earthers who could not be disabused of what we consider their delusions. Relevantly to PT, Burton hauls out the creationist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurt_Wise&quot;&gt;Kurt Wise&lt;/a&gt;, who has a BA degree in geophysics from the University of Chicago, an MA degree in geology from Harvard, and a PhD in paleontology under no less a personage than Stephen Jay Gould. He is now director of the Creation Research Center at Truett McConnell University in Georgia. For all that, Wikipedia quotes him as saying,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Although there are scientific reasons for accepting a young Earth, I am a young age [sic] creationist because that is my understanding of the Scripture. As I shared with my professors years ago when I was in college, if all the evidence in the universe turns against creationism, I would be the first to admit it, but I would still be a creationist because that is what the Word of God seems to indicate.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wise is now director of the Creation Research Center at a Baptist institution, Truett McConnell University in Georgia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least Wise has the humility to use the qualifier “&lt;i&gt;seems to&lt;/i&gt; indicate.” Richard Dawkins, as Barton describes him, seems absolutely sure of himself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Faith is the great cop-out, the great excuse to evade the need to think and evaluate evidence. Faith is belief in spite of, even perhaps because of, the lack of evidence.&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;And&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;I will respect your views if you can justify them. But if you justify your views only by saying you have faith in them, I shall not respect them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though I am far more sympathetic to Dawkins than to Wise, I fear that Dawkins has succumbed to the &lt;i&gt;feeling of knowing&lt;/i&gt; and assumes that his thoughts are purely rational. Burton argues to the contrary, that your thoughts are shaped by your past and the structure of your brain. The disembodied rational mind, he says, does not exist. Both Dawkins and Wise have the &lt;i&gt;feeling of knowing&lt;/i&gt;, and Dawkins is downright evangelical in his need to propagate his atheism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lest you get the wrong idea, Barton is not a nihilist and clearly sees the need for evidence. He takes the physician Andrew Weil to task for refusing to believe a null result, instead saying,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; We were unable in those tests to prove that this had an effect. The problem is, I’m sure there’s an effect there. 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was reminded of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brainyquote.com/quotes/richard_p_feynman_137642&quot;&gt;Richard Feynman’s famous quotation&lt;/a&gt;, “The first principle is that you must not fool yourself, and you are the easiest person to fool.” At any rate, you do not need a disembodied rational mind to know that if you do an experiment properly you ought to accept the results. As Barton notes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The failures of science … begin with personal self-deception and an unjustified &lt;i&gt;sense of knowing&lt;/i&gt;. … &quot;I am sure&quot; is a mental sensation, not a testable conclusion.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will not go into detail, but besides Weil and Dawkins, Barton subjects to scrutiny Russell Targ, Paul Davies, Leon Kass, Francis Collins, Richard Lewontin, Daniel Dennett, Stephen Jay Gould, Stephen Hawking, and Malcolm Gladwell. Some of them fare better than others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will conclude, as does Barton, with a speculation as to whether&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;some of the toughest age-old philosophical issues arise out of attempts to resolve perceptual tricks created by our brains.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Dos_caras_una_copa.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Vase-faces illusion&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubin_vase&quot;&gt;Rubin's vase.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Dos_caras_una_copa.jpg&quot;&gt;Photograph&lt;/a&gt; by Sebasgiu.  Own work. Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 4.0 international license. &lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barton notes the famous “optical illusion of the silhouette of two opposing faces that can also be seen as a vase.” I think virtually everyone knows this illusion, Rubin’s vase, pictured at left, so Barton does not see a need to show it. When you look at the picture one way, you see a vase; when you look at it another way, you see two opposing faces in profile. Evidently it is not possible to see both at once. Barton wonders whether mind-body dualism, for example, or our inability to understand whether time or space begins or is infinite, is roughly equivalent to our inability to view Rubin’s vase as both two faces and a vase at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completely off-task: The discussion made me wonder about wave-particle duality. Very roughly, if we perform a diffraction experiment with a phosphorescent screen, a photon will propagate through space as if it were a wave but react with the screen as if it were a particle. Presumably it is something much more complicated than either a wave or a particle, something that is occasionally called a wavicle. Is it possible that the perceived duality is no more than our inability to perceive both aspects, wave and particle, simultaneously, a sort of physical Rubin’s vase?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">This little book, On Being Certain: Believing You Are Right Even When You’re Not, is not exactly about epistemology, that is, how we know what we know; rather, it is about how we think we know, even when potentially we do not. Indeed, it seems to me that it explains why the philosopher Lee McIntyre was by his own account singularly unsuccessful in convincing virtually any science denier about anything (see my article here). The author of the present book, Robert Alan Burton, is a neurologist, not a philosopher. The book was originally published in 2009 and recently rereleased. It is well out of my area, so I have no way of knowing how much is dated. To oversimplify, Burton argues, somewhat apologetically, that there may be evolutionary advantage to having a module that quickly tells you, you are right. As he notes in the Preface,</summary></entry></feed>