<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-03-14T02:32:08-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Creationism, accreditation, and the rules of evidence</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/creationism-accreditation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creationism, accreditation, and the rules of evidence" /><published>2021-03-08T08:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-03-08T08:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/creationism-accreditation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/creationism-accreditation.html">&lt;p&gt;Last month I argued  that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.snopes.com/news/2021/02/04/why-creationism-bears-all-the-hallmarks-of-a-conspiracy-theory/&quot;&gt;present-day creationism is a conspiracy theory&lt;/a&gt;, that like other conspiracy theories, it has its own rules of evidence, and that one underlying driver for this conspiracy theory is a struggle for power. Two recent developments give substance to my claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, regarding the rules of evidence. We are familiar with the creationist claim that ancient-earth geology and the related studies such as the fossil record are mere historical sciences, based on unproven and unprovable assumptions about unrepeatable past events, whereas the scientific method requires reproducibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The errors here are obvious. The observations must, circumstances permitting, be reproducible, but the past event inferred need not be. For example, recent DNA evidence established that the father of the Archbishop of Canterbury was not the person named on his birth certificate. We can test this conclusion, to the highest scientific standards, by repeating the DNA test, but there is no need to beget additional Archbishops to prove our point. We do indeed assume, with Hutton, that the present is the key to the past, but this assumption is itself the result of repeated observation. We can see rain splashes in billion-year-old mudstone and rounded pebbles in ancient riverbeds. The resemblance between past and present is not, as creationists claim, an input into interpretation but an outcome of observation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this month the world’s most noted creationist organisation has gone even further.  In a piece titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/apologetics/critical-thinking/thinking-critically-ape-man-messages/&quot;&gt;Thinking Critically About “Ape-Man” Messages&lt;/a&gt;, Patricia Engler of Answers in Genesis tells us “how to sort through such claims with biblical, critical thinking.” Her recommended procedure is dramatically effective: “The first way to detect a lie is by comparing it to the truth, with the ultimate standard for truth being God’s Word.” Unsurprisingly, this leads her to conclude, “Hominid claims fail this test.” The first test for truth, she tells us, is correspondence with AiG’s views. Whatever does not correspond to these views is not true. The insulation from criticism is perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted find out more about Ms Engler, but Answers in Genesis tells us &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/bios/patricia-engler/&quot;&gt;tantalizingly little&lt;/a&gt;. We are told that after 12 years homeschooling, she completed a BSc with distinction at a liberal arts college, where “she studied intensely evolutionary courses to learn firsthand how Christian students can navigate secular education without compromising their biblical worldview,” but we are not told the subject matter of her BSc nor the identity of the college where she acquired these navigational skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the role of power in creationism, we have an example this week, when the Transnational Association of Christian Colleges and Schools (Tracs) will have the status of its accreditations reviewed by the Council for Higher Education Accreditation. Joshua Swamidass has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/a-compromise-on-creationism-11614901537&quot;&gt;discussed the issues concerned in the Wall Street Journal&lt;/a&gt;, and Panda’s Thumb has covered Dr. Swamidass’s article &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/should-colleges-that-teach.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I discuss Tracs as an instrument of power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to be accredited by Tracs, an institution must, &lt;a href=&quot;https://tracs.org/resources/&quot;&gt;as their website makes plain&lt;/a&gt; submit a Faith Statement which&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;should identify it as part of the evangelical protestant tradition in higher education. It is to be written so as to conform to the historic creeds and statements of Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As to what those historic creeds and statements may be, they would seem to require compatibility with at least the spirit of Tracs’s own &lt;a href=&quot;https://tracs.org/statement-of-faith/&quot;&gt;Statement of Faith&lt;/a&gt;, which concludes with the following statements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Biblical Creation&lt;/strong&gt;. Special creation of the existing space-time universe and all its basic systems and kinds of organisms in the six literal days of the creation week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Satan&lt;/strong&gt;. The existence of a personal, malevolent being called Satan who acts as tempter and accuser, for whom the place of eternal punishment was prepared, where all who die outside of Christ shall be confined in conscious torment for eternity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Readers may remember that Charles Darwin, in his Autobiography, expressed his repugnance towards the “damnable doctrine” of punishment of unbelievers, and that his widow wished to suppress his remarks on the grounds that &lt;a href=&quot;http://darwin-online.org.uk/content/frameset?itemID=F1497&amp;amp;viewtype=side&amp;amp;pageseq=89&quot;&gt;surely nobody really believed anything of the sort any more&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My present concern, however, is not with the content of this Statement of Faith, but with Tracs’s enforcement of it. Since its inception, Christianity has given rise to endless differences of doctrine and interpretation. Yet Tracs claims the right to determine which particular doctrines and interpretations an institution must adhere to, and which historic creeds and statements it must accept, before it will recognize that institution as Christian. Power indeed!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman</name></author><summary type="html">Last month I argued that present-day creationism is a conspiracy theory, that like other conspiracy theories, it has its own rules of evidence, and that one underlying driver for this conspiracy theory is a struggle for power. Two recent developments give substance to my claim. Firstly, regarding the rules of evidence. We are familiar with the creationist claim that ancient-earth geology and the related studies such as the fossil record are mere historical sciences, based on unproven and unprovable assumptions about unrepeatable past events, whereas the scientific method requires reproducibility. The errors here are obvious. The observations must, circumstances permitting, be reproducible, but the past event inferred need not be. For example, recent DNA evidence established that the father of the Archbishop of Canterbury was not the person named on his birth certificate. We can test this conclusion, to the highest scientific standards, by repeating the DNA test, but there is no need to beget additional Archbishops to prove our point. We do indeed assume, with Hutton, that the present is the key to the past, but this assumption is itself the result of repeated observation. We can see rain splashes in billion-year-old mudstone and rounded pebbles in ancient riverbeds. The resemblance between past and present is not, as creationists claim, an input into interpretation but an outcome of observation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Should colleges that teach creationism be accredited?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/should-colleges-that-teach.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Should colleges that teach creationism be accredited?" /><published>2021-03-05T14:45:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-03-05T14:45:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/should-colleges-that%20teach</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/should-colleges-that-teach.html">&lt;p&gt;Should sectarian religious colleges that teach creationism be accredited? Our colleague, Joshua Swamidass, writing in the Wall Street Journal, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/a-compromise-on-creationism-11614901537&quot;&gt;answers with a qualified yes&lt;/a&gt;. Specifically, the issue involves an accrediting agency known as Transnational Association of Christian Colleges and Schools, or Tracs. Tracs was established in the 1970’s to provide accreditation for colleges and universities that taught young-earth creationism and six literal days of creation, rather than modern science. Eventually, Tracs was recognized by the Council for Higher Education Accreditation, or CHEA, which is in essence an umbrella agency that accredits accrediting agencies. The recognition of Tracs by CHEA is up for renewal this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But should Tracs colleges be accredited? Should Tracs be recognized? Dr. Swamidass thinks so but would require stringent conditions. To oversimplify his position, he thinks that colleges should be allowed to teach creationism, but if Tracs is to accredit them, then they must agree to teach modern science as well. He writes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As a matter of academic freedom, scientists should tolerate institutions that teach creation science. But deviations from national norms in a science curriculum need to be prominently disclosed, tracked and reported. In practice, that means transcripts that clearly state which courses and degrees include creation science. Credit from courses that include creation science should not be used toward science degrees. Nor should they be eligible for transfer to secular institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Swamidass notes that the “public arena” is pluralistic and concludes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… Avoiding conflict by unconditionally renewing Tracs’ membership is an unacceptable approach. But we need a more constructive solution than simply excluding those with whom we disagree—even if they seem obviously wrong, as creationists do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The best solution is to respect Tracs institutions’ unique character while holding them to high academic standards. Insisting on policies of transparency and academic freedom might even lay the groundwork for change in future generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix&lt;/strong&gt;. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chea.org/node/80121&quot;&gt;CHEA Committee on Recognition meets virtually March 8-10&lt;/a&gt;. You may register for meetings at 9:00 a.m. EST on March 9 and 10 &lt;a href=&quot;https://us02web.zoom.us/meeting/register/tZYrfuusrz0oHtZlo3yk9oJ-4fMgNGn_xQ3F&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I understand that they will discuss Tracs the morning of March 10 and make a recommendation to the full board, which will decide the matter in October. They no longer accept new comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Should sectarian religious colleges that teach creationism be accredited? Our colleague, Joshua Swamidass, writing in the Wall Street Journal, answers with a qualified yes. Specifically, the issue involves an accrediting agency known as Transnational Association of Christian Colleges and Schools, or Tracs. Tracs was established in the 1970’s to provide accreditation for colleges and universities that taught young-earth creationism and six literal days of creation, rather than modern science. Eventually, Tracs was recognized by the Council for Higher Education Accreditation, or CHEA, which is in essence an umbrella agency that accredits accrediting agencies. The recognition of Tracs by CHEA is up for renewal this year. But should Tracs colleges be accredited? Should Tracs be recognized? Dr. Swamidass thinks so but would require stringent conditions. To oversimplify his position, he thinks that colleges should be allowed to teach creationism, but if Tracs is to accredit them, then they must agree to teach modern science as well. He writes, As a matter of academic freedom, scientists should tolerate institutions that teach creation science. But deviations from national norms in a science curriculum need to be prominently disclosed, tracked and reported. In practice, that means transcripts that clearly state which courses and degrees include creation science. Credit from courses that include creation science should not be used toward science degrees. Nor should they be eligible for transfer to secular institutions.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pink sky</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/pink-sky.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pink sky" /><published>2021-03-01T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-03-01T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/pink-sky</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/pink-sky.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Vivian Dullien&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Vivian_Pink_Sky_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pink sky&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;center&gt;Pink sky, February 20, 2021, approximately 7 a.m., Boulder, Colorado.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The photographer was facing west, a short time, possibly as much as an hour, after sunrise. The mountain is illuminated by direct sunlight, but you can see the shadow of the mountain on which Dr. Dullien is perched. The top of the mountain looks reddish, in part because the rocks are red and probably in part because the sun is reddish early in the morning. In the shadow, the mountain is bluish because, well, because shadows are bluish because they are illuminated by scattered light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why is the sky pink? The photograph of the mountain is sharp, so there is no aerosol to the west. I was stumped. For an answer, I checked in with Stephen Corfidi of the NOAA/NWS Storm Prediction Center in Norman, Oklahoma. I discovered Dr. Corfidi through his splendid post, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spc.noaa.gov/publications/corfidi/sunset/&quot;&gt;The Colors of Sunset and Twilight&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without going into detail, Dr. Corfidi thinks that the pink sky in the west is essentially a reflection of the red sky in the east, by the aerosols in the west. That is, the aerosols in the west are scattering (reflecting) some of the red light back eastward. The scattered light may be pink rather than red or red-orange if there are scatterers in the lower atmosphere, but that explanation gets a little messy. I am also going to guess that some blue sky resulting from direct sunlight peeks through and shifts the spectrum slightly to the blue, as well as possibly reducing the saturation of the back-scattered light.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Vivian Dullien. Pink sky, February 20, 2021, approximately 7 a.m., Boulder, Colorado. The photographer was facing west, a short time, possibly as much as an hour, after sunrise. The mountain is illuminated by direct sunlight, but you can see the shadow of the mountain on which Dr. Dullien is perched. The top of the mountain looks reddish, in part because the rocks are red and probably in part because the sun is reddish early in the morning. In the shadow, the mountain is bluish because, well, because shadows are bluish because they are illuminated by scattered light. But why is the sky pink? The photograph of the mountain is sharp, so there is no aerosol to the west. I was stumped. For an answer, I checked in with Stephen Corfidi of the NOAA/NWS Storm Prediction Center in Norman, Oklahoma. I discovered Dr. Corfidi through his splendid post, The Colors of Sunset and Twilight. Without going into detail, Dr. Corfidi thinks that the pink sky in the west is essentially a reflection of the red sky in the east, by the aerosols in the west. That is, the aerosols in the west are scattering (reflecting) some of the red light back eastward. The scattered light may be pink rather than red or red-orange if there are scatterers in the lower atmosphere, but that explanation gets a little messy. I am also going to guess that some blue sky resulting from direct sunlight peeks through and shifts the spectrum slightly to the blue, as well as possibly reducing the saturation of the back-scattered light.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Behe Meets the Peaceful Science Forum</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/behe-meets-peaceful.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Behe Meets the Peaceful Science Forum" /><published>2021-03-01T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-03-01T10:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/behe-meets-peaceful</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/behe-meets-peaceful.html">&lt;p&gt;Today Nathan H. Lents authored an &lt;a href=&quot;https://skepticalinquirer.org/2021/03/behe-bias-and-bears-oh-my/&quot;&gt;article in the &lt;em&gt;Skeptical Inquirer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, telling the story of how we responded to Michael Behe’s last book. Specifically, in February of 2019, Michael Behe published the third book in his trilogy critiquing evolutionary science, &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/363/6427/590&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Darwin Devolves&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this book, Dr. Behe argues that adaptive evolution proceeds almost entirely by degrading or damaging genes. Even when evolution increases the fitness of organisms, it does so by destroying information in the genome, so evolution is a self-limited process that cannot explain the diversity of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The month before his book was published, in January of 2019, Richard Lenski, Nathan Lents, and I published &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/363/6427/590&quot;&gt;an 800-word review that was critical of &lt;em&gt;Darwin Devolves&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; together in &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We expected a reaction from the Discovery Institute (DI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There certainly was a strong reaction. In the ensuing weeks, the DI published &lt;a href=&quot;https://discourse.peacefulscience.org/t/darwin-devolves-the-end-of-evolution/4270&quot;&gt;over seventeen articles&lt;/a&gt;. In just days, they flooded search engine results with thousands and thousands of words written in response to us. These articles were written by Michael Behe himself and other scientists associated with intelligent design (ID).* Some articles were unsigned without identifying any authors by name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sort of “squid ink” response to criticism is surely unorthodox, but do not underestimate its effectiveness. It performs a particular public theater, one that benefits the DI in its quest to promote ID. The cloud of articles attracts attention. The DI and Behe can claim to have “responded” to all the criticism directed at them. Most non-scientists cannot follow the details or assess the quality of the responses. Some might interpret the exchange as a legitimate debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This theater is normally where it ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facing this ink cloud, most scientists just do not have the time or platform to respond. Most scientists find the flurry of articles off-putting, but the public might see evolutionary scientists abandoning a scientific debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this &lt;em&gt;particular&lt;/em&gt; case, however, Dr. Lents and I anticipated what was coming. We were prepared. We did not have millions of dollars of funding and a team of staff.  But we did have the &lt;a href=&quot;https://discourse.peacefulscience.org&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Peaceful Science&lt;/em&gt; forum&lt;/a&gt;. That forum made all the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The forum is fairly small, with only 50 or so active participants each day, but it is closely watched by several people in the origins debate. It is also an open forum, where anyone can join the conversation, adding information, expertise, and questions. As an open forum, it is also chaotic and unpredictable, not fully under our control. Still, it proved to be an effective platform, turning the tables on the DI’s typical public theater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DI had a turnaround time of days, but the forum had a far quicker turnaround, in minutes at best and hours at worst. Many of our contributors are scientists, and that became important. Quick analysis and rebuttal of DI articles was possible, at the moment when the public was watching, and these rebuttals did not depend on just the three co-authors of the &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DI did technically respond to our review in &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;. On the forum, several of us explained in detail why their responses were not “responsive” and why they did not convince us. That response disrupted the story DI wanted to tell. In that way, we interrupted their theater and told a better story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is all true, but it doesn’t quite capture the beautiful experience we shared together on the forum. Here we were, a group of scientists with demanding day jobs, participating in several discussion threads and dissecting the science of polar bear evolution together. None of us had closely studied polar bear evolution before, and we may never have done so if not for &lt;em&gt;Darwin Devolves&lt;/em&gt;. So, on the forum, we held an &lt;em&gt;impromptu&lt;/em&gt; journal club on polar bear evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We began with the specific paper that Behe referenced in his book, but went beyond, doing some of our work with genomic data from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/&quot;&gt;National Center for Biotechnology Information&lt;/a&gt;. Each of us commented on each other’s contributions in real time, taking questions from the non-scientist readers as we went. There were doubts and disagreements, different expertise brought to bear, and even some messy discussion. The general public was able to look behind the curtain to see how scientists think through and work on questions like these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one afternoon and evening, about eight of us did the homework that Behe should have done on polar bear genomics. This wasn’t just a discussion, we were doing science, &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; science, the same way we would tackle our own research questions, while the public looked on and asked questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This stands as a stark contrast to the DI. They did not and do not transparently reveal deliberations or disagreement. Instead, they present a united front, never publicly contradicting or criticizing each other. That is not how science actually works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we dug in more and more, a plant biologist, Arthur Hunt, recognized several serious problems with Michael Behe’s analysis of polar bear genetics in his first chapter. What began as a forum post by Dr. Hunt was quickly upgraded to a full-fledged &lt;a href=&quot;https://discourse.peacefulscience.org/t/lents-and-hunt-behe-and-the-polar-bears-fat/4473&quot;&gt;blog post co-authored by Drs. Hunt and Lents&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Behe responded with a blog post of his own, in which he called us “incompetent.” Surprising all of us, though, he doubled down by presenting data from the polar bear paper in a very misleading way. Just as important, his discussion revealed fundamental misunderstanding of the algorithms used to predict the function of mutations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This exchange was really important for several reasons. It certainly made it very clear exactly where Dr. Behe’s reasoning had gone wrong in a prominent example in his book. He could have conceded this example, without necessarily destroying his whole argument. But he doubled down instead. If a scientist can’t correct &lt;a href=&quot;https://discourse.peacefulscience.org/t/three-misrepresentations-on-darwin-devolves-back-cover/5237&quot;&gt;ancillary mistakes&lt;/a&gt;, why would anyone trust him to correct more important errors?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visible on the forum are several entertaining subplots within the larger story, far too much to cover here. The twists and turns were wild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were more blog posts, of course, including a few from &lt;a href=&quot;https://telliamedrevisited.wordpress.com/2019/02/22/on-damaged-genes-and-polar-bears/&quot;&gt;Richard Lenski&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://peacefulscience.org/fair-hearing-behe/&quot;&gt;me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The never-ending debate over ID can tax anyone’s patience and often seems pedantic. But the quick back and forth of a forum was different. With other scientists to help us along, responding to the DI felt more like play than pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DI still uses this same strategy, so we will not be the last to face the cloud of ink. Next time you are caught in the cloud, come join us at &lt;em&gt;Peaceful Science&lt;/em&gt;. Together we might succeed turning the theater around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are lucky, we might even get to explore some interesting science together. It was polar bear evolution this time, but next time? I cannot wait to find out.  Whatever comes, I’m sure that we will have far more success tackling it together than alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;i&gt;On March 8th, this article was updated to correct an editing error, replacing a reference to “ID creationism” with a reference to “ID” alone.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joshua Swamidass</name></author><summary type="html">Today Nathan H. Lents authored an article in the Skeptical Inquirer, telling the story of how we responded to Michael Behe’s last book. Specifically, in February of 2019, Michael Behe published the third book in his trilogy critiquing evolutionary science, Darwin Devolves. In this book, Dr. Behe argues that adaptive evolution proceeds almost entirely by degrading or damaging genes. Even when evolution increases the fitness of organisms, it does so by destroying information in the genome, so evolution is a self-limited process that cannot explain the diversity of life. The month before his book was published, in January of 2019, Richard Lenski, Nathan Lents, and I published an 800-word review that was critical of Darwin Devolves together in Science. We expected a reaction from the Discovery Institute (DI).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Grant County Loses to Ark Park – Again</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/grant-county-loses.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grant County Loses to Ark Park – Again" /><published>2021-02-21T10:35:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-02-21T10:35:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/grant-county-loses</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/grant-county-loses.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Ark_Bow.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bow of Ark&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;small&gt;Photo courtesy of Dan Phelps.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Dan Phelps&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt; Posted with permission. Mr. Phelps sent this note to us by way of an e-mail.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is very old news, but I just learned of the resolution of the lawsuit Grant County Board of Education v. Ark Encounter. Unsurprisingly, the Grant County News (a very pro-Ark newspaper) did not cover the outcome of this case, although the paper had covered the initial lawsuit. The Louisville Courier-Journal also did a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.courier-journal.com/story/news/local/northeast/2019/08/27/ark-encounter-kentucky-pva-sued-for-undervalued-property/2128604001/&quot;&gt;story on the initial lawsuit&lt;/a&gt; on August 27, 2019. I discussed the situation with many people back in 2019, but was unaware of the final result until now, since it was unreported outside legal databases. The final decision (summarized briefly below) was not given until July 29, 2020, and was not widely reported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the school board lost the lawsuit in 2020, the following is moot, but shows yet another way the Ark has shortchanged the locals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of the lawsuit, Grant County education is, remarkably, going to be funded by taxes on the Ark at &lt;i&gt;less than 50 % of what the Ark itself claims it is worth&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2017/07/when-is-a-for-profit.html&quot;&gt;AiG/Crosswater Canyon&lt;/a&gt; claim the Ark is worth well more than $100 million on their Form 990’s submitted to the IRS. The &amp;gt;$100 million amount makes AiG/Ark look better when borrowing money from financial institutions. However, the local Property Value Administrators evaluate the Ark at only $48 million for taxes (and, further, the Ark does not pay the full property tax amount because of an agreement/incentive given them before the Ark was built). Thus the financially strapped local schools do not receive as much tax money as they would if the PVA had evaluated the Ark at what AiG says it is worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lexology.com/library/detail.aspx?g=c6699337-99ef-4799-8c91-885c952c39b4&quot;&gt;Grant County Board of Education v. Ark Encounter&lt;/a&gt;, LLC, No. 19-CI-00204 (Grant Cir. Ct. July 29, 2020, affirming, File No. K18-S-15, Final Order No. K-25927 (KCC May 31, 2019) – Property Tax – Standing to Appeal Assessment&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; 
The Board of Education (BOE) attempted to appeal PVA’s tax assessment of Ark Encounter property assessed at $48 million, alleging a value of $130 million. The KCC [Kentucky Circuit Court] dismissed the BOE’s appeal for lack of standing under the statute since the BOE was not a taxpayer or an aggrieved party, while also noting that historically this has never been done. On appeal to the Grant County Circuit Court, the parties entered an Agreed Order affirming the Final Order of the KCC.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photo courtesy of Dan Phelps. By Dan Phelps. Posted with permission. Mr. Phelps sent this note to us by way of an e-mail. This is very old news, but I just learned of the resolution of the lawsuit Grant County Board of Education v. Ark Encounter. Unsurprisingly, the Grant County News (a very pro-Ark newspaper) did not cover the outcome of this case, although the paper had covered the initial lawsuit. The Louisville Courier-Journal also did a story on the initial lawsuit on August 27, 2019. I discussed the situation with many people back in 2019, but was unaware of the final result until now, since it was unreported outside legal databases. The final decision (summarized briefly below) was not given until July 29, 2020, and was not widely reported. Since the school board lost the lawsuit in 2020, the following is moot, but shows yet another way the Ark has shortchanged the locals.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Was the origin of cave paintings in the stratosphere?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/origin-of-cave-paintings.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Was the origin of cave paintings in the stratosphere?" /><published>2021-02-20T08:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-02-20T08:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/origin-of-cave-paintings</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/origin-of-cave-paintings.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Red_Hands_Cave001_Wikimedia_600.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Aboriginal hand stencils, Red Hands Cave, Blue Mountains NP, NSW, Australia. &lt;small&gt;Sardaka, own work (Kodachrome slide scanned at 6400). Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 4.0 International.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A team from the University of New South Wales in Australia has discovered a very ancient and well-preserved log that they used to &lt;a href=&quot;https://phys.org/news/2021-02-ancient-relic-earth-history-years.html&quot;&gt;date the last reversal of the earth’s magnetic field very precisely to 42 ka (thousand years) ago&lt;/a&gt;. Using climate modelling and whatnot, they calculated a detailed timescale and deduced that the magnetic-field reversal – known as the Laschamps Excursion – coincided with high solar activity and may have caused glaciation in North America and a relatively sudden change in the climate in Australia, which may in turn have led to the extinction of the Neanderthals and some early modern human cultures, and of megafaunas in Australia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the field reversal occurred 42 millennia ago, the team dubbed it the Adams Event, in honor of Douglas Adams, who wrote in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Hitchhiker%27s_Guide_to_the_Galaxy&quot;&gt;Hitchhiker’s Guide to the Galaxy&lt;/a&gt; that the answer to life, the universe, and everything is 42.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very briefly, the team used the trunk of an ancient &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agathis_australis&quot;&gt; kauri tree&lt;/a&gt;, which had been well preserved in a bog, carbon-dated each ring, and correlated the results with other, existing data. As &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/371/6531/766.full&quot;&gt;described in a news article in Science&lt;/a&gt;, they applied a climate model and, very briefly, deduced that the excess high-energy radiation from the sun depleted the ozone layer and caused high-altitude cooling, which in turn altered the wind patterns and thus the climate near the surface. The change of climate caused the extinctions noted above. (You may find the technical article &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/371/6531/811&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I read portions of it, but not surprisingly I found that it was not just Greek to me, but technical Greek to me.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What caught my eye, however, was the claim that the field reversal somehow brought about the origin of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cave_painting&quot;&gt;cave paintings&lt;/a&gt; in Eurasia. In brief, the argument is that the high UV levels caused by the destruction of the ozone layer forced people into caves. Indeed, they argue that the handprints signal that the red ochre used for the paintings may also have been used as sunscreen. Well, IANAX[pert], but Wikipedia claims that a red hand stencil was made by a Neanderthal 64 ka ago. Their dates for modern humans are indeed in their range of 42 ka ago, or less. Still, it is hard to conceive that humans did not discover caves until they got severely sunburned, and I am at least partly sympathetic with those who told &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; that the study may be too speculative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Vivian Dullien directed my attention to the phys.org article. Nothing in this brief report is her fault.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Aboriginal hand stencils, Red Hands Cave, Blue Mountains NP, NSW, Australia. Sardaka, own work (Kodachrome slide scanned at 6400). Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 4.0 International. A team from the University of New South Wales in Australia has discovered a very ancient and well-preserved log that they used to date the last reversal of the earth’s magnetic field very precisely to 42 ka (thousand years) ago. Using climate modelling and whatnot, they calculated a detailed timescale and deduced that the magnetic-field reversal – known as the Laschamps Excursion – coincided with high solar activity and may have caused glaciation in North America and a relatively sudden change in the climate in Australia, which may in turn have led to the extinction of the Neanderthals and some early modern human cultures, and of megafaunas in Australia. Because the field reversal occurred 42 millennia ago, the team dubbed it the Adams Event, in honor of Douglas Adams, who wrote in Hitchhiker’s Guide to the Galaxy that the answer to life, the universe, and everything is 42.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Report: Are jellyfish so dumb that their evolution needed help?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/Are-jellyfish-so-dumb.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Report: Are jellyfish so dumb that their evolution needed help?" /><published>2021-02-19T12:01:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-02-19T12:01:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/Are-jellyfish-so-dumb</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/Are-jellyfish-so-dumb.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/AureliaEkranoplan.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;The moon jelly &lt;em&gt;Aurelia aurita&lt;/em&gt; and a Russian Soviet-era Ekranoplan ground-effect craft, the A-90 Orlyonok.  Both images courtesy of Wikimedia Commons under the Creative Commons license.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Posts labeled “Report:” will discuss material posted on other sites, particularly ones that contain silly arguments&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting report in this paper:&lt;br /&gt;
Gemmell, Brad J., Kevin T. Du Clos, Sean P. Colin, Kelly R. Sutherland and John H. Costello.  2021. The most efficient metazoan swimmer creates a ‘virtual wall’ to enhance performance.  Proceedings of the Royal Society B (Biological Sciences)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2020.2494&quot;&gt;http://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2020.2494&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
argues that jellyfish use a subtle fluid dynamic effect, the ‘ground effect’, to swim efficiently.  The suthors used sophisticated monitoring techniques to measure the movement of water, as well as computationally intensive calculation methods of fluid dynamics.  They found that when the body of the common Moon Jelly &lt;em&gt;Aurelia aurita&lt;/em&gt; contracts, it creates two vortices, each like a smoke ring, but rotating in opposite directions.  Together they function as a ‘virtual wall’ against which water is pushed.  The result is extraordinarily efficient swimming.  The paper is open access and may be read at the link above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ground effect has been known in fluid dynamics since the 1920s, when pilots reported that their planes flew more efficiently when close to the ground, an effect due to the air beneath the wings being compressed by being squeezed between the wings and the ground.  A number of countries have tested vehicles used the ground effect to “fly” just above the surface of the ocean.  The most active development program was the models of “ekranoplans” produced in Soviet-era Russia in the 1970s and 1980s, one of which you will see above.  The model shown there was also capable of a limited amount of actual flight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as astonishing as jellyfish are, and as surprising as ground-effect vehicles are,
they have inspired an actual flight of fancy.  This was by the ever-astonishing
Denyse O’Leary, who writes for the ID advocacy blog Uncommon Descent.  Her
argument needs to be quoted – you would not believe me if I summarized it …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O’Leary, who writes for Uncommon Descent as “News”, is an expert at invective.  A common trope of her reports is that science is wrong, a position that she backs up with frequent reports on fudged data, failures of peer review, and failure of further work to confirm initial reports.  This time, for a change, she is merely implying that scientists have failed to notice a dramatic implication of some work – that the feature could not be explained by ordinary evolutionary mechanisms but must imply that there was Intelligent Design.
After citing a report on jellyfish and ground effect and indicating that the original paper is open access, she simply says &lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/jellyfish-enhance-their-skills-by-building-a-virtual-wall/&quot;&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Either jellyfish are smarter than we think or there is design in nature.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is astonishing – I am glad I am not a coffee drinker because I would have had to replace my computer after reading it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are only two comments on that post.  True to the form of UD commenters, who are the ultimate ID cheering section, one from commenter Mahuna says&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; ....
OK, clearly some INDIVIDUAL jellyfish did NOT invent this technique on a slow afternoon and then TEACH it to his bros. It is MUCH more likely, since ALL jellyfish know how to do this, that the skill was INSTALLED way back when the Designer was messing around with the pre-production prototypes. ....
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;while commenter Querius says “Yes, indeed!”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently ID advocates, or at least these ones, cannot understand how natural selection could favor an adaptation that makes use of a sophisticated concept of physics or engineering &lt;em&gt;unless the organism understands the physics&lt;/em&gt;.  I suppose that the fact that trees use capillary action to bring water from the roots up to the leaves must also be evidence for ID, since trees scarcely understand the relevant physics.  Years ago, I saw an ID advocate argue that it was hard to explain how the colors of some birds could come from diffraction of light &lt;em&gt;since birds do not understand the concept of diffraction&lt;/em&gt;.  (I wish I had kept a link to that quote).  Likewise all the adaptations of single-celled protists must be the result of Design, since protists understand so little chemistry and physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s facepalm time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A slightly off-topic aside:&lt;/em&gt; The ‘flight’ of ground-effect vehicles is related to the way hovercraft move across water.  I’ve experienced that myself.  In 1983 I crossed the English Channel on the hovercraft ferry from Boulogne, France to Dover, England.  The craft rested on pillars rising from a concrete pad which was at the top end of a smooth, sloping beach.  After we boarded it on a gangway and seated ourselves in rows of airline-style seats, the engines started up.  The fans that blew air down inside the skirt of the craft made it rise up a few feet, and it started to slide down the beach, just barely touching the sand.  It came to the water and started out across it, driven by the propellers mounted above the craft.  That was the fun part.  Unfortunately the motion of the hovercraft consisted of riding up the front of a wave, and then slamming down once past it.  This kicked up a lot of spray, which rose in a cloud around the craft, coating the windows so that one could not see much.  It also leaked in at one place in the plexiglas canopy.  The result was an uncomfortable ride, though it did get to Dover in only about an hour.  At the Dover end it drove up onto the beach, riding above it as it did on the water, until it settled onto its supports there.  There is still one hovercraft ferry service in England, between Southsea in Portsmouth and the Isle of Wight.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">The moon jelly Aurelia aurita and a Russian Soviet-era Ekranoplan ground-effect craft, the A-90 Orlyonok. Both images courtesy of Wikimedia Commons under the Creative Commons license. Posts labeled “Report:” will discuss material posted on other sites, particularly ones that contain silly arguments An interesting report in this paper: Gemmell, Brad J., Kevin T. Du Clos, Sean P. Colin, Kelly R. Sutherland and John H. Costello. 2021. The most efficient metazoan swimmer creates a ‘virtual wall’ to enhance performance. Proceedings of the Royal Society B (Biological Sciences) http://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2020.2494 argues that jellyfish use a subtle fluid dynamic effect, the ‘ground effect’, to swim efficiently. The suthors used sophisticated monitoring techniques to measure the movement of water, as well as computationally intensive calculation methods of fluid dynamics. They found that when the body of the common Moon Jelly Aurelia aurita contracts, it creates two vortices, each like a smoke ring, but rotating in opposite directions. Together they function as a ‘virtual wall’ against which water is pushed. The result is extraordinarily efficient swimming. The paper is open access and may be read at the link above. The ground effect has been known in fluid dynamics since the 1920s, when pilots reported that their planes flew more efficiently when close to the ground, an effect due to the air beneath the wings being compressed by being squeezed between the wings and the ground. A number of countries have tested vehicles used the ground effect to “fly” just above the surface of the ocean. The most active development program was the models of “ekranoplans” produced in Soviet-era Russia in the 1970s and 1980s, one of which you will see above. The model shown there was also capable of a limited amount of actual flight. But as astonishing as jellyfish are, and as surprising as ground-effect vehicles are, they have inspired an actual flight of fancy. This was by the ever-astonishing Denyse O’Leary, who writes for the ID advocacy blog Uncommon Descent. Her argument needs to be quoted – you would not believe me if I summarized it …</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Darwin's Window</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/darwins-window.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Darwin's Window" /><published>2021-02-15T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-02-15T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/darwins-window</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/darwins-window.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;David Rintoul&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Rintoul.darwins_window_4976.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Darwin's Window&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mr. Rintoul writes, &quot;Darwin's Window is the local name for a sea arch in an ancient cinder/ash cone known as Cerro Brujo (Hill of the Sorcerer), on the northwest-facing side of San Cristobal in the Galapagos Archipelago. The view through this arch includes three common noddies (&lt;i&gt;Anous stolidus&lt;/i&gt;, aka brown noddy) as well as a formation known as Kicker Rock. Darwin landed on San Cristobal during his time in the Galapagos, and this formation (along with Darwin's Bay, where he allegedly landed) is named in his honor. More information at http://www.galapagos.org/about_galapagos/about-galapagos/the-islands/san-cristobal/.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are posting this picture now in honor of &lt;a href=&quot;https://darwinday.org/events/?action=tribe_list&amp;amp;tribe_paged=1&amp;amp;tribe_event_display=list&amp;amp;tribe-bar-date=2021-02-01&quot;&gt;Darwin Day&lt;/a&gt;, which was Friday, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://theclergyletterproject.org/rel_evolution_weekend_2021.html&quot;&gt;Evolution Weekend&lt;/a&gt;. There were not a great many events, presumably due to the pandemic, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://darwinday.org/events/?action=tribe_list&amp;amp;tribe_paged=1&amp;amp;tribe_event_display=list&amp;amp;tribe-bar-date=2022-02-01&quot;&gt;wait till next year&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by David Rintoul. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Mr. Rintoul writes, &quot;Darwin's Window is the local name for a sea arch in an ancient cinder/ash cone known as Cerro Brujo (Hill of the Sorcerer), on the northwest-facing side of San Cristobal in the Galapagos Archipelago. The view through this arch includes three common noddies (Anous stolidus, aka brown noddy) as well as a formation known as Kicker Rock. Darwin landed on San Cristobal during his time in the Galapagos, and this formation (along with Darwin's Bay, where he allegedly landed) is named in his honor. More information at http://www.galapagos.org/about_galapagos/about-galapagos/the-islands/san-cristobal/.&quot; We are posting this picture now in honor of Darwin Day, which was Friday, and Evolution Weekend. There were not a great many events, presumably due to the pandemic, but wait till next year!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Does the genetic code reveal a Wow! signal? A team of scientists claim evidence for &quot;intelligent design&quot;</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/genetic-code-wow-signal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does the genetic code reveal a Wow! signal? A team of scientists claim evidence for &quot;intelligent design&quot;" /><published>2021-02-07T16:28:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-02-07T16:28:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/genetic-code-wow-signal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/genetic-code-wow-signal.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Neukamm_Wow_signal.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wow! sig-nal&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term “Wow! signal” represents a decade-long mystery in astronomy: In 1977, the astrophysicist Jerry Ehman received a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wow!_signal&quot;&gt;strong narrowband radio signal&lt;/a&gt; on the frequency of the 21 cm line of hydrogen with the gigantic big-ear radio telescope in Delaware in the US state of Ohio. There seemed to be no natural explanation for the persisting 72 s signal from the Sagittarius constellation, which was 30 standard deviations above the background noise. The profile of the strong, narrow-band signal corresponds to that of a communication antenna. Its discoverer highlighted the signal on the printout with a red circle and added an expression of astonishment by noting “Wow!” In the period that followed, there was a lively debate among experts as to whether it was an artificially generated or a natural signal. Although objects like pul-sars seem to be a possible source, the controversy continues to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, a team of Kazakh scientists published a &lt;a href=&quot;www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0019103513000791&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; claiming to have discovered a Wow! signal in the genetic code of living beings. The code structure, so they claimed, is statistically so striking that its origin could be explained only by the presumption of an intelligent actor. The paper, published in Icarus, was somewhat off-topic since Icarus is a journal for planetary science rather than molecular biology or evolution. Since then, the paper has been celebrated as evidence for the extraterrestrial origin of the genetic code by support-ers of ancient astronauts and by the intelligent design movement; see, for example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2013/03/a_wow_signal_of/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/extraterrestrial-life-genetic-code-as-wow-signal/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discovery.org/id/peer-review/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, as well as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.si-journal.de/index2.php?artikel=jg22/heft2/sij222-2.html&quot;&gt;this arti-cle&lt;/a&gt; in a German creationist journal. What’s it all about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ominous divisor 37 as a design signal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors of the paper are the mathematician Vladimir shCherbak from Al-Farabi University in Kazakhstan and the physicist Maxim Makukov from the Fessenkow Astrophysical Institute. The publisher of Icarus, a refereed journal, is the American Astronomical Society (AAS), an association of professional astronomers. The journal is mainly de-voted to initial publications in planetary scienceand is neither esoteric nor religious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to track down the alleged Wow! signal, shCherbak and Makukov first divided the 20 genetically encoded amino acids into two groups: In the first group, they listed all amino acids that are sufficiently defined by the first two bases of a base triplet (meaning that any change of the third base would not change the amino acid) (Fig. 1). A base triplet or codon is a sequence of three bases (“letters”) on the genetic molecule DNA (or on the RNA) coding for a specific amino acid. The authors placed the remaining amino acids into a second group. Then they calculated the nucleon number (molecular weight) of every amino acid in both groups, as well as the nucleon number of every amino acid basic structure (“block nucleons”) and side chain. Finally, they sorted the numbers and added them up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this operation, shCherbak and Makukov came across numerical ratios in which the divisor 37 appears again and again: In the first group, the nucleon sum of all side chains is 333 (= 37 x 3&lt;sup&gt;²&lt;/sup&gt;), that of all “block nucleons” 592 (= 37 x 4&lt;sup&gt;²&lt;/sup&gt;), and the total 925 = (37 x 5&lt;sup&gt;²&lt;/sup&gt;). Moreover: “With 037 cancelled out, this leads to 3&lt;sup&gt;²&lt;/sup&gt; + 4&lt;sup&gt;²&lt;/sup&gt; = 5&lt;sup&gt;²&lt;/sup&gt; – representation of the Egyptian triangle…” (p. 6). The number 37 also appears in the second group; the total number of nucleons in the amino acids is 1110 (= 30 x 37).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Neukamm_Figure_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Side chains&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Fig. 1. Structure of the side chains of those eight amino acids which are clearly defined by their first two codon bases. Side chains and their nucleon numbers (molecular weights) are shown in ascending order. The total is 333. However, this requires targeted manipulation (here: with proline). Further explanation in the text.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;shCherbak and Makukov discuss various other examples using different sorting and exchange operations. Another one is discussed in Fig. 2. In all those cases, the divisor 37 appears prominently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Neukamm_Figure_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Codons&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fig. 2 There are 24 codons, each with three very different bases (A, T, G, and C). shCherbak and Makukov arranged those codons in such a way that their nucleic bases are interchanged according to certain rules: Within each “block” of 3 codons, the first nucleic base is shifted from one row to the next one onto the third position. From block to block, A is exchanged for G, and T for C (and vice versa). On the left and right column, the codons are arranged mirror-imaged. Next to each codon, it is noted which amino acid it codes for, and the molecular weight of the side chains and whole molecules is noted. In total, there are numbers that are completely divisible by 37. Source: shCherbak and Makukov, p. 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the authors, the frequent appearance of “37”, the emergence of “Egyptian triangles”, etc. are far beyond the statistical significance of randomly generated patterns. Thus, these appearances cannot  be explained by natural processes since they are not relevant for biological function. The number “0” is also represented, as a corresponding symbol for start/stop codons. The authors claim: “Nature is indifferent to numerical languages contrived by intelligence to represent quantities, including zero”. Such a “privileged numerical system is therefore a reliable sign of artificiality” (p. 4). Ergo: “Whatever the actual reason behind the decimal system in the code, it appears that it was invented outside the solar system already several billions [of] years ago” (p. 8).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A method reminiscent of the Bible Code&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Neukamm_Figure_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bible code&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Fig. 3. The Bible Code. For detailed explanations see text. &lt;small&gt;Source: https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bibelcode. See  also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/No-Sense-Obligation-Religion-Impersonal/dp/0759610894/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, pp. 102-104.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/UFOs-Chemtrails-Aliens-What-Science/dp/025302692X&quot;&gt;Prothero and Callahan&lt;/a&gt; (p. 127) note that the approach of the authors shows clear similarities with the method of the so-called Bible code, which is as also called &lt;em&gt;equidistant letter spacing&lt;/em&gt; (ELS). It serves to track down presumed “hidden messages” and prophecies in biblical texts. How does this method work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To recognize the “message”, a rectangular grid with a constant but arbitrary number of columns and rows is placed over the text, and a freely selectable number of letters is skipped from a starting point in the horizontal and vertical direction. Then meaningful words or word constellations are sought (Fig. 3). According to this method, world historical events such as the Holocaust or 9/11 are said to have been predicted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is: Since the dimensions of the grid and the number of letters skipped when reading were freely defined, the “researchers”  most likely would have come up with different messages, had they chosen the width of the grid differently. Nobody read and verified relevant information that had not already been known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prothero and Callahan criticize the fact that the authors use the same subjective method to track down the presumed design signals in the genetic code. shCherbak and Makukov have also freely (meaning: arbitrarily) defined the logical criteria for dividing the amino acids into certain groups as well as the transformation and exchange rules according to which the “magic” sums appear. For example, if we would exchange A for T and G for C (rather than A for G and T for C) in Fig. 2, we would receive completely different sums and divisors. In other words, the authors get only results that they have already produced by their own rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interpretation of start/stop codons as a symbol for numerical 0 is just as arbitrary. And of course, if we interpret start and stop codons as numerical 0 on metaphysical grounds, it is not surprising, that we  “discover” a “privileged numerical system”, including 0. Garbage in, garbage out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice of molecular weights (nucleon numbers) of side chains, basic structures and whole molecules as an object of investigation is also arbitrary. It is as arbitrary as the determination of a certain number of letters to be skipped in the Bible code, which is needed to find meaningful word combinations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design signals generated by targeted manipulations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is another, more serious objection to shCherbak and Makukov’s method, which Prothero and Callahan do not mention: It works frequently only by a trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amino acid proline does not fit into the scheme, so the authors modify it. To do so, they formally remove an H atom from the side chain of proline and transfer it to the secondary amino group (see Fig. 4). This makes proline the primary amino acid. The purpose of this operation is to formally “standardize” the basic structures of all amino acids, as the authors mention. This is because proline is the only secondary amino acid in the genetic code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But “standardizing” means nothing other than purposefully changing facts to introduce the divisor 37 through the back door! In contrast to the other amino acids, the molecular weight of the proline basic structure (73) cannot be divided exactly by 37. This also applies, as discussed in Fig. 1, for the nucleon sum of the side chains. That undesirable fact only changes through the appropriate manipulation of numbers. Without it, the authors would never come up with the “magic” numbers 333 and 592. Strictly speaking, none of the examples in which the amino acid proline occurs, works “smoothly” in the sense of the authors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make matters worse, this formal H transfer would lead to an impossible molecule (see Fig. 4). The authors even implicitly admit this by stating that the H transfer in proline “can be simulated only in the mind of a recipient to achieve the array of amino acids with uniform structure. Such nucleon transfer thus appears artificial”. However, exactly this artificial operation, so the authors continue, “seems to be its destination: it protects the patterns from any natural explanation” (p. 3). In other words, targeted manipulations generate artifacts whose origin logically eludes any natural explanation! If that’s not a fatal circular argument, what then?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Neukamm_Figure_4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Clever trick&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Fig. 4 The clever trick of “standardizing” the nucleon number of proline: The authors formally transfer an H atom from the side chain to the secondary amino group (A). Thus, the molecule becomes the primary amino acid with a basic structure whose mo-lecular weight (74) is completely divisible by 37. Also, the side chain is open and has the “desired” molecular weight of 41 (B). But the molecule would now be in a chemically impossible state with an electron sextet on the terminal carbon atom (indicated by the two dots). Only on the basis of this extremely unstable carbene molecule, the nucleon sums are completely divisible by 37 (Fig. 1). Correctly, the authors should either have added two H atoms to the side chain – or left it as it is. By the way: They could have removed an H atom also from the alpha C atom of the basic structure (C, D). In none of these cases their method would have worked. This shows that the alleged “Wow! signal” is just an artifact of the authors. Without their manipulation, there would be no “magic” numbers.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The power of numerology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, it is not surprising that in the (numerical) cosmos, which functions under certain rules and laws, certain order patterns like Egyptian triangles, golden triangles, Fibonacci numbers, ascending numerical sequences, prime numbers, etc. can be found which, as brute facts, neither allow an explanation nor even demand one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s, for example, look at the natural three-digit numbers with identical digits and form their digit sums (111 = 3, 222 = 6, 333 = 9, etc.). If we divide these numbers by their digit sums, the result is in all cases … 37. Another example: 81 stable chemical elements exist. 81 may be represented formally as a “prime number cross” (3 x 3&lt;sup&gt;³&lt;/sup&gt;). The reciprocal of the number 81 can in turn be approximated by the decimal fraction 0.0123456789 (10) (11) (12)… (here, 10, 11, 12 are the next digits; the parentheses are for convenience). And if we look at Romanesco broccoli, we’ll see that its appearance is strictly mathematical: Its conical turrets are copies of the entire inflorescence, which is known as self-similarity or a fractal structure. Each of those turrets is also a so-called Fibonacci spiral, a sequence of numbers that ensures that one turret of vegetables never grows vertically above another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why should these pretty patterns, of which we could construct endless examples, represent design signals? Does it even make sense to ask how probable their “accidental” emergence is? Why 37 rather than 38 or 42? Why not π or e? Why not an alternating sequence of numbers? What if the laws were different? And what message are the “signals” supposed to convey? Shall we assume that a creator liked to line the world up with the number 3 or π and to introduce Fibonacci numbers into the cosmos? Such metaphysical interpretations cannot seriously pass as empirical arguments! All such patterns have no more objectively recognizable meaning (or semantic content) than the “Egyptian triangle” or the “appearance” of 37 in the genetic code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least: The more often we try out different mathematical transformations, the higher is the likelihood to find any mathematical pattern. We neither know the total set of possibilities nor how many unsuccessful trials the authors made to find their patterns. We only know that the number of potential mathematical transformations is infinite. Any number of counterexamples without any pattern can be constructed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a word, the approach of shCherbak and Makukov is pure number mysticism. They could only read an intelligent pattern from those numbers after they inserted it into the genetic code by convenient operations, targeted manipulations and reckless interpretations. Therefore, we have to agree with Prothero and Callahan (p. 128), who summarize:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The result is a paper that, despite the impressive credentials of its authors and the soundness of the journal it was printed in, is essentially without substance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mathematician Underwood Dudley (1997) shows in his book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Numerology-What-Pythagoras-Wrought-Spectrum/dp/0883855240&quot;&gt;Numerology&lt;/a&gt; in an entertaining way what nonsense can be done with such number games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Martin Neukamm is a German chemist and managing editor of the “AG Evolutionsbiologie” (www.ag-evolutionsbiologie.de), a German scientific association that deals with evolutionary biology and creationism. He has published various articles and books on evolution and creationism in the German language. Matt Young is the moderator of this post.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Neukamm</name></author><summary type="html">The term “Wow! signal” represents a decade-long mystery in astronomy: In 1977, the astrophysicist Jerry Ehman received a strong narrowband radio signal on the frequency of the 21 cm line of hydrogen with the gigantic big-ear radio telescope in Delaware in the US state of Ohio. There seemed to be no natural explanation for the persisting 72 s signal from the Sagittarius constellation, which was 30 standard deviations above the background noise. The profile of the strong, narrow-band signal corresponds to that of a communication antenna. Its discoverer highlighted the signal on the printout with a red circle and added an expression of astonishment by noting “Wow!” In the period that followed, there was a lively debate among experts as to whether it was an artificially generated or a natural signal. Although objects like pul-sars seem to be a possible source, the controversy continues to this day. A few years ago, a team of Kazakh scientists published a paper claiming to have discovered a Wow! signal in the genetic code of living beings. The code structure, so they claimed, is statistically so striking that its origin could be explained only by the presumption of an intelligent actor. The paper, published in Icarus, was somewhat off-topic since Icarus is a journal for planetary science rather than molecular biology or evolution. Since then, the paper has been celebrated as evidence for the extraterrestrial origin of the genetic code by support-ers of ancient astronauts and by the intelligent design movement; see, for example, here, here, and here, as well as this arti-cle in a German creationist journal. What’s it all about?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">We Believe in Dinosaurs Not on YouTube</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/we-believe-in-dinosaurs-on-youtube.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We Believe in Dinosaurs Not on YouTube" /><published>2021-02-07T10:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-02-07T10:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/we-believe-in-dinosaurs-on-youtube</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/we-believe-in-dinosaurs-on-youtube.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Dinosaurs_Amazon_Ratings.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Amazon ratings&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Amazon ratings of &quot;We believe in Dinosaurs,&quot; showing unusual bimodal distribution.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;strike&gt;We received an e-mail today from our penpal Dan Phelps, informing us that the Independent Lens version of We Believe In Dinosaurs is available on YouTube [link removed]. Mr. Phelps asks that we&lt;/strike&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh dear, we jumped on this message too fast. Mr. Phelps now tells us,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It looks as if the site is a well-done fake. Please don’t promote it. The copyright people at the distribution company are on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may still, however,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[c]onsider &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/aw/reviews/B081S9Y898&quot;&gt;rating it on Amazon&lt;/a&gt; since creationists have been leaving inaccurate and negative reviews there misrepresenting the film indicating they probably didn’t watch it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of them obviously watched it, some plainly did not, and some read into it what they wanted to see. I resisted reviewing the film on Amazon until over the summer, when I saw a spate of 1-star reviews by people who had plainly not seen the film. In case anyone is interested, I will post my own 5-star Amazon review, posted on August 25, below the fold:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I initially decided not to review this splendid movie. I am penpals with two of its principal subjects, David MacMillan and Dan Phelps, and was peripherally involved with promoting the movie, as when I detailed its progress in The Panda’s Thumb blog. The film has been well received by critics and initially earned a respectable number of 5-star reviews here [on Amazon]. Since early July, however, a number of 1-star reviews began to show up, many of them one-liners by people who had probably never seen the film and others that are simply irrelevant to the actual film. In short, these reviews suggest the possibility of a coordinated effort to lower the average rating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I thought that the film was an excellent documentary, clear and evenhanded. The film shows how hard and irrefutable evidence forced David MacMillan to evolve from a young-earth creationist and a charter member of the Creation Museum to a scientist, though he remains a committed Christian (contrary to at least one review). Doug Henderson, a lead designer for the Ark is a dedicated creationist who seems to think that he is doing God’s work; he is shown with at least as much sympathy as is given to MacMillan. So are the merchants of downtown Williamstown, which was left desolate after the Ark opened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This movie is not a hatchet job on the Ark Encounter, creationism, Ken Ham, Christianity, or anything else. It is not a liberal screed, much less an atheist screed. It is a fair depiction of the design, construction, and (shall we say) chaotic opening of the Ark. You may buy it or rent it here, or see it in slightly abridged form on PBS’s Independent Lens, provided that you are a member of a local station. Watch it for yourself and do not believe any overwrought depictions in 1-star reviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Revised 2:10 MST.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Amazon ratings of &quot;We believe in Dinosaurs,&quot; showing unusual bimodal distribution. We received an e-mail today from our penpal Dan Phelps, informing us that the Independent Lens version of We Believe In Dinosaurs is available on YouTube [link removed]. Mr. Phelps asks that we Oh dear, we jumped on this message too fast. Mr. Phelps now tells us, It looks as if the site is a well-done fake. Please don’t promote it. The copyright people at the distribution company are on it. You may still, however, [c]onsider rating it on Amazon since creationists have been leaving inaccurate and negative reviews there misrepresenting the film indicating they probably didn’t watch it. Some of them obviously watched it, some plainly did not, and some read into it what they wanted to see. I resisted reviewing the film on Amazon until over the summer, when I saw a spate of 1-star reviews by people who had plainly not seen the film. In case anyone is interested, I will post my own 5-star Amazon review, posted on August 25, below the fold:</summary></entry></feed>