<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-01T00:49:28-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Science bridges divides</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/science-bridges-divides.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science bridges divides" /><published>2020-12-29T13:05:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-12-29T13:05:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/science-bridges-divides</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/science-bridges-divides.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Lents_Swamidass_1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Venn diagram&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science bridges divides. That is the lesson enunciated by our colleagues &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nathan_H._Lents&quot;&gt;Nathan Lents&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://swami.wustl.edu/&quot;&gt;Joshua Swamidass&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stltoday.com/opinion/columnists/nathan-h-lents-and-s-joshua-swamidass-the-lesson-of-kitzmiller-science-bridges-divides/article_829435cc-154f-5940-bf26-2456da663965.html&quot;&gt;St. Louis Post-Dispatch&lt;/a&gt; yesterday and earlier in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://triblive.com/opinion/nathan-lents-and-dr-s-joshua-swamidass-science-bridges-divides-for-a-better-world/&quot;&gt;Pittsburgh Tribune-Review&lt;/a&gt; on December 18.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The occasion? The fifteenth &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/where-were-you.html&quot;&gt;anniversary&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2005/12/unconstitutiona.html&quot;&gt;Dover decision&lt;/a&gt; by District Court Judge John E. Jones III “that it is unconstitutional to teach ID as an alternative to evolution in a public school science classroom.” December 20 has come to be known as Kitzmas, and the Panda’s Thumb &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2005/12/unconstitutiona.html&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; by PZ Myers may be the &lt;a href=&quot;http://itre.cis.upenn.edu/~myl/languagelog/archives/002718.html&quot;&gt;first use of that term&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is unusual about the Lents-Swamidass collaboration is that Prof. Lents is a professed atheist and Prof. Swamidass is an evangelical Christian (and indeed the proprietor of the blog &lt;a href=&quot;https://peacefulscience.org/&quot;&gt;Peaceful Science&lt;/a&gt; and the author of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B07V4TBL5Z/&quot;&gt;The Genealogical Adam and Eve&lt;/a&gt;). Besides their own collaboration, which has led to speaking engagements “with audiences from the ‘liberal elites’ at Columbia University to the ‘biblically conservative’ at Concordia University,” they note the collaboration between Catholic biologist Kenneth Miller and “non-believer” Barbara Forrest at Dover. They further point out that, a year or so after the Dover decision, Francis Collins published his book &lt;em&gt;The Language of God&lt;/em&gt;, in which Dr. Collins attempts to reconcile his Christian belief with his acceptance of evolutionary science. (We discussed &lt;em&gt;The Language of God&lt;/em&gt; on Panda’s Thumb &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2009/07/francis-collins-3.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, when Dr. Collins was nominated to be director of the National Institutes of Health.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drs. Lents and Swamidass collaborated with Richard E. Lenski to pen a negative &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/363/6427/590.full&quot;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; of the book &lt;em&gt;Darwin Devolves&lt;/em&gt; by Michael Behe in the journal &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; (behind a paywall, incidentally). They claim in the &lt;em&gt;Post-Dispatch&lt;/em&gt; article that they are risking their reputations by collaborating with each other. That may be so, but, as an accommodationist myself, I can only support their collaboration. Atheists need to understand that some people have a need to believe in a force greater than ourselves, and fundamentalists (for want of a better, general term) need to accept the findings of modern science and develop ways to integrate them with their religious beliefs. If collaborations such as Lents-Swamidass will encourage atheists to deal better with their religious friends, and fundamentalists to deal better with the reality of science, then I am all for such collaborations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Science bridges divides. That is the lesson enunciated by our colleagues Nathan Lents and Joshua Swamidass in the St. Louis Post-Dispatch yesterday and earlier in the Pittsburgh Tribune-Review on December 18. The occasion? The fifteenth anniversary of the Dover decision by District Court Judge John E. Jones III “that it is unconstitutional to teach ID as an alternative to evolution in a public school science classroom.” December 20 has come to be known as Kitzmas, and the Panda’s Thumb article by PZ Myers may be the first use of that term.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mark Meadows and his skeletons</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/mark-meadows-skeletons.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mark Meadows and his skeletons" /><published>2020-12-28T17:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-12-28T17:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/mark-meadows-skeletons</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/mark-meadows-skeletons.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Allosaurus_Wide_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Allosaurus skeleton&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Allosaurus skeleton. &lt;small&gt;''Allosaurus fragilis'' skeleton mounted in the lobby of the San Diego Natural History Museum. Wikimedia. Photograph by user Sheep81.  Public domain. https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Allosaurus_SDNHM.jpg. &lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we have not been paying enough attention to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Meadows_(North_Carolina_politician)&quot;&gt;Mark Meadows&lt;/a&gt;, the White House Chief of Staff. We noted recently that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mr. Meadows may or may not be a creationist, but he is certainly a fellow traveler: At one time [2002], he purchased a piece of property on which an Allosaurus specimen had been discovered (supposedly by some home-schooled children). He then [2014] sold the property to Answers in Genesis, arguably in order to keep the fossils under the control of young-earth creationists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a bit anodyne. In fact, according to an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.salon.com/2020/12/27/mark-meadows-has-skeletons-in-the-closet--dinosaur-skeletons-to-be-precise/&quot;&gt;article In Salon&lt;/a&gt;, it was Mr. Meadows’s daughter Haley who supposedly discovered the dinosaur on the last day of the dig. In fact, according to the Salon article, the fossil had been discovered two years earlier by the person, Dana Forbes, who had sold the property to Mr. Meadows. It was identified in 2001 by paleontologist Joe Taylor. That skeleton, as &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2014/05/dinosaur-fossil.html&quot;&gt;we reported&lt;/a&gt;, was eventually donated to the Creation “Museum” by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the Elizabeth Streb Peroutka Foundation. The foundation’s leader Michael Peroutka until recently was also a board member of the League of the South, a white supremacist, neo-Confederate and pro-secessionist organization that has been named a hate group by the Southern Poverty Law Center[,]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;according to a press release from paleontologist Daniel Phelps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Salon article, besides involving his 9-year-old daughter in some kind of apparent fraud, Mr. Meadows&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;had since at least 2018 apparently failed to disclose a loan and monthly income of $11,000 related to the sale of a deed to a Colorado fossil park dedicated to promoting the creationist fiction that humans coexisted with dinosaurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, Salon reports that Mr. Meadows was sanctioned in 2018 for misusing taxpayer money and may have done so again in 2020. Finally, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.salon.com/2020/10/30/watchdog-files-complaint-accusing-trumps-chief-of-staff-mark-meadows-of-campaign-finance-crimes/&quot;&gt;Salon reporting&lt;/a&gt; has apparently inspired a watchdog group to file a complaint against Mr. Meadows with the Federal Election Commission.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Allosaurus skeleton. ''Allosaurus fragilis'' skeleton mounted in the lobby of the San Diego Natural History Museum. Wikimedia. Photograph by user Sheep81. Public domain. https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Allosaurus_SDNHM.jpg. I think we have not been paying enough attention to Mark Meadows, the White House Chief of Staff. We noted recently that Mr. Meadows may or may not be a creationist, but he is certainly a fellow traveler: At one time [2002], he purchased a piece of property on which an Allosaurus specimen had been discovered (supposedly by some home-schooled children). He then [2014] sold the property to Answers in Genesis, arguably in order to keep the fossils under the control of young-earth creationists. That was a bit anodyne. In fact, according to an article In Salon, it was Mr. Meadows’s daughter Haley who supposedly discovered the dinosaur on the last day of the dig. In fact, according to the Salon article, the fossil had been discovered two years earlier by the person, Dana Forbes, who had sold the property to Mr. Meadows. It was identified in 2001 by paleontologist Joe Taylor. That skeleton, as we reported, was eventually donated to the Creation “Museum” by the Elizabeth Streb Peroutka Foundation. The foundation’s leader Michael Peroutka until recently was also a board member of the League of the South, a white supremacist, neo-Confederate and pro-secessionist organization that has been named a hate group by the Southern Poverty Law Center[,] according to a press release from paleontologist Daniel Phelps. According to the Salon article, besides involving his 9-year-old daughter in some kind of apparent fraud, Mr. Meadows had since at least 2018 apparently failed to disclose a loan and monthly income of $11,000 related to the sale of a deed to a Colorado fossil park dedicated to promoting the creationist fiction that humans coexisted with dinosaurs. In addition, Salon reports that Mr. Meadows was sanctioned in 2018 for misusing taxpayer money and may have done so again in 2020. Finally, Salon reporting has apparently inspired a watchdog group to file a complaint against Mr. Meadows with the Federal Election Commission.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is natural selection a meaningless tautology?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Fitness-Tautology.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is natural selection a meaningless tautology?" /><published>2020-12-27T16:45:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-12-27T16:45:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Fitness-Tautology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Fitness-Tautology.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/mothceiling.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Moth on ceiling&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;A moth on our dining room ceiling, with
 unsuccessful&lt;br /&gt; cryptic coloration -- most likely
 a geometrid moth of the tribe&lt;br /&gt; Hydriomenini, perhaps the Tissue Moth, &lt;em&gt;Triphosa haesitata&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt; (thanks to John Morgan and Matt Young for the leads)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In argument with creationists one often hears the point made, triumphantly,
that natural selection is a tautology.  The implication is that evolutionary
biologists are so generally incompetent that they don't recognize this, and that
when they invoke the concept of fitness they are engaging in a meaningless
circular argument.  Natural selection, creationists argue, is supposed to be &quot;survival
of the fittest&quot;.  Yet how do we define fittest?  Why, merely as those that
survive.  So it reduces to &quot;survival of the survived&quot;, and thus cannot be
more than a meaningless incantation.  Gotcha!
&lt;p&gt;
But ...
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
... it's &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a tautology.  First of all, an aside: fitness is not merely &quot;survival&quot;.  For some reason creationists are fixated on survival and do not realize that
evolutionary biologists also count in fitness the expected amount of reproduction of
those parents that survive.  But that technicality aside ...
&lt;p&gt;
I saw on a blog (&lt;a href=&quot;http://theskepticalzone.com/wp/is-darwinian-evolution-teleonomic/comment-page-4/#comment-104569&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) a good analogy:
Is it tautological or circular or meaningless
to say that when we make up a track team we should choose runners who are
faster than the others?  Is it meaningless to look at earlier races or practice
sessions to see who are the best runners?  Obviously this is not meaningless, because ability to run fast often carries over from one race to another, even though
this will not always be perfectly true.
&lt;p&gt;
It is when we expand our view beyond the single sample of individuals and the single generation that we can see that fitness is not a tautology.  We can, for
example:
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Assess the fitness of different genotypes in our initial one-generation study
and look at whether different genotypes have different fitnesses.  And then we
can validate the results by looking at how fit those genotypes are in additional
samples of individuals in the same generation, or looking at samples in other populations or in later generations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; We can do the same for phenotypes: for example, are larger individuals more
fit?  Do hawks with longer wings catch more prey?  Does this carry over into
other samples, other populations, other generations?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; We can ask what will be the consequences if the relative fitnesses (the ratios of the fitnesses) of different genotypes remain the same over many generations. Starting with initial gene frequencies, there are standard equations of
theoretical population genetics that predict long-term outcomes. And we can
calculate what will happen if fitnesses vary between populations, or vary across generations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My colleagues in evolutionary biology are not idiots.  They devote a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of time and effort to measuring fitnesses of different genotypes and phenotypes, and in different populations and in different generations.  Right now &quot;experimental evolution&quot; studies which mutate sequences and then ask how those genotypes
change frequency in cultures of yeast are very popular, now that DNA sequencing
of large samples can be done. These are popular methods for assessing the
effect of changes in the sequence.  There are good reasons for all of these studies,
and calling fitness a tautology will not make any impression -- it certainly
won't cause these studies to come to a screeching halt.
&lt;p&gt;
And in case you need more elaborate philosophical consideration of this issue,
here are two discussions you can access online:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.talkorigins.org/faqs/evolphil/tautology.html&quot;&gt;John Wilkins's discussion&lt;/a&gt; of the charge of tautology at the Talk.Origins Archive site,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the Wikipedia article on &quot;Survival of the fittest&quot;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Survival_of_the_fittest#Tautology&quot;&gt;the section on this issue&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;`
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">A moth on our dining room ceiling, with unsuccessful cryptic coloration -- most likely a geometrid moth of the tribe Hydriomenini, perhaps the Tissue Moth, Triphosa haesitata (thanks to John Morgan and Matt Young for the leads) In argument with creationists one often hears the point made, triumphantly, that natural selection is a tautology. The implication is that evolutionary biologists are so generally incompetent that they don't recognize this, and that when they invoke the concept of fitness they are engaging in a meaningless circular argument. Natural selection, creationists argue, is supposed to be &quot;survival of the fittest&quot;. Yet how do we define fittest? Why, merely as those that survive. So it reduces to &quot;survival of the survived&quot;, and thus cannot be more than a meaningless incantation. Gotcha! But ...</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Conjunction of Jupiter and Saturn (and the Moon)</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/conjunction-jupiter-saturn.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Conjunction of Jupiter and Saturn (and the Moon)" /><published>2020-12-21T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-12-21T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/conjunction-jupiter-saturn</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/conjunction-jupiter-saturn.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/DSC03959_Cropped_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jupiter, Saturn, and the Moon&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/feature/the-great-conjunction-of-jupiter-and-saturn&quot;&gt;conjunction&lt;/a&gt; of Jupiter and Saturn will be seen tonight if the sky is clear. But the Moon cooperated better a few days ago, on December 18. Directly above, you can see Jupiter and, slightly above Jupiter, a dimmer Saturn.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">The conjunction of Jupiter and Saturn will be seen tonight if the sky is clear. But the Moon cooperated better a few days ago, on December 18. Directly above, you can see Jupiter and, slightly above Jupiter, a dimmer Saturn.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Where were you on December 20, 2005?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/where-were-you.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Where were you on December 20, 2005?" /><published>2020-12-20T08:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-12-20T08:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/where-were-you</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/where-were-you.html">&lt;p&gt;Where were you on December 20, 2005? I was in Cusco, Peru, …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/IMG_3424_Cusco_Cathedral_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cathedral&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cusco_Cathedral&quot;&gt;Cusco Cathedral&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… with a handful of others, when we entered a hotel, foraging for coffee. Immediately, a copy of the day’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://timesdigest.com/&quot;&gt;Times Digest&lt;/a&gt; bearing this headline …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Dover_Pic_Montage.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Newspaper clipping&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/20/education/judge-bars-intelligent-design-from-pa-classes.html&quot;&gt;Article in the New York Times&lt;/a&gt; by Laurie Goodstein on December 20, 2005.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… or some approximation thereto positively leaped off a table and into my hand, and screamed, “&lt;em&gt;We won in Dover!&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where were you that day? What were you doing when you heard the news? Let us know in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Where were you on December 20, 2005? I was in Cusco, Peru, … Cusco Cathedral. … with a handful of others, when we entered a hotel, foraging for coffee. Immediately, a copy of the day’s Times Digest bearing this headline … Article in the New York Times by Laurie Goodstein on December 20, 2005. … or some approximation thereto positively leaped off a table and into my hand, and screamed, “We won in Dover!” Where were you that day? What were you doing when you heard the news? Let us know in the comments.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why latkes are better than hamantashen</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/why-latkes-better.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why latkes are better than hamantashen" /><published>2020-12-17T10:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-12-17T10:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/why-latkes-better</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/why-latkes-better.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jerry Coyne &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2020/12/17/tonight-the-university-of-chicagos-world-famous-latke-hamentash-debate/&quot;&gt;informs us&lt;/a&gt; that the latke-versus-hamantash debate originated at the University of Chicago. He also reminds me that tonight is the last night of Chanukah, so I had better post this piece now. I wrote it years ago for the debate, Are Latkes Better Than Hamantashen? at my local synagogue. For those not in the know, latkes are a Chanukah delicacy: potato pancakes cooked in oil to represent the oil lamp that miraculously burned for eight days after the Maccabees rededicated the Temple. Hamantashen are triangular cookies eaten on the holiday of Purim (which is based on the Book of Esther).&lt;/em&gt; Penimah &lt;em&gt;is a play on the Hebrew name&lt;/em&gt; Peninah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, hamantashen are not kosher. (1) They have 3 sides, which symbolizes the Trinity.  (2) As if to drive the point home, they are filled with poppy seeds; these were originally popey seeds, from the Latin word &lt;em&gt;papaver&lt;/em&gt;, which means true pope. (3) Finally, the word is really a corruption of Haman-&lt;em&gt;toosh&lt;/em&gt;, and everyone knows that the hindquarters of an animal are not kosher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the word for hamantashen in Hebrew is &lt;em&gt;oznay haman&lt;/em&gt;, which means &lt;em&gt;Haman’s ears&lt;/em&gt;. This means they give your children selective hearing and inspire them to poke holes in their earlobes (and maybe elsewhere).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latkes are called &lt;em&gt;latkes&lt;/em&gt; in Yiddish because they were developed by Lot, unlike Haman a righteous man and a nephew of my ancestor Abraham. The Hebrew word is &lt;em&gt;levivah&lt;/em&gt;, which comes from the word &lt;em&gt;lev&lt;/em&gt; for &lt;em&gt;heart&lt;/em&gt;. The first words of the Israeli national anthem are
&lt;em&gt;Kol ohd ba-levav penimah&lt;/em&gt;, which means &lt;em&gt;Everyone wants another of Penima’s latkes&lt;/em&gt;. This shows that all that oil is really good for your heart and further that, when modern science disagrees with the Torah, the Torah is right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, if G-dash-d had wanted us to eat hamantashen, not latkes, he or she would have had us fill them with carrots so that at least they would be good for our eyes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Jerry Coyne informs us that the latke-versus-hamantash debate originated at the University of Chicago. He also reminds me that tonight is the last night of Chanukah, so I had better post this piece now. I wrote it years ago for the debate, Are Latkes Better Than Hamantashen? at my local synagogue. For those not in the know, latkes are a Chanukah delicacy: potato pancakes cooked in oil to represent the oil lamp that miraculously burned for eight days after the Maccabees rededicated the Temple. Hamantashen are triangular cookies eaten on the holiday of Purim (which is based on the Book of Esther). Penimah is a play on the Hebrew name Peninah. First, hamantashen are not kosher. (1) They have 3 sides, which symbolizes the Trinity. (2) As if to drive the point home, they are filled with poppy seeds; these were originally popey seeds, from the Latin word papaver, which means true pope. (3) Finally, the word is really a corruption of Haman-toosh, and everyone knows that the hindquarters of an animal are not kosher. Furthermore, the word for hamantashen in Hebrew is oznay haman, which means Haman’s ears. This means they give your children selective hearing and inspire them to poke holes in their earlobes (and maybe elsewhere). Latkes are called latkes in Yiddish because they were developed by Lot, unlike Haman a righteous man and a nephew of my ancestor Abraham. The Hebrew word is levivah, which comes from the word lev for heart. The first words of the Israeli national anthem are Kol ohd ba-levav penimah, which means Everyone wants another of Penima’s latkes. This shows that all that oil is really good for your heart and further that, when modern science disagrees with the Torah, the Torah is right. In short, if G-dash-d had wanted us to eat hamantashen, not latkes, he or she would have had us fill them with carrots so that at least they would be good for our eyes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is the NABT statement on teaching evolution flawed?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Is-the-NABT-statement-flawed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is the NABT statement on teaching evolution flawed?" /><published>2020-12-12T09:36:01-07:00</published><updated>2020-12-12T09:36:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Is-the-NABT-statement-flawed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Is-the-NABT-statement-flawed.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/SistineDarwinApe.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;SistineDarwinApe&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Copyright Michelangelo di Lodovico Buonarroti Simoni and anonymous&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This post consists of two statements reacting to the statement on teaching of evolution by National Association of Biology Teachers.  They are by Paul Braterman and Anj Petto.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Statement by Paul Braterman&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Biology teachers, especially in the US, often find themselves called upon to defend their teaching of evolution, on the grounds that it arbitrarily rejects the possibility of supernatural causes, and that since it is a theory it should not be taught as fact. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://nabt.org/Position-Statements-NABT-Position-Statement-on-Teaching-Evolution&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Position Statement from the National Association of Biology Teachers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is meant to address such concerns. In my opinion, it lamentably fails to do so, and indeed gives ammunition to the enemies of evolution science.
&lt;!--more--&gt;
Regarding supernatural causes, the Statement says that
&lt;blockquote&gt;
“[E]ducators should support science education by rejecting calls to account for the history of life or describe the mechanisms of evolution by invoking any non-natural or supernatural notions, whether under the banner of “creation science,” “scientific creationism,” “intelligent design,” or similar designations. Such notions are outside the scope of science, do not adhere to the shared scientific standards governing the collection and interpreting of evidence, and should not be presented as part of the science curriculum.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
In other words, according to the NABT, non-natural or supernatural notions regarding the history of life should be excluded from scientific discussion from the outset, without further examination, although they may be presented outside the context of science.
&lt;p&gt;
This is the worst of all possible worlds. It is philosophically inaccurate,&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; since “non-natural or supernatural notions” such as extra-sensory perception and the existence of ghosts, have been and should be within the domain of scientific inquiry. Indeed it is only as the result of such inquiry that we are able to state without circular argument that these notions are devoid of merit. Precisely the same is true of supernatural notions regarding the history of life, including specifically the notions of the separate creation of kinds (“creation science”), and of the intervention of a designer (“Intelligent Design”). Finally, it is not the role of NABT to rule about what may be presented outside the science curriculum, least of all to suggest that a notion that is unacceptable in the context of science may nonetheless be acceptable elsewhere.
As to why this is important, consider what Phillip Johnson, former Supreme Court clerk to Earl Warren, Professor of Law at UC Berkeley, and founder of the modern Intelligent Design movement, wrote about this specific topic in Defeating Darwin by Opening Minds:&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
“I agree with the common people [in seeing a role for God in the history of life]. If we are right, the consequences are very, very important. The ruling naturalists know that too, although they may deny it. That is why they are so determined to define words like evolution and science in such a way that naturalism is true by definition.” (pp 22-23)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
And again later (p 56):
&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Contemporary scientists… consider things supernatural to be outside of science. In other words, scientists start by assuming the naturalism is true, and they try to give purely natural explanations for everything, including our existence.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Notice how skilfully Johnson uses the NABT’s philosophical error to invoke anti-elitism and anti-intellectualism, and to suggest, as he repeatedly does in this book, that scientists accept evolution in the face of the evidence in order to justify atheism. I think it of the highest importance that we should not give the creationists a legitimate opening to do this. We can avoid doing so, while retaining what is of merit in this section of the Statement, by replacing the offending words with a short statement such as
“Non-naturalistic notions, such as &quot;Intelligent Design&quot;, have not proved fruitful, while separate creation is refuted by numerous lines of evidence&quot;
Relatedly, consider what NABT has to say regarding theories:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Scientific data overwhelmingly supports the theory of evolution. Scientific theories are supported by extensive evidence.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
The statement that “Scientific theories are supported by extensive evidence” is sometimes true, sometimes untrue, and claims to the contrary will correctly be seen as self-serving and based on circular reasoning. The study of evolution is a research program containing numerous theoretical and observational components, while common descent, which is what is really under discussion here, is not theory, but fact.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;footnotes&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
1] ABT is incorrectly imposing Intrinsic Methodological Naturalism on science as an a priori constraint, whereas it should be using Provisory Methodological Naturalism, in which naturalism emerges from the failure of the supernatural under scientific scrutiny. See How not to attack Intelligent Design Creationism: Philosophical misconceptions about Methodological Naturalism, Maarten Boudry, Stefaan Blancke, Johan Braeckman, Foundations of Science, 15(3), 227–244, 2010; draft publicly available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/maartenboudry/teksten-1/methodological-naturalism&quot;&gt;https://sites.google.com/site/maartenboudry/teksten-1/methodological-naturalism&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;
2] 2nd Edition, Intervarsity Press, 1997. The current NABT Statement differs in wording from the one that he is attacking, but not in ways that affect his argument.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I thank Joe Felsenstein and Maarten Boudry  for useful discussions.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Statement by Anj Petto&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The National Association on Biology Teachers (NABT) is one of several organizations that has released position statements over the last few decades on the centrality of evolution in the life sciences and its proper place in life sciences education. Let's frame the issues that NABT faced with its position statements using the A-B-T (And/But/Therefore) model for science communication of Filmmaker Randy Olsen.
&lt;p&gt;
Evolution is the foundation of the modern life sciences, &lt;b&gt;and&lt;/b&gt; no one can be “educated” in these disciplines unless the instruction is grounded in modern evolutionary science. &lt;b&gt;But&lt;/b&gt;, evolution education is considered “controversial” by some members of the general public; they object to its inclusion in the curriculum and they pressure teachers, administrators, political leaders, and community organizations to eliminate, weaken or challenge evolution education in public schools. Furthermore, all the efforts in science education reform in the United States since the late 1950s have had minimal success in convincing the public at large that evolution is real, is a valid scientific theory and research framework, explains the history and diversity of life on Earth, and applies to humans as well as to other organisms. &lt;b&gt;Therefore&lt;/b&gt;, professional organizations, such as NABT, issue policy statements and position papers to make clear their support for evolution education, its role in the scientific disciplines that its members teach, and the fundamental role that evolution serves in how we understand the history and diversity of life on Earth.
&lt;p&gt;
There is no fundamental disagreement within the sciences on the validity of evolutionary sciences (the AND). The problem, of course, is the public perception that there is such a disagreement, and that science education should include the objections to evolutionary science (the BUT). In other words, after close to 70 years of trying to improve the acceptance and understanding of evolution through science education reform, the nation is still sharply and almost equally divided between those who accept and those who reject evolution.
&lt;p&gt;
To address this problem (the THEREFORE), policy statements from national professional scientific or science education organizations have to publicize both the widespread scientific success of evolutionary science and the reluctance of close to half the general public to accept that this could be so. Of course, they need to affirm (and re-affirm) their support of and commitment to evolution education. At the same time, these organizations—especially science education organizations—must avoid making the situation worse for teachers and school personnel working in districts with strong and active religious communities. Many religious communities long ago made a peace with evolution consistent with their doctrines and practices (for example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/statements-religious-organizationse&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;https://ncse.ngo/statements-religious-organizations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). To force a choice between religious practice and acceptance of evolution runs the risk of alienating potential allies that science educators need to help overcome challenges in their districts.
&lt;p&gt;
In a series of revisions to its policy on teaching evolution, NABT (and other organizations) tried various ways of expressing that their intention is not to oppose religious belief per se among their students, but to focus on the natural laws and processes that produce the patterns of similarities and differences that we can observe in living organisms on the Earth in all the places and over all the time that life has occupied the planet; or, in a word: evolution.
&lt;p&gt;
Objections to evolutionary science are essentially unchanged since the 1950s. They promote the same arguments and objections to evolution rooted in the original “creation science” movement—evolution reserves no role for an omniscient creator spirit. The newer arguments appear to be different to the general public—for example, invoking an unnamed “intelligent agent” instead of naming a specific deity; showing mathematical formulae or alternative interpretation of geologic observations—and so policy statements need to keep up with the latest iterations.
&lt;p&gt;
Revisions in policy statements over time have addressed specific forms that objections to evolution have taken. Newer phrases and reworked arguments raise specific issues at specific points in time, and the policy statement has responded appropriately—if not always effectively—to those objections. We clearly haven't found the “one” policy statement that works: one that will convince communities that evolutionary science is solid and productive; that its track record of successful performance is why it should be included in the curriculum. But the “perfect” statement must always recognize the community context in which most evolution education is practiced; its wording must not alienate or exclude members of the community who would support evolution education by directly (and unnecessarily) challenging fundamental beliefs and values that are not in conflict with the principles of evolutionary science. It is threading scientific filament through the eye of a sociocultural needle.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman and Anj Petto</name></author><summary type="html">Copyright Michelangelo di Lodovico Buonarroti Simoni and anonymous This post consists of two statements reacting to the statement on teaching of evolution by National Association of Biology Teachers. They are by Paul Braterman and Anj Petto. Statement by Paul Braterman Biology teachers, especially in the US, often find themselves called upon to defend their teaching of evolution, on the grounds that it arbitrarily rejects the possibility of supernatural causes, and that since it is a theory it should not be taught as fact. The Position Statement from the National Association of Biology Teachers is meant to address such concerns. In my opinion, it lamentably fails to do so, and indeed gives ammunition to the enemies of evolution science.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Macrosiphini</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/macrosiphini.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Macrosiphini" /><published>2020-12-07T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-12-07T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/macrosiphini</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/macrosiphini.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/DSC03667_Aphid_Crop_600_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aphid&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;An aphid of the tribe &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugguide.net/node/view/359390/bgpage&quot;&gt;Macrosiphini&lt;/a&gt;, enjoying a tomato plant.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Natalie Hernandez in BugGuide identified the aphid as Macrosiphini, a “tribe” of aphids. She adds, “Tough to ID it further from this angle, the shape and texture of the head between the antennae (dorsal view) separates some of the similar genera. Reticulations on the siphunculi are important too but tough to see in photos, and this one isn’t helping by breaking the siphunculus that is in view.” The &lt;a href=&quot;http://aphid.aphidnet.org/siphunculus.php&quot;&gt;siphunculus&lt;/a&gt; is a small tube for emitting pheromones; I have not the foggiest idea where the siphunculus is in this picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Sturtevant, who provided many helpful tips on macrophotography, wrote me,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Aphids are weird. Late in the season like this they will likely start laying eggs soon to overwinter. But during the main part of the season they give live birth – regularly pooping out a young-un, which is simply dropped behind the parent, facing in the same direction as the mother [see the video &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hEoo-6InDA8&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;]. Furthermore, unless they are tended by ants, which tickle them for nectar and make them move, most aphids in a colony will all be facing the same direction. I think the reason for that is because what I just mentioned: They are born facing the same direction as their parent, and there they pretty much just sit. They grow, and soon start pooping out their own youngsters, until you have a dense colony, all facing the same direction which is the direction they were born (!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While this is happening, if you look closely at a “big” one you can often see pairs of red dots inside the abdomen. Those are the compound eyes of their unborn young.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And other weird things: These live births are done by parthenogenesis, so the babies are clones of the mothers. Aphids are all female for most of the season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And then there is another weird thing. Their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/news/photosynthesis-like-process-found-in-insects-1.11214&quot;&gt;bright colors&lt;/a&gt; (green, yellow, red, depending on the species) are apparently from genes lifted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nsf.gov/news/news_summ.jsp?cntn_id=116842&quot;&gt;fungi&lt;/a&gt; who-knows-how-long ago. This seems a case of gene transfer from fungi to animals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And then there are all the parasites and predators they get. You can sit for hours watching a large aphid colony and see lots of drama. Live births, and various forms of horrible death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">An aphid of the tribe Macrosiphini, enjoying a tomato plant. Natalie Hernandez in BugGuide identified the aphid as Macrosiphini, a “tribe” of aphids. She adds, “Tough to ID it further from this angle, the shape and texture of the head between the antennae (dorsal view) separates some of the similar genera. Reticulations on the siphunculi are important too but tough to see in photos, and this one isn’t helping by breaking the siphunculus that is in view.” The siphunculus is a small tube for emitting pheromones; I have not the foggiest idea where the siphunculus is in this picture. Mark Sturtevant, who provided many helpful tips on macrophotography, wrote me,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Are there any new ID arguments?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Any-new-arguments.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are there any new ID arguments?" /><published>2020-12-01T20:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-12-01T20:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Any-new-arguments</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Any-new-arguments.html">&lt;p&gt;In a discussion of the future of arguments with creationists and/or ID advocates, someone said there were no new arguments from them.  Here is my response, from an email.  It is mostly about the sort of ID arguments that I have paid most attention to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There have been attempts to come up with new versions of Dembski's arguments, from the Marks-Ewert-Holloway &quot;Design Inference&quot; axis.  But they are all somewhat vague and cannot be made explicit without it becoming clear how weak the arguments are.  Marks and Dembski have had an argument that on average &quot;evolutionary searches&quot; do no better than random guessing.  But they could do that only by including among the &quot;evolutionary&quot; searches as many that actively tried to get a bad result as there were ones that tried to get a good result.  Holloway and others also put forward arguments that Algorithmic Specified Complexity that is high because things are unusually non-complex (huh?) would be very rare among all possible bitstrings.  But they left it unclear why evolution should in some sense be trying to achieve that, and they made no argument about what natural selection would do with that measure.  There is also some rigorous math from George Monta&amp;ntilde;ez of that group on how to unify a whole bunch of measures of specified complexity -- without ever exploring whether any of them help make an argument against the effectiveness of evolutionary processes.  There are also works by Marks and co. on &quot;active information&quot;, which is, however, information that can be put into the genome by natural selection, so not at all a refutation of its involvement.
&lt;p&gt;
So ...
&lt;!--more--&gt;
they're trying, and doing lots of very mathy things, and these can get cited by creationists and other ID advocates as powerful mathy disproofs of the effectiveness of evolutionary processes, as long as no one really looks inside the argument to see what it actually shows.  And so far they have not dotted the i's and crossed the t's in any way that actually argues against natural selection being able to result in adaptation.
&lt;p&gt;
For posts here at PT on the Dembski/Marks/Ewert &quot;evolutionary algorithms&quot; argument, and on the relevance of the ASC measure of (non-)complexity see &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2015/03/fitness-surface.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/12/Is-Algorithmic-Specified-Complexity-Useless-for-Analyzing-Evolution.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;
There's also &lt;a href=&quot;https://discourse.peacefulscience.org/t/intelligent-design-1-0-2-0-3-0-and-beyond/12588&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;a recent discussion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at Josh Swamidass's site Peaceful Science of a video in which Stephen Meyer and Douglas Axe present &quot;ID 3.0&quot;. Many of the commenters conclude that it is vaporware.  I must have missed 2.0 as well.
&lt;p&gt;
What do people see out there that would qualify as a new, and possibly even valid, ID argument?  
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">In a discussion of the future of arguments with creationists and/or ID advocates, someone said there were no new arguments from them. Here is my response, from an email. It is mostly about the sort of ID arguments that I have paid most attention to. There have been attempts to come up with new versions of Dembski's arguments, from the Marks-Ewert-Holloway &quot;Design Inference&quot; axis.  But they are all somewhat vague and cannot be made explicit without it becoming clear how weak the arguments are.  Marks and Dembski have had an argument that on average &quot;evolutionary searches&quot; do no better than random guessing.  But they could do that only by including among the &quot;evolutionary&quot; searches as many that actively tried to get a bad result as there were ones that tried to get a good result.  Holloway and others also put forward arguments that Algorithmic Specified Complexity that is high because things are unusually non-complex (huh?) would be very rare among all possible bitstrings.  But they left it unclear why evolution should in some sense be trying to achieve that, and they made no argument about what natural selection would do with that measure.  There is also some rigorous math from George Monta&amp;ntilde;ez of that group on how to unify a whole bunch of measures of specified complexity -- without ever exploring whether any of them help make an argument against the effectiveness of evolutionary processes.  There are also works by Marks and co. on &quot;active information&quot;, which is, however, information that can be put into the genome by natural selection, so not at all a refutation of its involvement. So ...</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Penumbral eclipse of moon</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/penumbral-eclipse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Penumbral eclipse of moon" /><published>2020-11-30T10:08:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-11-30T10:08:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/penumbral-eclipse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/penumbral-eclipse.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/DSC03929_Penumbral_Eclipse_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot; Penumbral eclipse&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Penumbral eclipse of the moon, 2:40 a. m., MST, November 30, 2020.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeanddate.com/eclipse/lunar/2020-november-30&quot;&gt;penumbral eclipse&lt;/a&gt; of the moon last night. During a penumbral eclipse, the moon enters the penumbra of the Earth’s shadow, rather than the umbra, or the deep shadow. Unless I am mistaken, if you were in the penumbra, on the moon, you would see a partial eclipse of the sun. At any rate, the penumbral eclipse was supposed to last from 12:32 a. m. to 4:53 and peak at 2:42, Mountain Standard Time, this morning. I went out with my trusty digital camera and a 210-millimeter lens at about 12:30 and 1:30, but I could see nothing, and the photographs revealed nothing. At 2:40, however, I exposed the photograph above. Although I adjusted the exposure using Affinity software, the image is not doctored in any way. You can see a darkening of the limb in the upper-right corner. Once I saw the photograph in the camera, I could see the limb darkening with the naked eye, but evidently my retina was overexposed slightly, because I had to squint to see it. Given my lack of success at 1:30, I forwent the opportunity to take a picture at 3:30 and retired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had the good fortune to see a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2017/08/total-eclipse.html&quot;&gt;total eclipse of the sun&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/01/total-eclipse-moon.html&quot;&gt;total eclipse of the moon&lt;/a&gt; not very long ago. Unfortunately, the penumbral eclipse, though mildly interesting in principle, could not hold a candle to either of those.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Penumbral eclipse of the moon, 2:40 a. m., MST, November 30, 2020. There was a penumbral eclipse of the moon last night. During a penumbral eclipse, the moon enters the penumbra of the Earth’s shadow, rather than the umbra, or the deep shadow. Unless I am mistaken, if you were in the penumbra, on the moon, you would see a partial eclipse of the sun. At any rate, the penumbral eclipse was supposed to last from 12:32 a. m. to 4:53 and peak at 2:42, Mountain Standard Time, this morning. I went out with my trusty digital camera and a 210-millimeter lens at about 12:30 and 1:30, but I could see nothing, and the photographs revealed nothing. At 2:40, however, I exposed the photograph above. Although I adjusted the exposure using Affinity software, the image is not doctored in any way. You can see a darkening of the limb in the upper-right corner. Once I saw the photograph in the camera, I could see the limb darkening with the naked eye, but evidently my retina was overexposed slightly, because I had to squint to see it. Given my lack of success at 1:30, I forwent the opportunity to take a picture at 3:30 and retired. I had the good fortune to see a total eclipse of the sun and a total eclipse of the moon not very long ago. Unfortunately, the penumbral eclipse, though mildly interesting in principle, could not hold a candle to either of those.</summary></entry></feed>