<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-09-27T16:33:51-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Bubo virginianus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/bubo-virginianus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bubo virginianus" /><published>2021-09-27T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-27T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/bubo-virginianus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/bubo-virginianus.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;David Young&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/IMG_2840_David_Owl_Crop_2_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Great horned owl&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_horned_owl&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Bubo virginianus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; great horned owl that flew into the back yard one day, Boulder, Colorado, September, 2021.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by David Young. Bubo virginianus &amp;ndash; great horned owl that flew into the back yard one day, Boulder, Colorado, September, 2021.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Apex predator was vegetarian: AIG</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/apex-predator-vegetarian.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Apex predator was vegetarian: AIG" /><published>2021-09-23T09:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-23T09:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/apex-predator-vegetarian</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/apex-predator-vegetarian.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Carcharodontosaurus_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dinosaur&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Carcharodontosaurus.png&quot;&gt;Carcharodontosaurus reconstruction.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt; Credit: Fred Wierum. Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 4.0 International license.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Guest post by &lt;strong&gt;Dan Phelps&lt;/strong&gt;, to whom we are indebted for unearthing this whopper from Answers in Genesis:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, creationists are misrepresenting a recent dinosaur discovery. This time it is a large carcharodontosaur from Uzbekistan that was recently described in a paper, &lt;a href=&quot;https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rsos.210923&quot;&gt;A new carcharodontosaurian theropod dinosaur occupies apex predator niche in the early Late Cretaceous of Uzbekistan&lt;/a&gt;, by Kohei Tanaka and colleagues from the universities of Tsukuba, Hokkaido, and Calgary.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On today’s “Answers News,” an online news video by Answers in Genesis, their employees (including Ken Ham’s son-in-law, Bodie Hodge) discuss this dinosaur. The discussion can be found from about 9 minutes, 30 seconds to about 14 minutes in &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/4Jhf2eKXwAc&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; YouTube video.  As is par for the course, they ignore the actual publication and rely instead on popular press discussions such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.deseret.com/u-s-world/2021/9/9/22664700/tyrannosaurus-rex-ulughbegsaurus-uzbekistanensis-bigger-dinosaur&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; . They also add their bizarre creationist interpretations and claim the fossil was buried in Noah’s Flood. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even more ridiculously, they suggest the theropod dinosaur – the apex predator! – may have been a vegetarian. This would be amusing except that AIG is misinforming children and adults via such broadcasts as above, the Creation “Museum,” and their Kentucky-taxpayer–subsidized “Ark Encounter.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Carcharodontosaurus reconstruction. Credit: Fred Wierum. Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 4.0 International license. Guest post by Dan Phelps, to whom we are indebted for unearthing this whopper from Answers in Genesis: Once again, creationists are misrepresenting a recent dinosaur discovery. This time it is a large carcharodontosaur from Uzbekistan that was recently described in a paper, A new carcharodontosaurian theropod dinosaur occupies apex predator niche in the early Late Cretaceous of Uzbekistan, by Kohei Tanaka and colleagues from the universities of Tsukuba, Hokkaido, and Calgary. On today’s “Answers News,” an online news video by Answers in Genesis, their employees (including Ken Ham’s son-in-law, Bodie Hodge) discuss this dinosaur. The discussion can be found from about 9 minutes, 30 seconds to about 14 minutes in this YouTube video. As is par for the course, they ignore the actual publication and rely instead on popular press discussions such as this one . They also add their bizarre creationist interpretations and claim the fossil was buried in Noah’s Flood. Even more ridiculously, they suggest the theropod dinosaur – the apex predator! – may have been a vegetarian. This would be amusing except that AIG is misinforming children and adults via such broadcasts as above, the Creation “Museum,” and their Kentucky-taxpayer–subsidized “Ark Encounter.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Will the name of Huxley College be changed on a pretext?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/thhuxley-3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Will the name of Huxley College be changed on a pretext?" /><published>2021-09-17T13:24:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-17T13:24:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/thhuxley-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/thhuxley-3.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/WWU_Viking.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Viking mascot&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western_Washington_Vikings&quot;&gt;Western Washington University mascot&lt;/a&gt;. You may see their Viking ship &lt;a href=&quot;https://designsystem.wwu.edu/athletics-branding-and-spirit-marks&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, toward the bottom. &lt;small&gt;Credit: Wikipedia. Fair Use.&lt;/small&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Board of Trustees of Huxley College met the day before yesterday, September 17, &lt;a href=&quot;https://trustees.wwu.edu/files/00%20BOT%20Sept%202021%20Work%20Session%20Agenda%20-%20FINAL.pdf&quot;&gt;solely to discuss renaming the college &lt;/a&gt;. According to a source whom I prefer to leave anonymous,*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;[T]he consensus seems to be to drop the Huxley name. They acknowledge that there was lots of information submitted both in support of and opposed to dropping the Huxley name. They acknowledge that Huxley did lots of great stuff both as a scientist and as a strong abolitionist and a defender of universal human rights, and in expanding educational opportunities for a diverse audience. However, they were troubled by some of the bigoted and sexist language that Huxley made at times. They also point out that Huxley had no real links to the Pacific Northwest or North America. Fair point. It sounds like they just don’t have the stomach to deal with the blowback of rejecting the &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/files/2021-07/LRTF%20Report%20and%20Recommendations_June%202021.pdf&quot;&gt;Legacy Review Task Force&lt;/a&gt;. No decision but it seems clear where they want to go.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

They then went on the discuss &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/files/2021-02/WWU%20Building%20Names%20Report%20Sept%202020.pdf&quot;&gt;Mathes and Haggard&lt;/a&gt; [two dormitories]. They are not inclined to reject these two, in spite of the majority recommendation of the Task Force to do so, and made comments along the line that “you should judge people based on the standards and language used in their time, not by modern standards.” Interesting that they are not inclined to use the same standard for Huxley. They want to judge him based on modern standards.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is curious that they only now discovered that Huxley had no direct connection to their area. If I wanted to be suspicious, I might suspect that they plan to change the name of the college on a pretext.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another source thought it was&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;[a] very sad and embarrassing spectacle all around.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

It started well enough, with written comments from the student board member who couldn’t be there. His comments were read/summarized by the chair. He expressed concern with the Task Force report and the impact it would have on the academic reputation of the university. He also seemed concerned with a “purity” test that was being applied to Huxley.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

From there I couldn’t tell which Board member was speaking, so I’ll just refer to them generically in the order in which they spoke.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

The first Board member obviously felt uncomfortable with the racism claims in the Task Force report and sought to distance the Board from them by suggesting a wholly different reason for changing the name: that Huxley had no real historic connection to WWU. On that principle alone she said she was prepared to dename the college.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

President Randhawa supported this, saying the key principle should be a direct connection to the university. Huxley's contributions pro and con are moot if relationship to the university is the main criterion.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

It was all downhill from there.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

The next board member said that denaming would have a de minimis impact on T.H. Huxley’s reputation because WWU is a regional university, so it wasn’t as if an organization with a national or international reputation made such a name change. He said there was a high cost in defending the name with little return. He accused Huxley of being an early eugenicist, and claimed that he had no connection to public education institutions like Huxley College. He called Huxley’s reputation “controversial.”&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

The next board member recognized that she was talking from an emotional perspective. She repeated the creationist trope that Huxley advocated a hierarchical theory of race and, because of that, going to a school named after him reminded her of the harm caused by going to a high school in Baltimore named after Roger B. Taney, the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court who wrote the Dred Scott decision. So in short, she compared Huxley’s legacy to Taney's.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Sensing the overwhelming sentiment, the Board chair than suggested that they needed to start thinking through how they were going to communicate the thought process behind their decision.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Another Board member asked if they need more input, more process. The chair restated this, asking if they needed to rehear the case? The response overall from several board members was no, there was plenty of opportunity for input.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

One Board member suggested voting at the October meeting. The president suggested it would be better to do so at the December meeting, or it will look like it was all worked out in advance. Several others concurred and suggested that the October meeting focus on communicating the rationale for the denaming.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

So in summary, they totally bought the creationist narrative in the Task Force report. I was embarrassed for them, for WWU, and for my own association with WWU.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another source observed that, when a committee was appointed,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;usually the decision on the path forward had already been made.  We were part of the required process.  But I do think all that work did make a difference.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Universities in Washington are essentially non-regulatory State Agencies and therefore policy making political bodies.  The process here is clearly political, and the members of the Board are political appointees.  It does now appear that at least some of the members of the Board are realizing the significance of the misinformation presented by the Huxley section of the report.  Without our efforts [I think he refers to comments submitted to the task force and the article &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seattletimes.com/opinion/reconsider-cancel-culture-target-at-wwu/&quot;&gt;Reconsider cancel-culture target at WWU&lt;/a&gt; in the Seattle Times, and maybe even the earlier articles in PT] the motion to change the name would have been presented and passed at yesterday’s and certainly by October’s Board meeting.  [At least we have gotten their attention, and] the Board and the President are now looking for ways to remove the name of Huxley from the college without claiming social injustice or racism.  The Seattle Times piece stated that there may be other reasons for removing Huxley as the name of the college, but that the racist and injustice charges were not true. Perhaps that is where they are thinking of going now.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps amusingly, the Task Force also discussed changing the name of the Viking Union, which I assume is the student union. The Viking is also the mascot of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western_Washington_Vikings&quot;&gt;University’s sports teams&lt;/a&gt;. Footnote 49 in their report tells you more than you want to know about the choice of the Viking mascot. If nothing else, the Task Force seems concerned that “Vikings have been romanticized by white supremacist groups as icons of conquest,” and white supremacists have been active on campus. One final source said that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;they seemed pretty resigned to the idea that that name would eventually change also.  There was some comment along the lines that any group of people has probably done something awful to someone else at some point, probably true.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* I have cited several sources and I have tacit permission to quote them, but I have left them anonymous to protect them from any possible retaliation. I have lightly edited their comments, for example, by replacing initialisms with full spellings when appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Western Washington University mascot. You may see their Viking ship here, toward the bottom. Credit: Wikipedia. Fair Use. The Board of Trustees of Huxley College met the day before yesterday, September 17, solely to discuss renaming the college . According to a source whom I prefer to leave anonymous,* [T]he consensus seems to be to drop the Huxley name. They acknowledge that there was lots of information submitted both in support of and opposed to dropping the Huxley name. They acknowledge that Huxley did lots of great stuff both as a scientist and as a strong abolitionist and a defender of universal human rights, and in expanding educational opportunities for a diverse audience. However, they were troubled by some of the bigoted and sexist language that Huxley made at times. They also point out that Huxley had no real links to the Pacific Northwest or North America. Fair point. It sounds like they just don’t have the stomach to deal with the blowback of rejecting the Legacy Review Task Force. No decision but it seems clear where they want to go. They then went on the discuss Mathes and Haggard [two dormitories]. They are not inclined to reject these two, in spite of the majority recommendation of the Task Force to do so, and made comments along the line that “you should judge people based on the standards and language used in their time, not by modern standards.” Interesting that they are not inclined to use the same standard for Huxley. They want to judge him based on modern standards. It is curious that they only now discovered that Huxley had no direct connection to their area. If I wanted to be suspicious, I might suspect that they plan to change the name of the college on a pretext. Another source thought it was</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AIG creationists want auctioned triceratops donated to them</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/aig-wants-triceratops.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AIG creationists want auctioned triceratops donated to them" /><published>2021-09-17T09:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-17T09:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/aig-wants-triceratops</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/aig-wants-triceratops.html">&lt;p&gt;Guest post by &lt;strong&gt;Dan Phelps&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Triceratops.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Triceratops fossil&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Triceratops_Royal_Tyrrell_(retouched-1).png&quot;&gt;Triceratops on display at the Royal Tyrrell Museum, Alberta, Canada.&lt;/a&gt; (Not the triceratops referred to in the text.) &lt;small&gt;Credit: User:Etemenanki3 and User:PawełMM, Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 4.0 International License.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creationists at Answers in Genesis do a twice weekly “news” show called, unsurprisingly, “Answers News.” Besides their usual nonsense, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/uEnGzwOguyQ &quot;&gt;this week&lt;/a&gt;, approximately 15 minutes in, they state that they want one of their followers to buy a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livescience.com/big-john-triceratops-auction.html&quot;&gt;triceratops that is up for auction in France&lt;/a&gt; and donate the fossil to the Creation “Museum.” They estimate that the triceratops will bring in $1.8 million at auction. The triceratops was unearthed in South Dakota, so they argue that it should be repatriated to the US. If anything ever illustrates why the commercialization of fossils, especially vertebrates, is not a good thing, this is it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Guest post by Dan Phelps. Triceratops on display at the Royal Tyrrell Museum, Alberta, Canada. (Not the triceratops referred to in the text.) Credit: User:Etemenanki3 and User:PawełMM, Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 4.0 International License. The creationists at Answers in Genesis do a twice weekly “news” show called, unsurprisingly, “Answers News.” Besides their usual nonsense, this week, approximately 15 minutes in, they state that they want one of their followers to buy a triceratops that is up for auction in France and donate the fossil to the Creation “Museum.” They estimate that the triceratops will bring in $1.8 million at auction. The triceratops was unearthed in South Dakota, so they argue that it should be repatriated to the US. If anything ever illustrates why the commercialization of fossils, especially vertebrates, is not a good thing, this is it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Speyeria atlantis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/Speyeria-atlantis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Speyeria atlantis" /><published>2021-09-13T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-13T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/Speyeria-atlantis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/Speyeria-atlantis.html">&lt;p&gt;Atlantis fritillary, by &lt;strong&gt;Steve Watson&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Watson_Steve_Speyeria_atlantis.jpg&quot; alt=&quot; &quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbif.gc.ca/eng/species-bank/butterflies-of-canada/atlantis-fritillary/?id=1370403265542&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Speyeria atlantis&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – Atlantis fritillary on goldenrod (&lt;i&gt;Solidago&lt;/i&gt; sp.?), Neys Provincial Park, Ontario.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Atlantis fritillary, by Steve Watson. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Speyeria atlantis – Atlantis fritillary on goldenrod (Solidago sp.?), Neys Provincial Park, Ontario.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Evaluating Alan Kleinman’s arguments</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/evaluating-alan-kleinmans-arguments.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evaluating Alan Kleinman’s arguments" /><published>2021-09-06T18:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-06T18:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/evaluating-alan-kleinmans-arguments</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/evaluating-alan-kleinmans-arguments.html">&lt;p&gt;Alan Kleinman has been commenting on various threads here at PT, in ways that repeatedly argue that he has done
the first correct probabilistic analysis of “DNA evolutionary adaptation” and “competition”, and that call for
evolutionary biologists to provide an analysis of the Lenski and Kishony experiments in bacterial evolution.  He
also argues that we have not provided a correct analysis of bacterial antibiotic resistence or of the evolution
of drug resistance in cancer.  This thread is intended to allow discussion of these assertions, without disrupting discussions of other topics at PT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me explain.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kleinman has published 7 papers on modeling evolutionary processes.  I have provided links to PDFs of these, when I encountered ones that might be free:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kleinman, A.  2014.  The basic science and mathematics of random mutation and natural
 selection &lt;em&gt;Statistics in Medicine&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;33 (29):&lt;/strong&gt; 5074–5080 &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1002/sim.6307&quot;&gt;(PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kleinman, A. 2015.  Random recombination and evolution of drug resistance. &lt;em&gt;Statistics in Medicine&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;34 (11):&lt;/strong&gt; 1977–1980.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kleinman, A.  2016.  The mathematics of random mutation and natural selection for multiple simultaneous selection
 pressures and the evolution of antimicrobial drug resistance. &lt;em&gt;Statistics in Medicine&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;35 (29):&lt;/strong&gt; 5391-5400&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kleinman, A. 2018a.  Random mutation and natural selection in competitive and 
noncompetitive environments.  &lt;em&gt;Biomedical Journal of Scientific &amp;amp; Technical Research&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;9 (1):&lt;/strong&gt; 6903–6906. &lt;a href=&quot;https://biomedres.us/volume9-issue1.php&quot;&gt;(PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kleinman, A. 2018b. Malaria and other infectious diseases, Suppression of the evolution
 of drug resistance. &lt;em&gt;Biomedical Journal of Scientific &amp;amp; Technical Research&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;12 (2):&lt;/strong&gt; 9083-9085. &lt;a href=&quot;https://biomedres.us/fulltexts/BJSTR.MS.ID.002219.php&quot;&gt;(PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kleinman, A. 2019. Fixation and adaptation in the Lenski E. coli Long Term Evolution Experiment. &lt;em&gt;Biomedical Journal of Scientific &amp;amp; Technical Research&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;20 (1):&lt;/strong&gt; 14754–14760. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Alan-Kleinman/publication/335243441_Fixation_and_Adaptation_in_the_Lenski_E_coli_Long_Term_Evolution_Experiment/links/5d5ae99d4585152102521f7f/Fixation-and-Adaptation-in-the-Lenski-E-coli-Long-Term-Evolution-Experiment.pdf&quot;&gt;(PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kleinman, A. M. 2020.  Drug resistance, An enemy of targeted cancer therapies. &lt;em&gt;Annals of Clinical and Medical Case Reports&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;4 (9):&lt;/strong&gt; 1–4.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has also brought his argument up repeatedly at Peaceful Science and at 
Panda&quot;s Thumb,
usually in the middle of threads devoted to other issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic calculation he does is to consider a haploid clonally-reproducing organism such
a bacterial culture, one which has no recombination.  He develops a formula for the
probability that the clone has beneficial mutations occuring at &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; sites, where the
first such mutation has &lt;em&gt;nGA&lt;/em&gt; generations to occur, the second has &lt;em&gt;nGB&lt;/em&gt; generations to
occur, and so on.  Note that an important feature of his model is that he considers,
not the time in generations but the number of cells that have ever arisen in the clone.
So with a probability &lt;em&gt;mu PA&lt;/em&gt; for each new cell that
it has a beneficial mutation, it takes about &lt;em&gt;1/(mu PA)&lt;/em&gt; cells before there is a
reasonable probability of seeing the beneficial mutation once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mystery (to me, anyway) is where selection is in all this.  We are computing
probabilities that, when a given number of cells has arisen, we have had
beneficial mutation at all of the &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; sites.  Once one has occurred, there seems to
be no futher mutation at that site.  Why?   This calculation is supposed to show
us the fundamental mathematical theory of mutation &lt;em&gt;and selection&lt;/em&gt;, but aside from
waiting until a mutation labelled “beneficial” occurs, there is no further
effect of selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same theory is also used in most of his other papers (an exception being the paper
on recombination which I will get back to later).  He has an idiosyncratic terminology.
As far as I can tell it involves calling the occurrence of beneficial mutations by
mutation “DNA adaptive evolution” while he calls their subsequent changes of gene
frequency in the population “competition”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some questions arise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kleinman sees two processes at work: “competition” which is survival of the fittest, and “DNA evolutionary adaptation” which is
changes of genotypes by mutation, either deleterious or beneficial.  Is this terminology helpful?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;His equations are all about how many organisms (or cells) need to have arisen to get a given probability that a beneficial
allele will arise by mutation.  The theory uses the stochastic process of mutation. How does natural selection affect
this?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;His treatment of recombination between genotypes with two or more loci assumes that offspring of a cross between a haploid
Ab genotype and a haploid  aB  genotype will all be  AB.  Is that true?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He seems to think that he is the first to give a correct mathematical theory of
mutation and natural selection.  Was he?  For example, his first paper has the
rather astonishingly grand title “The basic science and mathematics of random mutation and
natural selection”. Would RA Fisher
(1922) or JBS Haldane (1924) have agreed?  I think he is off by 97-99 years.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is he really the first to apply the mathematics of population genetics theory to evolution or drug resistance in cancer, or to
success of multidrug therapies for diseases?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I must be misunderstanding how his theory works, and I hope that this thread will explain his theory to me.
After all, if it is the fundamental mathematical theory of my own field, then it is surely important to know.
By doing the discussion here, we can avoid being so rudely interrupted by the folks in the previous threads who were trying to discuss arguments
other than Kleinman&quot;s.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Alan Kleinman has been commenting on various threads here at PT, in ways that repeatedly argue that he has done the first correct probabilistic analysis of “DNA evolutionary adaptation” and “competition”, and that call for evolutionary biologists to provide an analysis of the Lenski and Kishony experiments in bacterial evolution. He also argues that we have not provided a correct analysis of bacterial antibiotic resistence or of the evolution of drug resistance in cancer. This thread is intended to allow discussion of these assertions, without disrupting discussions of other topics at PT. Let me explain.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dendrocygna viduata</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/Dendrocygna-viduata.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dendrocygna viduata" /><published>2021-09-06T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-06T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/Dendrocygna-viduata</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/Dendrocygna-viduata.html">&lt;p&gt;Whistling ducks, by &lt;strong&gt;John Harshman&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Harshman_whistling_duck.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Whistling duck&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whistling_duck&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Dendrocygna viduata&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – white-faced whistling ducks, Botswana. The photographer writes, &quot;Here is a trio of white-faced whistling ducks. It’s not a particularly scientifically informative shot, but it’s one of my all-time favorite photos. Whistling ducks, on the other hand, are interesting from a number of perspectives. They’re the sister group of all other Anatidae, and they’re a very old genus: genetic divergence within &lt;i&gt;Dendrocygna&lt;/i&gt; is approximately equal to that within the rest of Anatidae. And yet they all look pretty much alike, so we have a fine example of morphological stasis. That may also be the reason that white-faced whistling ducks, with fairly sedentary habits, are nevertheless found in both Africa and South America with no recognized subspecific variation. (Fulvous whistling ducks &lt;i&gt;D. bicolor&lt;/i&gt; are worse: they’re found in North and South America, Africa, and India, still with no subspecies.)&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Whistling ducks, by John Harshman. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Dendrocygna viduata – white-faced whistling ducks, Botswana. The photographer writes, &quot;Here is a trio of white-faced whistling ducks. It’s not a particularly scientifically informative shot, but it’s one of my all-time favorite photos. Whistling ducks, on the other hand, are interesting from a number of perspectives. They’re the sister group of all other Anatidae, and they’re a very old genus: genetic divergence within Dendrocygna is approximately equal to that within the rest of Anatidae. And yet they all look pretty much alike, so we have a fine example of morphological stasis. That may also be the reason that white-faced whistling ducks, with fairly sedentary habits, are nevertheless found in both Africa and South America with no recognized subspecific variation. (Fulvous whistling ducks D. bicolor are worse: they’re found in North and South America, Africa, and India, still with no subspecies.)&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Euphydryas colon</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Euphydryas-colon.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Euphydryas colon" /><published>2021-08-30T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-30T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Euphydryas-colon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Euphydryas-colon.html">&lt;p&gt;Snowberry checkerspot butterfly, by &lt;strong&gt;Malcom Schongalla&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Schongalla_Euphydryas_colon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Snowberry checkerspot butterfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.butterfliesoforegon.com/euphydryas-colon&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt; Euphydryas colon&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – snowberry checkerspot butterfly, Hillscreek, Oregon, June, 2021.  The photographer writes, &quot;Some references list this as a subspecies of &lt;i&gt;Euphydryas chalcedona&lt;/i&gt; (chalcedon or variable checkerspot).  I am not a butterfly expert and this is my best attempt at identification.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Snowberry checkerspot butterfly, by Malcom Schongalla. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Euphydryas colon – snowberry checkerspot butterfly, Hillscreek, Oregon, June, 2021. The photographer writes, &quot;Some references list this as a subspecies of Euphydryas chalcedona (chalcedon or variable checkerspot). I am not a butterfly expert and this is my best attempt at identification.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Phyciodes batesii</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Phyciodes-batesii.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Phyciodes batesii" /><published>2021-08-23T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-23T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Phyciodes-batesii</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Phyciodes-batesii.html">&lt;p&gt;Tawny crescent butterfly, by &lt;strong&gt;Seanna Watson&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Watson_Seanna_Phyciodes_batesii.jpg&quot; alt=&quot; Tawny crescent butterfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbif.gc.ca/eng/species-bank/butterflies-of-canada/tawny-crescent/?id=1370403265789&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Phyciodes batesii&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – tawny crescent, Neys Provincial Park, Ontario.
&lt;/figcaption&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Tawny crescent butterfly, by Seanna Watson. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Phyciodes batesii – tawny crescent, Neys Provincial Park, Ontario.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Answers in Genesis, climate change, and vaccination</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/aig-climate-change-vaccination.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Answers in Genesis, climate change, and vaccination" /><published>2021-08-22T12:38:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-22T12:38:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/aig-climate-change-vaccination</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/aig-climate-change-vaccination.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Great_Unmasked.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Audience&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/aigkenham/status/1425040762052427776?s=21&quot;&gt;Forty days &amp;amp; nights of gospel music at the Ark&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; The Great Unmasked.&lt;/div&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was dismayed last Thursday to see &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/science/conservatives-have-difficult-relationship-science/&quot;&gt;the following paragraph&lt;/a&gt; posted by AiG under Ken Ham’s byline:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/many-conservatives-have-a-difficult-relationship-with-science-we-wanted-to-find-out-why-165499&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; [in &lt;i&gt;The Conversation&lt;/i&gt;], the author uses the term &lt;i&gt;science&lt;/i&gt; to refer to the so-called “scientific consensus” regarding things such as climate change alarmism, vaccinations, evolution, and a lack of “human exceptionalism.” But what the author is failing to recognize is the difference between observational and historical science. In other words, this author has a “difficult relationship with science” because the author doesn’t understand the word &lt;i&gt;science&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some time, Answers in Genesis has &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/environmental-science/ice-cores-secret-understanding-earths-climate/&quot;&gt;minimized the importance of human-made climate change&lt;/a&gt;, as have &lt;a href=&quot;https://creation.com/climate-change&quot;&gt;Creation Ministries International&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2020/04/tyson-and-cosmos-sound-the-climate-alarm-again/&quot;&gt;Discovery Institute&lt;/a&gt;, and this position of necessity involves denying the authority of a declared scientific consensus. However, Answers in Genesis has hitherto accepted the value of vaccines, and in two recent related articles, &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/human-body/wise-blood-overcoming-in-disease-immunity-part-1/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/human-body/wise-blood-antibodies-principle-overcoming-disease-part-2/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, gives a detailed scientific account of how vaccines work, and praises their effectiveness in the context of the complexity of the immune system, which of course for AiG is evidence for creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/many-conservatives-have-a-difficult-relationship-with-science-we-wanted-to-find-out-why-165499&quot;&gt;article in &lt;i&gt;The Conversation&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, cited above, reports that “[p]eople with a libertarian or conservative worldview are more likely to reject climate change and evolution and &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0250123&quot;&gt;are less likely to be vaccinated against COVID-19&lt;/a&gt;,” and in the US context relates such rejection of science and an exaggerated view of human exceptionalism, to religiosity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The historical versus observation nonsense is familiar, as are the attacks on scientific consensus and on concern about climate change, and our models of climate change do indeed involve the “historical science” that uses ice cores and other techniques to map climate change throughout the Ice Ages and beyond. But including “vaccinations” in the areas of scientific consensus apparently to be rejected is alarming. The study of vaccine effectiveness is very much part of current observational science, and we can see no good reason for Answers in Genesis to be turning against it, even on their own terms.
What we must fear is that AiG may be about to fall in line with other creationist institutions ranging from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gty.org/library/blog/B200723&quot;&gt;Grace Community Church&lt;/a&gt; to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2020/08/in-fauci-we-trust-c-s-lewis-foresaw-scientific-authoritarianism/&quot;&gt;Discovery Institute&lt;/a&gt; in minimizing the severity of an epidemic that is known to have killed 644,840 people in the US and 4,442,332 worldwide (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/&quot;&gt;as of August 22&lt;/a&gt;). AiG was from the outset &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/coronavirus/coronavirus-biblical-practical/&quot;&gt;ambivalent about masks&lt;/a&gt;, and even jokingly (or blasphemously) telling its readers &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2020/11/28/therefore-tell-you-do-not-be-anxious-about-covid/&quot;&gt;not to be anxious about COVID&lt;/a&gt; just as Jesus told his disciples (Matthew 6:25-34) not to worry about the necessities of life. Despite a rash of articles in March and April of last year, arguing that the mutations giving rise to COVID were not really examples of evolution, AiG has published nothing of significance on the subject since that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does not bode well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Dan Phelps for simultaneously alerting us to the AIG post and also for unearthing the photograph. Matt Young will be the primary moderator of this thread.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman</name></author><summary type="html">Forty days &amp;amp; nights of gospel music at the Ark &amp;ndash; The Great Unmasked. I was dismayed last Thursday to see the following paragraph posted by AiG under Ken Ham’s byline: In the article [in The Conversation], the author uses the term science to refer to the so-called “scientific consensus” regarding things such as climate change alarmism, vaccinations, evolution, and a lack of “human exceptionalism.” But what the author is failing to recognize is the difference between observational and historical science. In other words, this author has a “difficult relationship with science” because the author doesn’t understand the word science.</summary></entry></feed>