<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-06-11T23:02:14-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Pituophis catenifer sayi</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/pituophis-catenifer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pituophis catenifer sayi" /><published>2024-06-10T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-06-10T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/pituophis-catenifer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/pituophis-catenifer.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Mark Lee&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Lee_Bullsnake.JPEG&quot; alt=&quot;Head shot of snake&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bullsnake&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Pituophis catenifer sayi&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; bullsnake.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;** The Photography Contest will begin next Monday, June 17. **&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see comments on this post click below: &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Mark Lee. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Pituophis catenifer sayi &amp;ndash; bullsnake. ** The Photography Contest will begin next Monday, June 17. ** To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Teach Grown-Ups about Climate Change: A Review</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/how-to-teach-grown-ups.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Teach Grown-Ups about Climate Change: A Review" /><published>2024-06-06T09:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-06-06T09:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/how-to-teach-grown-ups</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/how-to-teach-grown-ups.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/HT_Teach_Grownups_Cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope I am not entering my &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_childhood&quot;&gt;second childhood&lt;/a&gt;, but I just read a splendid book aimed at third through seventh graders: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Teach-Grown-Ups-About-Climate-Change/dp/1804660310&quot;&gt;How to Teach Grown-Ups about Climate Change&lt;/a&gt;. A picture book, no less, written by Patricia Daniels and illustrated by Aaron Blecha, with a foreword by Michael Mann, the discoverer of the “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hockey_stick_graph_(global_temperature)&quot;&gt;hockey stick&lt;/a&gt;.” I have not been a (5 ± 2)th grader, nor have I had one, in a very long time, but I am going to guess that the material is suitable for that age group, though possibly a bit hard for a third grader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone once told me that if you want to get the attention of a fifth grader, just say “fart.” Sure enough, on page 27, the authors write,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Cow_Farts.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Infographic&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They explain, though, that cow &lt;i&gt;burps&lt;/i&gt; inject a significant amount of methane into the atmosphere, and methane is a very significant greenhouse gas. Fifth graders will also be interested to know that sea snot is plugging harbors in Turkey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am getting ahead of myself, but the book is well illustrated and has a myriad of infographics, many of them headlined IT’S A FACT! These infographics are shown as a cloud emitted by a burping cow. A nice discussion on information, misinformation, and disinformation shows you how “your grown-ups” can check any claim they think is suspicious: by going to an encyclopedia, a reputable news source, or a scientific authority. They are also advised to ask who paid for the message and what they get out of it. I might have added, trust dot-gov and dot-edu websites more than dot-com and dot-org websites, in that order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a technical book in some sense. It begins by asking whether your grown-ups might be clueless. If so, here is what you need to teach them. The book then goes through the history of climate change, explaining that we damned well know that it is human caused. It explains precisely what fossil fuels are and how burning them injects CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; into the atmosphere. Beginning with Eunice Foote, who predated even John Tyndall, the authors explain how we know that CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; traps heat. I was surprised that there was no history between Arrhenius and Greta Thunberg. (I was also somewhat dismayed when they called Foote, the woman, by her first name; they would never have called Arrhenius “Svante.”)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An infographic on how we know it is hot details the different measuring systems that we use to discern the average temperature of the earth. Another infographic shows the hockey stick and explains that the temperature was pretty steady between 1100 CE and the mid-twentieth century, when it began to rise precipitously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it too late? No, and boxes shaped like leaves explain WHAT YOU CAN DO in response to various problems. Other boxes, similar to the one we saw about cow farts, respond NOPE! to various misconceptions and explain precisely why they are misconceptions and should not be believed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weather now is often “weird,” so they coined the term &lt;i&gt;global weirding&lt;/i&gt;. Global weirding is responsible for temperatures of 47 °C in northwestern United States and nearby southwestern Canada on the one hand, and 40 °C warmer than normal in Antarctica (the temperature at one station in Antarctica &lt;a href=&quot;https://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/146322/antarctica-melts-under-its-hottest-days-on-record&quot;&gt;reached 18 °C&lt;/a&gt; in 2020, about the same as Los Angeles on that day). Additionally, we are seeing heat waves in cities, droughts and wildfires, and severe hurricanes, all above normal or what was formerly normal. Some plants and animals will survive all this, and some will not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors are optimistic about our own survival and note that we can tackle global weirding in two ways: personal choices and changing the system. They advise you to do both: change to LED light bulbs, tell your grown-ups not to idle their cars, reduce their consumption of meat (in particular, beef), and so on. But also get your grown-ups to work toward changing the system, as by introducing renewable energy sources, including geothermal, and manufacturing electric cars and trucks, for example. I was gratified to see that they are suspicious of carbon sequestration, in part because the oil industry plans to inject CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and use it to extract more oil. They likewise take a somewhat dim view of geo-engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, they offer some advice to your grown-ups when they try to influence friends and acquaintances: find things you have in common; do not argue with doctrinaire climate deniers; do not be “doom-y” and make people want to give up; and do not shame people who, for example, eat beef and drive behemoths. All to my mind good advice, provided sometimes that you can bite your tongue hard enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book ends with a quiz that you can give your grown-ups, as well as more detail on What You Can Do. It has a good glossary and what looks like a good index.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 1&lt;/strong&gt;. The book is of course timely, but perhaps moreso because of the roughly simultaneous announcement of a book by Ken Ham and &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/bios/jessica-deford/&quot;&gt;Jessica DeFord&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2024/05/25/truth-about-climate-change/&quot;&gt;The Truth [sic!] about Climate Change&lt;/a&gt;. I have not read this book, but I think all you need to know about it is this sentence written by Ms. DeFord,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; Climate alarmists will not solve the problem of man’s sin by switching to alternative energy or reducing carbon emissions &lt;i&gt;that they believe&lt;/i&gt; are caused by human activity. [Emphasis added.]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and Mr. Ham’s reminder of Genesis 8:22,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;While the earth remaineth, seedtime and harvest, and cold and heat, and summer and winter, and day and night shall not cease [KJV],&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which he interprets as a promise. (I guess he does not believe that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/God_helps_those_who_help_themselves&quot;&gt; God helps those who help themselves &lt;/a&gt;, because, after all, it is not Biblical.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 2&lt;/strong&gt;. Physicist’s last inch. I found two explanations that were possibly misleading and could be caught by a bright seventh grader. First, electrons are not &lt;i&gt;knocked off&lt;/i&gt; the solar cell. If they were, they would have nowhere to go, and the cell would become positive and attract them back. Instead, electrons are made free to move within the cell and therefore generate a current (holes too, but never mind; that would be too complicated). Readers of PT may be interested to know, incidentally, that China has built an array of solar cells in the shape of a panda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the term heat is used imprecisely in the discussion of “how the atmosphere works.” Again, a bright seventh grader might notice. Specifically, the “heat” that falls on the earth is mostly visible light. The “heat” that escapes into space is mostly infrared radiation, so they are not the same thing. The atmosphere is more or less transparent to visible light and more or less opaque to infrared radiation. It blocks much of the loss of “heat” by absorbing infrared radiation. That could have been made clear in a sentence or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A greenhouse, incidentally, does not work primarily by the greenhouse effect. Rather, it mostly reduces heat loss by convection. It is therefore very different from the atmosphere, but I would not quibble over that point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Glenn Branch, whose review you may read &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/review-how-teach-grown-ups-about-climate-change&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, for some assistance. Another reader, who wants to remain anonymous, exclaimed, “Sounds wonderful! I want to read it.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I hope I am not entering my second childhood, but I just read a splendid book aimed at third through seventh graders: How to Teach Grown-Ups about Climate Change. A picture book, no less, written by Patricia Daniels and illustrated by Aaron Blecha, with a foreword by Michael Mann, the discoverer of the “hockey stick.” I have not been a (5 ± 2)th grader, nor have I had one, in a very long time, but I am going to guess that the material is suitable for that age group, though possibly a bit hard for a third grader. Someone once told me that if you want to get the attention of a fifth grader, just say “fart.” Sure enough, on page 27, the authors write,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Giant pandas return to National Zoo</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/giant-pandas-return.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Giant pandas return to National Zoo" /><published>2024-05-29T13:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-05-29T13:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/giant-pandas-return</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/giant-pandas-return.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/IMG_3617_Steve_Steve_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Prof. Steve Steve&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a headline in the Washington Post, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s2.washingtonpost.com/3ddacd0/665719e273e72c3ea1cffc06/596a8aedae7e8a0ef33f6950/3/13/665719e273e72c3ea1cffc06&quot;&gt;Giant pandas are returning to D.C. this year, the Smithsonian’s National Zoo announces, after reaching a lease agreement with China&lt;/a&gt;. The two pandas, a two-year-old male named Bao Li and a two-year-old female named Qing Bao, are due to arrive later in the year. Bao Li’s mother is Bao Bao, a giant panda who was born at the zoo in 2013. Both are of course relatives of Prof. Steve Steve, the mascot of The Panda’s Thumb. Prof. Steve Steve is impressed that his relatives will cost the zoo $1 million per year for 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt;  &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">According to a headline in the Washington Post, Giant pandas are returning to D.C. this year, the Smithsonian’s National Zoo announces, after reaching a lease agreement with China. The two pandas, a two-year-old male named Bao Li and a two-year-old female named Qing Bao, are due to arrive later in the year. Bao Li’s mother is Bao Bao, a giant panda who was born at the zoo in 2013. Both are of course relatives of Prof. Steve Steve, the mascot of The Panda’s Thumb. Prof. Steve Steve is impressed that his relatives will cost the zoo $1 million per year for 10 years. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The nose of the Texas Gop is inside the tent</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/the-nose-of-the-texas-gop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The nose of the Texas Gop is inside the tent" /><published>2024-05-28T11:22:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-05-28T11:22:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/the-nose-of-the-texas-gop</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/the-nose-of-the-texas-gop.html">&lt;p&gt;A little bird alerted us yesterday to an article, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.friendlyatheist.com/p/the-texas-gops-proposed-platform?publication_id=95153&amp;amp;post_id=145010548&quot;&gt;The Texas GOP’s proposed platform would force the Bible in schools&lt;/a&gt;,” subtitled “The Texas Republican Party’s agenda contains everything on conservative Christians’ wishlist.” That about says it all. The article describes a tentative platform offered by the Texas Republican Party, which will be finalized by Wednesday. The author, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hemant_Mehta&quot;&gt;Friendly Atheist&lt;/a&gt;, calls the platform a wish list for the far right but considers much of the document more performative than real. I wish I was as certain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atheist’s article singles out a handful of planks from the proposed platform. They are very troubling to anyone who believes in the separation of church and state, and particularly to anyone who does not conflate religion with right-wing Christianity. For example,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Plank_18.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Plank 18&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plank 88, according to Atheist’s article, demands “instruction on the Bible, servant leadership, and Christian self-governance,” as well as demands that chaplains in schools “give guidance from a traditional Biblical perspective….” (I do not know what servant leadership means, but I can guess that Christian self-governance means governance over the rest of us.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is more, but it seems to me that what is most relevant to The Panda’s Thumb is this gem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Plank_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Plank d&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already teach scientific method, practices, and theories, including what we know about the origin of life; this sentence is a not so oblique reference to intelligent-design creationism. The phrase about climate changing throughout geological history is an equally not so oblique reference to climate change and in particular to climate-change denial. The Texas Republicans may pretend if they like, but evolution, that is, descent with modification, is an established fact, and the modern theory of evolution, while not perfect, is the best explanation we have for that fact. Anthropogenic climate change is likewise an established fact; the equally well-established fact that the climate has changed throughout geological times is an irrelevant smokescreen. You could nibble around the edges of both theories if you liked, but attacking them head-on is a fool’s errand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is more, and Atheist both explains and refutes it well. You may look aghast and exclaim that most of the platform is clearly unconstitutional. Well, maybe. To coin a phrase, the Constitution says what the Supreme Court says it says, and, given the opportunity, the present Supreme Court or an even more reactionary future Court could well overturn the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kitzmiller_v._Dover_Area_School_District&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; decision that intelligent-design creationism is not science and may not be taught as an alternative to evolution. It may even allow climate-change denial to supersede real science. Indeed, the nose of the camel may already be well inside the tent.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">A little bird alerted us yesterday to an article, “The Texas GOP’s proposed platform would force the Bible in schools,” subtitled “The Texas Republican Party’s agenda contains everything on conservative Christians’ wishlist.” That about says it all. The article describes a tentative platform offered by the Texas Republican Party, which will be finalized by Wednesday. The author, Friendly Atheist, calls the platform a wish list for the far right but considers much of the document more performative than real. I wish I was as certain. Atheist’s article singles out a handful of planks from the proposed platform. They are very troubling to anyone who believes in the separation of church and state, and particularly to anyone who does not conflate religion with right-wing Christianity. For example, Plank 88, according to Atheist’s article, demands “instruction on the Bible, servant leadership, and Christian self-governance,” as well as demands that chaplains in schools “give guidance from a traditional Biblical perspective….” (I do not know what servant leadership means, but I can guess that Christian self-governance means governance over the rest of us.) There is more, but it seems to me that what is most relevant to The Panda’s Thumb is this gem:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Phidippus audax</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/phidippus-audax.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Phidippus audax" /><published>2024-05-27T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-05-27T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/phidippus-audax</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/phidippus-audax.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/DSC05680_Spider_Phidippus_audax_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jumping spider&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.donerickson.name/spiders/spiders.html&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Phidippus audax&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; jumping spider, often called bold jumper, found in an enclosed, unheated space, Boulder, Colorado, April, 2024. I was interested in the powerful forelegs, if that is the right word (the left foreleg must have been folded under, because a later photograph shows that it is intact). The spider in this photograph was running along the edge of a dish from which it could apparently not get out. Despite the designation jumping spider, it very kindly hung around while I managed a few photographs.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see comments on this post click below: &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Phidippus audax &amp;ndash; jumping spider, often called bold jumper, found in an enclosed, unheated space, Boulder, Colorado, April, 2024. I was interested in the powerful forelegs, if that is the right word (the left foreleg must have been folded under, because a later photograph shows that it is intact). The spider in this photograph was running along the edge of a dish from which it could apparently not get out. Despite the designation jumping spider, it very kindly hung around while I managed a few photographs. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Who Am I?” by Martyn Iles, Executive CEO of Answers in Genesis: Book Review</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/who-am-i.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Who Am I?” by Martyn Iles, Executive CEO of Answers in Genesis: Book Review" /><published>2024-05-22T10:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-05-22T10:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/who-am-i</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/who-am-i.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Braterman_Iles_Book_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Martyn Iles, as many readers will know, was managing Director of the Australian Christian Lobby until sacked by the Board in February 2023, was appointed Chief Ministry Officer of Answers in Genesis in May of that year, and in November was &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/Martyn-Iles-Is-Executive.html&quot;&gt; promoted to Executive CEO&lt;/a&gt;, working alongside Ken Ham, who remains as Founding CEO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While still in Australia, Iles promoted right-wing causes in the name of individual religious freedom, expressed support on his YouTube channel for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/BrBgSjAC7kE 20:15&quot;&gt;claim that the 2020 US presidential election had been stolen&lt;/a&gt;, and in a Facebook post on January 21 2020, just two weeks after the January 6 insurrection, reaffirmed his admiration for Donald Trump. However, since joining Answers in Genesis he has, to the best of my knowledge, refrained from overtly political comment. In a Facebook post on March 17 this year he explicitly rejected the idea of a “Christian nation,” since being a Christian or not is a characteristic of individuals. Thus he has placed a welcome distance between himself and the extremes of US Christian Nationalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one important difference in style between Iles and Ham. Ham, in the tradition of Henry Morris and, before him, George McCready Price, argues that science supports his version of Bible-based Young Earth Creationism. Iles, however, does not even condescend to discuss such mere details. As he &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/martynlloydiles/posts/635836281247343/&quot;&gt; posted on Facebook&lt;/a&gt; in October 2022, “Truth is in the [biblical] word itself. Other things are true insofar as they conform to it.” Moreover, Iles is clear in his own mind that his understanding of the Bible, however far-fetched, is the correct one. So when he tells us what it means, he is speaking for God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On his appointment, &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2023/11/13/aig-appoints-new-executive-ceo-martyn-iles/&quot;&gt;Iles wrote&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Just as evolutionary naturalism has threatened the faith of so many, postmodernism and new critical theories threaten the faith of a new generation. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given his position at the head of the world’s leading Young Earth Creationist organization, we need to know what he has in mind by this laconic statement,and we can gain some insight into this from the book under discussion here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book itself, like others from the same publisher, appears to be directed at young adults. It is an easy read, with large clear print, and the text is liberally illustrated by silhouettes of young people, generating a warm and welcoming impression at odds with the fundamentally dictatorial nature of the content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That content is mass of self-contradictions. We are told that man is made in the image of God, but there are multiple biblical references to human sinfulness and corruption. It is our duty to look after the world, but not to take responsibility for human-caused climate change. And Iles deplores, as do I, the upsurge in young people seeking to mutilate their bodies when their personalities do not fit gender stereotypes, but claims biblical authority for stereotypes of the most constricting kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iles begins by deploring what he sees as the modern emphasis on the self:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Actually, I didn’t realize you could use it [self-] as a prefix quite so much until I started my research. Self-ideation, self-love, self-discovery, self-definition, self-perception, self-determination, self-narrative, self-image, self-concept, self-esteem … All of these I have encountered in contemporary works on identity. This word has brought with it the age of the inward turn — the looking at the self. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably absent from this list: self-knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He goes on to build up an enormous superstructure on a very narrow theological base. He makes extensive use of a handful of verses from the opening chapters of Genesis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Be fruitful and multiply and fill the earth and subdue it, and have dominion over the fish of the sea and over the birds of the heavens and over every living thing that moves on the earth. (Genesis 1:28) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increase greatly on the earth and multiply in it. (Genesis 9:7) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the earth remains, seedtime and harvest, cold and heat, summer and winter, day and night, shall not cease. (Genesis 8:22) &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this he infers that there cannot be an overpopulation problem, that it is a duty of fertile couples to have children, and that concerns about such large-scale matters as climate change are fundamentally misplaced, since these things are in the hands of God and, to use his expression, when we imagine that we can affect them we are “getting too big for our boots.” This is the sin of pride, and pride is a very serious sin indeed. Climate alarmism (his expression) is only one example of such pride, part of a list that includes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;abortion, transgenderism, queer sexuality [sic], critical race theory, feminism, family breakdown, …, childlessness, cultural Marxism, post-modernism, and all that stuff. The common thread is this: all of them seek to usurp God’s authority as Creator by redefining what He has already defined. All of them seek to do His job for Him, only better. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He accepts unquestioningly the interpretation of Genesis 3:15:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;And I will put enmity between you and the woman, and between your offspring and her offspring; he shall bruise your head, and you shall bruise his heel.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;as the very first prophesy of the coming of Jesus. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seed_of_the_woman&quot;&gt;this interpretation&lt;/a&gt;, which goes back to the 2nd Century CE, the serpent is identified with Satan, the woman’s offspring is Jesus, born of a woman, the bruising of his heel is the agony of the crucifixion, and the bruising of Satan’s head is Christ’s triumph over evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this he infers that the highest vocation of woman is motherhood, and that Satan bears special enmity towards pregnant women and babies. Satan is very prominent in Iles’s view of the world, and is mentioned 11 times in this short book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Male and female roles were spelt out at the creation. God decides to create woman because:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;It is not good that the man should be alone; I will make him a helper fit for him. (Genesis 2:18) &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Adam is duly appreciative:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;This at last &lt;sup&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt; is bone of my bones and flesh of my flesh; she shall be called Woman, because she was taken out of Man. (Genesis 2:23). &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, according to Iles,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;woman was made with such care and purpose that she perfectly complemented and completed him [man]. She too was not made to be alone. The two became one. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One, but different:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The LORD God took the man and put him in the garden of Eden to work it and keep it. (Genesis 2:15) &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iles draws our attention to two words, which define a man’s God-given purpose; first, to “work,” and second to “keep.” The reference to “the garden” directs attention to his external responsibilities. And so, he tells us, men are called to industry and must beware the sin of idleness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why, Iles asks, was it Adam that God addressed by name after the Fall:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Adam, where art thou? (Genesis 3:17, KJV) &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This although Eve and the serpent were also present at the scene, the serpent was the primary initiator of the sin, and Eve was the first to eat of the forbidden fruit. The reason for singling out Adam is that, as a man, he had primary responsibility for what had happened in the garden that had been entrusted to his care. Responsibility is a male prerogative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of women, Iles says&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The woman was at her best when making another person their best. That was her commission. And it spills over into her motherhood too. Only women are mothers, and this is a good and beautiful thing indeed — a commission from God, for which she is designed biologically, psychologically, and spiritually. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iles goes on to mentions meekness as part of woman’s special virtue, and uses the word “meek” with reference to women on seven separate occasions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a passage worth quoting in full, he compares the different ways in which men and women go about getting their own way when not entitled to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;While men might prefer to exercise illegitimate control through brutishness, force, and cruelty, women tend to use different methods. They play games. They manipulate circumstances. They might even get their girlfriends involved to “make” things happen or drop ideas, seeds, and prompts through third parties. Their minds are always storyboarding, working out what people are thinking, how they’re feeling, and preempting next moves. They operate in the realm of the emotional, subjective, and interpersonal. To use such powers of discernment to manipulate circumstances and control outcomes is ultimately an abuse of those feminine giftings. They were given to be exercised selflessly and meekly, without the taint of self-will and premeditated outcomes. There is a difference between godly help and controlling “femcraft.” &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when challenged as to what the besetting sin of woman might be, as compared to idleness in men, he answers “Control.” As he put it on Facebook (6 June 2023)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;A word like “independent” is a direct assault on God’s design for women… A woman who prizes strength in independence is a woman rebelling against her nature. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There you have it. You and I may think that our identity is a puzzle, but the book promises in its title to solve it for us, and does so. We may even have imagined that there are many possible solutions, but Iles knows God’s design, and there’s an end of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the book is devoted to theological questions, with heavy emphasis on our sinful nature, but since I have no special insight to offer on such matters, I will leave it there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Who am I? Solving the identity puzzle&lt;/i&gt;, Martyn Iles, with a foreword by Ken Ham, 35,000 words spread out over 208 pages, Master Books, 2024, $19.99 on Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“At last” because in between the two verses cited, we have the creation of the animals, and their being brought to Adam as potential partners and found wanting for that purpose. But if you include this in your materials, you will find yourself with something far more interesting than Iles’s blinkered moralizing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman</name></author><summary type="html">Martyn Iles, as many readers will know, was managing Director of the Australian Christian Lobby until sacked by the Board in February 2023, was appointed Chief Ministry Officer of Answers in Genesis in May of that year, and in November was promoted to Executive CEO, working alongside Ken Ham, who remains as Founding CEO. While still in Australia, Iles promoted right-wing causes in the name of individual religious freedom, expressed support on his YouTube channel for the claim that the 2020 US presidential election had been stolen, and in a Facebook post on January 21 2020, just two weeks after the January 6 insurrection, reaffirmed his admiration for Donald Trump. However, since joining Answers in Genesis he has, to the best of my knowledge, refrained from overtly political comment. In a Facebook post on March 17 this year he explicitly rejected the idea of a “Christian nation,” since being a Christian or not is a characteristic of individuals. Thus he has placed a welcome distance between himself and the extremes of US Christian Nationalism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Prunus americana</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/prunus-americana.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Prunus americana" /><published>2024-05-13T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-05-13T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/prunus-americana</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/prunus-americana.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/P1021077_Prunus_Americana_Crop_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wild plum blossoms&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prunus_americana&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Prunus americana&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; wild plum, with erratic honeybee, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Honey_bee&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Apis mellifera&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Bobolink Trail, Boulder, Colorado, May, 2024.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Prunus americana &amp;ndash; wild plum, with erratic honeybee, Apis mellifera, Bobolink Trail, Boulder, Colorado, May, 2024. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Marmota flaviventris</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/marmota-flaviventris.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Marmota flaviventris" /><published>2024-04-29T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-04-29T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/marmota-flaviventris</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/marmota-flaviventris.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photograph by Vivian Dullien&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Vivian_Dullien_Marmot_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Marmot&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/romo/learn/nature/marmot.htm&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Marmota flaviventris&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; young yellow-bellied marmot, preparing for hibernation, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/romo/index.htm&quot;&gt;Rocky Mountain National Park&lt;/a&gt;, fall, 2023.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Vivian Dullien. Marmota flaviventris &amp;ndash; young yellow-bellied marmot, preparing for hibernation, Rocky Mountain National Park, fall, 2023. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Intelligent Design for Dummies, Part 2</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/intelligent-design-dummies-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intelligent Design for Dummies, Part 2" /><published>2024-04-25T08:09:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-04-25T08:09:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/intelligent-design-dummies-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/intelligent-design-dummies-2.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Branch_Part_2_Pandas.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pandas&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Pandas at National Zoo in Washington.&lt;small&gt; Photograph by Asiir. Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 2.5 Generic license.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;This is Part 2 of 2. You may find Part 1 &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/intelligent-design-dummies.html&quot;&gt; here &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Third Problem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Finally, your story has a practical problem,” Questor says: “Is the panda’s thumb a poor design?” — whereupon a panda peeks its head through the panel and confides, “I rather like it, you know” (page 78). In essence, she is attacking premise (4) of Teller’s argument, by a clever appeal to the literature. Questor is presumably a college biology professor, and Wiester, who provided “the science input” for WDGDWI, is a college biology professor. Where do they go to get the information on the panda’s thumb? The &lt;i&gt;Encyclopedia Americana&lt;/i&gt;, which Questor quotes as saying that the panda’s thumb “enables the panda to eat bamboo efficiently” and to “handle stems with great dexterity” (page 78, charmingly illustrated with a panda twirling stalks of bamboo in drum-major fashion). Gould, in contrast, consulted D. Dwight Davis’s monograph &lt;i&gt;The Giant Panda&lt;/i&gt; (1964), which he characterized as “the greatest work of modern evolutionary comparative anatomy” (Gould 1980: 22).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the far-from-authoritative nature of their source, Newman and Wiester’s emphasis on the efficiency of the panda’s thumb reveals that they have again misrepresented Gould’s argument, apparently due to their conflation of two senses in which it is possible for design (or, if you prefer, “design”) to be suboptimal. In the first sense, a biological feature is suboptimally designed if it accomplishes its function not as efficiently as it (or a plausible substitute) might. Thus in the first sense, to say that the panda’s thumb is suboptimally designed is to say that it is not as useful for stripping leaves from bamboo as it (or a plausible substitute) might be. In the second sense, however, a biological feature is suboptimally designed if it is not designed as well as it might have been, that is, if the process whereby it acquired the ability to accomplish its function was not as efficient as it (or a plausible substitute) might have been. That there is such a sense of what it is for design to be suboptimal is testified to by the computer engineer’s word “kludge,” which refers to a clumsy and inelegant, but not necessarily ineffective, solution to a problem. In the second sense, to say that the panda’s thumb is suboptimally designed is to say that the process whereby it acquired the ability to strip leaves from bamboo was a kludge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is obvious that in “The Panda’s Thumb” Gould was thinking about suboptimal design in the second, kludgy, sense: in a passage that Newman and Wiester quote, he explains that “[o]dd arrangements and funny solutions” provide striking evidence for evolution (Gould 1980: 20). Referring to the panda’s thumb, he writes, “An engineer’s best solution is debarred by history … the panda must use parts on hand and settle for … a somewhat clumsy, but quite workable, solution … a contraption, not a lovely contrivance” (Gould 1980: 24). And he acknowledges that the panda’s thumb is not suboptimally designed in the first sense: “I was amazed by their dexterity” (Gould 1980: 21). Thus WDGDWI’s discussion of whether the panda’s thumb is suboptimally designed in the first sense is irrelevant to the question Gould was addressing, whether the panda’s thumb is a kludge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parenthetically, the same conflation is committed by the Discovery Institute’s Paul A. Nelson, in a paper not cited by Newman and Wiester. Nelson quotes the same passages about odd arrangements and funny solutions from Gould (1980: 20–21), glossing the argument as “God is an optimizing creator. This structure, and hence, [&lt;i&gt;sic&lt;/i&gt;] organism, is imperfect. Therefore this organism evolved” (Nelson 2002: 678). Here he is misrepresenting Gould by taking his argument about suboptimal design in the second, kludgy, sense as about suboptimal design in the first sense. Later, considering the panda in particular, Nelson writes, “other observers heap praise on the panda’s use of its forelimbs” (Nelson 2002: 690, emphasis in original), citing such praise from &lt;i&gt;The Giant Pandas of Wolong&lt;/i&gt; (Schaller and others 1986). But, again, whether the panda’s thumb is suboptimally designed in the first sense is irrelevant to Gould’s question of whether the panda’s thumb is a kludge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the third problem is spurious. I conclude that none of the problems that Questor sees in Gould’s and Teller’s argument is at all compelling. And it is hard to avoid reaching the conclusion that she — and hence the authors of WDGDWI — are disingenuous in their purported desire to explore the issues raised by it in a fair and careful manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s Diogenes Got to Do with It?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is surprising that Questor quotes “the Greek philosopher Diogenes” as saying,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The regularity of the season would not have been possible without intelligence, that all things should have their measure: winter and summer and night and day … [which] if one will study them will be found to have the best possible arrangement” (pages 74–75).&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For there were at least five ancient Greek philosophers named Diogenes: Diogenes of Oenoanda (a follower of Epicurus), Diogenes of Smyrna (a Protagorean), Diogenes of Sinope (the Cynic), Diogenes Laertius (the historian of philosophy), and Diogenes of Apollonia. As it happens, it is from the last of these that Questor quotes; the passage is from fragment B3 in the standard collection of Presocratic fragments (Diels and Kranz 1951–2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is Diogenes of Apollonia suddenly the hero of the intelligent design movement? Not due to his philosophical importance: Jonathan Barnes describes him as “essentially second-rate” and “a bore,” and declares that “[b]y common scholarly consent, he was least as well as last” of the Presocratic philosophers (Barnes 1993: 567–568). Edward Hussey says that his “general level of philosophical awareness suggests the age of Anaximenes” (Hussey 1972: 141), implying that he was about a century behind the times. Even his contemporaries were unimpressed by him: the playwrights Euripides and Aristophanes and the poet Philemon all poked fun at his philosophical views (Barnes 1993: 580, 645n3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer, I suggest, is provided by the fact that the passage from B3 is generally considered to be “the first extant exposition of the Teleological Argument for the existence of God, or the Argument from Design” (Barnes 1993: 577).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for the proponents of intelligent design, their hero’s conception of the intelligent designer is not congenial for their purposes. The intelligent designer of which Diogenes speaks in B3 is revealed in B5 to be — believe it or not — &lt;i&gt;air&lt;/i&gt;. “And it seems to me that that which possesses intelligence is what men call air … For it is this which seems to me to be god” (Barnes 1987: 291). To be fair, he adds in B8 that “it is great and strong, eternal and immortal, and knows many things” (Barnes 1987: 292), but it is easy to see why his views were derided by his contemporaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not just the embarrassing airiness of Diogenes’ intelligent designer that disqualifies him as a suitable emblem for the intelligent design movement, however, but the fact that Diogenes embraced the bête noire of intelligent design: methodological naturalism. Like the rest of the Presocratic philosophers, Diogenes was no atheist, but also like them, he believed that the gods do not interfere with the natural world: for these thinkers, the world was orderly arranged without being divinely administered. Reflecting scholarly consensus, Barnes writes that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Presocratic explanations are marked by several characteristics. They are, as I have said, &lt;i&gt;internal&lt;/i&gt;: they explain the universe from within, in terms of its own constituent features, and they do not appeal to arbitrary intervention from without. They are &lt;i&gt;systematic&lt;/i&gt;: they explain the whole sum of natural events in the same terms and by the same methods. Thus the general principles in terms of which they seek to account for the origins of the world are also applied to the explanations of earthquakes or hailstorms or eclipses or diseases or monstrous births. Finally, Presocratic explanations are &lt;i&gt;economical&lt;/i&gt;: they use few terms, invoke few operations, assume few “unknowns.” (Barnes 1987: 17, emphasis in original)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diogenes clearly was working within the naturalistic framework delineated by Barnes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, Newman and Wiester contend that “a &lt;i&gt;preexisting&lt;/i&gt; intelligence created and designed the universe, life and human beings” (page v, emphasis added), violating the internality principle. They contend that although “nobody in their right mind questions that some animals [doubly &lt;i&gt;sic&lt;/i&gt;: they presumably have species, not individuals, in mind, and they presumably do not wish to limit their claim to the animal kingdom] have changed some through the course of their existence on earth” (page 7), it is questionable in other cases, thus violating the systematicity principle. And it would be tedious to detail all the myriad ways in which they violate the economy principle. One example: when Teller remarks that the intelligent designer is “not exactly available for study or experiment,” Questor responds, “That doesn’t prove that an intelligence doesn’t exist, does it?” (pages 14–25). Arguing from ignorance to the existence of the supernatural is a paradigm of the uneconomical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Diogenes of Apollonia is not really the ancient Greek philosopher whom the intelligent design movement should be showcasing. Nor should it be Diogenes of Sinope either — it was he who, according to legend, walked about with a lantern, searching for an honest man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Anonymous]. Report on cartoon book, Darwinism for Skeptics. &lt;i&gt;Newsletter of the American Scientific Affiliation &amp;amp; Canadian Scientific and Christian Affiliation&lt;/i&gt; 1999 May/Jun; 41 (3): 5–6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barnes J. &lt;i&gt;Early Greek Philosophy&lt;/i&gt;. London: Penguin, 1987.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barnes J. &lt;i&gt;The Presocratic Philosophers&lt;/i&gt;, revised ed. London: Routledge, 1993.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behe M. J. &lt;i&gt;Darwin’s Black Box&lt;/i&gt;. New York: The Free Press, 1996.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Davis D. D. &lt;i&gt;The Giant Panda: A Morphological Study of Evolutionary Mechanisms&lt;/i&gt;. Chicago: Chicago Natural History Museum, 1964.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DeHaan R. F., Wiester J. L. The Cambrian explosion: the fossil record &amp;amp; intelligent design. &lt;i&gt;Touchstone&lt;/i&gt; 1999 Jul/Aug; 12 (4): 65–69.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diels H., Kranz W. &lt;i&gt;Die Fragmente der Vorsokratiker&lt;/i&gt;, 6th ed. Dublin and Berlin: Weidmann, 1951–2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forrest B. The wedge at work. In: &lt;i&gt;Intelligent Design Creationism and its Critics&lt;/i&gt;, ed. Pennock R. T. Cambridge MA: The MIT Press, 2002. pp. 3–53.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gould S. J. The panda’s thumb. In: Gould S. J. &lt;i&gt;The Panda’s Thumb: More Reflections in Natural History&lt;/i&gt;. New York: WW Norton &amp;amp; Company, 1980. pp. 19–26.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hussey E. &lt;i&gt;The Presocratics&lt;/i&gt;. New York: Scribners Press, 1972.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nelson P. A. The role of theology in current evolutionary reasoning. &lt;i&gt;Biology &amp;amp; Philosophy&lt;/i&gt; 1996; 11 (4): 493–517. Reprinted in: &lt;i&gt;Intelligent Design Creationism and its Critics&lt;/i&gt;, ed. Pennock R. T. Cambridge MA: The MIT Press, 2002. pp. 677–704.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newman R. C. Progressive creationism. In: &lt;i&gt;Three Views on Creation and Evolution&lt;/i&gt;, ed. Moreland J. P, Reynolds J. M. Grand Rapids MI: Zondervan Publishing House, 1999. pp. 105–133.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newman R. C., Eckelmann H. J. Jr. &lt;i&gt;Genesis One and the Origin of the Earth&lt;/i&gt;. Downers Grove IL: InterVarsity Press, 1977.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newman R. C., Wiester J. L. &lt;i&gt;What’s Darwin Got to Do With it?&lt;/i&gt; Downers Grove IL: InterVarsity Press, 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schaller G., Jinchu H., Wenshi P., Jing Z. &lt;i&gt;The Giant Pandas of Wolong&lt;/i&gt;. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1986.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wiester J. L. &lt;i&gt;The Genesis Connection&lt;/i&gt;. Hatfield PA: Interdisciplinary Biblical Research Institute, 1992.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wiester J. L. Wiester interviewed by BBC. &lt;i&gt;Newsletter of the American Scientific Affiliation &amp;amp; Canadian Scientific &amp;amp; Christian Affiliation&lt;/i&gt; 2000 Jan/Feb; 42 (1): 6–7.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Glenn Branch</name></author><summary type="html">Pandas at National Zoo in Washington. Photograph by Asiir. Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 2.5 Generic license. This is Part 2 of 2. You may find Part 1 here . The Third Problem “Finally, your story has a practical problem,” Questor says: “Is the panda’s thumb a poor design?” — whereupon a panda peeks its head through the panel and confides, “I rather like it, you know” (page 78). In essence, she is attacking premise (4) of Teller’s argument, by a clever appeal to the literature. Questor is presumably a college biology professor, and Wiester, who provided “the science input” for WDGDWI, is a college biology professor. Where do they go to get the information on the panda’s thumb? The Encyclopedia Americana, which Questor quotes as saying that the panda’s thumb “enables the panda to eat bamboo efficiently” and to “handle stems with great dexterity” (page 78, charmingly illustrated with a panda twirling stalks of bamboo in drum-major fashion). Gould, in contrast, consulted D. Dwight Davis’s monograph The Giant Panda (1964), which he characterized as “the greatest work of modern evolutionary comparative anatomy” (Gould 1980: 22). Regardless of the far-from-authoritative nature of their source, Newman and Wiester’s emphasis on the efficiency of the panda’s thumb reveals that they have again misrepresented Gould’s argument, apparently due to their conflation of two senses in which it is possible for design (or, if you prefer, “design”) to be suboptimal. In the first sense, a biological feature is suboptimally designed if it accomplishes its function not as efficiently as it (or a plausible substitute) might. Thus in the first sense, to say that the panda’s thumb is suboptimally designed is to say that it is not as useful for stripping leaves from bamboo as it (or a plausible substitute) might be. In the second sense, however, a biological feature is suboptimally designed if it is not designed as well as it might have been, that is, if the process whereby it acquired the ability to accomplish its function was not as efficient as it (or a plausible substitute) might have been. That there is such a sense of what it is for design to be suboptimal is testified to by the computer engineer’s word “kludge,” which refers to a clumsy and inelegant, but not necessarily ineffective, solution to a problem. In the second sense, to say that the panda’s thumb is suboptimally designed is to say that the process whereby it acquired the ability to strip leaves from bamboo was a kludge.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unlikely Allies: Biology Teachers and Creationists</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/unlikely-allies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unlikely Allies: Biology Teachers and Creationists" /><published>2024-04-22T07:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-04-22T07:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/unlikely-allies</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/unlikely-allies.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Braterman_Unlikely_Allies_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Journal cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am writing in response to the article &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.12775/SetF.2024.010&quot;&gt;Bridging ideological divides: Why Christians still disagree about evolution and what we whould do about it&lt;/a&gt;, by Hans Madueme and Todd Charles Wood, &lt;i&gt;Scientia et Fides&lt;/i&gt; 12(1), 2024, 189–213; open access &lt;a href=&quot;https://apcz.umk.pl/SetF/article/view/45459/38251&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is written by two young earth creationists, who take 25 closely argued pages including 93 references to show complete misunderstanding of the relationship between observation and interpretation in evolution science, in order to claim a false epistemic symmetry between this science and the theological perspective which forces them to reject it; a more sophisticated version of the “two pairs of spectacles” thesis that has been with us since George McCready Price. So why am I bothering to review this article? And why, to my own surprise, do I find myself welcoming its appearance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For three reasons. Firstly, because the authors, unlike “creation science” young earth creationists, accept the validity of the science in its own terms, rather than claiming that it is inferior to their own fantastical offerings. Secondly, because they lay out extremely clearly (and self-revealingly) their own epistemic position. And finally, because their recommendations, made regarding conversations within the evangelical community, are applicable (and indeed to some extent already applied) to the very practical problem of how to teach evolution science in places with a faith-based culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Todd Wood is a name that will be familiar to many readers here. He has a PhD from University of Virginia, conducted postdoctoral work for two years at Clemson, and has published five papers in leading journals on different aspects of molecular phylogeny. He is now applying his skills to baraminology, the attempt to explain the multiplicity of present species in terms of descent from the limited number that could have fitted onto Noah’s Ark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a joke. He describes his book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Understanding-Pattern-Life-Origins-Organization/dp/0805427147&quot;&gt;Understanding the Pattern of Life: Origins and Organization of the Species&lt;/a&gt;, in the preface, as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;an expression of my attempt, however feeble, to allow the truth of God to transform my view of biology. Rather than trying to prove the truth of Scripture, I use it as a starting point. From there, I build what I believe to be a reasonable model of biology that fits both the facts of Scripture and the data of creation.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://henrycenter.tiu.edu/contributor/hans-madueme/&quot;&gt;Hans Madueme&lt;/a&gt;, Associate Professor at Covenant College Georgia, appears to be highly regarded in his field, and has edited a volume, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomsbury.com/us/reading-christian-theology-in-the-protestant-tradition-9780567266149/&quot;&gt;Reading Christian Theology in the Protestant Tradition&lt;/a&gt;, published by Bloomsbury. Despite (or perhaps because of) his own convictions, he has &lt;a href=&quot;https://henrycenter.tiu.edu/2019/06/creationism-embattled-yet-resilient-a-redirect/&quot;&gt;been highly critical&lt;/a&gt; of claims made on behalf of creation science..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the authors are adamant in their own beliefs, they are opposed to polemics, and for this reason, as we shall see, single out for praise Jason Rosenhouse’s Among the Creationists (reviewed in PT &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2012/07/among-the-creat.html&quot;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core of their argument lies in the introduction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The scientific theory of evolution involves higher-level models that are associated with a range of non-scientific factors, including exegetical and theological judgments.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something seems (and indeed is) back to front here. Some scientists work for the greater glory of God, and some to put God out of business, while I expect that most have never given a thought to theological issues. Their conclusions may have implications in “exegetical and theological judgments,” but these are consequences, not components, of the scientific framework. Why do Wood and Madueme (W&amp;amp;M) think otherwise?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors spell out their position, early on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;[W]e argue that the scientific theory of evolution involves higher-level models that are shaped by non-scientific factors. We then show that theological commitments—held not only by Christians but by non-theists as well—affect those higher-level models that influence our epistemic assessment of evolution.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So non-theists ln their attitude to evolution science are influenced in ways that presumably they do not realize by theological commitments. As a non-theist and former theist who has always accepted mainstream evolution science on its merits, I consider this claim both unwarranted and presumptuous, and disconcertingly close to the claim made by many creationists that evolution is itself a form of religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, gradually, we find out what is behind the claim, and why it is crucial to the authors’ entire outlook. They admit the range and strength of the scientific evidence for common ancestry, which is the aspect of evolution science most directly relevant to their own theological concerns, and quote the appraisal by the philosophers McCain and Weslake:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The evidence for common ancestry includes the fossil record, comparative anatomy, embryology, genetics, and geographic species distribution, while natural selection gains support from natural and laboratory work, including computer simulations and mathematical models.&lt;sup&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And later:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Gijsbert van den Brink and his colleagues distinguish three different layers of evolutionary theory, namely, 1) historical evolution, 2) common descent, and 3) natural selection.2 They conclude that multiple, mutually reinforcing lines of evidence for historical evolution render it strongly beyond reasonable doubt. The evidence for common descent, they argue, is also strong though less than the evidence for historical evolution (“weaky beyond reasonable doubt”). They give the lowest evidential score to natural selection, given notable scientific disagreements about its importance in evolution (van den Brink et al. 2017, 466–68).&lt;sup&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt; Most scientists would agree with these conclusions.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I think would most readers here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How, then, could W&amp;amp;M maintain their own rejection of evolution? Easily! They have prepared the ground by saying (p. 198), in response to this classification,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;Common ancestry acts as a higher-level model that coordinates and supports more directly empirical models (like natural selection) within or beneath it.&lt;/i&gt; [Emphasis in original]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The keyword here is “supports.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. Common ancestry does not support the data. It is an outcome, not an input, much as process uniformitarianism is an outcome from looking at ancient rocks. Or, to take an example with which I do not think W&amp;amp;M could possibly disagree, atomic theory is the higher-level model used by chemists since long before they could observe the effects of individual atoms. However, this status is not an overarching presupposition, but the outcome of diverse observations, ranging from the combining ratios of elements to the properties of gases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors give another example of why they regard common ancestry as a higher-level model:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The fact that common ancestry was accepted during the eclipse of Darwinism indicates that scientists could accept this higher-level model independently of any details of how common ancestry came to be.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the contrary. Common ancestry continued to be accepted, even though (in W&amp;amp;M’s version of history) Darwin’s causal mechanism had been rejected, because of the way in which it was supported by the many lines of evidence that they themselves had listed. Bottom-up, not top-down. John Paul II &lt;a href=&quot;https://humanorigins.si.edu/sites/default/files/MESSAGE%20TO%20THE%20PONTIFICAL%20ACADEMY%20OF%20SCIENCES%20(Pope%20John%20Paul%20II).pdf&quot;&gt;got it right&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;It is indeed remarkable that this theory [evolution] has been progressively accepted by researchers, following a series of discoveries in various fields of knowledge. The convergence, neither sought nor fabricated, of the results of work that was conducted independently is in itself a significant argument in favor of this theory.&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If W&amp;amp;M do not see things this way, it is because they are committed to top-down reasoning. As they say, in a section titled “Evolution without theological presuppositions is impossible,”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Dogmatic commitments inevitably shape our overall judgments of the epistemic status of evolution. Theology is the epistemic linchpin.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They impose such dogmatic commitments even when they are absent.&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; Thus they cite Richard Dawkins’s famous remark, “Darwin made it possible to be an intellectually fulfilled atheist,” as evidence that our theology shapes our views on evolution, when Dawkin himself tells us that it was the other way round; learning about evolution led him to reject his former faith. This inverted perspective makes it possible for them to say in all seriousness,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Some epistemic judgments depend on how one evaluates the clarity of nature against the clarity of Scripture. Young-earth creationists tend to foreground the perspicuity of Scripture and the fallibility of science, while theistic evolutionists tend to emphasize the clarity of science and the ambiguity of exegesis.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My translation: Young earth creationists think that their own exegesis of Scripture and commitment to its truth gives them the right to overlook both the scientific evidence and the possibility that their exegesis itself may be in error. This on the basis of a false equivalence between the two epistemic evaluations: on the one side, a priori commitment to a doctrinal position, and on the other, willingness to pay attention to facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later they elaborate on this very point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;We agree with scientific realists that the objective data in creation should inform any assessment of evolution, but the process of interpreting the data should also entail theological oh judgments.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the authors are claiming the right to interpret facts to fit their theological preconceptions. If they do not like the outcome of a scientific enquiry, they will demand that the evidence be tortured until it says what they want to hear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, something interesting happens, that changes the reader’s perspective on everything that has gone before. Having established that for Christians like them, the epistemic status of evolution will depend on theological considerations, they then admit that Christians can reasonably disagree about this theology. Understandably, they deplore the way in which unbelievers and evolution-accepting believers alike regard young earth creationism as absurd. More surprisingly, they deplore the mirror-image attitude of young earth creationists such as Henry Morris and John MacArthur, who describe those who accept evolution as atheistic, irrational, and amoral. They invoke the great commandment to love one another, too often neglected as “we evangelicals find group identity and security in our confessions, doctrinal statements, and ideological consortiums,” and for this reason urge dialogue even when such dialogue seems impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors, I now belatedly realize, are not really talking to me but to those who share their own fundamental outlook. If they have been at great pains to affirm their own epistemic position, that is partly to establish their own credentials, and partly to suggest to their fellows that respectful treatment of a different epistemic position may be possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are practical reasons for the dialogue that they are commending. Evolution-accepting Christians should not be made to feel unwelcome in churches where they are in the minority. Conversely, creationism-accepting students should not be ignored or silenced in the science classroom. Here they cite the philosopher and former biology teacher Douglas Allchin, who discusses how to engage such students, and advocates examining epistemology, building trust, and considering evolution in the context of the moral order.&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; As practical examples of the mutually respectful attitude that they recommend, they quote at some length from Jason Rosenhouse’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Among-Creationists-Dispatches-Anti-Evolutionist-Front/dp/0199744637&quot;&gt;Among the Creationists&lt;/a&gt; (reviewed on PT &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2012/07/among-the-creat.html&quot;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;), with his emphasis on the enriching experience of seeing those we disagree with as real people, not merely defined by stereotypes and the oddity of their beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this also reminded me of James Krupa, award-winning biology professor at the University of Kentucky, who concludes his lectures with explicit discussion of social resistance to evolution.&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; Even more relevant is the approach being developed by Constance Bertka and colleagues.&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt; Here, as a prelude to the discussion of evolution, students consider the range of possible views on the relationship between religion and science, from conflict to integration. Comparing hermeneutics, just as W&amp;amp;M are advocating. A strange alliance, between those dedicated to the effective teaching of evolution science, and those who fundamentally oppose its conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is as different as possible from the attitude that runs through the mainstream creationist literature, from George McCready Price onwards, and that is expressed in the blurb&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt; to Wood’s own book, &lt;i&gt; Understanding the Pattern of Life&lt;/i&gt;, I mentioned earlier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Darwinian evolutionary theory has been largely recognized over the last century to be the most pervasive and damaging influence on modern society. As a frontal assault on the Kingdom, evolution has been Christianity's most notorious detractor and its greatest foe.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What has changed? The times have changed. As W&amp;amp;M put it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;In the North American context, the polarized and fractured political climate illustrates how sinful division can fester in the absence of ideological interaction. Sober reflection on the consequences of ideological segregation should motivate us to cultivate the true discipline of dialogue.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed. And we do not need more riots on the steps of the Capitol, or more pastors forced out of their congregations for showing independence of thought, or more memoirs like Tim Alberta’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Kingdom-Power-Glory-Evangelicals-Extremism/dp/006322688X &quot;&gt;The Kingdom, the Power, and the Glory&lt;/a&gt;, to show us what they mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Notes and References.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;McCain, Kevin and Brad Weslake 2013, “Evolutionary Theory and the Epistemology of Science.” In &lt;i&gt;The Philosophy of Biology: A Companion for Educators&lt;/i&gt;, edited by Kostas Kampourakis, 101–19. Dordrecht: Springer, p 106&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Van den Brink, Gijsbert, Jeroen de Ridder, and René van Woudenberg. 2017. “The Epistemic Status of Evolutionary Theory.” &lt;i&gt;Theology and Science&lt;/i&gt; 15(4): 454–72.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, evolutionary science does not consist of a single theory, but of numerous theories interacting. The Pope was aware of this, and spelled it out later in his message.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As also illustrated by their treatment of Denis Lamoureux’s position in the same Section.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Allchin, Douglas. 2013. “Sacred Bovines.” &lt;i&gt;The American Biology Teacher&lt;/i&gt; 75(2) : 144-147. https://doi.org/10.1525/abt.2013.75.2.16&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Krupa, James. “Defending Darwin.” &lt;i&gt;Orion&lt;/i&gt; March/April 2015:  https://orionmagazine.org/article/defending-darwin/&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Constance M. Bertka, Briana Pobiner, Paul Beardsley and William A. Watson, 2019. “Acknowledging students’ concerns about evolution: a proactive teaching strategy.” &lt;i&gt;Evo Edu Outreach&lt;/i&gt; (2019) 12:3. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12052-019-0095-0&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As shown on the &lt;i&gt;Alibris &lt;/i&gt;website. We do not know if Wood himself wrote this blurb, but it could hardly have been adopted without his approval.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman</name></author><summary type="html">I am writing in response to the article Bridging ideological divides: Why Christians still disagree about evolution and what we whould do about it, by Hans Madueme and Todd Charles Wood, Scientia et Fides 12(1), 2024, 189–213; open access here. This article is written by two young earth creationists, who take 25 closely argued pages including 93 references to show complete misunderstanding of the relationship between observation and interpretation in evolution science, in order to claim a false epistemic symmetry between this science and the theological perspective which forces them to reject it; a more sophisticated version of the “two pairs of spectacles” thesis that has been with us since George McCready Price. So why am I bothering to review this article? And why, to my own surprise, do I find myself welcoming its appearance? For three reasons. Firstly, because the authors, unlike “creation science” young earth creationists, accept the validity of the science in its own terms, rather than claiming that it is inferior to their own fantastical offerings. Secondly, because they lay out extremely clearly (and self-revealingly) their own epistemic position. And finally, because their recommendations, made regarding conversations within the evangelical community, are applicable (and indeed to some extent already applied) to the very practical problem of how to teach evolution science in places with a faith-based culture.</summary></entry></feed>