<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-21T04:11:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">The Questions of Race and Evolution</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/questions-race-evolution.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Questions of Race and Evolution" /><published>2021-01-18T14:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-01-18T14:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/questions-race-evolution</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/questions-race-evolution.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/ML_King_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Martin Luther King, Jr.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://abc7news.com/mlk-martin-luther-king-jr-nobel-prize-lecture/1163922/&quot;&gt;Rev. Martin Luther King, Jr.&lt;/a&gt; delivering his Nobel Peace Prize acceptance speech. &lt;small&gt;ABC News, Channel 7, San Francisco; Associated Press.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today is Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. Day in the United States. This day, we remember the courage that was required to engage with racism in our society. The history here is both hopeful and discouraging. For all the progress made, much is left undone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some question why we should even address race on &lt;em&gt;The Panda’s Thumb&lt;/em&gt;, a blog devoted to defending evolutionary science. Perhaps this will just end into a contentious debate about the scientific particulars about the biological meaning of race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to talk about race. Still, we should find the courage to engage. The questions matter here. There are important things that can and should be said by us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to follow Todd Wood’s example. This summer, this young earth creationist asked, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://discourse.peacefulscience.org/t/todd-wood-is-evolution-racist/11287&quot;&gt;Is Evolution Racist?&lt;/a&gt;” Knowing this genre well, we should expect a diatribe of race-baiting, but that is not what Wood did. Instead, he took an honest look at his camp’s own history of racism, explaining how creationism has been used to justify racism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wood’s approach displays obvious integrity. His direct explanation of the history of racism in his own camp, to his own community, was not easy. It was not costless. He demonstrated courage, and in doing so sets an important example for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, much of the same reality is true of evolution too. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientific_racism&quot;&gt;There is a complex and troubled history of racism among evolutionary scientists&lt;/a&gt;. Evolution has often been used to justify false understandings of race and the evil of racism. It serves the common good to acknowledge this, to teach its history, and to model how to move past it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is difficulty in reckoning our history here. Dr. King has words for us. He was a theologian by training, but he also discussed science. In fact, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/alexknapp/2014/01/20/martin-luther-king-jr-on-science-and-religion&quot;&gt;he said quite a bit about science&lt;/a&gt;. In his Nobel Prize lecture, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/peace/1964/king/lecture/&quot;&gt;King observes&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Yet, in spite of these spectacular strides in science and technology, and still unlimited ones to come, something basic is missing…We have learned to fly the air like birds and swim the sea like fish, but we have not learned the simple art of living together as brothers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be disagreements with the particulars of what he said of science and religion. Still, it seems that we should agree with him here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been more than 50 years since MLK was murdered. Over that half century, we certainly have not learned how to live together as a common family. Now, it is legal to integrate; the law does not force us to segregate. In that sense, we are desegregated. Yet we still live apart from one another. We have not managed well what MLK called the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.faculty.umb.edu/lawrence_blum/courses/318_11/readings/king_ethical_demands.pdf&quot;&gt;ethical demands for integration&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evolutionary science is important, in part because it brings us to grand questions about who we are and where we came from. Origins, at its best, brings us to the grand question of what it means to be human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this front, looking past our disagreements, it seems there is broad consensus among evolutionary scientists on these points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. There are &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/phc3.12468&quot;&gt;many definitions of race&lt;/a&gt;, especially if we include &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/epdf/10.1111/phc3.12467&quot;&gt;folk and historical definitions&lt;/a&gt;. For that reason, we have to be careful about equivocation in the term &quot;race.&quot; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. Evolutionary science certainly &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; rule out many understandings of biology race, but perhaps not all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3. Some of the versions of &quot;race&quot; ruled out were quite prevalent in the past, including among evolutionary scientists. It is worth understanding why they were wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4. We now know that the human species is far more linked by interbreeding that we realized even just 50 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5. Even if biological races are real in some sense, that reality would not grant moral legitimacy to racism. Even as we debate the legitimacy of certain understanding of race, recognizing differences would not legitimize dehumanizing people based on those differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6. There is, regrettably, a near total absence of African American scientists in evolutionary science, and in the biological sciences as a whole. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is much more I could say here, but these points of agreement seem like a good place to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our points of disagreement, also, are important. I want to work through them. A full telling of evolutionary science includes the questions of race. These questions are difficult, in part &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; they extend beyond evolutionary science. The payoff is worth the trouble. The science here is interesting, and it can serve the common good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps, in a conversation among scientists, we can find a better way. The conversation is difficult for obvious reasons. We are faced with questions about our moral worth, dignity, and place in society. How we think about race matters. Scientists can and should be a model community for navigating the complexity here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>S. Joshua Swamidass</name></author><summary type="html">Rev. Martin Luther King, Jr. delivering his Nobel Peace Prize acceptance speech. ABC News, Channel 7, San Francisco; Associated Press. Today is Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. Day in the United States. This day, we remember the courage that was required to engage with racism in our society. The history here is both hopeful and discouraging. For all the progress made, much is left undone. Some question why we should even address race on The Panda’s Thumb, a blog devoted to defending evolutionary science. Perhaps this will just end into a contentious debate about the scientific particulars about the biological meaning of race. It is difficult to talk about race. Still, we should find the courage to engage. The questions matter here. There are important things that can and should be said by us. I want to follow Todd Wood’s example. This summer, this young earth creationist asked, “Is Evolution Racist?” Knowing this genre well, we should expect a diatribe of race-baiting, but that is not what Wood did. Instead, he took an honest look at his camp’s own history of racism, explaining how creationism has been used to justify racism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Great Sand Dunes</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/great-sand-dunes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Great Sand Dunes" /><published>2021-01-18T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-01-18T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/great-sand-dunes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/great-sand-dunes.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;C. Joseph Long&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Long_great_sand_dunes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Great Sand Dunes&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/grsa/learn/nature/index.htm&quot;&gt;Great Sand Dunes National Park and Preserve&lt;/a&gt;.  Mr. Long writes, “Dunes up to 200 m are formed where wind sweeping across the cold semi-desert of southern Colorado’s San Luis Valley is funneled toward Mosca Pass in the Sangre de Cristo range on the eastern edge of the southern Rocky Mountains.  The valley itself is a deep graben toward the upper end of the Rio Grande Rift with no surface drainage in its northern reaches.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by C. Joseph Long. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Great Sand Dunes National Park and Preserve. Mr. Long writes, “Dunes up to 200 m are formed where wind sweeping across the cold semi-desert of southern Colorado’s San Luis Valley is funneled toward Mosca Pass in the Sangre de Cristo range on the eastern edge of the southern Rocky Mountains. The valley itself is a deep graben toward the upper end of the Rio Grande Rift with no surface drainage in its northern reaches.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Does op-doc unintentionally tout Ark Park?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/does-op-doc-tout-ark.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does op-doc unintentionally tout Ark Park?" /><published>2021-01-07T14:55:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-01-07T14:55:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/does-op-doc-tout-ark</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/does-op-doc-tout-ark.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Times_Ark_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;aerial view of Ark&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Aerial view of the “Ark,” from the op-doc. &lt;small&gt; Credit: &lt;i&gt;Super Deluxe Films&lt;/i&gt;. Fair use.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Times&lt;/em&gt; the other day posted an “op-doc,” or an op-ed in documentary-film format, concerning the “Ark” Park in Kentucky. I have received a handful of communications about this op-doc, and I have decided to plagiarize all of them. I will not identify the authors, but if they feel like identifying themselves, they can do so in the comments. The op-doc is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2021/01/05/opinion/noahs-ark-kentucky.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It is behind a pay wall, but you may be entitled to access a few pages each month without a subscription. At any rate, I found a range of opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first person to contact me noted that the piece had been posted in the &lt;em&gt;Times&lt;/em&gt; and called it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[a]n uncritical free ad for the Ark Park disguised as an op-ed “documentary.” The NYT let this in as an “opinion” piece. It is directed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jeremyseifert.com/&quot;&gt;Jeremy Seifert&lt;/a&gt;. Seifert’s other work doesn’t appear to be aligned with fundamentalism; he does seem to have directed or produced a film attacking GMO foods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remainder of the comments come from a listserv I subscribe to. A second person wrote, 
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The documentary doesn’t state a point of view overtly, but subtly conveys the incongruities of the place as a tourist attraction, as well as the silliness of the exhibits. It also conveys the humanity of the locals. Doing those things together is a pretty neat trick. And there’s more to the film than I’m saying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a third person:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Basically, it seems to make it clear that there was no “secular intent” in the approval and promotion of the Ark by proponents in Williamstown or in Grant County.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This was, for them, a part of their expression of faith and evangelism – the “tourist attraction” and economic development bits were a secondary motive, though they were used to justify putting a lot of public money and resources into the construction and infrastructure (and it is also clear that the economic boom never happened).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is also clear that there is a shared culture in the region – such that the people in the film cite biblical stories and recite passages that only make sense if people are already familiar with the biblical passages. The one that struck me was the mention of the 3 holy children[,]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mechon-mamre.org/p/pt/pt34.htm&quot;&gt;Daniel&lt;/a&gt; 3. I certainly did not see all of that in that film, and I thought that Person 3 might be reading more into it because of prior knowledge. At any rate, he then added,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I don’t entirely disagree with [the first person]. It is clearly uncritical of the whole operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But what it does do, IMHO, is to make clear that the support for the Ark and Creation Museum in Grant County, Williamstown, and Kentucky &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; religiously motivated and that the “economic development/tourism” promotion was little more than a cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The economic legacy of the projects makes that clear – the “secular” authorities are still strongly in support despite the fact that none of the economic predictions have come to pass (and [Ken] Ham et al. backtracked on the issue, saying – I think this is made clear in &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/04/reviews-of-documentary.html&quot;&gt;We Believe in DInosaurs&lt;/a&gt; – that they never really &lt;em&gt;promised&lt;/em&gt; that these economic outcomes would happen).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But one would have to have context to see that underneath all the testimonials – and the film clearly does not provide such.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, you may see a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/11/we-believe-on-PBS.html&quot;&gt;slightly shortened version&lt;/a&gt; of the film &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/independentlens/films/we-believe-in-dinosaurs/&quot;&gt;We Believe in Dinosaurs&lt;/a&gt; on PBS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If other people read things into the op-doc or thought it was kind of an anodyne commercial for the “Ark” Park, another person asked,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Is it just me? I thought it was crude and indeed insulting satire of a creationist. &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/environmental-science/climate-change/im-climate-change-alarmist/&quot;&gt;Ham does believe in the fire to come&lt;/a&gt;, but do we want to go there?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reference is to a web page where Ken Ham acknowledges the reality of climate change and then avers that “Jesus will return and the earth (and whole universe) will be judged with fire and God will make a new heavens and earth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I was directed to &lt;a href=&quot;https://friendlyatheist.patheos.com/2021/01/06/this-short-film-about-ark-encounter-functions-as-an-unintentional-advertisement/&quot;&gt;This Short Film about Ark Encounter Functions as an Unintentional Advertisement&lt;/a&gt;, by Hemant Mehta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Mehta’s article is somewhat more wide-ranging than the title suggests, but he concludes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ultimately, it functions as an unintentional advertisement for the Ark precisely because there’s nothing critical about it in the film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me? I did not read much into the film. I thought it was somewhat tedious and completely uncritically showed various people quoting the Bible, not to mention a mannequin. Granted that it was short, perhaps one-quarter the length of “We Believe in Dinosaurs,” but it seemed to me that it lacked the analysis and the counterpoint that we saw in “We Believe in Dinosaurs.” All in all, yes, an unintentional ad for the fake Ark. My Wife and Harshest Critic, however, thinks it was deliberately favorable, if not an intentional ad: It was not just uncritical, but downright laudatory, and it did not explore any of the implications of locating the “Ark” near Williamstown. A talented musician, she did not think the music helped the film along and was unimpressed when I told her that it was credited to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arvo_P%C3%A4rt&quot;&gt;Arvo Pärt&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Aerial view of the “Ark,” from the op-doc. Credit: Super Deluxe Films. Fair use. The Times the other day posted an “op-doc,” or an op-ed in documentary-film format, concerning the “Ark” Park in Kentucky. I have received a handful of communications about this op-doc, and I have decided to plagiarize all of them. I will not identify the authors, but if they feel like identifying themselves, they can do so in the comments. The op-doc is available here. It is behind a pay wall, but you may be entitled to access a few pages each month without a subscription. At any rate, I found a range of opinions. The first person to contact me noted that the piece had been posted in the Times and called it [a]n uncritical free ad for the Ark Park disguised as an op-ed “documentary.” The NYT let this in as an “opinion” piece. It is directed by Jeremy Seifert. Seifert’s other work doesn’t appear to be aligned with fundamentalism; he does seem to have directed or produced a film attacking GMO foods. The remainder of the comments come from a listserv I subscribe to. A second person wrote,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Vulpes vulpes</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/vulpes-vulpes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vulpes vulpes" /><published>2021-01-04T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-01-04T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/vulpes-vulpes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/vulpes-vulpes.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/DSC03943_Foxes_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Red foxes&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Pair of red foxes, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cpw.state.co.us/fox&quot;&gt;Vulpes vulpes&lt;/a&gt;, um, enjoying the outdoors. The Boulder &lt;i&gt;Daily Camera&lt;/i&gt; on December 21 called it a Festive Frolic. I had to take the picture through a dirty glass window to avoid disturbing them, and I confess to a little image processing.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Pair of red foxes, Vulpes vulpes, um, enjoying the outdoors. The Boulder Daily Camera on December 21 called it a Festive Frolic. I had to take the picture through a dirty glass window to avoid disturbing them, and I confess to a little image processing.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Science bridges divides</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/science-bridges-divides.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science bridges divides" /><published>2020-12-29T13:05:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-12-29T13:05:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/science-bridges-divides</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/science-bridges-divides.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Lents_Swamidass_1200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Venn diagram&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science bridges divides. That is the lesson enunciated by our colleagues &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nathan_H._Lents&quot;&gt;Nathan Lents&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://swami.wustl.edu/&quot;&gt;Joshua Swamidass&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stltoday.com/opinion/columnists/nathan-h-lents-and-s-joshua-swamidass-the-lesson-of-kitzmiller-science-bridges-divides/article_829435cc-154f-5940-bf26-2456da663965.html&quot;&gt;St. Louis Post-Dispatch&lt;/a&gt; yesterday and earlier in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://triblive.com/opinion/nathan-lents-and-dr-s-joshua-swamidass-science-bridges-divides-for-a-better-world/&quot;&gt;Pittsburgh Tribune-Review&lt;/a&gt; on December 18.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The occasion? The fifteenth &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/where-were-you.html&quot;&gt;anniversary&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2005/12/unconstitutiona.html&quot;&gt;Dover decision&lt;/a&gt; by District Court Judge John E. Jones III “that it is unconstitutional to teach ID as an alternative to evolution in a public school science classroom.” December 20 has come to be known as Kitzmas, and the Panda’s Thumb &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2005/12/unconstitutiona.html&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; by PZ Myers may be the &lt;a href=&quot;http://itre.cis.upenn.edu/~myl/languagelog/archives/002718.html&quot;&gt;first use of that term&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is unusual about the Lents-Swamidass collaboration is that Prof. Lents is a professed atheist and Prof. Swamidass is an evangelical Christian (and indeed the proprietor of the blog &lt;a href=&quot;https://peacefulscience.org/&quot;&gt;Peaceful Science&lt;/a&gt; and the author of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B07V4TBL5Z/&quot;&gt;The Genealogical Adam and Eve&lt;/a&gt;). Besides their own collaboration, which has led to speaking engagements “with audiences from the ‘liberal elites’ at Columbia University to the ‘biblically conservative’ at Concordia University,” they note the collaboration between Catholic biologist Kenneth Miller and “non-believer” Barbara Forrest at Dover. They further point out that, a year or so after the Dover decision, Francis Collins published his book &lt;em&gt;The Language of God&lt;/em&gt;, in which Dr. Collins attempts to reconcile his Christian belief with his acceptance of evolutionary science. (We discussed &lt;em&gt;The Language of God&lt;/em&gt; on Panda’s Thumb &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2009/07/francis-collins-3.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, when Dr. Collins was nominated to be director of the National Institutes of Health.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drs. Lents and Swamidass collaborated with Richard E. Lenski to pen a negative &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/363/6427/590.full&quot;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; of the book &lt;em&gt;Darwin Devolves&lt;/em&gt; by Michael Behe in the journal &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; (behind a paywall, incidentally). They claim in the &lt;em&gt;Post-Dispatch&lt;/em&gt; article that they are risking their reputations by collaborating with each other. That may be so, but, as an accommodationist myself, I can only support their collaboration. Atheists need to understand that some people have a need to believe in a force greater than ourselves, and fundamentalists (for want of a better, general term) need to accept the findings of modern science and develop ways to integrate them with their religious beliefs. If collaborations such as Lents-Swamidass will encourage atheists to deal better with their religious friends, and fundamentalists to deal better with the reality of science, then I am all for such collaborations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Science bridges divides. That is the lesson enunciated by our colleagues Nathan Lents and Joshua Swamidass in the St. Louis Post-Dispatch yesterday and earlier in the Pittsburgh Tribune-Review on December 18. The occasion? The fifteenth anniversary of the Dover decision by District Court Judge John E. Jones III “that it is unconstitutional to teach ID as an alternative to evolution in a public school science classroom.” December 20 has come to be known as Kitzmas, and the Panda’s Thumb article by PZ Myers may be the first use of that term.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mark Meadows and his skeletons</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/mark-meadows-skeletons.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mark Meadows and his skeletons" /><published>2020-12-28T17:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-12-28T17:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/mark-meadows-skeletons</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/mark-meadows-skeletons.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Allosaurus_Wide_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Allosaurus skeleton&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Allosaurus skeleton. &lt;small&gt;''Allosaurus fragilis'' skeleton mounted in the lobby of the San Diego Natural History Museum. Wikimedia. Photograph by user Sheep81.  Public domain. https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Allosaurus_SDNHM.jpg. &lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we have not been paying enough attention to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Meadows_(North_Carolina_politician)&quot;&gt;Mark Meadows&lt;/a&gt;, the White House Chief of Staff. We noted recently that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mr. Meadows may or may not be a creationist, but he is certainly a fellow traveler: At one time [2002], he purchased a piece of property on which an Allosaurus specimen had been discovered (supposedly by some home-schooled children). He then [2014] sold the property to Answers in Genesis, arguably in order to keep the fossils under the control of young-earth creationists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a bit anodyne. In fact, according to an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.salon.com/2020/12/27/mark-meadows-has-skeletons-in-the-closet--dinosaur-skeletons-to-be-precise/&quot;&gt;article In Salon&lt;/a&gt;, it was Mr. Meadows’s daughter Haley who supposedly discovered the dinosaur on the last day of the dig. In fact, according to the Salon article, the fossil had been discovered two years earlier by the person, Dana Forbes, who had sold the property to Mr. Meadows. It was identified in 2001 by paleontologist Joe Taylor. That skeleton, as &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2014/05/dinosaur-fossil.html&quot;&gt;we reported&lt;/a&gt;, was eventually donated to the Creation “Museum” by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the Elizabeth Streb Peroutka Foundation. The foundation’s leader Michael Peroutka until recently was also a board member of the League of the South, a white supremacist, neo-Confederate and pro-secessionist organization that has been named a hate group by the Southern Poverty Law Center[,]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;according to a press release from paleontologist Daniel Phelps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Salon article, besides involving his 9-year-old daughter in some kind of apparent fraud, Mr. Meadows&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;had since at least 2018 apparently failed to disclose a loan and monthly income of $11,000 related to the sale of a deed to a Colorado fossil park dedicated to promoting the creationist fiction that humans coexisted with dinosaurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, Salon reports that Mr. Meadows was sanctioned in 2018 for misusing taxpayer money and may have done so again in 2020. Finally, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.salon.com/2020/10/30/watchdog-files-complaint-accusing-trumps-chief-of-staff-mark-meadows-of-campaign-finance-crimes/&quot;&gt;Salon reporting&lt;/a&gt; has apparently inspired a watchdog group to file a complaint against Mr. Meadows with the Federal Election Commission.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Allosaurus skeleton. ''Allosaurus fragilis'' skeleton mounted in the lobby of the San Diego Natural History Museum. Wikimedia. Photograph by user Sheep81. Public domain. https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Allosaurus_SDNHM.jpg. I think we have not been paying enough attention to Mark Meadows, the White House Chief of Staff. We noted recently that Mr. Meadows may or may not be a creationist, but he is certainly a fellow traveler: At one time [2002], he purchased a piece of property on which an Allosaurus specimen had been discovered (supposedly by some home-schooled children). He then [2014] sold the property to Answers in Genesis, arguably in order to keep the fossils under the control of young-earth creationists. That was a bit anodyne. In fact, according to an article In Salon, it was Mr. Meadows’s daughter Haley who supposedly discovered the dinosaur on the last day of the dig. In fact, according to the Salon article, the fossil had been discovered two years earlier by the person, Dana Forbes, who had sold the property to Mr. Meadows. It was identified in 2001 by paleontologist Joe Taylor. That skeleton, as we reported, was eventually donated to the Creation “Museum” by the Elizabeth Streb Peroutka Foundation. The foundation’s leader Michael Peroutka until recently was also a board member of the League of the South, a white supremacist, neo-Confederate and pro-secessionist organization that has been named a hate group by the Southern Poverty Law Center[,] according to a press release from paleontologist Daniel Phelps. According to the Salon article, besides involving his 9-year-old daughter in some kind of apparent fraud, Mr. Meadows had since at least 2018 apparently failed to disclose a loan and monthly income of $11,000 related to the sale of a deed to a Colorado fossil park dedicated to promoting the creationist fiction that humans coexisted with dinosaurs. In addition, Salon reports that Mr. Meadows was sanctioned in 2018 for misusing taxpayer money and may have done so again in 2020. Finally, Salon reporting has apparently inspired a watchdog group to file a complaint against Mr. Meadows with the Federal Election Commission.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is natural selection a meaningless tautology?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Fitness-Tautology.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is natural selection a meaningless tautology?" /><published>2020-12-27T16:45:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-12-27T16:45:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Fitness-Tautology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Fitness-Tautology.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/mothceiling.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Moth on ceiling&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;A moth on our dining room ceiling, with
 unsuccessful&lt;br /&gt; cryptic coloration -- most likely
 a geometrid moth of the tribe&lt;br /&gt; Hydriomenini, perhaps the Tissue Moth, &lt;em&gt;Triphosa haesitata&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt; (thanks to John Morgan and Matt Young for the leads)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In argument with creationists one often hears the point made, triumphantly,
that natural selection is a tautology.  The implication is that evolutionary
biologists are so generally incompetent that they don't recognize this, and that
when they invoke the concept of fitness they are engaging in a meaningless
circular argument.  Natural selection, creationists argue, is supposed to be &quot;survival
of the fittest&quot;.  Yet how do we define fittest?  Why, merely as those that
survive.  So it reduces to &quot;survival of the survived&quot;, and thus cannot be
more than a meaningless incantation.  Gotcha!
&lt;p&gt;
But ...
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
... it's &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a tautology.  First of all, an aside: fitness is not merely &quot;survival&quot;.  For some reason creationists are fixated on survival and do not realize that
evolutionary biologists also count in fitness the expected amount of reproduction of
those parents that survive.  But that technicality aside ...
&lt;p&gt;
I saw on a blog (&lt;a href=&quot;http://theskepticalzone.com/wp/is-darwinian-evolution-teleonomic/comment-page-4/#comment-104569&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) a good analogy:
Is it tautological or circular or meaningless
to say that when we make up a track team we should choose runners who are
faster than the others?  Is it meaningless to look at earlier races or practice
sessions to see who are the best runners?  Obviously this is not meaningless, because ability to run fast often carries over from one race to another, even though
this will not always be perfectly true.
&lt;p&gt;
It is when we expand our view beyond the single sample of individuals and the single generation that we can see that fitness is not a tautology.  We can, for
example:
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Assess the fitness of different genotypes in our initial one-generation study
and look at whether different genotypes have different fitnesses.  And then we
can validate the results by looking at how fit those genotypes are in additional
samples of individuals in the same generation, or looking at samples in other populations or in later generations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; We can do the same for phenotypes: for example, are larger individuals more
fit?  Do hawks with longer wings catch more prey?  Does this carry over into
other samples, other populations, other generations?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; We can ask what will be the consequences if the relative fitnesses (the ratios of the fitnesses) of different genotypes remain the same over many generations. Starting with initial gene frequencies, there are standard equations of
theoretical population genetics that predict long-term outcomes. And we can
calculate what will happen if fitnesses vary between populations, or vary across generations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My colleagues in evolutionary biology are not idiots.  They devote a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of time and effort to measuring fitnesses of different genotypes and phenotypes, and in different populations and in different generations.  Right now &quot;experimental evolution&quot; studies which mutate sequences and then ask how those genotypes
change frequency in cultures of yeast are very popular, now that DNA sequencing
of large samples can be done. These are popular methods for assessing the
effect of changes in the sequence.  There are good reasons for all of these studies,
and calling fitness a tautology will not make any impression -- it certainly
won't cause these studies to come to a screeching halt.
&lt;p&gt;
And in case you need more elaborate philosophical consideration of this issue,
here are two discussions you can access online:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.talkorigins.org/faqs/evolphil/tautology.html&quot;&gt;John Wilkins's discussion&lt;/a&gt; of the charge of tautology at the Talk.Origins Archive site,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the Wikipedia article on &quot;Survival of the fittest&quot;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Survival_of_the_fittest#Tautology&quot;&gt;the section on this issue&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;`
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">A moth on our dining room ceiling, with unsuccessful cryptic coloration -- most likely a geometrid moth of the tribe Hydriomenini, perhaps the Tissue Moth, Triphosa haesitata (thanks to John Morgan and Matt Young for the leads) In argument with creationists one often hears the point made, triumphantly, that natural selection is a tautology. The implication is that evolutionary biologists are so generally incompetent that they don't recognize this, and that when they invoke the concept of fitness they are engaging in a meaningless circular argument. Natural selection, creationists argue, is supposed to be &quot;survival of the fittest&quot;. Yet how do we define fittest? Why, merely as those that survive. So it reduces to &quot;survival of the survived&quot;, and thus cannot be more than a meaningless incantation. Gotcha! But ...</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Conjunction of Jupiter and Saturn (and the Moon)</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/conjunction-jupiter-saturn.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Conjunction of Jupiter and Saturn (and the Moon)" /><published>2020-12-21T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-12-21T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/conjunction-jupiter-saturn</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/conjunction-jupiter-saturn.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/DSC03959_Cropped_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jupiter, Saturn, and the Moon&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/feature/the-great-conjunction-of-jupiter-and-saturn&quot;&gt;conjunction&lt;/a&gt; of Jupiter and Saturn will be seen tonight if the sky is clear. But the Moon cooperated better a few days ago, on December 18. Directly above, you can see Jupiter and, slightly above Jupiter, a dimmer Saturn.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">The conjunction of Jupiter and Saturn will be seen tonight if the sky is clear. But the Moon cooperated better a few days ago, on December 18. Directly above, you can see Jupiter and, slightly above Jupiter, a dimmer Saturn.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Where were you on December 20, 2005?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/where-were-you.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Where were you on December 20, 2005?" /><published>2020-12-20T08:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-12-20T08:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/where-were-you</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/where-were-you.html">&lt;p&gt;Where were you on December 20, 2005? I was in Cusco, Peru, …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/IMG_3424_Cusco_Cathedral_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cathedral&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cusco_Cathedral&quot;&gt;Cusco Cathedral&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… with a handful of others, when we entered a hotel, foraging for coffee. Immediately, a copy of the day’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://timesdigest.com/&quot;&gt;Times Digest&lt;/a&gt; bearing this headline …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Dover_Pic_Montage.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Newspaper clipping&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/20/education/judge-bars-intelligent-design-from-pa-classes.html&quot;&gt;Article in the New York Times&lt;/a&gt; by Laurie Goodstein on December 20, 2005.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… or some approximation thereto positively leaped off a table and into my hand, and screamed, “&lt;em&gt;We won in Dover!&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where were you that day? What were you doing when you heard the news? Let us know in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Where were you on December 20, 2005? I was in Cusco, Peru, … Cusco Cathedral. … with a handful of others, when we entered a hotel, foraging for coffee. Immediately, a copy of the day’s Times Digest bearing this headline … Article in the New York Times by Laurie Goodstein on December 20, 2005. … or some approximation thereto positively leaped off a table and into my hand, and screamed, “We won in Dover!” Where were you that day? What were you doing when you heard the news? Let us know in the comments.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why latkes are better than hamantashen</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/why-latkes-better.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why latkes are better than hamantashen" /><published>2020-12-17T10:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-12-17T10:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/why-latkes-better</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/why-latkes-better.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jerry Coyne &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2020/12/17/tonight-the-university-of-chicagos-world-famous-latke-hamentash-debate/&quot;&gt;informs us&lt;/a&gt; that the latke-versus-hamantash debate originated at the University of Chicago. He also reminds me that tonight is the last night of Chanukah, so I had better post this piece now. I wrote it years ago for the debate, Are Latkes Better Than Hamantashen? at my local synagogue. For those not in the know, latkes are a Chanukah delicacy: potato pancakes cooked in oil to represent the oil lamp that miraculously burned for eight days after the Maccabees rededicated the Temple. Hamantashen are triangular cookies eaten on the holiday of Purim (which is based on the Book of Esther).&lt;/em&gt; Penimah &lt;em&gt;is a play on the Hebrew name&lt;/em&gt; Peninah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, hamantashen are not kosher. (1) They have 3 sides, which symbolizes the Trinity.  (2) As if to drive the point home, they are filled with poppy seeds; these were originally popey seeds, from the Latin word &lt;em&gt;papaver&lt;/em&gt;, which means true pope. (3) Finally, the word is really a corruption of Haman-&lt;em&gt;toosh&lt;/em&gt;, and everyone knows that the hindquarters of an animal are not kosher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the word for hamantashen in Hebrew is &lt;em&gt;oznay haman&lt;/em&gt;, which means &lt;em&gt;Haman’s ears&lt;/em&gt;. This means they give your children selective hearing and inspire them to poke holes in their earlobes (and maybe elsewhere).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latkes are called &lt;em&gt;latkes&lt;/em&gt; in Yiddish because they were developed by Lot, unlike Haman a righteous man and a nephew of my ancestor Abraham. The Hebrew word is &lt;em&gt;levivah&lt;/em&gt;, which comes from the word &lt;em&gt;lev&lt;/em&gt; for &lt;em&gt;heart&lt;/em&gt;. The first words of the Israeli national anthem are
&lt;em&gt;Kol ohd ba-levav penimah&lt;/em&gt;, which means &lt;em&gt;Everyone wants another of Penima’s latkes&lt;/em&gt;. This shows that all that oil is really good for your heart and further that, when modern science disagrees with the Torah, the Torah is right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, if G-dash-d had wanted us to eat hamantashen, not latkes, he or she would have had us fill them with carrots so that at least they would be good for our eyes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Jerry Coyne informs us that the latke-versus-hamantash debate originated at the University of Chicago. He also reminds me that tonight is the last night of Chanukah, so I had better post this piece now. I wrote it years ago for the debate, Are Latkes Better Than Hamantashen? at my local synagogue. For those not in the know, latkes are a Chanukah delicacy: potato pancakes cooked in oil to represent the oil lamp that miraculously burned for eight days after the Maccabees rededicated the Temple. Hamantashen are triangular cookies eaten on the holiday of Purim (which is based on the Book of Esther). Penimah is a play on the Hebrew name Peninah. First, hamantashen are not kosher. (1) They have 3 sides, which symbolizes the Trinity. (2) As if to drive the point home, they are filled with poppy seeds; these were originally popey seeds, from the Latin word papaver, which means true pope. (3) Finally, the word is really a corruption of Haman-toosh, and everyone knows that the hindquarters of an animal are not kosher. Furthermore, the word for hamantashen in Hebrew is oznay haman, which means Haman’s ears. This means they give your children selective hearing and inspire them to poke holes in their earlobes (and maybe elsewhere). Latkes are called latkes in Yiddish because they were developed by Lot, unlike Haman a righteous man and a nephew of my ancestor Abraham. The Hebrew word is levivah, which comes from the word lev for heart. The first words of the Israeli national anthem are Kol ohd ba-levav penimah, which means Everyone wants another of Penima’s latkes. This shows that all that oil is really good for your heart and further that, when modern science disagrees with the Torah, the Torah is right. In short, if G-dash-d had wanted us to eat hamantashen, not latkes, he or she would have had us fill them with carrots so that at least they would be good for our eyes.</summary></entry></feed>