<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-08-24T21:04:30-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Ginkgo biloba</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/ginkgo-biloba.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ginkgo biloba" /><published>2025-08-18T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-08-18T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/ginkgo-biloba</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/ginkgo-biloba.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Denelsbeck_Ginkgo_biloba.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ginkgo biloba showing water droplets&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ginkgo_biloba&quot;&gt; Ginkgo biloba&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; ginkgo leaf after a heavy rain. Mr. Denelsbeck notes, &quot;The leaves are quite water-repellent (hydrophobic) and cause the water to form almost-spherical drops under their own surface tension, which allows them to become lenses by themselves &amp;ndash; you can see them showing further drops behind themselves. Often called a &quot;living fossil,&quot; ginkgos are the last of their 300 my order, Ginkgoales, and easily distinguished by the leaf 'veins' which do not branch, but all originate from the base of the stem in a fanlike manner. This trait, along with the water-repellence, helps funnel water down to the trunk and thus to roots that would otherwise be blocked or redirected by the leaves. Canon 7D, Canon 18-135 STM at 135&amp;nbsp;mm, ISO 250, F/13, 1/200&amp;nbsp;s with custom softbox flash unit.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Al Denelsbeck. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Ginkgo biloba &amp;ndash; ginkgo leaf after a heavy rain. Mr. Denelsbeck notes, &quot;The leaves are quite water-repellent (hydrophobic) and cause the water to form almost-spherical drops under their own surface tension, which allows them to become lenses by themselves &amp;ndash; you can see them showing further drops behind themselves. Often called a &quot;living fossil,&quot; ginkgos are the last of their 300 my order, Ginkgoales, and easily distinguished by the leaf 'veins' which do not branch, but all originate from the base of the stem in a fanlike manner. This trait, along with the water-repellence, helps funnel water down to the trunk and thus to roots that would otherwise be blocked or redirected by the leaves. Canon 7D, Canon 18-135 STM at 135&amp;nbsp;mm, ISO 250, F/13, 1/200&amp;nbsp;s with custom softbox flash unit.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Knowing you are right, even when you are not</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/knowing-you-are-right.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Knowing you are right, even when you are not" /><published>2025-08-17T10:58:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-08-17T10:58:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/knowing-you-are-right</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/knowing-you-are-right.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/On_Being_Certain_Cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This little book, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B003J5UJHW/&quot;&gt; On Being Certain&lt;/a&gt;: Believing You Are Right Even When You’re Not&lt;/i&gt;, is not exactly about epistemology, that is, how we know what we know; rather, it is about how we think we know, even when potentially we do not. Indeed, it seems to me that it explains why the philosopher Lee McIntyre was by his own account singularly unsuccessful in convincing virtually any science denier about anything (see my article &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/how-to-talk-science-denier.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author of the present book, Robert Alan Burton, is a neurologist, not a philosopher. The book was originally published in 2009 and recently rereleased. It is well out of my area, so I have no way of knowing how much is dated. To oversimplify, Burton argues, somewhat apologetically, that there may be evolutionary advantage to having a module that quickly tells you, you are right. As he notes in the Preface,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Despite how certainty feels, it is neither a conscious choice nor even a thought process. Certainty and similar states of “knowing what we know” arise out of involuntary brain mechanisms that, like love or anger, function independently of reason.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He calls this sentence “[t]he revolutionary premise at the heart of this book….”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another oversimplification (mine, that is): Burton tells us that the brain is a neural network (or perhaps a network of neural networks) that can be characterized as having an input, an output, and between them a hidden layer that does all the processing. We know that the layer is hidden, in part because we can bring to the surface only one or two of our thought processes at a time. Other thought processes are clearly going on, as we know, for example, when we have a sudden realization of something that we did not consciously know we were thinking about. Suddenly, we just &lt;i&gt;know&lt;/i&gt; the solution to an important problem; we have what Burton calls a &lt;i&gt;feeling of knowing&lt;/i&gt;, and he considers this phrase so important that he italicizes it throughout the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This insight, that we have a &lt;i&gt;feeling of knowing&lt;/i&gt; whether we know or not, is important to discussions of pseudoscience. In my article on McIntyre’s book &lt;i&gt;On Being Certain&lt;/i&gt; (see link above), we met flat-earthers who could not be disabused of what we consider their delusions. Relevantly to PT, Burton hauls out the creationist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurt_Wise&quot;&gt;Kurt Wise&lt;/a&gt;, who has a BA degree in geophysics from the University of Chicago, an MA degree in geology from Harvard, and a PhD in paleontology under no less a personage than Stephen Jay Gould. He is now director of the Creation Research Center at Truett McConnell University in Georgia. For all that, Wikipedia quotes him as saying,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Although there are scientific reasons for accepting a young Earth, I am a young age [sic] creationist because that is my understanding of the Scripture. As I shared with my professors years ago when I was in college, if all the evidence in the universe turns against creationism, I would be the first to admit it, but I would still be a creationist because that is what the Word of God seems to indicate.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wise is now director of the Creation Research Center at a Baptist institution, Truett McConnell University in Georgia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least Wise has the humility to use the qualifier “&lt;i&gt;seems to&lt;/i&gt; indicate.” Richard Dawkins, as Barton describes him, seems absolutely sure of himself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Faith is the great cop-out, the great excuse to evade the need to think and evaluate evidence. Faith is belief in spite of, even perhaps because of, the lack of evidence.&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;And&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;I will respect your views if you can justify them. But if you justify your views only by saying you have faith in them, I shall not respect them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though I am far more sympathetic to Dawkins than to Wise, I fear that Dawkins has succumbed to the &lt;i&gt;feeling of knowing&lt;/i&gt; and assumes that his thoughts are purely rational. Burton argues to the contrary, that your thoughts are shaped by your past and the structure of your brain. The disembodied rational mind, he says, does not exist. Both Dawkins and Wise have the &lt;i&gt;feeling of knowing&lt;/i&gt;, and Dawkins is downright evangelical in his need to propagate his atheism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lest you get the wrong idea, Barton is not a nihilist and clearly sees the need for evidence. He takes the physician Andrew Weil to task for refusing to believe a null result, instead saying,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; We were unable in those tests to prove that this had an effect. The problem is, I’m sure there’s an effect there. 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was reminded of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brainyquote.com/quotes/richard_p_feynman_137642&quot;&gt;Richard Feynman’s famous quotation&lt;/a&gt;, “The first principle is that you must not fool yourself, and you are the easiest person to fool.” At any rate, you do not need a disembodied rational mind to know that if you do an experiment properly you ought to accept the results. As Barton notes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The failures of science … begin with personal self-deception and an unjustified &lt;i&gt;sense of knowing&lt;/i&gt;. … &quot;I am sure&quot; is a mental sensation, not a testable conclusion.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will not go into detail, but besides Weil and Dawkins, Barton subjects to scrutiny Russell Targ, Paul Davies, Leon Kass, Francis Collins, Richard Lewontin, Daniel Dennett, Stephen Jay Gould, Stephen Hawking, and Malcolm Gladwell. Some of them fare better than others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will conclude, as does Barton, with a speculation as to whether&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;some of the toughest age-old philosophical issues arise out of attempts to resolve perceptual tricks created by our brains.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Dos_caras_una_copa.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Vase-faces illusion&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubin_vase&quot;&gt;Rubin's vase.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Dos_caras_una_copa.jpg&quot;&gt;Photograph&lt;/a&gt; by Sebasgiu.  Own work. Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 4.0 international license. &lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barton notes the famous “optical illusion of the silhouette of two opposing faces that can also be seen as a vase.” I think virtually everyone knows this illusion, Rubin’s vase, pictured at left, so Barton does not see a need to show it. When you look at the picture one way, you see a vase; when you look at it another way, you see two opposing faces in profile. Evidently it is not possible to see both at once. Barton wonders whether mind-body dualism, for example, or our inability to understand whether time or space begins or is infinite, is roughly equivalent to our inability to view Rubin’s vase as both two faces and a vase at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completely off-task: The discussion made me wonder about wave-particle duality. Very roughly, if we perform a diffraction experiment with a phosphorescent screen, a photon will propagate through space as if it were a wave but react with the screen as if it were a particle. Presumably it is something much more complicated than either a wave or a particle, something that is occasionally called a wavicle. Is it possible that the perceived duality is no more than our inability to perceive both aspects, wave and particle, simultaneously, a sort of physical Rubin’s vase?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">This little book, On Being Certain: Believing You Are Right Even When You’re Not, is not exactly about epistemology, that is, how we know what we know; rather, it is about how we think we know, even when potentially we do not. Indeed, it seems to me that it explains why the philosopher Lee McIntyre was by his own account singularly unsuccessful in convincing virtually any science denier about anything (see my article here). The author of the present book, Robert Alan Burton, is a neurologist, not a philosopher. The book was originally published in 2009 and recently rereleased. It is well out of my area, so I have no way of knowing how much is dated. To oversimplify, Burton argues, somewhat apologetically, that there may be evolutionary advantage to having a module that quickly tells you, you are right. As he notes in the Preface,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Archilestes grandis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/archilestes-grandis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Archilestes grandis" /><published>2025-08-04T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-08-04T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/archilestes-grandis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/archilestes-grandis.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Joel Eissenberg&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Eissenberg_Archilestes grandis.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Damselfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_spreadwing&quot;&gt;Archilestes grandis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; great spreadwing damselfly spotted at the Denver zoo. Prof. Eissenberg notes that &quot;the resemblance between the damselfly and the twig to which it is clinging shows mimicry.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Joel Eissenberg. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Archilestes grandis &amp;ndash; great spreadwing damselfly spotted at the Denver zoo. Prof. Eissenberg notes that &quot;the resemblance between the damselfly and the twig to which it is clinging shows mimicry.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Worst Scopes Article Ever</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/worst-scopes-article-ever.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Worst Scopes Article Ever" /><published>2025-08-03T08:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-08-03T08:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/worst-scopes-article-ever</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/worst-scopes-article-ever.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Braterman_Darrow_Interrogating_Bryan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Darrow interrogating Bryan out-of-doors&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/0d/Tennessee_v._John_T._Scopes_Trial-_Outdoor_proceedings_on_July_20%2C_1925%2C_showing_William_Jennings_Bryan_and_Clarence_Darrow._%282_of_4_photos%29_%282898243103%29_crop.jpg&quot;&gt;William Jennings Bryan (seated, left) being cross-examined by Clarence Darrow&lt;/a&gt;, the trial having been moved outside because of the heat. Photograph by Watson Davis. Public domain.&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a close run thing. I would narrowly give second place to Answers in Genesis, which blames Bryan’s humiliation on &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2025/06/13/partnering-with-faithful-fathers/&quot;&gt;his willingness to contemplate an ancient Earth&lt;/a&gt;. But first place, to Mike Mueller, writing for &lt;strike&gt;Creation Research International (CRI)&lt;/strike&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icr.org/article/scopes-monkey-trial-battle-worldviews/&quot;&gt;Institute for Creation Research (ICR)&lt;/a&gt; , which takes on the interesting task of seeing how well the scientific evidence has held up, gets every single detail wrong, and tells more than the usual number of lies in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early on: “Eventually the Butler Act was overturned.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Eventually” means in 1967! Forty-two years after the trial, seventeen years after the establishment of the National Science Foundation, and six years after the publication of &lt;i&gt;The Genesis Flood&lt;/i&gt; led to the resurgence of young Earth creationism. And it was not “overturned,” but repealed. This matters because of ongoing creationist complaints about judicial activism; it was a decision by the State Governor, rather than the outcome of a lawsuit, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Butler_Act&quot;&gt;although&lt;/a&gt; it was indeed a pending freedom of speech lawsuit that forced the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;[S]upposed experts presented some of the following topics as proof. Many are still used, but the scientific evidence actually supports creation, not evolution. Consider the claims and our brief responses.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “supposed” experts included half a dozen professors of geology, zoology, agriculture, and education from the Universities of Chicago, New Jersey, and Missouri, Johns Hopkins, and Harvard, as well as the State Geologist of Tennessee (the location of the trial), and, for good measure, a rabbi. Their combined testimony, available &lt;a href=&quot;https://profjoecain.net/scopes-monkey-trial-1925-complete-trial-transcripts/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, runs to 35 closely argued pages. It is an admirable document, including among other things the use of molecular biology (in the form of serology) to show that whales are related to hoofed animals. And of course none of it was “presented” at the trial, but merely deposited without being presented to jury, since the judge (in a sense, correctly) regarded it as irrelevant to whether Scopes had broken the law. But consider now the individual claims as summarized and allegedly refuted by &lt;strike&gt;CRI&lt;/strike&gt; ICR:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Claim&lt;/strong&gt;: Evolution from simple cells to complex life, bacteria to man, is a fact.

&lt;strong&gt;Response&lt;/strong&gt;: The trial experts admitted they didn’t know where the first cell came from and weren’t clear on the process or method evolution uses. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, we don’t know the origins of life. So what? We don’t know the origins of language, either, but we do know an enormous amount about how languages have evolved. As for not being clear on process or method, we are as would be expected a lot clearer now than we were a hundred years ago. Again, so what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, Mueller makes reference to a new theory being developed by Randy Giulizza, which he describes as based on engineering approach. This asserts that organisms have an inbuilt ability to modify their development in the face of new environmental challenges. Lamarckism, combined with the gift of prophecy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Claim&lt;/strong&gt;: Ape-to-human evolution is demonstrated by fossils.

&lt;strong&gt;Response&lt;/strong&gt;: The so-called missing links between ape and man are still missing. No discoveries show that humans descended from primates, and the fossil specimens presented in the trial and since have turned out to be fully human, fully ape or animal, a mixture of human and animal, or fraudulent.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The specimens described at the trial were Java Man (now classified as &lt;i&gt;Homo erectus&lt;/i&gt;, which branched off from our own line of descent some 2 million years ago); Heidelberg Man (now regarded as ancestral to both Neanderthal Man and anatomically modern humans); Piltdown Man, concerning which Professor Horatio Hackett Newman stated in his deposition that “there has been a great deal of controversy as to their significance. Until the experts arrive at an agreement about this type it might be well for others to reserve judgment”; Neanderthal Man (whose status as a close but distinct sister species to us is of course now well established); Rhodesia Man (regarded as related to Heidelberg Man); and a then recently discovered child’s skull which we now classify as &lt;i&gt;Australopithecus africanus&lt;/i&gt;. So there were already an impressive collection of “missing links,” which could not really be classified either as fully human or as fully ape, and the only fraud in the bunch came with a warning label. What we have learned since has greatly added to the number of ancestral species and sister lines of descent. As for any attempted division into “fully human” or “fully ape,” that is simply a pathology of rigid binary thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Claim&lt;/strong&gt;: The geological record proves evolution because simple life forms are buried in the deepest geological layers.

&lt;strong&gt;Response&lt;/strong&gt;: The fossil record documents the ecological zones that were progressively flooded and buried in the global Flood of Genesis. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All geological layers display a full range of ecological zones, to the point that we can compare extinct species with modern species showing similar lifestyles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Claim&lt;/strong&gt;: The earth is millions of years old, allowing for evolution to have occurred.

&lt;strong&gt;Response&lt;/strong&gt;: Many dating methods used to assign millions-of-years ages to rock specimens are based on unprovable assumptions and/or produce inconsistent results. Most evidence clearly supports a young earth and coincides with the biblical timeframe of around 6,000 years.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creationist list of “unprovable assumptions,” namely amount of daughter material initially present, the possible mobility of isotopes, and the constancy of radioactive decay constants, is cut-and-paste from classical papers on the subject, dating back to around 1910. My favorite account of how these problems have been overcome is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.asa3.org/ASA/resources/Wiens2002.pdf&quot;&gt;Radiometric dating; a Christian perspective&lt;/a&gt;, by Roger Wiens at Los Alamos, himself an evangelical Christian. Simply put, the first two problems are overcome by looking at more than two isotopes, and where possible at rock grains within which the initial incorporation of daughter would have been impossible, while the radioactive decay constants depend on fundamental laws that must have been the same when the rocks were laid down, or we would never have had such rocks. As for “Most evidence,” this refers to methods based on such things as the thickness of sediments or the salinity of the oceans, which consider the rate of deposition of substances but not their removal. These were in any case regarded, until superseded by radiometric dating, as indicating an age of the earth of around 100 million years. I’m not aware of any method that supports 6,000 years, except for recent geological phenomena such as Niagara Falls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Claim&lt;/strong&gt;: The tailbone, appendix, wisdom teeth, and other organs are vestigial features.

&lt;strong&gt;Response&lt;/strong&gt;: Parts of organisms once thought to be useless evolutionary leftovers are today known to have important functions. They were designed according to God’s plan.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If evolution is correct, we would expect organs that had lost their initial function to undergo one of two fates: total disappearance (in which case we would not see them now even as vestiges) or, an interesting possibility clearly realized by Darwin, modification with change of function. Thus the human appendix is now thought to act as a useful refugium for essential gut bacteria, while the whale’s residual hind limbs serve to anchor muscles used, I have read, to hold the parties together during sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Claim&lt;/strong&gt;: Genetic similarity and breeding results support evolution.

&lt;strong&gt;Response&lt;/strong&gt;: Human and ape DNA are now known to be 84% similar, not 98% as initially claimed. And variation between plant and animal species can be managed by controlled genetic breeding. This is not evidence of gradual change driven by random mutations over millions of years.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been known for a very long time that roughly 15% of human and chimpanzee DNA is not directly comparable, because of major deletions and inversions, while the 98% similarity refers to that part of the genome where direct comparison is possible. Every so often, some new analysis reminds creationists of these familiar facts, and they gleefully point out that 84% is less than 98%, thus to their satisfaction refuting the argument from genetic similarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Claim&lt;/strong&gt;: Embryonic development and comparative embryology between animals prove that living organisms came from a common ancestor because their developing embryos echo evolutionary stages.

&lt;strong&gt;Response&lt;/strong&gt;: This idea was popularized in 1866 by Ernst Haeckel. He was later reprimanded for using fraudulent drawings. Unfortunately, students are still told that developing babies go through evolutionary history with gill slits, a tail, and yolk sacs, even though this is false. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all dishonest creationist arguments, this is the one that I find most annoying. There is no way in which our present knowledge of embryology is affected by possible dishonesty in Haeckel’s work over 150 years ago. Human embryos do indeed “go through evolutionary history with gill slits, a tail, and yolk sacs,” as is evident in the freely viewable images of weeks 6 and 7 on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.babycenter.com/pregnancy/week-by-week&quot;&gt;the Babycenter site&lt;/a&gt;. As spelled out in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.280.5366.983c&quot;&gt;a key paper&lt;/a&gt; by the very author that creationists most frequently quote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;On a fundamental level, Haeckel was correct: All vertebrates develop a similar body plan (consisting of notochord, body segments, pharyngeal pouches, and so forth). This shared developmental program reflects shared evolutionary history. It also fits with overwhelming recent evidence that development in different animals is controlled by common genetic mechanisms.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a fundamental level, I have questions of my own. Are the &lt;strike&gt;CRI&lt;/strike&gt; ICR scientists, some with reputable training, knowingly telling lies? Or do they think that they are legitimately simplifying complex matters to make them clearer to a lay audience? Or are their cognitive filters and biases so well developed that they can see only what confirms their case, even when looking directly at information that refutes it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficult questions, but relevant to the choice of counter-tactics, and on which I would much appreciate readers’ opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Braterman_Embryo_Stage_12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Human embryo, stage 12&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Human embryo, stage 12, Shigehito Yamada and Tetsuya Takakuwa, &lt;i&gt;The Human Embryo&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footnote: The freely downloadable book chapter, &lt;i&gt;Developmental Overview of the Human Embryo&lt;/i&gt;,  DOI &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.5772/38232&quot;&gt;10.5772/38232&lt;/a&gt;, by Shigehito Yamada and Tetsuya Takakuwa, in the book &lt;i&gt;The Human Embryo&lt;/i&gt; (Intech Open, 2012), gives an excellent detailed account of developmental stages, with gill pouches, tail, and yolk sac clearly visible at 28 days, as shown.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman</name></author><summary type="html">William Jennings Bryan (seated, left) being cross-examined by Clarence Darrow, the trial having been moved outside because of the heat. Photograph by Watson Davis. Public domain. It’s a close run thing. I would narrowly give second place to Answers in Genesis, which blames Bryan’s humiliation on his willingness to contemplate an ancient Earth. But first place, to Mike Mueller, writing for Creation Research International (CRI) Institute for Creation Research (ICR) , which takes on the interesting task of seeing how well the scientific evidence has held up, gets every single detail wrong, and tells more than the usual number of lies in the process. Early on: “Eventually the Butler Act was overturned.” “Eventually” means in 1967! Forty-two years after the trial, seventeen years after the establishment of the National Science Foundation, and six years after the publication of The Genesis Flood led to the resurgence of young Earth creationism. And it was not “overturned,” but repealed. This matters because of ongoing creationist complaints about judicial activism; it was a decision by the State Governor, rather than the outcome of a lawsuit, although it was indeed a pending freedom of speech lawsuit that forced the issue.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy Lamarck day</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/HappybirthdayLamarck.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy Lamarck day" /><published>2025-08-01T13:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2025-08-01T13:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/HappybirthdayLamarck</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/HappybirthdayLamarck.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Buffon2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Not Lamarck but instead Buffon]&quot; /&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Not actually Lamarck, but instead 
his superior, Buffon.&lt;br /&gt; Painting by François-Hubert Drouais. From Wikimedia.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, it is the birthday (August 1st) of Jean Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet, the Chevalier de 
Lamarck.  He was the first major evolutionary biologist (as far as I am concerned).  He drew some of 
the first evolutionary trees, and suggested mechanisms for evolution, including adaptation. (His mechanisms 
were wrong, of course).  He was also a major pioneer of invertebrate biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On past birthdays I have covered many aspects of Lamarck’s life and work, down to and including the 
avenue and Paris Metro station named after him.  This time, allow me to digress to the life of 
his patron Buffon, who also has a claim to be an early evolutionist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Georges-Louis Leclerc, Comte de Buffon (1707-1788) was a sometime-aristocrat who was 
interested in many scientific and mathematical questions.  Among other investigations, he had 
his employees measure the rate of cooling of a metal sphere after it was taken out of a 
furnace, and from this estimated the age of the Earth as almost 75,000 years.  This is much 
more than the biblical figure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was most famous for writing a 39-volume &lt;em&gt;Histoire Naturelle&lt;/em&gt; which surveyed many 
aspects of natural history, and was widely read.  In the course of this, he raised the issue of evolutionary 
change, and argued that it was due to degeneration of forms from an original continuum of 
life.  He was actually forced by Paris academicians to recant his views because they 
conflicted with the biblical account.  He gave no mechanism for the evolution of adaptation, 
however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His connection with Lamarck was direct.  When Lamarck started writing on the flora of 
France, Buffon, who was head of the royal botanical garden, was impressed and gave him 
a job there.  When I visited the garden, which now contains the museum of natural 
history as well, I saw an impressive 18th century mansion there.  On it was a 
plaque announcing that Buffon has lived in it and had died there, and so had Lamarck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without Buffon, Lamarck would probably not have accomplished much of what he did. 
Perhaps Buffon’s cleverest achievement was that he died one year before the start 
of the French Revolution.  So here’s a toast to Buffon, and thus indirectly to Lamarck.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Not actually Lamarck, but instead his superior, Buffon. Painting by François-Hubert Drouais. From Wikimedia. &amp;nbsp; Once again, it is the birthday (August 1st) of Jean Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet, the Chevalier de Lamarck. He was the first major evolutionary biologist (as far as I am concerned). He drew some of the first evolutionary trees, and suggested mechanisms for evolution, including adaptation. (His mechanisms were wrong, of course). He was also a major pioneer of invertebrate biology. On past birthdays I have covered many aspects of Lamarck’s life and work, down to and including the avenue and Paris Metro station named after him. This time, allow me to digress to the life of his patron Buffon, who also has a claim to be an early evolutionist.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Evolution News finds the problem with the evolution of mimicry</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/olearymimicry.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evolution News finds the problem with the evolution of mimicry" /><published>2025-07-28T13:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-28T13:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/olearymimicry</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/olearymimicry.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Butterflyfish.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[The Four-eyed Butterflyfish]&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Four-eyed Butterflyfish, &lt;em&gt;Chaetodon capistratus&lt;/em&gt;, 
with the real pair of eyes obscured by stripes, allowing the large spots 
to be mistaken for eyes. From Wikimedia.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Discovery Institute’s &lt;em&gt;Evolution News&lt;/em&gt; website is the foremost site for 
advocacy of Intelligent Design.  We should therefore expect its arguments to 
be technically sound and convincing.  An extraordinary example of their 
standards appeared recently there.  On the 23rd of July, Denyse O’Leary,
who posts there often, explained why: 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2025/07/for-darwinism-here-is-the-problem-with-butterfly-mimicry/&quot;&gt;For Darwinism, Here Is the Problem with Butterfly Mimicry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She starts by noting a scientific paper which examined the evolution of 
a type of mimicry in which what look like large eyespots occur near the 
rear end of butterfly wings.  A similar example in butterflyfish will be 
seen in the image above.  These false eyespots might tempt a predator to 
attack that end of the butterfly rather than its actual head.  The 
paper examines such color patterns across many butterfly species, and 
finds that the elements of the pattern evolve together in different 
parts of the evolutionary tree, multiple times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors of that paper conclude that this repeated correlated evolution 
is most likely the result of natural selection for mimicry.
Not so Denyse O’Leary.  She sees a big problem: the fallacy of 
“the five percent solution”.  If the pattern is only five 
percent present, how can it be favored by natural selection?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charles Darwin (uncredited by O’Leary) gave a convincing 
argument for how eyes in animals could evolve, starting 
with a mere light-sensitive spot.  O’Leary argues that 
no such argument can be made for the false eyespots:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I call this the “five percent solution” because of a question asked in the article at PBS above, “What good is five percent of an eye?” And a reasonable answer is: Some good. Even a light-sensitive spot is better than no vision at all.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But Now What about the Five Percent Problem?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The dead leaf butterfly’s challenge — to take one example — is quite different from the one a blind worm faces. The blind worm is better off with five percent of visual information, as opposed to none at all.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;But a method of deception that is only five percent persuasive is not a first step on a road to a solution. Looking only five per cent like a dead leaf would likely prove fatal to the insect that relied on it. The false head butterfly would face the same problem: If the wing spots looked only a bit like a head for aeons, the gradually evolving insect would need a different method of self-protection for quite a long time. And, under the circumstances, why would either the dead leaf or false head mimicry continue to evolve?
There really isn’t an adequate answer to this problem because Darwinian evolution is not thought to show foresight. The usual response has been to Cancel the question instead. That submerges the question but doesn’t make it go away.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not convinced. &lt;!--more--&gt; O’Leary assumes an all-or-nothing view of adaptation.  Either a 
species is fully adapted, so that the mimicry is fully effective, or it has 
no adaptation at all.  But encounters between predators and prey occur in many 
different circumstances, sometimes with predators having a good view of the 
potential prey for a long time, and sometimes with them having only a brief 
and obscured glimpse for just a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A prey individual may be covered with irregular blotches, as a means of 
cryptic coloration.  And these blotches may occasional strike the predator 
as eyes.  If that can cause the predator to misdirect its attack, this 
pattern may have a small increase in fitness.  The resulting small 
selection pressure can gradually make the pattern of blotches more like 
a pair of eyes. (I should add another possibility – that the false eyes 
make the prey look like the head of a larger species, such as a 
snake.  That would tend to deter the predator from attacking.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Invoking the 5% problem and assuming that only a 100% mimicry can have 
any effect on fitness follows a common argument of opponents of 
natural selection.  Both of the two main ID arguments, complex specified 
information and irreducible complexity, seek to do away with the 
possibility that effective adaptations could arise step by step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The common thread in all this is that advocates of ID and/or creationism 
simply don’t understand how natural selection works in populations. 
Any noise, uncertainty, or weakness of selection pressure is assumed to 
prevent adaptation from being achieved at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denyse O’Leary’s argument, like most others she makes, reveal a 
thorough misunderstanding of evolutionary biology.  They end up 
being astonishingly weak arguments.  They reveal that the DI, in 
Evolution News, is willing to endorse absurd arguments as meeting 
its supposedly-high standards.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">The Four-eyed Butterflyfish, Chaetodon capistratus, with the real pair of eyes obscured by stripes, allowing the large spots to be mistaken for eyes. From Wikimedia. &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The Discovery Institute’s Evolution News website is the foremost site for advocacy of Intelligent Design. We should therefore expect its arguments to be technically sound and convincing. An extraordinary example of their standards appeared recently there. On the 23rd of July, Denyse O’Leary, who posts there often, explained why: For Darwinism, Here Is the Problem with Butterfly Mimicry. She starts by noting a scientific paper which examined the evolution of a type of mimicry in which what look like large eyespots occur near the rear end of butterfly wings. A similar example in butterflyfish will be seen in the image above. These false eyespots might tempt a predator to attack that end of the butterfly rather than its actual head. The paper examines such color patterns across many butterfly species, and finds that the elements of the pattern evolve together in different parts of the evolutionary tree, multiple times. The authors of that paper conclude that this repeated correlated evolution is most likely the result of natural selection for mimicry. Not so Denyse O’Leary. She sees a big problem: the fallacy of “the five percent solution”. If the pattern is only five percent present, how can it be favored by natural selection? Charles Darwin (uncredited by O’Leary) gave a convincing argument for how eyes in animals could evolve, starting with a mere light-sensitive spot. O’Leary argues that no such argument can be made for the false eyespots: I call this the “five percent solution” because of a question asked in the article at PBS above, “What good is five percent of an eye?” And a reasonable answer is: Some good. Even a light-sensitive spot is better than no vision at all. But Now What about the Five Percent Problem? The dead leaf butterfly’s challenge — to take one example — is quite different from the one a blind worm faces. The blind worm is better off with five percent of visual information, as opposed to none at all. But a method of deception that is only five percent persuasive is not a first step on a road to a solution. Looking only five per cent like a dead leaf would likely prove fatal to the insect that relied on it. The false head butterfly would face the same problem: If the wing spots looked only a bit like a head for aeons, the gradually evolving insect would need a different method of self-protection for quite a long time. And, under the circumstances, why would either the dead leaf or false head mimicry continue to evolve? There really isn’t an adequate answer to this problem because Darwinian evolution is not thought to show foresight. The usual response has been to Cancel the question instead. That submerges the question but doesn’t make it go away.” I’m not convinced.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Booster Shots, book by Adam Ratner</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/booster-shots-book.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Booster Shots, book by Adam Ratner" /><published>2025-07-28T09:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-28T09:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/booster-shots-book</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/booster-shots-book.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Ratner_Booster_Shots_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book Cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This splendid little book (202 pp. not counting the notes) is ostensibly about measles, but it covers a lot more, not least how we are probably unprepared for the next pandemic. I learned two main things: Vaccines do not prevent disease; &lt;i&gt;vaccinations&lt;/i&gt; prevent disease. And successful campaigns against contagious diseases contain within them the seeds of their own destruction. The first of these is perhaps obvious; the second, perhaps less so, but once a disease is eradicated or nearly eradicated, people forget, become complacent, possibly exaggerate the side effects of immunization, and sometimes tragically fail to get their vaccinations. Later in the book, the author discusses the libertarian conceit that individual rights take precedence over obligations to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first things first. The book is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/670274/booster-shots-by-adam-ratner-md-mph/&quot;&gt;Booster Shots&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://nyulangone.org/doctors/1972558187/adam-j-ratner&quot;&gt;Adam Ratner&lt;/a&gt;, a specialist in infectious pediatric diseases at New York University’s Grossman School of Medicine. He is also, judging by the contents of his book, a good historian and a talented writer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;History first. I was fascinated by the story of Peter Panum, a Norwegian doctoral student (!), who was sent with his fellow student August Manicus, to the Faroe Islands in 1846 to study an outbreak of measles. The Faroes had never suffered from measles and were sparsely populated. The two facts together made them a “natural laboratory” and enabled Panum to, in effect, invent the science of epidemiology and also show that measles was a contagious disease and not caused by a “miasma,” or bad air, as from a swamp. Panum went on to a distinguished career and according to Ratner contributed to immunology, physiology, nutrition, and binocular vision, as well as integrating Scandinavian medicine with European medicine. He worked about a decade before John Snow, who found the origin of the cholera epidemic in London, but Panum is not well known, at least in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ratner’s detailed history also brought home that measles is not a childhood disease. When the population is dense, however, everyone who is not a child has already had the disease and is immune or has died from it, so children are almost the only ones who contract the disease today. Contrary to what many think, measles is a serious disease with a mortality rate of a few per thousand cases. In the early twentieth century, the disease was exacerbated by the architecture of the tenements in which the urban poor typically lived. Even today, mortality in the industrialized nations is higher among the poor than among the rich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The eradication of smallpox is well and widely known, but Ratner’s telling is nevertheless interesting. Cotton Mather, whom Ratner calls “ostensibly a man of God,” lost much of his family to measles, but then promoted variolation to prevent smallpox. For his pains he was sent a Molotov cocktail (fortunately, a dud) along with a note, “Cotton Mather, You Dog, Dam you: I’ll inoculate you with this, with a Pox to you.” Anti-vaxxers have a longer history than I ever imagined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonas Salk and Albert Sabin developed polio vaccines based on the work of John Enders and colleagues. Polio was virtually wiped out in the United States. Why not measles, for which Enders developed a vaccine that was licensed around a decade after polio? It is complicated, but I well remember how frightened parents were during the polio epidemic, whereas measles (and mumps and whooping cough) were considered “just” childhood diseases. Also, says Ratner, there was no plan for purchasing and distributing measles vaccine. There were two measles vaccines, and it was unclear which one was preferred. Ratner’s lessons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;that messages matter, that policy decisions about vaccine availability and recommendations matter, and that early confusion on the part of parents and pediatricians can prove difficult to overcome….&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still have not learned all those lessons with regard to Covid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even so, we eventually came close to wiping out measles, but then the anti-vaxx movement hit and combined with our collective amnesia to result in a substantial number of unvaccinated children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do people fear vaccination (Ratner politely calls them vaccine-hesitant)? He tells us early on: “fear of vaccines and minimization of the real dangers of the diseases that those vaccines protect against.” Ethical lapses, such as the infamous Tuskegee experiment, also did not help. Ratner stresses, correctly, I think, that the vaccine-hesitant are not fools, and their concerns need to be taken seriously and addressed sympathetically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will not go into detail, but Ratner describes the situation in Texarkana, a city that straddles the border between Texas and Arkansas. The two halves of the city are evidently completely integrated, but Arkansas required vaccination for measles, whereas Texas did not. You can guess what is coming next: in a measles outbreak in 1970, 96 % of all cases in Texarkana were found among people who lived in Texas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ratner is almost unfailingly polite; remember, he advised approaching vaccine-hesitant patients sympathetically. He shows no sympathy for Robert F. Kennedy Jr. who, he says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;traveled to Samoa to meet with the prime minister and local activists, ghoulishly spreading unfounded anti-vaccine messages in an attempt to ensure that no tragedy would go to waste.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book was almost certainly submitted for publication before Kennedy lied to a congressional committee and set about destroying the National Institutes of Health and other agencies under his purview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ratner worries that we made mistakes letting measles back in. We similarly made mistakes with Covid, but these were more mistakes of ignorance than of omission. He worries that we will not be ready for the next pandemic, whatever it is and wherever it strikes. He is, however, optimistic that we can eliminate measles if we put our minds to it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">This splendid little book (202 pp. not counting the notes) is ostensibly about measles, but it covers a lot more, not least how we are probably unprepared for the next pandemic. I learned two main things: Vaccines do not prevent disease; vaccinations prevent disease. And successful campaigns against contagious diseases contain within them the seeds of their own destruction. The first of these is perhaps obvious; the second, perhaps less so, but once a disease is eradicated or nearly eradicated, people forget, become complacent, possibly exaggerate the side effects of immunization, and sometimes tragically fail to get their vaccinations. Later in the book, the author discusses the libertarian conceit that individual rights take precedence over obligations to others. But first things first. The book is Booster Shots by Adam Ratner, a specialist in infectious pediatric diseases at New York University’s Grossman School of Medicine. He is also, judging by the contents of his book, a good historian and a talented writer.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Garrulus glandarius</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/garrulus-glandarius.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Garrulus glandarius" /><published>2025-07-21T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-21T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/garrulus-glandarius</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/garrulus-glandarius.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Philip Abrams&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Abrams_Eurasian_Jay_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Eurasian jay.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wildlondon.org.uk/wildlife-explorer/birds/crows-and-shrikes/jay&quot;&gt;Garrulus glandarius&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; Eurasian jay, 16 June 2025, in a narrow lane in Chelsea, London SW3, iPhone 15. Mr. Abrams notes, &quot;This juvenile, judging by size,  Eurasian jay was sheltering in a doorway from attacks by a couple of adult magpies (&lt;i&gt;Pica pica&lt;/i&gt;).  Once they’d been driven off it let me approach quite close &amp;ndash; within a couple of metres.  Unsurprisingly, it was panting, so I assume it felt stressed.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Philip Abrams. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Garrulus glandarius &amp;ndash; Eurasian jay, 16 June 2025, in a narrow lane in Chelsea, London SW3, iPhone 15. Mr. Abrams notes, &quot;This juvenile, judging by size, Eurasian jay was sheltering in a doorway from attacks by a couple of adult magpies (Pica pica). Once they’d been driven off it let me approach quite close &amp;ndash; within a couple of metres. Unsurprisingly, it was panting, so I assume it felt stressed.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Teach Your Dog Quantum Mechanics: book report</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/hot-to-teach-your-dog.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Teach Your Dog Quantum Mechanics: book report" /><published>2025-07-19T12:45:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-19T12:45:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/hot-to-teach-your-dog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/hot-to-teach-your-dog.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Orzel_Physics_Dog_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I accidentally came across &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/How-Teach-Quantum-Physics-Your-ebook/dp/B002ZJCQT2/&quot;&gt;this little book&lt;/a&gt;, originally published in 2009, a short while ago and thought it deserved a review in Amazon. It is a little bit off-task here, but it is a solid science book and still deserves some publicity. This report, which you will find below the fold, is necessarily a little technical. If you cannot understand it, read the book!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dog was a little cutesy at times, but on the whole I thought this was a splendid book. Not that it exactly explained why quantum will mechanics is the way it is – I have a feeling we will never know the answer to that question – but rather it was breezy yet got into surprising depth. The dog and the bunnies she always chased turned out to be a good device for explaining why we do not see quantum effects in the macroscopic world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the realists among us, Orzel explains that the wave-particle duality is real, and the particle truly does not have a definite state until it is “observed.” Likewise, Heisenberg’s uncertainty principle is a purely quantum effect and has no classical analog. It is good for an experimental physicist like me to be reminded of that every now and then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orzel spends considerable time with the Copenhagen and the many-worlds interpretations. He does not like the Copenhagen interpretation, but if he embraces the many-worlds interpretation, he did not convince me. That we cannot understand quantum mechanics does not mitigate our desire for an explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quantum Zeno effect was vaguely familiar to me, and Orzel explains it well. Oversimplified slightly, if you repeatedly make measurements immediately after you start a transition, you repeatedly put the system back into the initial condition, and the system never completes the transition. In classical mechanics, the system would keep going, perhaps with small perturbations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quantum tunneling is nothing to someone who is used to electromagnetic waves, but entanglement can drive a naïve realist crazy. The book was published in 2009, and I think entangled photons have since been discovered over much greater distances than described in the book. Unless I completely misunderstand, one of two entangled photons could travel to Alpha Centauri, while the other one went back and forth to Jupiter a zillion times.* As soon as we measure the second photon, the state of the Alpha Centauri photon will be determined instantly (in our reference frame), but we will have to wait several years to receive a telephone call at the speed of light.†&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chapter on quantum teleportation might be a little too “hairy” for the casual reader, but I had not realized that a particle is not literally teleported; rather, another particle down the road somewhere is prepared, with some difficulty, in the same state as the initial particle (sort of, but not precisely, the way a fax machine sends a copy of an original).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The attraction between, say, an electron and a proton is caused by an exchange of virtual particles. These particles are exceedingly short-lived and are never observed. They may sound like woo, but in fact they are the basis for the most precise calculations in physics (or anywhere else).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last chapter of the book discusses misuses of quantum physics by quacks who promise free energy from something known as zero-point energy; quantum healing, which is so convoluted that you will have to read it to believe it was written by someone with an advanced degree; healing at a distance, supposedly based on a unified field theory, which does not exist, or entanglement, or something; and homeopathy, which evidently has taken up entanglement since I last studied it. Such a lot of nonsense! As Orzel notes, quantum mechanics is not magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;I had a relatively few quibbles, most of which I will not detail here. I thought that the Dirac bracket, &amp;lt;a&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;b&amp;gt;, should have been defined more clearly. Physicists may not be “widely admired for their ability to think up clever names,” but Dirac very cleverly divided his brackets into two segments, &amp;lt;a&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;and&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;b&amp;gt;, and called them bras and kets. (I had a professor in the 1960’s who said that it took him several years before he could say “bra” without blushing, but in fact the Dirac bra was invented before the brassiere.)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not know why Orzel used gamma, rather than the usual lambda, for the wavelength of light. A mirror that is “not quite perfect” would have better been described as a partially reflecting or transmitting mirror. You do not send a laser through a crystal; you send a &lt;i&gt;laser beam&lt;/i&gt;. And finally, never, as I once did, let a philosopher hear you say that virtual particles annihilate each other &lt;i&gt;in order to satisfy the uncertainty principle&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* I will take this opportunity to point out (a) that the book uses far, far too many footnotes in order to include material that mostly should have been written into the text, and (b) that entanglement is very, very fussy, and it would be very difficult in reality for a photon to travel all the way to Alpha Centauri without having an interaction that destroys the entanglement. Such an interaction brings about decoherence, which is covered in some detail in the book. Decoherence is arguably one reason we do not see quantum effects with macroscopic objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;† Unfortunately, we cannot use entanglement to send messages instantaneously to Alpha Centauri, because if we knew the state of “our” photon before sending it off, it would be a different experiment, with no entanglement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Judah Levine for providing helpful comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I accidentally came across this little book, originally published in 2009, a short while ago and thought it deserved a review in Amazon. It is a little bit off-task here, but it is a solid science book and still deserves some publicity. This report, which you will find below the fold, is necessarily a little technical. If you cannot understand it, read the book!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Echium candicans</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/echium-candicans.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Echium candicans" /><published>2025-07-14T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-14T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/echium-candicans</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/echium-candicans.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;John Trawick&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Runner-up&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Trawick_Apis_mellifera_Echium_candicans.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pride of Madeira with honeybee.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smgrowers.com/products/plants/plantdisplay.asp?plant_id=543&quot;&gt;Echium candicans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; pride of Madeira. Mr. Trawick notes, &quot;Pride of Madeira is rare in its native Madeira but has become very common in California, especially the San Diego area. Though very pretty, the sap is toxic. These attract a lot of honeybees (&lt;i&gt;Apis mellifera&lt;/i&gt;) when blooming.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by John Trawick. Photography Contest, Runner-up. Echium candicans &amp;ndash; pride of Madeira. Mr. Trawick notes, &quot;Pride of Madeira is rare in its native Madeira but has become very common in California, especially the San Diego area. Though very pretty, the sap is toxic. These attract a lot of honeybees (Apis mellifera) when blooming.</summary></entry></feed>