<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-07-13T11:36:20-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Vitalism in New Zealand science education (in Science Magazine)</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/vitalism-NZ-science_education2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vitalism in New Zealand science education (in Science Magazine)" /><published>2024-07-12T01:24:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-07-12T01:24:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/vitalism-NZ-science_education2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/vitalism-NZ-science_education2.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Science_2024-07-12_letters.png&quot; alt=&quot;[Screenshots of Science 2024 letters on Mātauranga Māori]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Screenshots of Science 2024 letters on Mātauranga Māori&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Panda’s Thumb readers may recall &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/2024-07-12-vitalism-NZ-science_education.html&quot;&gt;my 2022 post&lt;/a&gt; on the controversy in New Zealand about the the NZ Ministry of Education sticking the concept of “mauri” into the high school Chemistry/Biology curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said at the time, this content was a big problem scientifically, as it was inserting vitalism into basic chemistry. I also made a prediction which some were skeptical of, that it would eventually have to be taken out. In October 2022, Paul Kilmartin, the chemistry professor whose talk I quoted, published a detailed analysis of the issue in &lt;a href=&quot;https://nzic.org.nz/unsecure_files/cinz/2022-86-4.pdf&quot;&gt;the journal &lt;i&gt;Chemistry in New Zealand&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spectator.co.uk/article/why-im-sticking-up-for-science/&quot;&gt;Richard Dawkins&lt;/a&gt; and others eventually commented.  In early 2024, &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; published a Policy Forum article, by Black and Tyliankankis, “&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Teach Indigenous knowledge alongside science&lt;/a&gt;,” which cited Dawkins’s critique and rebutted it by proclaiming the virtues of the Ministry of Education’s policy of “Mana ōrite: equal status for mātauranga Māori.” However, Black and Tyliankankis left out any discussion of Dawkins’s mention of vitalism, or indeed any discussion of the controversy over the mauri/vitalism issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I viewed this as pretty misleading, especially because, in late 2022, the Ministry of Education’s mana ōrite policy began to come crashing down, at least for science education. Mauri and a variety of other material was stripped out, the schedule for the rollout of the NCEA Level 1 science curriculum (15-16 year olds) was pushed back by years (it looks like the whole approach may be being scrapped by the new government, elected in late 2023; NCEA Levels 2 and 3 have been pushed back by several more years), and several other scandals involving the science curriculum reform &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.google.com/search?q=science%20education%20nz&amp;amp;hl=en-NZ&amp;amp;gl=NZ&amp;amp;ceid=NZ%3Aen&quot;&gt;hit the news in 2023-2024&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To inform &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;’s readership about some of the problems, I wrote a response letter which has just been published. Another response was also published by a group of New Zealand scientists and academics (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ado6679&quot;&gt;Adhar et al. 2024&lt;/a&gt;), along with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ado9278&quot;&gt;a reply from Black and Tylianakis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I paste the final text of my letter below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;(Asides: (1) Unfortunately, some copyediting misadventure occurred after my last look at the proof; I clarify after the main text. (2) I have added the full references for google-ability. (3) If it had been up to me, I would not have italicized “mauri” except for the first non-quoted instance. I follow my preference below.)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Vitalism in New Zealand science education&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
NICHOLAS J. MATZKE&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;SCIENCE&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
11 Jul 2024&lt;br /&gt;
Vol 385, Issue 6705&lt;br /&gt;
p. 152&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
DOI: &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.ado6728&quot;&gt;10.1126/science.ado6728&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A. Black and J. M. Tylianakis (&quot;Teach Indigenous knowledge alongside science,&quot; Policy Forum, 9 February, p. 592) give an overly rosy picture of New Zealand's policy of &quot;mana ōrite,&quot; or equal status for mātauranga Māori, in science education, which they say teaches Indigenous knowledge &quot;alongside&quot; science rather than &quot;as&quot; science. They suggest that this policy avoids problems such as teaching creationist myths in science class. However, the New Zealand Ministry of Education placed supernatural content directly into science and math curricula with no clarification that it was nonscientific material.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
The chemistry curriculum required students to &quot;recognise that mauri is present in all matter which exists as particles held together by attractive forces&quot; (1), with a glossary that defined &lt;i&gt;mauri&lt;/i&gt; as &quot;[t]he vital essence, life force of everything.&quot; This concept, known as vitalism, has long been debunked (2). Teaching concepts that directly conflict with empirical evidence undermines the goals of science education. Dozens of science teachers opposed the inclusion of mauri in the chemistry curriculum, but the Ministry steamrolled their objections, citing &quot;the requirement for mana ōrite&quot; (1). The objective was only removed after 18 months of controversy, at a time when the 2023 election was looming. The Ministry, ignoring vitalism's evidentiary flaws, claimed the reversal occurred because inserting concepts such as mauri into science curricula ran the &quot;risk of recolonisation&quot; (3), despite the fact that mana ōrite's entire rationale was decolonization.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Problems remain in 2024. Despite its removal from exam objectives, mauri remains in the chemistry curriculum, in which students are told, &quot;Revisit the concept of mauri (&lt;a href=&quot;http://giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&quot;&gt;giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&lt;/a&gt; [in the publication, ref. 4 was substituted for the link]). This learning can sit beside learnings in atomic theory&quot; (5), and the Gulf Innovation Fund Together website (4) says that mauri is &quot;the force that interpenetrates all things to bind and knit them together.&quot; A math qualification on practical problems of &quot;life in...the Pacific&quot; asks trigonometry students to calculate how much flaxen rope the demigod Maui made to lasso the Sun, slowing it to lengthen the day (6). The text of the exercise is studiously agnostic about the literal truth of this story, describing it as a &quot;narrative.&quot; Black and Tylianakis might categorize this as teaching Indigenous knowledge alongside math, but teachers face the prospect of strife among students over whether it is appropriate to call it knowledge or myth and if students of various backgrounds are expected to defend or disclaim its verity.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Black and Tylianakis provide some examples of cases in which Indigenous knowledge can unproblematically sit alongside science, such as uses of a particular plant. However, the Ministry's failure to avoid supernatural content indicates that the mana ōrite policy operated with a postmodern relativist philosophy that gave equal status to poorly evidenced ideas. If the policy goal is cross-cultural understanding and appreciation of Māori interests, values, philosophy, and worldview, then the curriculum should include a nonscience class or unit that provides an overview of the traditional worldview as an integrated belief system and also gives due attention to the diversity of beliefs among Māori today.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;References&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
1. Paul Kilmartin (2022). Mātauranga Māori and chemistry teaching: 'mauri is present in all matter.' &lt;i&gt;Chemistry in New Zealand&lt;/i&gt;. 86, 157 (2022). &lt;a href=&quot;https://nzic.org.nz/unsecure_files/cinz/2022-86-4.pdf&quot;&gt;https://nzic.org.nz/unsecure_files/cinz/2022-86-4.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
2. Peter J. Ramberg (2000). The Death of Vitalism and The Birth of Organic Chemistry: Wohler's Urea Synthesis and the Disciplinary Identity of Organic Chemistry. &lt;i&gt;Ambix&lt;/i&gt; 47, 170 (2000). &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1179/amb.2000.47.3.170&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1179/amb.2000.47.3.170&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
3. Sara Tolbert, Rosemary Hipkins, Bronwen Cowie, Pauline Waiti (2024). Epistemic agency, Indigenous knowledge, and the school science curriculum: reflections from Aotearoa New Zealand. &lt;i&gt;International Journal of Science Education&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/09500693.2024.2356229&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/09500693.2024.2356229&lt;/a&gt; (2024).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
4. Gulf Innovation Fund Together (GIFT), &quot;What is Mauri?&quot; (2020); &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&quot;&gt;https://www.giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
5. New Zealand Ministry of Education (2024); &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/chemistry-and-biology?view=teaching&quot;&gt;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/chemistry-and-biology?view=teaching&lt;/a&gt; . Download &quot;CB Level 1 Course Outline 3&quot; and see page 3.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
6. New Zealand Ministry of Education (2024); Mathematics and Statistics / Assessment / 1.2 / Activities / Activity A / Ko Māui me te Rā: Ākonga will use mathematics to explore the pūrākau of how Māui and his brothers slowed down Tama-nui-te-rā. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/mathematics-and-statistics/mathematics-and-statistics/1/2?view=activities&quot;&gt;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/mathematics-and-statistics/mathematics-and-statistics/1/2?view=activities&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;


&lt;b&gt;RELATED LETTERS&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Black, Amanda; Tylianakis, Jason M. (2024). Teach Indigenous knowledge alongside science. &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;, 383(6683), 592-594. February 9, 2024.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.adi9606&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.adi9606&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.adi9606&quot;&gt;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.adi9606&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Ahdar, Rex; Boyd, Brian; Chaudhuri, Ananish; Clements, Kendall D.; Cooper, Garth; Elliffe, 
Douglas; Gill, Brian; Gray, Russell D.; Hamilton-Hart,  Natasha; Lillis, David; Matthews, Michael; Raine, John; Rata, Elizabeth; Schwerdtfeger, Peter (2024). World science and Indigenous knowledge. &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;, 385(6705), 151-152. July 12, 2024. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.ado6679&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.ado6679&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ado6679&quot;&gt;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ado6679&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Matzke, Nicholas J. (2024). Vitalism in New Zealand science education. &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;, 385(6705), 152. July 12, 2024. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.ado6728&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.ado6728&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ado6728&quot;&gt;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ado6728&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Black, Amanda; Tylianakis, Jason M. (2024). Vitalism in New Zealand science education -- Response. &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;, 385(6705), 152-3. July 12, 2024. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.ado9278&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.ado9278&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ado9278&quot;&gt;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ado9278&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Typo issue&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published version:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
Problems remain in 2024. Despite its removal from exam objectives, mauri remains in the chemistry curriculum, in which students are told, &quot;Revisit the concept of mauri&quot; (4). This learning can sit beside learnings in atomic theory&quot; (5), and the Gulf Innovation Fund Together website (4) says that mauri is &quot;the force that interpenetrates all things to bind and knit them together.&quot;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Matzke says: This sentence somehow got garbled in a final copyedit, after my last look at the proof.  Presumably this was due to there being a link in the original verbatim quote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original read (using the published citation numbers):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
Despite its removal from exam objectives, mauri remains in the chemistry curriculum, in which students are told, &quot;Revisit the concept of mauri (&lt;a href=&quot;http://giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&quot;&gt;giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&lt;/a&gt;). This learning can sit beside learnings in atomic theory,&quot; (5) and the link (4) says that mauri is &quot;the force that interpenetrates all things to bind and knit them together.&quot;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Brief further comments&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the response by Black and Tylianakis mostly speaks for itself. Critical issues remain unaddressed, including the importance of evidence for the content taught in science classes, the definitions of &lt;i&gt;knowledge&lt;/i&gt; versus &lt;i&gt;belief&lt;/i&gt;, how the problems of postmodern relativism can be avoided, and what the heck actually happened to produce the Ministry of Education’s mauri-in-chemistry curriculum episode of 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If both scientists and Mātauranga Māori experts were actually &lt;i&gt;against&lt;/i&gt; mauri-in-chemistry, how the heck did it get in?  Why were the objections of science teachers – in the end, well-informed and correct objections – &lt;i&gt;overridden&lt;/i&gt; by the Ministry of Education, specifically by referencing the “mana ōrite” policy?  Why did it take 18 months to make the correction?  Why wasn’t the correction actually done thoroughly, instead of some of this material being reintroduced via example materials, still online in 2024?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Education touted an extensive series of expert review committees to advise the NCEA Change Process, including specifically experts on Mātauranga Māori. In addition to the Subject Expert Groups (SEG), which provided the expertise on science content for NCEA, the Ministry of Education quite publicly announced an elaborate feedback system for drafting the new curriculum. It included these formal entities to provide expertise and expert feedback:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
Te Whakaruruhau - Mātauranga Māori experts&lt;br /&gt;
NCEA Māori Panel&lt;br /&gt;
Māori Pathways Advisory Group&lt;br /&gt;
NCEA Mātauranga Māori Expert Reviewers&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The descriptions are online here:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://curriculumtimelines.education.govt.nz/sector-reach-advice-and-input/&quot;&gt;https://curriculumtimelines.education.govt.nz/sector-reach-advice-and-input/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s my guess. I think what &lt;i&gt;actually&lt;/i&gt; happened is that a lot of people at the Ministry of Education &lt;i&gt;thought&lt;/i&gt; that including mauri in chemistry was a great idea and an instance of implementing the mana ōrite policy. Experts were either not consulted, or didn’t realize the embarrassing scientific problems that would result.  Ministry staff who were skeptical either kept quiet, or were overridden, in the highly ideological environment that prevails in many academic and governmental institutions, especially in 2020-2021.  Initial objections from science teachers were overridden as just being objections from colonialist-hangover sticks in the mud, people with objections to be swept aside in the coming decolonialisation revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, once the curriculum was online publicly, scientists objected, the story went international, and it became sufficiently embarrassing that higher-ups at the Ministry of Education, and experts, took another look and re-thought it, resulting in partial corrections in late 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, with the 2023 election looming, the retroactive explanation started, with Rosemary Hipkins (cited above; and, coincidentally, mother of Chris Hipkins, Minister of Education from 2017-2023 and New Zealand’s Prime Minister from January 2023 through to the election loss in October 2023) proffering the “recolonisation” explanation for why mauri-in-chemistry was bad. Rosemary Hipkins first made this claim &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencelearn.org.nz/resources/3228-enduring-competencies-for-designing-science-learning-pathways&quot;&gt;in PLD training sessions for teachers&lt;/a&gt; in early 2023 (PLD sessions – Professional Learning and Development). (The mauri/recolonisation discussion occurs at about minute 19.) In May 2024, the same recolonisation claim is made in the publication of Tolbert, Hipkins et al. 2024, cited above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black and Tylianakis introduce another, different explanation, “The change was made because of inappropriate and inadequate references supporting its use.” But how could this have possibly happened, with all of the expert advice the Ministry of Education had recruited?  It’s not like scientists were begging for mauri to be included in chemistry!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, are Black and Tylianakis saying that &lt;a href=&quot;http://giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&quot;&gt;giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&lt;/a&gt;, cited in several places in NCEA Level 1 materials pertaining to mauri (from 2021-present), is actually an “inappropriate and inadequate reference”? Are they saying the speakers in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&quot;&gt;giftofthegulf.org.nz/mauri&lt;/a&gt; webpages/videos are making &lt;i&gt;incorrect&lt;/i&gt; statements of mātauranga Māori when they endorse (several times) interpretations of mauri involving molecular forces and vibrations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the legend of Maui and the Sun, this requires a longer post.  Briefly, I agree that the story could have truths and/or value in the sense of its literary, cultural, artistic (etc.) aspects.  But (a) if so, why is none of this mentioned in the cited Maths curriculum as it was posted online? (b) Why would this be useful or important in a trigonometry assignment in a math class? (c) What are the grand nonliteral truths of this story?  It’s a nice story, my daughters have already learned it in New Zealand daycare.  But the purpose of a curriculum is to &lt;i&gt;explain&lt;/i&gt; what the learning objectives are and how the material gets students there, not to leave everyone guessing. (d) Are Black and Tylianakis prepared to say that, yes, parts of Mātauranga Māori are legend and myth, and that is it OK for teachers, students, and scientists to say so, when it really does appear to be the case?  (Cases of legends with some historical truth are a different matter.)  There is tremendous pushback in New Zealand against the phrase “myths and legends”, so speaking the plain truth on these matters seems to often be viewed very negatively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, (e) How does any of this help students learn trigonometry?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Matzke</name></author><summary type="html">Screenshots of Science 2024 letters on Mātauranga Māori Panda’s Thumb readers may recall my 2022 post on the controversy in New Zealand about the the NZ Ministry of Education sticking the concept of “mauri” into the high school Chemistry/Biology curriculum. As I said at the time, this content was a big problem scientifically, as it was inserting vitalism into basic chemistry. I also made a prediction which some were skeptical of, that it would eventually have to be taken out. In October 2022, Paul Kilmartin, the chemistry professor whose talk I quoted, published a detailed analysis of the issue in the journal Chemistry in New Zealand. Richard Dawkins and others eventually commented. In early 2024, Science published a Policy Forum article, by Black and Tyliankankis, “Teach Indigenous knowledge alongside science,” which cited Dawkins’s critique and rebutted it by proclaiming the virtues of the Ministry of Education’s policy of “Mana ōrite: equal status for mātauranga Māori.” However, Black and Tyliankankis left out any discussion of Dawkins’s mention of vitalism, or indeed any discussion of the controversy over the mauri/vitalism issue. I viewed this as pretty misleading, especially because, in late 2022, the Ministry of Education’s mana ōrite policy began to come crashing down, at least for science education. Mauri and a variety of other material was stripped out, the schedule for the rollout of the NCEA Level 1 science curriculum (15-16 year olds) was pushed back by years (it looks like the whole approach may be being scrapped by the new government, elected in late 2023; NCEA Levels 2 and 3 have been pushed back by several more years), and several other scandals involving the science curriculum reform hit the news in 2023-2024. To inform Science’s readership about some of the problems, I wrote a response letter which has just been published. Another response was also published by a group of New Zealand scientists and academics (Adhar et al. 2024), along with a reply from Black and Tylianakis. I paste the final text of my letter below. (Asides: (1) Unfortunately, some copyediting misadventure occurred after my last look at the proof; I clarify after the main text. (2) I have added the full references for google-ability. (3) If it had been up to me, I would not have italicized “mauri” except for the first non-quoted instance. I follow my preference below.) Vitalism in New Zealand science education NICHOLAS J. MATZKE SCIENCE 11 Jul 2024 Vol 385, Issue 6705 p. 152 DOI: 10.1126/science.ado6728 A. Black and J. M. Tylianakis (&quot;Teach Indigenous knowledge alongside science,&quot; Policy Forum, 9 February, p. 592) give an overly rosy picture of New Zealand's policy of &quot;mana ōrite,&quot; or equal status for mātauranga Māori, in science education, which they say teaches Indigenous knowledge &quot;alongside&quot; science rather than &quot;as&quot; science. They suggest that this policy avoids problems such as teaching creationist myths in science class. However, the New Zealand Ministry of Education placed supernatural content directly into science and math curricula with no clarification that it was nonscientific material.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ardea herodias herodias</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/ardea-herodias.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ardea herodias herodias" /><published>2024-07-08T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-07-08T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/ardea-herodias</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/ardea-herodias.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Winner&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Denelsbeck_Ardea_herodias_herodias.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Great Blue Heron&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Great_Blue_Heron/overview&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Ardea herodias herodias&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – great blue heron with red-bellied watersnake &lt;a href=&quot;https://herpsofnc.org/red-bellied-watersnake&quot;&gt;Nerodia erythrogaster&lt;/a&gt;. Mr. Denelsbeck writes, &quot;Late afternoon on World Migratory Bird Day last year, having little luck all day, my brother spotted this heron and we realized it had a capture. The snake was still writhing as we attempted to get close enough for a clean shot, and managed it just before the heron flew off with its prey. It's challenging enough for a heron to get a large fish in the right position to swallow whole &amp;ndash; I imagine it's quite a bit harder with something as wickedly aggressive as a watersnake, though we missed that action. There are now &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_blue_heron&quot;&gt;four recognized subspecies of great blue herons&lt;/a&gt;, with the possibility of &lt;i&gt;A. h. wardi&lt;/i&gt; creeping into the area, but this is much more likely &lt;i&gt;A. h. herodias&lt;/i&gt;, as noted. Canon 7D, Tamron SP 150-600 at 600mm, handheld, cropped.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We received only around a dozen submissions this year, and all were very good indeed. In the past, we have polled our readers, but participation in the polls has dropped off. We therefore decided, consistently with Rules 8 and 12, to choose the winners ourselves rather than poll our readers. In this endeavor, we enlisted the assistance of our Wife and Harshest Critic, Deanna, and also our Son the Geek, David. Deanna grew up making dye transfers, and David is a formidable photographer himself. The one thing we three agreed upon was to place Al Denelsbeck’s photograph of what David called “sad snake, happy bird” first. We will announce the runner-up and the bronze medalist, so to speak, in subsequent weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Denelsbeck, who blogs &lt;a href=&quot;https://wading-in.net/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, will be offered his choice between Why Intelligent Design Fails, A Scientific Critique of the New Creationism, edited by Taner Edis and me (and autographed by me); and What’s Gotten Into You by Dan Levitt, generously contributed by NCSE. The runner-up will be offered the remaining book.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Al Denelsbeck. Photography Contest, Winner. Ardea herodias herodias – great blue heron with red-bellied watersnake Nerodia erythrogaster. Mr. Denelsbeck writes, &quot;Late afternoon on World Migratory Bird Day last year, having little luck all day, my brother spotted this heron and we realized it had a capture. The snake was still writhing as we attempted to get close enough for a clean shot, and managed it just before the heron flew off with its prey. It's challenging enough for a heron to get a large fish in the right position to swallow whole &amp;ndash; I imagine it's quite a bit harder with something as wickedly aggressive as a watersnake, though we missed that action. There are now four recognized subspecies of great blue herons, with the possibility of A. h. wardi creeping into the area, but this is much more likely A. h. herodias, as noted. Canon 7D, Tamron SP 150-600 at 600mm, handheld, cropped.&quot; We received only around a dozen submissions this year, and all were very good indeed. In the past, we have polled our readers, but participation in the polls has dropped off. We therefore decided, consistently with Rules 8 and 12, to choose the winners ourselves rather than poll our readers. In this endeavor, we enlisted the assistance of our Wife and Harshest Critic, Deanna, and also our Son the Geek, David. Deanna grew up making dye transfers, and David is a formidable photographer himself. The one thing we three agreed upon was to place Al Denelsbeck’s photograph of what David called “sad snake, happy bird” first. We will announce the runner-up and the bronze medalist, so to speak, in subsequent weeks. Mr. Denelsbeck, who blogs here, will be offered his choice between Why Intelligent Design Fails, A Scientific Critique of the New Creationism, edited by Taner Edis and me (and autographed by me); and What’s Gotten Into You by Dan Levitt, generously contributed by NCSE. The runner-up will be offered the remaining book.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ulmus pumila</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/ulmus-pumila.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ulmus pumila" /><published>2024-07-01T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-07-01T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/ulmus-pumila</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/ulmus-pumila.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;** Please do not forget the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/photography-contest-xv.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photography Contest&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Entries close next Friday, July 5. **&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/P1021093_Galls_Siberian_Elm_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Galls on a Siberian elm&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulmus_pumila&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Ulmus pumila&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – galls on a saw cut on a Siberian elm, Boulder, Colorado, April, 2024.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">** Please do not forget the Photography Contest. Entries close next Friday, July 5. ** Ulmus pumila – galls on a saw cut on a Siberian elm, Boulder, Colorado, April, 2024.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Steatoda sp.</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/steatoda-sp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Steatoda sp." /><published>2024-06-24T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-06-24T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/steatoda-sp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/steatoda-sp.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;** Reminder to enter the Photography Contest, and thanks to those who already have done so. Entries close on July 5. **&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/DSC05784_Spider_Steatoda_sp_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spider with egg sac&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steatoda&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Steatoda&lt;/i&gt; sp.&lt;/a&gt; – false black widow spider with egg sac, Boulder, Colorado, June, 2024. &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugguide.net/node/view/6926&quot;&gt;Bugguide lists several species&lt;/a&gt; that are found here in Colorado, sometimes without pictures. If anyone can identify the species, I will gladly modify the post, besides of course giving you credit. I will also keep an eye on the egg sac and notify you if my porch becomes crawling with spiders.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">** Reminder to enter the Photography Contest, and thanks to those who already have done so. Entries close on July 5. ** Steatoda sp. – false black widow spider with egg sac, Boulder, Colorado, June, 2024. Bugguide lists several species that are found here in Colorado, sometimes without pictures. If anyone can identify the species, I will gladly modify the post, besides of course giving you credit. I will also keep an eye on the egg sac and notify you if my porch becomes crawling with spiders. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest XV</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/photography-contest-xv.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest XV" /><published>2024-06-17T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-06-17T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/photography-contest-xv</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/photography-contest-xv.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/DSC05740_Argus_75_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Argus 75&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Argus 75 twin-lens reflex camera, 1958-1964. It is a fixed-focus camera with a single shutter speed of 1/60&amp;nbsp;s or bulb, and a relative aperture of approximately F/11 or less. It used 620 film and produced a 6&amp;times;6&amp;nbsp;cm negative. It looks like it was a considerable improvement over many box cameras in that it gave a substantially larger image in the viewfinder. Additionally, all the optics is glass. Judging by the little red opening in the back, it was designed for orthochromatic film. I infer from the description of the camera on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.filmstillphotography.com/argus-75.html&quot;&gt;Film Still Photography website&lt;/a&gt; that 620 film is no longer available, and you have to buy 120 film and transfer it to a 620 spool. The camera in the photograph, which belonged to my sister-in-law around 1960, no longer works, so we do not have to worry about the film.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 15th annual Panda’s Thumb Photography Contest begins now, Monday, June 17, at 12:00 p.m., MDT (MDT = UTC(GMT) – 6 h). Entries will be accepted between now and Friday, July 5, at 12:00 p.m., MDT. The rules are precisely the same as previous years’, except, obviously, that the dates have been updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We encourage entries in a single, general category, which includes pictures of just about anything of scientific interest: any object of experimentation or observation, from single-celled organisms, through nematodes, fruit flies, rats, chimpanzees, and college sophomores to volcanoes, stars, and galaxies. In order not to omit theoreticians, we will consider computer-generated pictures and also photographs of equipment. Photomicrographs and electron micrographs are likewise welcomed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since rumor has it that the pandemic encouraged macro photography, we may, if we receive enough entries, establish a “macro” category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winner will receive a choice between &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/stores/Matt-Young/author/B001HPILDU/&quot;&gt;Why Intelligent Design Fails, A Scientific Critique of the New Creationism&lt;/a&gt;, edited by Taner Edis and me; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.harpercollins.com/products/whats-gotten-into-you-dan-levitt&quot;&gt;What’s Gotten Into You&lt;/a&gt; by Dan Levitt, generously contributed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/&quot;&gt;NCSE&lt;/a&gt;. The runner-up will receive the remaining book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we get enough entries, consistently with Rules 11 and 12, we may add categories and award additional prizes, presuming, of course, that we can find more prizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rules of the contest are simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;We will consider any photograph that displays scientific interest – biological, paleontological, geological, or astronomical, for example.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Submit photographs in JPEG format. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Reduce photographs to an information content of 600 pixels horizontally. If creationists require a definition of information, they may apply in writing to the management. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Photographs may be enhanced but may not be montages. High dynamic range photographs and focus-stacked photographs are, however, accepted. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Submit a maximum of 3 photographs (or 5 photographs per family) to &lt;strike&gt;thousandwords@pandasthumb.org&lt;/strike&gt; ProfessorSteveSteve@gmail.com. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Submit the photographs as attachments to an e-mail (not embedded in the body of the e-mail). The subject line to the e-mail must have the form YourLastName_PhotographyContest. The filenames for the photographs must have the form YourLastName_Descriptor as, for example, Young_Oxytropis_sericea or Young_Table_Mountain, as appropriate. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;In your e-mail, identify the subject of the photograph: common and biological name, mineral type, or geological formation, for example. Provide a link that will allow a reader to learn more about the subject. You may add descriptive text in the body of the e-mail if you like. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Depending on the number of photographs submitted, we may post the best submissions and ask our readers to vote for the best photograph. Likewise, we may establish several categories with separate entries and separate ballots. In particular, students 16 and under should so identify themselves; if we receive enough entries, we will establish a student category. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;By submitting a photograph, you stipulate that you are the owner of the copyright and grant The Panda’s Thumb a nonexclusive license to publish the photograph on its blog. The photograph will be subject to a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-No Derivatives license. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Regular contributors to The Panda’s Thumb are not eligible to enter the contest. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;The decision of the judges is irrevocable. The judges remain irrepressibly and irreducibly irascible, irreverent, and irredeemable, irregardless and irrespective, but not, we hope, irrational or irritable. So do not be irresolute; we hope for a veritable irruption of entries this year. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Even though we are getting fairly good at running contests, we reserve the right to change any of the rules, or add or subtract rules at any time at our discretion. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will choose a number of finalists and open voting for the winner at 12:00 p.m. MDT, Monday, July 8. Voting will end Friday, July 19, at 12:00 noon, and the winner will be announced on Monday, July 22, at 12:00 noon.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Argus 75 twin-lens reflex camera, 1958-1964. It is a fixed-focus camera with a single shutter speed of 1/60&amp;nbsp;s or bulb, and a relative aperture of approximately F/11 or less. It used 620 film and produced a 6&amp;times;6&amp;nbsp;cm negative. It looks like it was a considerable improvement over many box cameras in that it gave a substantially larger image in the viewfinder. Additionally, all the optics is glass. Judging by the little red opening in the back, it was designed for orthochromatic film. I infer from the description of the camera on the Film Still Photography website that 620 film is no longer available, and you have to buy 120 film and transfer it to a 620 spool. The camera in the photograph, which belonged to my sister-in-law around 1960, no longer works, so we do not have to worry about the film. The 15th annual Panda’s Thumb Photography Contest begins now, Monday, June 17, at 12:00 p.m., MDT (MDT = UTC(GMT) – 6 h). Entries will be accepted between now and Friday, July 5, at 12:00 p.m., MDT. The rules are precisely the same as previous years’, except, obviously, that the dates have been updated. We encourage entries in a single, general category, which includes pictures of just about anything of scientific interest: any object of experimentation or observation, from single-celled organisms, through nematodes, fruit flies, rats, chimpanzees, and college sophomores to volcanoes, stars, and galaxies. In order not to omit theoreticians, we will consider computer-generated pictures and also photographs of equipment. Photomicrographs and electron micrographs are likewise welcomed. Since rumor has it that the pandemic encouraged macro photography, we may, if we receive enough entries, establish a “macro” category. The winner will receive a choice between Why Intelligent Design Fails, A Scientific Critique of the New Creationism, edited by Taner Edis and me; and What’s Gotten Into You by Dan Levitt, generously contributed by NCSE. The runner-up will receive the remaining book.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ham, Höss, and Noah</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/ham-hoss-noah.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ham, Höss, and Noah" /><published>2024-06-12T14:04:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-06-12T14:04:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/ham-hoss-noah</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/ham-hoss-noah.html">&lt;p&gt;I have not seen the movie The Zone of Interest, though I have read a bit about it (not to mention more Holocaust books and articles than &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carter%27s_Little_Liver_Pills&quot;&gt;Carter’s has pills&lt;/a&gt;. See, for example, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2023/12/14/movies/the-zone-of-interest-review.html&quot;&gt;review by Manohla Dargis).&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What interested me about the movie was &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/the-zone-of-interest-auschwitz-and-ark-encounter/&quot;&gt;William Trollinger’s take on it&lt;/a&gt;. For those, like me, who have not seen the movie, it is based on the true story of Rudolf Höss , the Commandant of Auschwitz, and his family, who lived an idyllic existence on the very edge of the concentration camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Trollinger likens the Höss family to the imagined family presented by Ken Ham and his minions in the Ark Park (see photographs by Dan Phelps &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2016/07/ark-park-on-ope.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). The Ark Park &lt;i&gt;celebrates&lt;/i&gt; what they claim is the destruction of 20 billion people in the Flood. Mr. Ham and his staff have made up a long story about the family of Noah, and given them names, jobs, and so on. As Prof Trollinger puts it,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Taking “artistic license” to a whole new level (as very, very little of this in the Bible), placards accompanying the dioramas of [Noah's family] invent personalities and skills for the three sons, and names, personalities, and skills for the sons’ wives. Most striking is the plushness of the living quarters, which include a library, large kitchen, and lots and lots of delicious-looking food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life for these eight individuals is very good indeed – a paradise, as it were. And while the Noah family is blissfully reading, making music, creating artwork, eating, and so forth, what is going on outside the boat? Well, according to Ark Encounter, up to twenty billion (!) people were drowning. This includes folks with various disabilities as well as toddlers, infants, newborns, and the unborn.…&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He concludes by pointing out,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt; In contrast with &lt;i&gt;The Zone of Interest&lt;/i&gt;, Ark Encounter is quite blatant in encouraging visitors to identify with the comfortably content, albeit morally vacuous (to understate the case), Noah family.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always wondered why anyone would want to worship such a murderous God. I would say that Prof. Trollinger does not; Mr. Ham does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I have not seen the movie The Zone of Interest, though I have read a bit about it (not to mention more Holocaust books and articles than Carter’s has pills. See, for example, the review by Manohla Dargis). What interested me about the movie was William Trollinger’s take on it. For those, like me, who have not seen the movie, it is based on the true story of Rudolf Höss , the Commandant of Auschwitz, and his family, who lived an idyllic existence on the very edge of the concentration camp. Professor Trollinger likens the Höss family to the imagined family presented by Ken Ham and his minions in the Ark Park (see photographs by Dan Phelps here). The Ark Park celebrates what they claim is the destruction of 20 billion people in the Flood. Mr. Ham and his staff have made up a long story about the family of Noah, and given them names, jobs, and so on. As Prof Trollinger puts it, Taking “artistic license” to a whole new level (as very, very little of this in the Bible), placards accompanying the dioramas of [Noah's family] invent personalities and skills for the three sons, and names, personalities, and skills for the sons’ wives. Most striking is the plushness of the living quarters, which include a library, large kitchen, and lots and lots of delicious-looking food. Life for these eight individuals is very good indeed – a paradise, as it were. And while the Noah family is blissfully reading, making music, creating artwork, eating, and so forth, what is going on outside the boat? Well, according to Ark Encounter, up to twenty billion (!) people were drowning. This includes folks with various disabilities as well as toddlers, infants, newborns, and the unborn.… He concludes by pointing out, In contrast with The Zone of Interest, Ark Encounter is quite blatant in encouraging visitors to identify with the comfortably content, albeit morally vacuous (to understate the case), Noah family. I have always wondered why anyone would want to worship such a murderous God. I would say that Prof. Trollinger does not; Mr. Ham does. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dembski and Ewert dump functional information</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/dembskiewert1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dembski and Ewert dump functional information" /><published>2024-06-12T13:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2024-06-12T13:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/dembskiewert1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/dembskiewert1.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;600px&quot; src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Six_Grandfathers.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Six grandfathers image]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;The mountain called &lt;em&gt;Six Grandfathers&lt;/em&gt; by the 
Lakota people before it was &lt;br /&gt;renamed Mount Rushmore.  Does the Lakota name reflect 
a design inference?&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wikimedia, public domain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been reading the new 2nd edition of &lt;em&gt;The Design Inference: Eliminating Chance 
Through Small Probabilities&lt;/em&gt; and wanted 
to give some reactions to it, having reached the end of the chapter on “Specified 
Complexity”.  This new edition adds Winston Ewert as the second author.  Unlike the 
1998 first edition, which was published by Cambridge University Press, this “Revised 
and Expanded” 25th anniversary 2nd edition is published by Discovery Institute Press.  For 
a book of 582 pages, it is available 
rather inexpensively, in a paperback edition and in a 
Kindle edition.  (Its cover illustration shows the faces on Mount Rushmore, as an 
example of a design inference).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Dembski’s original Design Inference argument involved our seeing a 
pattern in nature, in an organism, that embodied what he called Specified 
Complexity.  Its argument became better known as a result of Dembski’s 2002 
book &lt;em&gt;No Free Lunch: Why Specified Complexity Cannot be Purchased Without Intelligence.&lt;/em&gt; 
This was much invoked as a major argument for Intelligent Design at the time of the 2005 Kitzmiller vs. Dover School Board trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Specified Complexity argument involves genotypes arrayed 
on a scale.  A scale of what, we will be discussing.  The general strategy of the design inference 
is to find a region of the scale that is so improbable under “chance” that natural evolutionary processes would be extremely unlikely to result in genotypes that good or better.  The probabilities that natural processes would produce anything that good have to be so small that such an event would be 
expected less than once in the whole history of the Universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years since 1998, there seem to have been several definitions of the scale and the probability:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A quantity which is fitness or a component of fitness, with the probability being simply
the fraction of all genotypes in the initial population having that high, or higher, a value, or,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The same scale, but with the probability being instead the chance that natural evolutionary processes
would produce that good a value, or higher, or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A more mysterious scale involving whether the genotype (or phenotype) could be produced by a small set of instructions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first one is related to a concept called Functional Information.  As I will show, the second is not at all useful.  The interesting new development is that Dembski and Ewert have moved to definition 3, resulting in a specification that no longer has any connection to Functional Information.  Functional Information has been thrown under the bus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll discuss the first two one at a time; the third will be considered in another post …
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the original 1998 edition of &lt;em&gt;The Design Inference&lt;/em&gt; William Dembski did not discuss using the design inference on genotypes that were argued to have arisen by natural selection and other ordinary evolutionary processes. (In section 2.3 he gives a “case study” of the “Creation-evolution controversy” but focuses that entirely on the origin of Life, not on evolution thereafter).  Four years later, he applied his inference to biological evolution in his work &lt;em&gt;No Free Lunch: Why Specified Complexity Cannot be Purchased without Intelligence&lt;/em&gt;. There he gave these examples of the specification scales that are of interest in discussions of evolution:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The specification of organisms can be cashed out in any number of ways. Arno Wouters cashes it out globally in terms of the &lt;em&gt;viability&lt;/em&gt; of whole organisms. Michael Behe cashes it out in terms of the &lt;em&gt;minimal function&lt;/em&gt; of  biochemical systems. Darwinist Richard Dawkins cashes out biological specification in terms of the &lt;em&gt;reproduction&lt;/em&gt; of genes.  Thus, in &lt;em&gt;The Blind Watchmaker&lt;/em&gt; Dawkins writes “Complicated things have some quality, specifiable in advance, that is highly unlikely to have been acquired by random chance alone.  In the case of living systems, the quality that is specified in advance is … the ability to propagate genes in reproduction.” (Dembski, &lt;em&gt;No Free Lunch&lt;/em&gt;, 2002 and 2007, p. 148).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dembski’s criterion for detecting Design was finding complex specified information (CSI), where “complex” did not refer to the complicatedness of the organism, but just to having a sufficiently low probability of of the specified information happening under “chance”.&lt;br /&gt;
So the scale is the level of specification, and the probability is the fraction of the initial population that is at or beyond that level, makes the scale be Functional  Information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;functional-information&quot;&gt;Functional Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Functional Information, a form of Specified Information, was discussed by Leslie Orgel in 1973.  He was trying to define a measure of the information that was useful to the organism, ruling out aspects of its phenotype that might require lots of elaborate description, but where the details did not particularly help the organism.  The concept was made more precise by Jack Szostak in a paper in &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; in 2003 (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/423689a&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), with a small correction by Hazen, Carothers, Griffin, and Szostak in &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA&lt;/em&gt; in 2007 (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/doi/full/10.1073/pnas.0701744104&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all of those papers, the null distribution assigns equal probability to all possible sequences.  Thus if we have 
a region of 1000 nucleotides, it assumes that all 4&lt;sup&gt;1000&lt;/sup&gt; possible sequences are equiprobable.  If we see a sequence which has 4^600 sequences with equal or higher fitness, then the functional information in that sequence is computed from the probability 4^600 / 4^1000 = 4^{-400}.  It is, in bits of information, minus the log to the base 2 of this probability, or -log2 (4^(-400)), which is 800 bits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Functional Information is computed for any sequence, by setting the level to its position on the scale.  The amount of FI that we get by choosing that sequence is -log2(P), where P is the fraction of the initial population that is at or above that level on the scale.  So if we have chosen a sequence that is up at the 90th percentile, then P = 0.10 and Functional Information is  -log2(0.10) which is 3.322 bits.   A sequence that is only at the 10th percentile has -log2(0.90) = 0.152 bits.  There is no requirement that the calculation be done at some special point on the scale, such as where a function is detectable.  Each possible sequence has some amount of Functional Information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-problem-with-functional-information&quot;&gt;The problem with Functional Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As sensible as Functional Information seems to be, it has one deficiency from the point of view of Dembski and Ewert.  Even when there is a very small probability that a randomly chosen sequence will be this good or better, there is no argument that natural evolutionary processes cannot find a sequence this good or better.  These evolutionary processes are not limited to making a single random choice.  They include natural selection, which can build up adaptations gradually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can a sequence with 800 bits of FI arise in a population by gradually fixing favorable alleles at 400 sites?  Unless a design advocate can present a sound argument that it is impossible (or extremely improbable) for this to happen, then observing 800 bits of FI is not evidence for Design Intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Dembski’s 2002 book &lt;em&gt;No Free Lunch&lt;/em&gt;, the probability of a sequence this good or better is described as the probability that it will arise by “chance” as opposed to “necessity”.  From that it was unclear whether “chance” included  processes such as natural selection.  Or was that included in “necessity”?
When I wrote a  refutation of Dembski’s 2002 argument, I showed an example where natural selection could increase Functional Information (the article is in &lt;em&gt;Reports of the National Center for Science Education&lt;/em&gt; in 2007, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/has-natural-selection-been-refuted-arguments-william-dembski&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Functional Information, as used by Szostak and Hazen, was never intended to measure the evidence for Design.  They never assumed that high levels of FI could not be achieved by natural evolutionary processes.  But FI has been used in that way by ID advocates such as, for example, Kirk Durston.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;durstons-argument&quot;&gt;Durston’s argument&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a post on his blog “Quest: Thoughts about God, Truth, and Beauty” in 2018, Durston, a clergyman who is a former engineer, argued in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kirkdurston.com/blog/idscience&quot;&gt;a post on July 22, 2018&lt;/a&gt; on “Why this scientist believes intelligent design was required for biological life” that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Design detection is firmly entrenched in science, including forensic science, defence research, SETI, archeology, and biology. In each area, a variety of methods are used, but the core aspect of all of them can be quantified in terms of functional information (defined in the literature by Szostak (1), Hazen et al., (2), and Durston et al. (3)). In layperson’s terms, functional information is the information required to produce a desired effect. A testable, verifiable, and falsifiable hypothesis that is highly useful to design detection can be stated as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Hypothesis: A unique property of intelligent minds is the ability to produce statistically significant levels of functional information as defined in the literature.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;A key word here is “unique”; intelligence is the only thing with enough intellectual horsepower to produce significant levels of functional information. The above hypothesis is certainly testable and falsifiable. To falsify it, all we need is to verify a natural, mindless process that will produce statistically significant levels of functional information. 
… the only option science has on the table that is observable, testable, and verified is intelligence. Almost anything, including dumping alphabet characters out of a box on to the floor, can produce functional information at trivial or non-significant levels. However, if one wishes to produce significant levels of functional information one needs something else in addition. Right now, the only option science has on the table that is observable, testable, and verified is intelligence. Although there are other creative scenarios as to how large quantities of functional information can be formed naturally, our failure to verify them suggests that they should be more properly classified as science fiction. (4)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An hour-long video presentation of his argument will be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://foclonline.org/talk/how-confident-can-we-be-genetic-information-required-intelligent-programmer&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Durston’s calculation for Ubiquitin  alignments is described in his paper, which will be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://tbiomed.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1742-4682-4-47&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It involves doing an alignment of all protein sequences that carry out a particular function, showing that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Applying that method to a multiple sequence alignment consisting of 30,176 sequences for the second PDZ domain (5) reveals that this protein domain requires at least 140 bits of functional information. To understand how significant that is, the probability that natural processes could generate that level of functional information is 1 chance in 10 with 41 zeros after it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This assumes that the lowest level of efficiency that we see now is the lowest that could be functional.  That does not follow: lower levels of function might help the organism, particular in early biochemistry where everything is going more slowly.  In studies of random sequences of amino acids, and of random single-stranded RNA molecules, low but noticeable levels of catalytic activity are commonly found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the ancestors of this protein domain in the common ancestors of these species could carry out the function of this protein without containing this much Functional Information, we cannot rule out that natural selection could have gradually improved the efficiency of function until, in the latest common ancestor, the PDZ domain contained 140 bits of functional information. (For more on 
the PDZ domain see &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PDZ_domain&quot;&gt;its Wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Durston’s argument seems to be that a “significant” amount of Functional Information is one which cannot have accumulated step-by-step by natural selection.  In William Dembski’s 2002 book, he sketches a “Law of Conservation of Complex Specified Information” which is supposed to somehow show that one must already have achieved CSI in previous generations in order to have it now. This would seem to be an argument that one cannot achieve a high degree of adaptation if you start from less adaptation. 
Exactly how this LCCSI is to be applied is unclear in Dembski’s 2002 argument, and is not discussed in Durston’s papers or his blog post, either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the years after Dembski’s 2002 argument, many advocates of Intelligent Design frequently 
assumed that Dembski had somehow proven that a level of Functional Information great 
enough to constitute CSI could not be achieved by incremental natural selection. He hadn’t.  But 
then the argument changed, or perhaps was clarified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dembskis-csi-argument-clarified-or-perhaps-changed&quot;&gt;Dembski’s CSI argument clarified, or perhaps changed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a 2005-2006 manuscript, which was published in 2005 in volume 7, number 2 of &lt;em&gt;Philosophia Christi&lt;/em&gt;, William Dembski either clarified or changed the CSI argument.  The manuscript version may be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://billdembski.com/documents/2005.06.Specification.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. In Section 7 he makes it clear that “chance” includes processes such as natural selection:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It follows that –log&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;[10&lt;sup&gt;120&lt;/sup&gt;·ϕ&lt;sub&gt;S&lt;/sub&gt;(T)·&lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt;(T|&lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;)] &amp;gt; 1
if and only if &lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt;(T|&lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;) &amp;lt; &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;/&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; 10&lt;sup&gt;-140&lt;/sup&gt;,
where &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;, as we noted in section 6, is an evolutionary chance hypothesis
that takes into account Darwinian and other material mechanisms and T, conceived not as a pattern but as an event, is the evolutionary pathway that brings about the flagellar structure (for definiteness, let’s say the flagellar structure in E. coli). Is &lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt;(T|&lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;) in fact less than  10&lt;sup&gt;-140&lt;/sup&gt;, thus making T a specification?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logic is now impeccable: once an adaptation is a “specification” in this sense, then by definition the probability of its occurrence by natural evolutionary processes is so low that such an event will occur fewer than one time in the entire history of the universe. Finding that the adaptation is a “specification” now guarantees us that it is so improbable that ordinary evolutionary mechanisms are in effect ruled out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-to-become-useless&quot;&gt;… to become useless&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is, neither Dembski nor Durston shows how to calculate the probability that natural evolutionary forces would achieve a result this improbable.  As far as I can see, the objective of the whole inference is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to find an actual event 
that is so improbably good that from natural evolutionary processes we would expect one that good less than once in the history of the universe.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If we can find an event that has Complex Specified Information, by definition it will be one that has this low a probability with natural evolutionary processes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;So how do we find an event that has Complex Specified Information?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why, by finding one that, with natural evolutionary processes, is this improbable!   (Then we can show that it has CSI, and that guarantees that it is this improbable).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we have already shown that, once we have proven that the event, or one this good 
or better, is this improbable, then the CSI part is completely unnecessary!  In the 2005 argument, no particular method was outlined to calculate the probability of the event with natural evolutionary processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Functional Information has been discarded because it could possibly 
evolve.  It has been replaced by Specification 
which is defined as only present when it cannot be increased by natural 
evolutionary processes.  Specification can be used to establish 
that it is very improbable that the adaptation could arise by 
natural evolutionary processes.  But we can only establish that 
Specification is present by somehow already knowing that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the part about calculating whether we have CSI is irrelevant to the Design Inference.  After you have (somehow) established improbability, it is just a bit of relabeling.
This has been pointed out since about 2007 by many critics of 
Dembski’s design inference.  For links, see &lt;a href=&quot;http://theskepticalzone.com/wp/circularity-of-using-csi-to-conclude-design/&quot;&gt;my 2013 article at The Skeptical Zone&lt;/a&gt;, 
which cites arguments by “Keith S.”, Elizabeth Liddle, and me at The Skeptical Zone, at PT, and at Uncommon Descent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Dembski’s colleague and frequent co-author Winston Ewert 
conceded the point &lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/the-circularity-of-the-design-inference/&quot;&gt;in a post at Uncommon Descent&lt;/a&gt; in 2014:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;CSI and Specified complexity do not help in any way to establish that the evolution of the bacterial flagellum is improbable. Rather, the only way to establish that the bacterial flagellum exhibits CSI is to first show that it was improbable. Any attempt to use CSI to establish the improbability of evolution is deeply fallacious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-new-criterion&quot;&gt;The new criterion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Dembski and Ewert’s new edition of &lt;em&gt;The Design Inference&lt;/em&gt;, neither “functional information” nor “information, functional” appear in the Index. The works by Szostak and by Hazen, Carothers, Griffin and Szostak do not appear in the Bibliography.  Nor, even, does Kirk Durston.  All the previous ways in which Specified Complexity could be “cashed out” are gone too.  They have been thrown under the bus, gone because it turned out that they could not accomplish a Design Inference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only one remains, the calculation in terms of Algorithmic Specified Complexity (ASC), which is now the foundation of their criticism of evolutionary biology. This criterion involves a sufficiently large quantity of Algorithmic Specified Complexity (ASC).  That 
measures the difference between the length of the algorithm that describes the adaptation and the algorithm that produces it.  If a short algorithm can produce a complex result, this indicates design.  There is apparently a conservation theorem that helps with this logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ASC criterion has previously been discussed by Eric Holloway, in discussions at Uncommon Descent and at The Skeptical Zone.  I have expressed my failure to follow those arguments at some length in &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/12/Is-Algorithmic-Specified-Complexity-Useless-for-Analyzing-Evolution.html&quot;&gt;a 2019 post at Panda’s Thumb&lt;/a&gt;.  But now, with Dembski and Ewert’s new book, presumably all these misunderstandings will be cleared up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the first part of my examination of Dembski and Ewert’s book and its argument.  In the second part of this review, I will see whether my doubts have been cleared up.  So time for me to resume reading …&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">The mountain called Six Grandfathers by the Lakota people before it was renamed Mount Rushmore. Does the Lakota name reflect a design inference?Wikimedia, public domain &amp;nbsp; I have been reading the new 2nd edition of The Design Inference: Eliminating Chance Through Small Probabilities and wanted to give some reactions to it, having reached the end of the chapter on “Specified Complexity”. This new edition adds Winston Ewert as the second author. Unlike the 1998 first edition, which was published by Cambridge University Press, this “Revised and Expanded” 25th anniversary 2nd edition is published by Discovery Institute Press. For a book of 582 pages, it is available rather inexpensively, in a paperback edition and in a Kindle edition. (Its cover illustration shows the faces on Mount Rushmore, as an example of a design inference). William Dembski’s original Design Inference argument involved our seeing a pattern in nature, in an organism, that embodied what he called Specified Complexity. Its argument became better known as a result of Dembski’s 2002 book No Free Lunch: Why Specified Complexity Cannot be Purchased Without Intelligence. This was much invoked as a major argument for Intelligent Design at the time of the 2005 Kitzmiller vs. Dover School Board trial. The Specified Complexity argument involves genotypes arrayed on a scale. A scale of what, we will be discussing. The general strategy of the design inference is to find a region of the scale that is so improbable under “chance” that natural evolutionary processes would be extremely unlikely to result in genotypes that good or better. The probabilities that natural processes would produce anything that good have to be so small that such an event would be expected less than once in the whole history of the Universe. Over the years since 1998, there seem to have been several definitions of the scale and the probability: A quantity which is fitness or a component of fitness, with the probability being simply the fraction of all genotypes in the initial population having that high, or higher, a value, or, The same scale, but with the probability being instead the chance that natural evolutionary processes would produce that good a value, or higher, or A more mysterious scale involving whether the genotype (or phenotype) could be produced by a small set of instructions. The first one is related to a concept called Functional Information. As I will show, the second is not at all useful. The interesting new development is that Dembski and Ewert have moved to definition 3, resulting in a specification that no longer has any connection to Functional Information. Functional Information has been thrown under the bus. We’ll discuss the first two one at a time; the third will be considered in another post …</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pituophis catenifer sayi</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/pituophis-catenifer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pituophis catenifer sayi" /><published>2024-06-10T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-06-10T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/pituophis-catenifer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/pituophis-catenifer.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Mark Lee&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Lee_Bullsnake.JPEG&quot; alt=&quot;Head shot of snake&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bullsnake&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Pituophis catenifer sayi&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; bullsnake.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;** The Photography Contest will begin next Monday, June 17. **&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see comments on this post click below: &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Mark Lee. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Pituophis catenifer sayi &amp;ndash; bullsnake. ** The Photography Contest will begin next Monday, June 17. ** To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Teach Grown-Ups about Climate Change: A Review</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/how-to-teach-grown-ups.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Teach Grown-Ups about Climate Change: A Review" /><published>2024-06-06T09:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-06-06T09:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/how-to-teach-grown-ups</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/how-to-teach-grown-ups.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/HT_Teach_Grownups_Cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope I am not entering my &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_childhood&quot;&gt;second childhood&lt;/a&gt;, but I just read a splendid book aimed at third through seventh graders: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Teach-Grown-Ups-About-Climate-Change/dp/1804660310&quot;&gt;How to Teach Grown-Ups about Climate Change&lt;/a&gt;. A picture book, no less, written by Patricia Daniels and illustrated by Aaron Blecha, with a foreword by Michael Mann, the discoverer of the “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hockey_stick_graph_(global_temperature)&quot;&gt;hockey stick&lt;/a&gt;.” I have not been a (5 ± 2)th grader, nor have I had one, in a very long time, but I am going to guess that the material is suitable for that age group, though possibly a bit hard for a third grader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone once told me that if you want to get the attention of a fifth grader, just say “fart.” Sure enough, on page 27, the authors write,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Cow_Farts.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Infographic&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They explain, though, that cow &lt;i&gt;burps&lt;/i&gt; inject a significant amount of methane into the atmosphere, and methane is a very significant greenhouse gas. Fifth graders will also be interested to know that sea snot is plugging harbors in Turkey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am getting ahead of myself, but the book is well illustrated and has a myriad of infographics, many of them headlined IT’S A FACT! These infographics are shown as a cloud emitted by a burping cow. A nice discussion on information, misinformation, and disinformation shows you how “your grown-ups” can check any claim they think is suspicious: by going to an encyclopedia, a reputable news source, or a scientific authority. They are also advised to ask who paid for the message and what they get out of it. I might have added, trust dot-gov and dot-edu websites more than dot-com and dot-org websites, in that order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a technical book in some sense. It begins by asking whether your grown-ups might be clueless. If so, here is what you need to teach them. The book then goes through the history of climate change, explaining that we damned well know that it is human caused. It explains precisely what fossil fuels are and how burning them injects CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; into the atmosphere. Beginning with Eunice Foote, who predated even John Tyndall, the authors explain how we know that CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; traps heat. I was surprised that there was no history between Arrhenius and Greta Thunberg. (I was also somewhat dismayed when they called Foote, the woman, by her first name; they would never have called Arrhenius “Svante.”)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An infographic on how we know it is hot details the different measuring systems that we use to discern the average temperature of the earth. Another infographic shows the hockey stick and explains that the temperature was pretty steady between 1100 CE and the mid-twentieth century, when it began to rise precipitously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it too late? No, and boxes shaped like leaves explain WHAT YOU CAN DO in response to various problems. Other boxes, similar to the one we saw about cow farts, respond NOPE! to various misconceptions and explain precisely why they are misconceptions and should not be believed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weather now is often “weird,” so they coined the term &lt;i&gt;global weirding&lt;/i&gt;. Global weirding is responsible for temperatures of 47 °C in northwestern United States and nearby southwestern Canada on the one hand, and 40 °C warmer than normal in Antarctica (the temperature at one station in Antarctica &lt;a href=&quot;https://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/images/146322/antarctica-melts-under-its-hottest-days-on-record&quot;&gt;reached 18 °C&lt;/a&gt; in 2020, about the same as Los Angeles on that day). Additionally, we are seeing heat waves in cities, droughts and wildfires, and severe hurricanes, all above normal or what was formerly normal. Some plants and animals will survive all this, and some will not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors are optimistic about our own survival and note that we can tackle global weirding in two ways: personal choices and changing the system. They advise you to do both: change to LED light bulbs, tell your grown-ups not to idle their cars, reduce their consumption of meat (in particular, beef), and so on. But also get your grown-ups to work toward changing the system, as by introducing renewable energy sources, including geothermal, and manufacturing electric cars and trucks, for example. I was gratified to see that they are suspicious of carbon sequestration, in part because the oil industry plans to inject CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and use it to extract more oil. They likewise take a somewhat dim view of geo-engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, they offer some advice to your grown-ups when they try to influence friends and acquaintances: find things you have in common; do not argue with doctrinaire climate deniers; do not be “doom-y” and make people want to give up; and do not shame people who, for example, eat beef and drive behemoths. All to my mind good advice, provided sometimes that you can bite your tongue hard enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book ends with a quiz that you can give your grown-ups, as well as more detail on What You Can Do. It has a good glossary and what looks like a good index.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 1&lt;/strong&gt;. The book is of course timely, but perhaps moreso because of the roughly simultaneous announcement of a book by Ken Ham and &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/bios/jessica-deford/&quot;&gt;Jessica DeFord&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2024/05/25/truth-about-climate-change/&quot;&gt;The Truth [sic!] about Climate Change&lt;/a&gt;. I have not read this book, but I think all you need to know about it is this sentence written by Ms. DeFord,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; Climate alarmists will not solve the problem of man’s sin by switching to alternative energy or reducing carbon emissions &lt;i&gt;that they believe&lt;/i&gt; are caused by human activity. [Emphasis added.]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and Mr. Ham’s reminder of Genesis 8:22,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;While the earth remaineth, seedtime and harvest, and cold and heat, and summer and winter, and day and night shall not cease [KJV],&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which he interprets as a promise. (I guess he does not believe that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/God_helps_those_who_help_themselves&quot;&gt; God helps those who help themselves &lt;/a&gt;, because, after all, it is not Biblical.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 2&lt;/strong&gt;. Physicist’s last inch. I found two explanations that were possibly misleading and could be caught by a bright seventh grader. First, electrons are not &lt;i&gt;knocked off&lt;/i&gt; the solar cell. If they were, they would have nowhere to go, and the cell would become positive and attract them back. Instead, electrons are made free to move within the cell and therefore generate a current (holes too, but never mind; that would be too complicated). Readers of PT may be interested to know, incidentally, that China has built an array of solar cells in the shape of a panda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the term heat is used imprecisely in the discussion of “how the atmosphere works.” Again, a bright seventh grader might notice. Specifically, the “heat” that falls on the earth is mostly visible light. The “heat” that escapes into space is mostly infrared radiation, so they are not the same thing. The atmosphere is more or less transparent to visible light and more or less opaque to infrared radiation. It blocks much of the loss of “heat” by absorbing infrared radiation. That could have been made clear in a sentence or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A greenhouse, incidentally, does not work primarily by the greenhouse effect. Rather, it mostly reduces heat loss by convection. It is therefore very different from the atmosphere, but I would not quibble over that point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Glenn Branch, whose review you may read &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/review-how-teach-grown-ups-about-climate-change&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, for some assistance. Another reader, who wants to remain anonymous, exclaimed, “Sounds wonderful! I want to read it.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I hope I am not entering my second childhood, but I just read a splendid book aimed at third through seventh graders: How to Teach Grown-Ups about Climate Change. A picture book, no less, written by Patricia Daniels and illustrated by Aaron Blecha, with a foreword by Michael Mann, the discoverer of the “hockey stick.” I have not been a (5 ± 2)th grader, nor have I had one, in a very long time, but I am going to guess that the material is suitable for that age group, though possibly a bit hard for a third grader. Someone once told me that if you want to get the attention of a fifth grader, just say “fart.” Sure enough, on page 27, the authors write,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Giant pandas return to National Zoo</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/giant-pandas-return.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Giant pandas return to National Zoo" /><published>2024-05-29T13:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-05-29T13:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/giant-pandas-return</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/giant-pandas-return.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/IMG_3617_Steve_Steve_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Prof. Steve Steve&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a headline in the Washington Post, &lt;a href=&quot;https://s2.washingtonpost.com/3ddacd0/665719e273e72c3ea1cffc06/596a8aedae7e8a0ef33f6950/3/13/665719e273e72c3ea1cffc06&quot;&gt;Giant pandas are returning to D.C. this year, the Smithsonian’s National Zoo announces, after reaching a lease agreement with China&lt;/a&gt;. The two pandas, a two-year-old male named Bao Li and a two-year-old female named Qing Bao, are due to arrive later in the year. Bao Li’s mother is Bao Bao, a giant panda who was born at the zoo in 2013. Both are of course relatives of Prof. Steve Steve, the mascot of The Panda’s Thumb. Prof. Steve Steve is impressed that his relatives will cost the zoo $1 million per year for 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt;  &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">According to a headline in the Washington Post, Giant pandas are returning to D.C. this year, the Smithsonian’s National Zoo announces, after reaching a lease agreement with China. The two pandas, a two-year-old male named Bao Li and a two-year-old female named Qing Bao, are due to arrive later in the year. Bao Li’s mother is Bao Bao, a giant panda who was born at the zoo in 2013. Both are of course relatives of Prof. Steve Steve, the mascot of The Panda’s Thumb. Prof. Steve Steve is impressed that his relatives will cost the zoo $1 million per year for 10 years. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry></feed>