<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-11-18T21:48:40-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Every Living Thing: book report</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/every-living-thing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Every Living Thing: book report" /><published>2024-11-12T19:15:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-11-12T19:15:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/every-living-thing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/every-living-thing.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Roberts_Every_Living_Thing_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The cover is kind of &quot;busy,&quot; but I shall try not to judge the book by its cover.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0C7TNQHKK/&quot;&gt;Every Living Thing&lt;/a&gt;, The Great and Deadly Race to Know All Life&lt;/i&gt;, by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jason_Roberts_(author)&quot;&gt;Jason Roberts&lt;/a&gt;. It is sort of a double biography of Carl Linnaeus (1707-1778) and Georges-Louis Leclerc, Comte de Buffon (1707-1788), but it continues to follow their legacies well beyond their lifetimes to the present. I cannot recommend it more highly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not know what impression Mr. Roberts intended, but if you thought Linnaeus was a young man on the make, something of a scoundrel who might say anything in the interests of self-promotion, you might not be too far from the truth. The hero of this book is not Linnaeus but rather his sometime rival, Buffon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let us deal with Linnaeus first. Linnaeus obtained a phony doctor’s degree from what we would now call a diploma mill. He anointed 14 (or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ikfoundation.org/books-and-art/linnaeus-apostles-full-set/&quot;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;
 of what he called his “apostles” (!), sent them on long journeys from which many never returned, and completely abandoned one who returned with no specimens. He has been criticized for not allowing his daughters their educations, to a degree, says Roberts, that was extreme even for the time (but he supported his daughter Elisabeth in her interest in botany. She wrote a paper devoted to what is now known as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nybg.org/blogs/science-talk/2013/12/flashes-in-the-twilight/&quot;&gt;Elizabeth Linnaeus phenomenon&lt;/a&gt;). Linnaeus also believed in the fixity of species, not to mention some very bizarre creatures, but in that he was probably not alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linnaeus developed a taxonomy that is largely in use today; that is a major accomplishment, to say the least. After defining and then apparently rejecting some ridiculous species within the genus &lt;i&gt;Homo&lt;/i&gt;, he divided &lt;i&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/i&gt; into four subspecies: in essence, European, African, indigenous American, and Asian. Europeans, to Linnaeus, were governed by laws, whereas Africans were governed by whim, Americans by customs, and Asians by opinions. Roberts notes that “apologists have attempted to absolve Linnaeus of racism,” but he insists that claiming that Europeans alone were governed by laws is a clear statement of superiority. He cannot forgive Linnaeus, who stood by these characterizations for the rest of his life. I do not know whether Roberts is engaging in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Presentism_(historical_analysis)&quot;&gt;presentism&lt;/a&gt;, but I suspect not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linnaeus occasionally defined species on the basis of scant evidence and sometimes published reviews of his own work using a pseudonym. Roberts accuses him of drawing “unmoored conclusions” in “an act of ignorance masquerading as savantry.” Buffon was the real thing; he would have been called a scientist, but the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/scientist&quot;&gt;first known use of the word&lt;/a&gt; was in 1834. Where Linnaeus required scant evidence, Buffon studied his “private menagerie” for years and concluded, in Roberts’s words, “The essence of species lay in reproduction, the ability of one generation to propagate another.” On the basis of what is essentially this definition, Buffon further concluded that there was only one human species, which “underwent diverse changes from the influence of the climate, food, mode of living, epidemical distempers, and the intermixture of individuals[.]” Charles Darwin, a century or so later, thought that Buffon’s theories were “laughably like mine.” Like Darwin, Buffon opposed slavery, and he did not care for the slave-owner Jefferson. Roberts does not discuss Linnaeus’s views on slavery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buffon ultimately published 35 volumes of his encyclopedia, &lt;i&gt;Histoire naturelle&lt;/i&gt;. According to the author, he outsold Rousseau, Voltaire, and Montesquieu, and his work continued in print for over 150 years. Roberts says it is the longest nonfiction work written by a single author and rivals encyclopedias written by many authors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides evolution, Buffon developed what Roberts calls “the first rough sketch of a working theory of reproduction,” which included an “internal matrix” that sort of resembles DNA. Where Linnaeus insisted on the fixity of species, Buffon studied fossil remains and concluded that some species had gone extinct and others had been born. Species, he thought, changed by adaptation to the environment, and later species were demarcated from their ancestors when they could no longer interbreed (cf. the modern &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution.berkeley.edu/biological-species-concept/&quot;&gt;biological species concept&lt;/a&gt;). He thought that related families may have a common ancestor and indeed that all life could be further traced to a yet earlier common ancestor. Buffon realized that these were dangerous thoughts in the mid-1700’s; he wrote to a friend, “One can slip ideas into a quarto volume which would cause a public outcry if they appeared in a pamphlet.” In consequence, he was very careful and penned a disclaimer any time he drew a conclusion that might offend the religious hierarchy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buffon also suggested that single-celled organisms may not all be animals or plants but rather “indeterminate species and in-between objects which we do not know where to place…” and suggested that living organisms might consist of building blocks now known as cells. On a less biological note, he opened an ironworks, which Roberts calls “a template for factories to come.” A gazebo that he had cast was the “first all-iron structure in Paris.” Its roof is a lattice shaped as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperboloid&quot;&gt;one-sheeted hyperboloid&lt;/a&gt; (a hyperboloid of revolution), which did not appear in architecture until the 20th century. According to Wikipedia, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buffon%27s_needle_problem&quot;&gt;Buffon’s needle&lt;/a&gt; was the first solved problem in geometric probability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buffon deduced that the earth was much older than a few thousand years and divided its history into seven “epochs.” Apart from not knowing the duration of any epoch, he got their chronology about right. (In fact, he used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.geolsoc.org.uk/Geoscientist/Archive/April-2018/Buffon-the-geologist&quot;&gt;cannonballs&lt;/a&gt; to estimate the rate of cooling of the earth and concluded that its age was around 75,000 years.) Roberts calls his work a deliberate provocation and an attack on the fixity of species. For his pains he was denounced by the Sorbonne and required to sign a retraction, which he promptly ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buffon speculated – &lt;i&gt;very&lt;/i&gt; carefully – as to whether nonhuman animals had souls, for which transgression apparently Madame Pompadour smacked him in the face with a fan. He recognized, nearly 300 years ago, that humans could “despoil and impoverish” the earth by out-producing its capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;History was kinder to Linnaeus than to Buffon. Buffon’s star began to fade during the French Revolution, when the Société de Linné took advantage of the turmoil to promote Linnaeus and minimize Buffon. By the 1860’s in England, Buffon’s &lt;i&gt;Natural History&lt;/i&gt; was sold in badly abridged, perhaps caricatured form alongside &lt;i&gt;Aesop’s Fables&lt;/i&gt;. Shaw remembers as a child hearing Buffon called “Buffoon” and says that within 10 years he was forgotten. Perhaps this book will succeed in &lt;strike&gt;reviving&lt;/strike&gt; enhancing his legacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I liked the writing very well and noticed only four editorial mistakes: seraphim for seraph, &lt;i&gt;Camillia sinsesis&lt;/i&gt; for &lt;i&gt;Camellia sinensis&lt;/i&gt;, counsel for consul, and Ernest Haeckel for Ernst Haeckel. Well, maybe one more: Rosalind Franklin arguably did not win a Nobel Prize because she had died before the prize was awarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgment. &lt;/strong&gt;Thanks to Ron Wittmann for discussing taxonomy and other topics with me. Deanna Young read a draft and offered several useful comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">The cover is kind of &quot;busy,&quot; but I shall try not to judge the book by its cover. The book is Every Living Thing, The Great and Deadly Race to Know All Life, by Jason Roberts. It is sort of a double biography of Carl Linnaeus (1707-1778) and Georges-Louis Leclerc, Comte de Buffon (1707-1788), but it continues to follow their legacies well beyond their lifetimes to the present. I cannot recommend it more highly. I do not know what impression Mr. Roberts intended, but if you thought Linnaeus was a young man on the make, something of a scoundrel who might say anything in the interests of self-promotion, you might not be too far from the truth. The hero of this book is not Linnaeus but rather his sometime rival, Buffon. But let us deal with Linnaeus first. Linnaeus obtained a phony doctor’s degree from what we would now call a diploma mill. He anointed 14 (or 17 of what he called his “apostles” (!), sent them on long journeys from which many never returned, and completely abandoned one who returned with no specimens. He has been criticized for not allowing his daughters their educations, to a degree, says Roberts, that was extreme even for the time (but he supported his daughter Elisabeth in her interest in botany. She wrote a paper devoted to what is now known as the Elizabeth Linnaeus phenomenon). Linnaeus also believed in the fixity of species, not to mention some very bizarre creatures, but in that he was probably not alone. Linnaeus developed a taxonomy that is largely in use today; that is a major accomplishment, to say the least. After defining and then apparently rejecting some ridiculous species within the genus Homo, he divided Homo sapiens into four subspecies: in essence, European, African, indigenous American, and Asian. Europeans, to Linnaeus, were governed by laws, whereas Africans were governed by whim, Americans by customs, and Asians by opinions. Roberts notes that “apologists have attempted to absolve Linnaeus of racism,” but he insists that claiming that Europeans alone were governed by laws is a clear statement of superiority. He cannot forgive Linnaeus, who stood by these characterizations for the rest of his life. I do not know whether Roberts is engaging in presentism, but I suspect not.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Butorides virescens</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/butorides-virescens.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Butorides virescens" /><published>2024-11-11T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-11-11T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/butorides-virescens</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/butorides-virescens.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Denelsbeck_Butorides_virescens.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Green heron&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Green_Heron/overview&quot;&gt;Butorides virescens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; green heron. Mr. Denelsbeck blogs at &lt;a href=&quot;https://wading-in.net/&quot;&gt;Wading-In Photography&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Al Denelsbeck. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Butorides virescens &amp;ndash; green heron. Mr. Denelsbeck blogs at Wading-In Photography. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dembski and Ewert wish upon a star</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/dembskiewert2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dembski and Ewert wish upon a star" /><published>2024-11-10T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-11-10T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/-dembskiewert2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/dembskiewert2.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;600px&quot; src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Six_Grandfathers.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Six grandfathers image]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;The mountain called &lt;em&gt;Six Grandfathers&lt;/em&gt; by the 
Lakota people before it was renamed Mount&lt;br /&gt; Rushmore. An image of Mount Rushmore adorns the cover of Dembski and 
  Ewert's book,&lt;br /&gt; as an example of a design inference we make. Does the Lakota name&lt;br /&gt; reflect 
a design inference? &lt;em&gt;Wikimedia, public domain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/06/dembskiewert1.html&quot;&gt;post of 12 June&lt;/a&gt;, I commented on the first part of William 
Dembski and Winston Ewert’s new book, the second edition of Dembski’s 
1998 book &lt;em&gt;The Design Inference: Eliminating Chance 
Through Small Probabilities&lt;/em&gt;.   I noted that to make the argument 
for a Design Inference they had set aside Dembski’s previous criterion 
of Complex Specified Information, and instead replaced it by 
Algorithmic Specified Complexity (ASC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a measure of the difference between the length of a bitstring and the length of a bitstring that describes it. 
It originates from the mathematical work on “randomness deficiciency”, where the bitstring is a binary number, and the smaller bitstring is a computer program that computes it.  In that field, numbers that are considered truly random are those generated by programs that are almost as long as the number.  A number that can be generated by a short program is not considered random.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dembski and Ewert intend to apply this to biology.  The longer number somehow specifies a phenotype (or maybe a 
genotype), while the shorter number “describes” it.  In my previous review, I had reached Chapter 7, “Evolutionary Biology”.  Here, let’s consider how they argue the ASC criterion can be applied to biological adaptations.  (Spoiler – we’re going to be disappointed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was full of expectations when I started reading Chapter 7.  I had a number of questions in mind, ones I have 
asked before in posts and comments about their ASC criterion for design inference (for example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/12/Is-Algorithmic-Specified-Complexity-Useless-for-Analyzing-Evolution.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Any-new-arguments.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/worst-of-2021.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What did the bitstring represent? A genotype?  A phenotype?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Was the “description” string a program for computing the larger string?  Was it perhaps some genetic encoding of developmental instructions?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the difference between the lengths of the two is large enough, this is supposed to be astronomically improbable.  Under what distribution?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the probability somehow able to take into account the possibility of natural selection building up such
large difference step by step?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 7 has a number of sections.  Let me describe briefly what each covers, and what it accomplishes.  I will summarize their arguments.  I will add comments of my own, in parentheses, or otherwise explicitly identified:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;insulating-evolution-against-small-probabilities-pages-321-326&quot;&gt;Insulating Evolution against Small Probabilities (pages 321-326)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dembski and Ewert describe the success and wide acceptance of their design inference in evolutionary biology.  They then say “And now back to the real world”.  The success and acceptance, they accept, has not happened in reality.  This is because evolutionary biologists have been resistant to accepting that evolution of biological systems involves 
probabilities that small.  The evolutionary biologists have done so by invoking mechanisms of cumulative selection.  As an example Dembski and Ewert describe Richard Dawkins’s teaching example of a simple form of simulated natural selection starting with a random 28-letter sequence of letters and spaces, and reaching the target phrase “METHINKS IT IS LIKE A WEASEL” in hundreds or thousands of steps, instead of the 10&lt;sup&gt;40&lt;/sup&gt; steps it would take if one simply drew new 28-letter sequences at random.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;variations-on-the-weasel-pages-326-330&quot;&gt;Variations on the WEASEL (pages 326-330)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evolutionary biologists are obsessed by the Weasel example (I would say it is creationists and advocates of Design that 
are actually the ones obsessed with it). “Perhaps design theorists should shift focus to the origin of life”.  (The infamous OTOOL diversion – Off To the Origin Of Life).  There cumulative selection cannot play a role, they argue.  Simulations like the Weasel are declared to be “suggestive but misleading, so removed from biological reality that they cannot decide the matter”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;resetting-darwinian-evolutions-bayesian-prior-pages-331-336&quot;&gt;Resetting Darwinian Evolution’s Bayesian Prior (pages 331-336)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering the choice between design and natural selection as a Bayesian Inference, it is important what prior probabilities one assigns these two hypotheses.  If one gives design a low enough prior probability, it cannot have any reasonably high posterior probability.  A design inference can be used to “sweep the field clear of all relevant chance hypotheses”. (Actually they could only do that if they could show that the probability of the data, given natural selection, was zero, but Demsbki and Ewert don’t quite mean that, they mean showing that the data is astronomically improbable).  Biologists argue that there may be many other “chance hypotheses”, but this is an argument by mere possibility as the biologists do not produce these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;who-is-arguing-from-ignorance-pages-337-339&quot;&gt;Who Is Arguing from Ignorance? (pages 337-339)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biologists are, since they essentially never produce the exact sequence of events needed to evolve these biological systems.  However, the biologists accuse the design theorists of arguing from ignorance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;john-stuart-mills-method-of-difference-pages-340-345&quot;&gt;John Stuart Mill’s Method of Difference (pages 340-345)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mill argued that if two situations differ in only one circumstance and a phenomenon occurs in one and not in the other, this circumstance is the effect, or cause.   Biologists such as Kenneth Miller say that all that is needed for natural selection to work is the presence of selection, replication, and mutation.  But these do not automatically lead to “complexity” or something “interesting”.  The evolution experiments of Sol Spiegelman and of Richard Lenski do not show those, but have genomes that rapidly decay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-challenge-of-multiple-simultaneous-mutations-pages-345-352&quot;&gt;The Challenge of Multiple Simultaneous Mutations (pages 345-352)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is basically a discussion of Michael Behe’s argument that major innovations require multiple mutations, each of which is individually disadvantageous, with an advantage only when they get together.  It is extremely improbable that these can be brought together by natural selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-to-make-of-bad-design-pages-353-to-368&quot;&gt;What to Make of Bad Design? (pages 353 to 368)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bad design arguments are not plausible for a number of reasons.  Quotes from “some naturalistic thinkers” who do not think there is actual design but are impressed with the design of the  cell.  These include James Shapiro.  Discussion of whether there is junk DNA, giving great credit to the 2012 (supposed) refutation of junk DNA by the ENCODE Consortium.  Dembski and Ewert cite an embarrassing quote by Richard Dawkins in 2012 accepting the ENCODE result and arguing that it is compatible with his views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;doing-the-calculation-pages-368-378&quot;&gt;Doing the Calculation (pages 368-378)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(At last, are we to be shown how?  Well, partly.)  Calculates the probability of a “biological system”, using protein folds as one example, invoking Douglas Axe’s experiments which that only one in 10&lt;sup&gt;-77&lt;/sup&gt; randomly constructed proteins would have enough of the proper structure and sequence 
to make a minimally functional β-lactamase enzyme.  Axe’s paper was in &lt;em&gt;Journal of Molecular Biology&lt;/em&gt;, volume 341, issue 5, page 1295 in 2004. The argument is based on the view that to get started evolving a β-lactamase enzyme one must have random assembly of such a protein, before natural selection can act. The example uses the protein sequence, with a 20-letter alphabet, as the string, equivalent to about a 648-bit string.  Dembski and 
Ewert do not try to quantitate the length of the “description” needed.  They acknowledge that evolutionary biologistss would argue that there might be other paths to the same functionality, without using these specific structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-breakdown-of-evolvability-pages-378-381&quot;&gt;The Breakdown of Evolvability (pages 378-381)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“whence the confidence that Darwinian evolution should allow untrammeled interconnectivity from any one living form to any other, whether by direct evolution or by indirect evolution from a common evolutionary precursor?”  They talk about protein alphabets, then uses a word game of changing a letter in a word, or deleting it, or adding a letter to change to another English word.  Argues that one cannot go from any word to any other this way.  Therefore although we have not proven that such interconnectedness in biological organisms cannot exist, we have shown it may not exist.  Therefore “there are indeed good reasons to think that a gradualist Darwinian form of evolution is very limited in what it can accomplish in biology, and that some features of biological systems not only resist Darwinian explanations but also invite design inferences”.  (This last part, the “some features” part, does not follow).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;where-to-look-for-small-probabilities-in-biology-pages-382-394&quot;&gt;Where to Look for Small Probabilities in Biology? (pages 382-394)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, the last section in Chapter 7, talks about Michael Behe’s arguments about Irreducible Complexity.  Lots of discussion of how the bacterial flagellum could or could not have arisen.  Evolutionary biologists never seem to come up with a detailed series of steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-have-dembski-and-ewert-accomplished&quot;&gt;What have Dembski and Ewert accomplished?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the questions I asked above, they have not answered most of them.   The one example that they give that involves a sequence of digital symbols 
asks about the probability of a particular protein sequence arising from random sequences of amino acids.  What they give is really not an Algorithmically 
Specified Complexity agument, but a much older argument.   Usually that argument takes the lengths of modern proteins as a necessary requirement for protein function, and does not take into account that many random protein sequences (and random RNA sequences) show a variety of weak enzymatic function.  And small changes in those sequences often lead to similar amounts of function.  It is therefore not impossible for evolution to follow steps uphill on a fitness surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difficulty with Dembski and Ewert’s definition of Algorithmically Specified Complexity is that when the quantity is large, it means that there is a long sequence (of something) which is “described” by a short sequence.  And there is simply no point in their argument that explains why (a) natural selection cannot achieve that, step by step, or (b) why achieving that is needed to result in any adaptation.  The matter is left without discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a large difference between the new argument and the previous specified complexity arguments.  As I noted in the first section of this review (12 June), the new concept is not a Functional Information argument.  The “probability” is not the probability that a random sequence has this much &lt;em&gt;or more&lt;/em&gt; of the desired trait.  It is just the probability of this sequence.  There is simply no discussion of how to compute a tail probability in some relevant distribution.  Or even in some nonrelevant distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we are left with the questions I asked, and re-asked, above.  How does this argument work?  What are the relevant distributions?  What is the “sequence”?  How does the “description” relate to some relevant probability?  Is it a tail probability under some relevant null distribution?  Is it a probability that ordinary evolutionary processes could achieve something?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-burden-of-proof&quot;&gt;A burden of proof&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By not explaining how their arguments work, in spite of 400+ pages of explanation, Dembski and Ewert are engaged in wish-fulfillment.  They have “wished upon a star”.  But it is not true that, as the song claims, that if you do, “your dreams come true”.  Dembski and Ewert do not fill in the blanks, not even close.  They do go off sideways into irreducible complexity arguments, and they do repeatedly claim that evolutionary biologists argue that natural selection will always succeed in meeting challenges.  Ask the passenger pigeon about that, or the Great Auk, or the Dodo, or the Carolina Paroquet, or the mammoth.  Or the trilobites, or the seed ferns. or the ammonites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is still possible for them to answer my objections by filling in the blanks.  Saying that this is unfair, because biologists have not outlined every last step of the evolution of a complicated biological adaptation is no excuse.   I’ll be happy to hear from them how their arguments actually work.  We’re waiting …&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">The mountain called Six Grandfathers by the Lakota people before it was renamed Mount Rushmore. An image of Mount Rushmore adorns the cover of Dembski and Ewert's book, as an example of a design inference we make. Does the Lakota name reflect a design inference? Wikimedia, public domain &amp;nbsp; In my post of 12 June, I commented on the first part of William Dembski and Winston Ewert’s new book, the second edition of Dembski’s 1998 book The Design Inference: Eliminating Chance Through Small Probabilities. I noted that to make the argument for a Design Inference they had set aside Dembski’s previous criterion of Complex Specified Information, and instead replaced it by Algorithmic Specified Complexity (ASC). This is a measure of the difference between the length of a bitstring and the length of a bitstring that describes it. It originates from the mathematical work on “randomness deficiciency”, where the bitstring is a binary number, and the smaller bitstring is a computer program that computes it. In that field, numbers that are considered truly random are those generated by programs that are almost as long as the number. A number that can be generated by a short program is not considered random. Dembski and Ewert intend to apply this to biology. The longer number somehow specifies a phenotype (or maybe a genotype), while the shorter number “describes” it. In my previous review, I had reached Chapter 7, “Evolutionary Biology”. Here, let’s consider how they argue the ASC criterion can be applied to biological adaptations. (Spoiler – we’re going to be disappointed).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Philosopher Michael Ruse dies</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/philosopher-michael-ruse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Philosopher Michael Ruse dies" /><published>2024-11-07T09:47:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-11-07T09:47:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/philosopher-michael-ruse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/philosopher-michael-ruse.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The following &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/michael-ruse-influential-historian-and-philosopher-biology-dies-84&quot;&gt;obituary&lt;/a&gt; by Glenn Branch is reproduced with permission from the National Center for Science Education. In addition, you may read over a dozen &lt;/i&gt;very&lt;i&gt; nice remembrances on Leiter Reports, &lt;a href=&quot;https://leiterreports.typepad.com/blog/2024/11/in-memoriam-michael-ruse-1940-2024.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Leiter Reports describes itself as “[t]he world’s most popular philosophy blog, since 2003.” Thanks to Nick Matzke for providing the link.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Michael Ruse, influential historian and philosopher of biology, dies at 84&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Ruse_Obit_Pic_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Michael Ruse with his pet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;Michael Ruse with his pet, McGruff, in 2020. &lt;small&gt;By Lizzie Ruse, CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The influential historian and philosopher of biology Michael Ruse died on November 1, 2024, at the age of 84, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.legacy.com/ca/obituaries/theglobeandmail/name/michael-ruse-obituary?id=56689886&quot;&gt;according&lt;/a&gt; to the obituary in &lt;i&gt;The Globe and Mail&lt;/i&gt; (November 4, 2024). Ruse was one of the founders of the field of philosophy of biology: the first of his more than 70 books was the seminal &lt;i&gt;The Philosophy of Biology&lt;/i&gt; (1970) and he founded the field’s first journal, &lt;i&gt;Biology and Philosophy&lt;/i&gt;. He was especially interested in evolutionary biology, which he discussed in books such as &lt;i&gt;The Darwinian Revolution&lt;/i&gt; (1979, second edition 1999), &lt;i&gt;Darwinism Defended&lt;/i&gt; (1982), &lt;i&gt;Taking Darwin Seriously&lt;/i&gt; (1986), &lt;i&gt;Monad to Man: The Concept of Progress in Evolutionary Biology &lt;/i&gt;(1996), and &lt;i&gt;Darwin and Design&lt;/i&gt; (2003), among others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Owing to his scholarly interest in evolutionary biology, Ruse was recruited by the plaintiffs in &lt;i&gt;McLean v. Arkansas&lt;/i&gt;, a legal case challenging the constitutionality of Arkansas’s 1981 equal time for creation science law. His testimony that creation science failed to qualify as scientific was central to the favorable ruling, although it excited considerable controversy among his fellow philosophers. Ruse continued to discuss and criticize creationism, editing a collection of essays related to &lt;i&gt;McLean&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;But Is It Science?&lt;/i&gt; (1988, second edition coedited with Robert T. Pennock 2008) as well as writing &lt;i&gt;The Evolution War &lt;/i&gt; (2000), and &lt;i&gt;The Evolution/Creation Struggle&lt;/i&gt; (2005). Raised as a Quaker, Ruse was not a believer, but he sought to promote peaceful coexistence of science and religion, articulating his views in books such as &lt;i&gt;Can a Darwinian Be a Christian?&lt;/i&gt; (2001) and &lt;i&gt;Science and Spirituality&lt;/i&gt; (2010). Despite his differences with his intellectual foes, Ruse was famed for his friendliness and conviviality. Kenneth R. Miller of Brown University, president of NCSE’s board of directors, commented, “I respected him as a philosopher who genuinely understood science and more importantly loved him as a friend.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ruse was born in Birmingham, England, on June 21, 1940. He earned his B.A. in philosophy and mathematics from the University of Bristol in 1962, his M.A. in philosophy from McMaster University in 1964, and his Ph.D. in philosophy from the University of Bristol in 1970. He spent his career at the University of Guelph from 1965 to 2000 and then at Florida State University, where he was the Lucyle T. Werkmeister Professor of Philosophy from 2000 onward. He was a Fellow of the Royal Society of Canada and of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, one of the Gifford Lecturers in Natural Theology for 2001, and the recipient of at least four honorary doctoral degrees.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">The following obituary by Glenn Branch is reproduced with permission from the National Center for Science Education. In addition, you may read over a dozen very nice remembrances on Leiter Reports, here. Leiter Reports describes itself as “[t]he world’s most popular philosophy blog, since 2003.” Thanks to Nick Matzke for providing the link. Michael Ruse, influential historian and philosopher of biology, dies at 84 Michael Ruse with his pet, McGruff, in 2020. By Lizzie Ruse, CC BY-SA 4.0. The influential historian and philosopher of biology Michael Ruse died on November 1, 2024, at the age of 84, according to the obituary in The Globe and Mail (November 4, 2024). Ruse was one of the founders of the field of philosophy of biology: the first of his more than 70 books was the seminal The Philosophy of Biology (1970) and he founded the field’s first journal, Biology and Philosophy. He was especially interested in evolutionary biology, which he discussed in books such as The Darwinian Revolution (1979, second edition 1999), Darwinism Defended (1982), Taking Darwin Seriously (1986), Monad to Man: The Concept of Progress in Evolutionary Biology (1996), and Darwin and Design (2003), among others. Owing to his scholarly interest in evolutionary biology, Ruse was recruited by the plaintiffs in McLean v. Arkansas, a legal case challenging the constitutionality of Arkansas’s 1981 equal time for creation science law. His testimony that creation science failed to qualify as scientific was central to the favorable ruling, although it excited considerable controversy among his fellow philosophers. Ruse continued to discuss and criticize creationism, editing a collection of essays related to McLean, But Is It Science? (1988, second edition coedited with Robert T. Pennock 2008) as well as writing The Evolution War (2000), and The Evolution/Creation Struggle (2005). Raised as a Quaker, Ruse was not a believer, but he sought to promote peaceful coexistence of science and religion, articulating his views in books such as Can a Darwinian Be a Christian? (2001) and Science and Spirituality (2010). Despite his differences with his intellectual foes, Ruse was famed for his friendliness and conviviality. Kenneth R. Miller of Brown University, president of NCSE’s board of directors, commented, “I respected him as a philosopher who genuinely understood science and more importantly loved him as a friend.” Ruse was born in Birmingham, England, on June 21, 1940. He earned his B.A. in philosophy and mathematics from the University of Bristol in 1962, his M.A. in philosophy from McMaster University in 1964, and his Ph.D. in philosophy from the University of Bristol in 1970. He spent his career at the University of Guelph from 1965 to 2000 and then at Florida State University, where he was the Lucyle T. Werkmeister Professor of Philosophy from 2000 onward. He was a Fellow of the Royal Society of Canada and of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, one of the Gifford Lecturers in Natural Theology for 2001, and the recipient of at least four honorary doctoral degrees.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Climate Change Denial for Creationist Kids</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/climate-change-denial.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Climate Change Denial for Creationist Kids" /><published>2024-11-06T09:22:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-11-06T09:22:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/climate-change-denial</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/climate-change-denial.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Branch_Climate_Change_Kids_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Screenshot image of Ken Ham and Jessica DeFord’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.masterbooks.com/climate-change-for-kids-and-parents-too&quot;&gt; &lt;i&gt;Climate Change for Kids…and Parents Too!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Originally posted in &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/climate-change-denial-for-creationist-kids/&quot;&gt;Righting America&lt;/a&gt;, October 29, 2024, and reprinted with permission. Glenn Branch is deputy director of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/&quot;&gt;National Center for Science Education&lt;/a&gt;, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as &lt;/i&gt;Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher, &lt;i&gt;and the &lt;/i&gt;Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics, &lt;i&gt;and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of &lt;/i&gt;Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools&lt;i&gt; (2006). He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.masterbooks.com/climate-change-for-kids-and-parents-too&quot;&gt; &lt;i&gt;Climate Change for Kids…and Parents Too!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the latest entry in a spate of climate change denial books aimed at a young audience, invites the reader to “[d]elve into the science of climate change and discover how science, removed from assumption and speculation, reflects the history and truth found in God’s Word” (in the words of the back cover). The reference to God’s Word is distinctive: the propaganda efforts in the same vein from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/climate-environment/2023/04/11/CO&amp;lt;sub&amp;gt;2&amp;lt;/sub&amp;gt;-coalition-climate-denial/&quot;&gt;the CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; Coalition&lt;/a&gt;, Mike Huckabee’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://insideclimatenews.org/news/31072023/huckabees-kids-guide-to-climate/&quot;&gt;EverBright Kids&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eenews.net/articles/in-desantis-fla-schools-get-ok-for-climate-denial-videos/&quot;&gt;PragerU&lt;/a&gt; are ostensibly secular. But the authors of &lt;i&gt;Climate Change for Kids&lt;/i&gt; are Ken Ham, the founder of the young-earth creationist ministry Answers in Genesis, and Jessica DeFord, who, armed with a master of science degree in wildlife ecology, works for the same organization. In consequence, their book is a mix of error and fantasy, with the errors resembling those of secular climate change deniers and the fantasies emanating from their own reading of — and creative additions to — the Bible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fair amount of the eighty-page book purports to address the evidence for climate change and for anthropogenic climate change from the historical record. It would be tedious to describe all of its errors, but a central misunderstanding deserves attention. Acknowledging that “[t]he observational data shows [&lt;i&gt;sic&lt;/i&gt;] that the global surface temperature of the earth has been warming over the past 100 years or so since it has been recorded” and reporting that the amount of warming is estimated to be about 1.5–1.8 °C, Ham and DeFord then caution, “But this warming estimate didn’t come solely from the observational data collected at weather stations and by satellites. It’s based on computer models. What you input into these models will decide what predications [&lt;i&gt;sic&lt;/i&gt;] the computer model provides” (p. 18). A footnote offers a 2022 paper by meteorologist Roy W. Spencer and climatologist John R. Christy, both at the University of Alabama in Huntsville, as evidence for the middle sentence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s the problem? Well, the cited paper, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchsquare.com/article/rs-2162757/v1&quot;&gt;Dependence of Climate Sensitivity Estimates on Internal Climate Variability During 1880–2020 &lt;/a&gt;,” is prominently labeled “This is a preprint; it has not been peer reviewed by a journal.” So Ham and DeFord have no business citing it. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00704-023-04634-7&quot;&gt;version&lt;/a&gt; of the paper was later published in the journal &lt;i&gt;Theoretical and Applied Climatology&lt;/i&gt;, although it seems not to have attracted significant scientific attention. More importantly, though, in neither version of their paper do Spencer and Christy claim that the warming estimate is based on computer models. And that is simply because the warming estimate is not based on predictive computer models! Rather, it is based on observational data, namely, measurements taken by surface and satellite thermometers. True, both data sets require adjustment and correction in light of factors that introduce biases. But their close agreement, unmentioned by Ham and DeFord, is strong confirmation that the climate is warming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ham and DeFord conclude, “So the predictions don’t necessarily reflect the real-world, observational data” (p. 18) — which is odd, since no predictions are under discussion. They add, “And one study that compared computer climate models to the observational data found every single climate model they studied overpredicted warming,” citing a 2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdfdirect/10.1029/2020EA001281&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; by Ross McKitrick, a professor of economics at the University of Guelph, and Christy. But the paper focuses on the ability of a certain class of models, not all models, to predict tropospheric, not surface, temperatures. (It is a robust scientific finding that we live on the surface of the planet.) A comprehensive analysis of climate models published between 1970 and 2007 &lt;a href=&quot;https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1029/2019GL085378&quot;&gt;found&lt;/a&gt; them to be “skillful in predicting subsequent GMST [global mean surface temperature] changes, with most models examined showing warming consistent with observations, particularly when mismatches between model-projected and observationally estimated forcings were taken into account.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Illustrated here is Ham and DeFord’s general approach to handling the scientific literature on climate change: cite a single source that seems to offer evidence for the necessary point without worrying about whether it is legitimate, relevant, or confirmed by the bulk of scientific research. Sometimes, however, they abandon the approach in favor of bald assertion. Continuing, Ham and DeFord assert, with dubious coherence, “Climate researchers generally assume Earth maintains a constant average temperature and that our atmosphere traps more heat from the sun than what is returned to outer space” (p. 19), but they provide no examples of any researcher making such assumptions. Similarly, they claim that there is evidence that both of these “assumptions” are wrong, thus invalidating any models incorporating them, but they provide no references to such evidence. In any case, the views of climate scientists on these questions are not a matter of assumption but of evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite their view that there’s no telling how much Earth has warmed since the 1880s, Ham and DeFord are apparently willing to concede that recent global warming is real. But they misrepresent the argument for its anthropogenic nature, writing, “Since humans burn fossil fuels and burning fossil fuels produces CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; traps heat … we must be responsible for any warming … right?” (p. 20, ellipses in original). In fact, climate scientists have not jumped to their conclusion as &lt;i&gt;Climate Change for Kids&lt;/i&gt; suggests; rather, they have meticulously examined all of the known mechanisms capable of changing the climate and have concluded that greenhouse gases released by human activities are responsible for recent global warming. Popular explanations of the way in which they reached their conclusion are easy to find. For Ham and DeFord to misrepresent the argument so badly suggests at best that they are incompetent to write a book about climate science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paleoclimatology is dismissed on the grounds of a general skepticism about scientific knowledge of the past: “You can’t directly test, observe, or repeat the past!” (p. 33). “Scientists cannot 100% accurately describe past events if they were not there to directly observe them,” Ham and DeFord assert (p. 33), ignoring the fact that, far from claiming 100% accuracy, scientists typically report their findings with error bars. From a secular point of view, their emphasis on dismissing paleoclimatology is odd: until recently, paleoclimatological data (as well as historical data) were not considered to be as reliable as data from climate models, so the best evidence for the anthropogenic nature of climate change was from climate models — which are, of course, rooted in basic physics as applied to observational data. But Answers in Genesis, as a young-earth creationist ministry, is heavily invested in disputing the possibility of scientific knowledge of the past, and Ham and DeFord evidently want to put the investment to work here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus &lt;i&gt;Climate Change for Kids&lt;/i&gt; insists, “God and His Word is the ultimate authority by which we must discern all climate and weather information” (p. 53), and Ham — who nominally takes over the narration from p. 54 onward — explains, “As I’ve read the Bible to understand ‘climate change’ events that affect us to this day, God has revealed 7 climate ages divided into the history in the Bible” (p. 58). There are seven of these ages, presumably to rhyme with the seven days of creation; Answers in Genesis similarly discerns &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/bible-history/seven-cs-of-history/&quot;&gt;seven eras of history&lt;/a&gt;: Creation, Corruption, Catastrophe, Confusion, Christ, Cross, and Consummation. The alliterative muse apparently having deserted him, and no explicit nomenclature to be found in the Bible, Ham calls the seven climate ages Perfect, Groaning (i.e., postlapsarian, the label referring to Romans 8:22: “For we know that the whole creation has been groaning together in the pains of childbirth until now” [ESV]), Flooding, Icy, Shifting, Fiery, and Heavenly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the displays at Answers in Genesis’s attractions, the Creation Museum and Ark Encounter, the discussion of the seven climate ages (sprawled from p. 60 to p. 77) presents a reading of the Bible that both confabulates details that aren’t visible in the text (starting with the seven climate ages themselves) and fails to acknowledge a diversity of opinion among Bible-believing Christians. (On the attractions, see, for example, Susan L. Trollinger and William Vance Trollinger Jr.’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.press.jhu.edu/books/title/10885/righting-america-creation-museum&quot;&gt; &lt;i&gt;Righting America at the Creation Museum&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and James S. Bielo’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://nyupress.org/9781479843244/ark-encounter/&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Ark Encounter&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;; for organizations of evangelical Christians who accept climate change, see, for example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://yecaction.org/&quot;&gt;Young Evangelicals for Climate Action&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://creationcare.org/&quot;&gt;Evangelical Environmental Network&lt;/a&gt;.) Puzzlingly, the Groaning climate age is described as “continuing to this day, because God has not yet made a new heavens and earth to restore perfection” (p. 65); what’s the point of distinguishing among seven climate ages if there’s going to be overlap among them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Climate Change for Kids&lt;/i&gt; is purportedly aimed at readers nine years and older, and there are features, beyond the color illustrations on every page, clearly aimed at a young audience, such as boxes headed “Let’s ask” and “Why then?” and “From God’s Word” (with highlighted and annotated verses from the Bible). Still, having a four-page introduction from a septuagenarian Australian complaining about the secularism infecting his college education in the early 1970s seems like not the best way to attract the intended readership. Similarly, a fourth-grader might gaze upon the admonition “When climate change panic is induced and alarms are sounded in the media or in the halls of academia, we must exercise discernment” (p. 11) with a degree of puzzlement. Many of the cited sources (with details crammed, in tiny text, on p. 80) would certainly be beyond the ability of a young audience even to comprehend, let alone assess for scientific credibility. (A number of those works are in fact not scientifically credible.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But probably none of its readers are going to exercise discernment while poring over the arguments of the book. A five-star review posted at its publisher’s website comments, “I have it sitting on our coffee table in the living room (strategically placed!) and the kids have all flipped through it and learned so much!” “Flipped through” rings true. Rather, &lt;i&gt;Climate Change for Kids&lt;/i&gt; is geared for a readership that expects Answers in Genesis to have answers — so to speak — to all questions of importance to the Bible-believing Christian and so is less concerned about the quality than about the existence of the answers. Owning a copy of the book, and thus manifesting solidarity with Answers in Genesis, is what matters. Unfortunately, the same attitude is likely to bolster continuing efforts to derail, delay, and degrade action on the very real disruptions caused by anthropogenic global warming that are already afflicting people, including Ken Ham’s base, around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgments.&lt;/strong&gt;
Thanks to Paul Braterman for useful discussion and to Barry Bickmore, Andrew Dessler, and Spencer Weart for discussion of the climate change literature.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Glenn Branch</name></author><summary type="html">Screenshot image of Ken Ham and Jessica DeFord’s Climate Change for Kids…and Parents Too! Originally posted in Righting America, October 29, 2024, and reprinted with permission. Glenn Branch is deputy director of the National Center for Science Education, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher, and the Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics, and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools (2006). He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers. Climate Change for Kids…and Parents Too!, the latest entry in a spate of climate change denial books aimed at a young audience, invites the reader to “[d]elve into the science of climate change and discover how science, removed from assumption and speculation, reflects the history and truth found in God’s Word” (in the words of the back cover). The reference to God’s Word is distinctive: the propaganda efforts in the same vein from the CO2 Coalition, Mike Huckabee’s EverBright Kids, and PragerU are ostensibly secular. But the authors of Climate Change for Kids are Ken Ham, the founder of the young-earth creationist ministry Answers in Genesis, and Jessica DeFord, who, armed with a master of science degree in wildlife ecology, works for the same organization. In consequence, their book is a mix of error and fantasy, with the errors resembling those of secular climate change deniers and the fantasies emanating from their own reading of — and creative additions to — the Bible. A fair amount of the eighty-page book purports to address the evidence for climate change and for anthropogenic climate change from the historical record. It would be tedious to describe all of its errors, but a central misunderstanding deserves attention. Acknowledging that “[t]he observational data shows [sic] that the global surface temperature of the earth has been warming over the past 100 years or so since it has been recorded” and reporting that the amount of warming is estimated to be about 1.5–1.8 °C, Ham and DeFord then caution, “But this warming estimate didn’t come solely from the observational data collected at weather stations and by satellites. It’s based on computer models. What you input into these models will decide what predications [sic] the computer model provides” (p. 18). A footnote offers a 2022 paper by meteorologist Roy W. Spencer and climatologist John R. Christy, both at the University of Alabama in Huntsville, as evidence for the middle sentence.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Protoceratops at the Creation Museum</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/10/Phelps_Protoceratops.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Protoceratops at the Creation Museum" /><published>2024-10-28T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-28T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/10/Phelps_Protoceratops</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/10/Phelps_Protoceratops.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Phelps_Protoceratops_Museum_Exhibit_600.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; alt=&quot;[AiG Protoceratops display image]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 1. 
&lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; display, comparing &quot;evolutionist&quot; versus
creationist explanations of fossilization. From Ken
Ham’s blog. Fair use.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since at least May, 2024, the Creation Museum and Ken Ham have been discussing a new display, meant to describe the dinosaur &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; being drowned in the Biblical Flood of Noah (see for example &lt;a href=&quot;https://creationmuseum.org/blog/2024/05/24/new-dinosaur-exhibit-coming-to-creation-museum/&quot;&gt;https://creationmuseum.org/blog/2024/05/24/new-dinosaur-exhibit-coming-to-creation-museum/&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2024/07/14/most-detailed-protoceratops-world/&quot;&gt;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2024/07/14/most-detailed-protoceratops-world/&lt;/a&gt;). This display finally opened in late October, 2024. Figure 1 is 
this ridiculous display from Ken Ham’s blog. Pictures of the display are available on several Answers in Genesis’ and Ken Ham’s social media pages. Long (2024) describes the artwork going into this new display. Although the artwork depicting the dinosaur itself is excellent, the display has absurd, inaccurate, misleading, and dishonest information on the depositional environment of the surrounding sediment and the taphonomy of &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; and other Cretaceous vertebrate fossils of Mongolia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Creation Museum and Ark Encounter, both owned by the Young Earth Creationistministry Answers in Genesis (AiG), espouse that the fossil record is a result of Noah’s Flood which occurred in 2348 BC. All employees of AiG must sign off on a “Statement of Faith” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/about/faith/&quot;&gt;https://answersingenesis.org/about/faith/&lt;/a&gt;), that states in part:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The great flood of Genesis was an actual historic event, worldwide (global) in its extent and catastrophic in its effects. At one stage during the flood, the waters covered the entire surface of the whole globe with no land surface being exposed anywhere—the flood of Noah is not to be understood as any form of local or regional flood. The Noachian flood was a significant geological event, and most fossiliferous sediments were deposited at that time (&lt;a href=&quot;https://biblia.com/bible/esv/Gen%207.19%E2%80%9320&quot;&gt;Genesis 7:19–20&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://biblia.com/bible/esv/2%20Pet%203.5%E2%80%937&quot;&gt;2 Peter 3:5–7&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And further:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;No apparent, perceived, or claimed evidence in any field of study, including science, history, and chronology, can be valid if it contradicts the clear teaching of Scripture obtained by historical-grammatical interpretation. Of primary importance is the fact that &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/evidence-for-creation/whats-the-best-proof-of-creation/&quot;&gt;evidence is always subject to interpretation&lt;/a&gt; by fallible people who do not possess all information (&lt;a href=&quot;https://biblia.com/bible/esv/Num%2023.19&quot;&gt;Numbers 23:19&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://biblia.com/bible/esv/2%20Sam%2022.31&quot;&gt;2 Samuel 22:31&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://biblia.com/bible/esv/Ps%2018.30&quot;&gt;Psalm 18:30&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://biblia.com/bible/esv/Isa%2046.9%E2%80%9310&quot;&gt;Isaiah 46:9–10&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://biblia.com/bible/esv/Isaiah%2055.9&quot;&gt;55:9&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://biblia.com/bible/esv/Rom%203.4&quot;&gt;Romans 3:4&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://biblia.com/bible/esv/2%20Tim%203.16&quot;&gt;2 Timothy 3:16&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course this ends any attempt at science by AiG employees and replaces geology, paleontology, and all other science and history with unchanging religious dogma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of their weird dogma, AiG has an unusual take on dinosaurs and other prehistoric life forms. Both the Ark and Creation Museum have problematic displays on dinosaurs. In dioramas, dinosaurs are depicted as living with people, among ancient buildings, in stalls on Noah’s Ark, and most amazingly, fighting with humans and giants in a pre-Flood arena of death (see Figure 3 below). The Creation Museum has a actual skeleton of the dinosaur &lt;em&gt;Allosaurus&lt;/em&gt; on display that was donated by white nationalist and neo-Confederate Michael Peroutka (see: &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/dinosaur-bones-mark-meadows-neo-confederates-and-the-tawdry-world-of-young-earth-creationism/&quot;&gt;https://rightingamerica.net/dinosaur-bones-mark-meadows-neo-confederates-and-the-tawdry-world-of-young-earth-creationism/&lt;/a&gt;). This &lt;em&gt;Allosaurus&lt;/em&gt; skeleton is depicted as drowning in Noah’s Flood in 2348 BC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers in Genesis original dinosaur modeler and country singer, the recently deceased Buddy Davis, even has a children’s song that cultishly is meant to repeat Ken Ham’s catchphrase dogma that the fossil record is “Billions of dead things, buried in rock layers, laid down by water, all over the earth.” Davis gets children to repeat this again and again to music, a very effective indoctrination technique. The song can be heard in part here &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/media/audio/audio-archives/billions-dead-things-sample/&quot;&gt;https://answersingenesis.org/media/audio/audio-archives/billions-dead-things-sample/&lt;/a&gt; (Davis, ND).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; display continues this stream of indoctrination and misinformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;protoceratops&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; is one of the most studied dinosaurs in the history of vertebrate paleontology. The peer-reviewed scientific literature on this dinosaur, the depositional environment of the surrounding sediments, and aspects of the dinosaur’s taphonomy (the study of how organisms decay and are fossilized) is simply enormous and only a fraction can be cited in this simple blog post. Surprisingly, Wikipedia has an excellent page describing &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt;‘s physical characteristics, discovery, paleoecology, and various aspects of the dinosaur’s biology, as well as citations of the primary sources. Good accounts of basic information about the dinosaur can also be found in Dodson (1996); Prothero (2019); and Fastovsky and Weishampel (2016).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Phelps_Protoceratops_Fossil_600.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; alt=&quot;[Protoceratops image]&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
Figure 2. Photo of &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; in the Field Museum, Chicago.
Photograph by Dan Phelps.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ceratopsian &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; was a fairly small ornithischian dinosaur with complete growth sequences from very small juvenile specimens to adults about 2.5 meters long being known. Maximum body weight was slightly above 100 kg. Adults were quadrupeds, but juveniles may have been capable of walking as bipeds. The skull 🪓has a fairly large frill, and the nose of &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; has a horn-like structure that doesn’t stand out as much as in other Ceratopsid dinosaurs. The teeth indicate the animal was a vegetarian, shearing off vegetation with the aid of a very sharp beak (a characteristic of many ornithischians). &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; had relatively large eyes (even the sclerotic ring is known) and strong limbs, suggesting it was well-adapted to dim light, and capable of burrowing, although burrowing is not certain. The &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; from Mongolia are a single species &lt;em&gt;P. andrewsi&lt;/em&gt;, while another, slightly larger species &lt;em&gt;P. hellenikorhinus&lt;/em&gt; is known from similar deposits in China. There are likely to be other species of &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt;, and the dinosaur &lt;em&gt;Bainoceratops&lt;/em&gt; may be a synonym or a very close relative. All members of the Family Protoceratopsidae are Late Cretaceous (Campanian) in age, which is approximately 75 to 71 million years old (Dingus &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;., 2008).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; was discovered in 1923 by scientists working for the American Museum of Natural History’s Third Central Asiatic Expedition to the Gobi Desert of Mongolia (for historical accounts see: Andrews, 1926; Andrews &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;., 1932; Colbert, 1968 and 2000; Gallenkamp, 2001; and Sullivan, &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;, 2012) and formally described by Granger and Gregory (1923). After WWII, the Soviets, and still later Polish researchers did geological and paleontological research in this part of the Gobi. As the Soviet Union disintegrated, Japanese, Canadian, American (once again mostly from the American Museum of Natural History), and scientists from many other nations studied the Late Cretaceous dinosaurs of the Gobi (Colbert, 1968, 2000; and Sullivan &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. 2012). Note that for all their posing as scientists, creationists haven’t actually contributed &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to this scientific exploration and original research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cretaceous-of-mongolia&quot;&gt;Cretaceous of Mongolia&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; specimens from Mongolia are found in the Late Cretaceous Djadochta (sometimes spelled Djadokata or Djadokhta) Formation. The Djadochta is primarily a reddish colored fine- to medium-grained well-sorted quartz sandstone. There are minor amounts of conglomerates, siltstones, and calcareous nodule layers to be found in the unit. Regionally, the Djadochta is approximately 90 m (~300 feet) thick. Many of the beds are cross-bedded, but some are massive and do not show apparent sedimentary structures. Good descriptions, including stratigraphic columns, of the unit, can be found in Dingus and Loope (2000); Dingus &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (2008); Fastovsky &lt;em&gt;et a_l. (1997); Jerzykiewicz (1997 and 2000); Jerzykiewicz and Russell (1991); Jerzykiewicz _et al&lt;/em&gt;. (1993); Loope &lt;em&gt;et al. _(1998); Loope _et al&lt;/em&gt;. (1999); and Shuvalov (2000). Wikipedia also has a very general description of the unit and cites some of the primary literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new display at the Creation Museum is rather short on describing the Djadochta Formation. It literally cartoonishly contrasts the “Naturalistic Evolutionist” versus “Biblical Creationist” interpretation with actual cartoons depicting the burial of &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt;. The display simplistically claims “Naturalistic Evolutionists” think that &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; was buried by eolian (wind-driven) dunes during sandstorms, while they claim the dinosaurs were drowned and buried by underwater sandslides, driven by currents, during Noah’s Flood. The Creation Museum display only presents a tiny amount of selective evidence for their view, then declares victory over the “Naturalistic Evolutionists.” A September 29, 2024 “X” (formerly Twitter) post by Ken Ham includes a photo of part of the display. The main portion of the signage reads:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DUNES OF DEATH&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;WATER OR WIND?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The circumstances surrounding the burial of fossilized animals at Ukhaa Tolgod in Mongolia help show the differences between observational and historical science and how worldviews shape one’s conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;THE SAME EVIDENCE&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Creationists and evolutionists observe the same bones and agree that they are buried in ancient sand dunes, which can be formed by wind or flowing water. Proponents of either perspective can see that the dune cross-beds (remnants of sand avalanches) have 25° slope angles. All agree that the fossilization of the bones occurred when waterborne minerals seeped in and replaced the organic material. But while creationists and evolutionists use the same scientific evidence, they frequently interpret the evidence in different ways.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;ANALYSIS&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Both interpretations are based on the same evidence, but only one explains all the available data. Wind-formed dunes often have 28 - 34° downwind slope angles, whereas these slopes at Ukhaa Tolgod measure 25°- an angle more typical of water-formed dunes. Also, the sandstone encasing the animals is saturated with the waterborne mineral calcium carbonate. Ultimately, the evidence is more reasonably explained by biblical creation model.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional text in the display includes a tear-jerking narrative about the poor &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; escaping by swimming in the early weeks of Noah’s Flood, only to face burial in a sand slide in “a water-formed dune.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual depositional environments of the Djadochta Formation are much more complex than the above creationist fantasy. While the Djadochta is considered to be primarily eolian sands, there is evidence of a complex facies mosaic that also includes alluvial fan deposition, fluvial deposits in the form of short-lived streams, as well as minor areas with lacustrine (lake) deposition (see: Dingus and Loope, 2000; Dingus &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;, 2008; Jerzykiewicz, 1997 and 2000; Jerzykiewicz and Russell, 1991; Jerzykiewicz et al., 1993; Loope &lt;em&gt;et al.,&lt;/em&gt; 1998 and Loope &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;., 1999; and Novacek &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;., 1994). Besides the well-sorted cross-bedded sandstone, other evidence for the rock being deposited in a semi-arid desert environment comes from the presence of caliche deposits that probably represent paleosols, and vertical traces that represent numerous invertebrate burrows. Loope &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (1998) illustrate the cross-bedding, carbonate nodules, and probable dinosaur tracks in the sandstone in their figure 3. Several examples of burrows and rhizoliths (fossil plant roots) are illustrated in Jerzykiewicz &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (1993).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the vertebrate fossil bearing layers lack any discernible sedimentary structures other than caliche layers that contain rhizoliths. These units are have been described as “structureless sands.” Dingus and Loope (2000) and Dingus &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (2008) interpret these “structureless sands” as dune-derived sand-slides from times of lessened aridity/increased humidity (mesic conditions). Some of the evidence for times of increased humidity is described by Dingus and Loope (2008), who document crayfish-like burrows that represent unknown arthropods that dug down through the dry sands to reach groundwater. During these relatively-humid “mesic” times, dunes were held in place by caliche paleosols and vegetation, only to become oversteepened and eventually suddenly collapse, burying &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops, _other dinosaurs&lt;/em&gt;, _and other vertebrates of the Djadochta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of features characterize eolian deposits in the rock record, but no single criterion characterizes &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; eolian rocks. Eolian depositional environments can be incredibly complex and not easily characterized be cartoonish diagrams. The Creation Museum signage claiming the cross-bedding has the exact slope angle of 25° in the Djadokata Formation at Ukhaa Tolgod as being significant is simply not correct. In reality, ancient dune deposits can display very shallow to extremely steep cross-bedding angles. In many cases the angle is due to the moisture content and composition of the sand. For example, dry, well-sorted sand tends to pile up at maximum angles of 30 to 34° (Hill and Moshier, 2016), while slightly more moisture from various causes can result in angles above 40° (Bigarella, 1974). However, when sands become saturated with water, they can not maintain a steep slope and collapse. Hill and Moshier remind their readers that have built sandcastles at a beach of this property of moisture-rich sand. Moreover, very shallow slopes are also possible near the base of the downwind side of dunes (Bigarella, 1974). Thus, although eolian dunes tend to have steeper maximum cross-bedding compared to sand deposits formed under water, the exact angle alone doesn’t differentiate them from underwater sandbars. Ahlbrandt and Fryberger (1982) beautifully illustrate a number of eolian deposits and discuss additional criteria for the recognition of eolianites. These include the mineralogy, sorting, and tabular nature of the deposits themselves, combined with numerous sedimentary structures besides cross-bedding. In their detailed study of the Djadochta Formation, Dingus &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (2008) also note many of the features discussed above, including calcareous paleosols, trace fossils in the form of dinosaur tracks, invertebrate burrows, and rhizoliths (fossil plant roots). Niedzwiedzki, &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;, (2012) note a track beneath a &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; skeleton. Dingus &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (2008) also note that the Djadochta is a mosaic of several facies, including dune deposits, siltstone interdune deposits, conglomerates that had their source in outwash from alluvial fans, and sandslide deposits from dunes that occasionally collapsed after a period of stability. Interspersed with this were small lakes or ponds that accumulated silty muds and sands. Interestingly, the Creation Museum signage mentions the presence of the mineral calcite (CaCO₃) as if it were indicative of a marine deposit, whereas the mineral is also often associated with the caliches and paleosols that form in arid desert environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Phelps_Protoceratops_Humans_Vs_Dinosaur_600.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; alt=&quot;[Giants-dinosaur-human death match image]&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Fig. 3. 
AiG dinosaur-related display at the Ark Encounter: Giants and
humans in a three-way death match with the dinosaur
&lt;em&gt;Carnotaurus&lt;/em&gt; in a pre-Flood arena. Fair
use.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what is the source for the creationist misinformation on the Djadochta Formation? I have only been able to find two discussions in the creationist literature, both by AiG geologist, Dr. Andrew Snelling (1998 and 2009).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Snelling (1998), he discusses unnamed creationists considering the possibility of the Djadochta Formation being post-Flood; as silly as this is, it would be a convenient way to accept the overwhelming evidence for eolian deposition. Snelling (2008) also represents Loope &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (1998) as somehow denying eolian deposits because of their proposal that the structureless sands were the result of sandslides that occurred suddenly during more humid (mesic) conditions. Snelling tries very hard to imply to his readers that since rainfall/water is involved, the rocks and fossils are somehow consistent with Flood geology. Putting the short review paper by Snelling side by side with the research by Loope &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (1998) just doesn’t jive. To be charitable, perhaps Dr. Snelling didn’t understand the conclusions of Loope &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (1998).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snelling (2009, pp. 547 - 549) appears to be the source of a lot of the misinformation on the Creation Museum’s signage associated with the &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; display. The signage and Snelling use almost identical language when discussing the cross-bedding slope angles. Lang (2024) discusses the artwork and signage of the new exhibit; one can conclude that the exhibit designer’s used Snelling (2009) as their major inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of ancient eolian deposits ends up having important economic benefits. Several eolian deposits in the Western United States and the North Sea produce oil and natural gas from porous and permeable eolian sediments. Additionally, groundwater is known to deposit of uranium and other economic minerals in eolian sedimentary rocks ( Ahlbrandt and Fryberger, 1982; Galloway and Hobday, 1983). Thus there are economic considerations in studying ancient eolian deposits, not just academic questions concerning earth history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;taphonomy-of-protoceratops&quot;&gt;Taphonomy of &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also an enormous literature on the taphonomy (the study of the death and postmortem history of an organism to fossilization) of the &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; specimens from the Djadochta Formation. Fastovsky &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (1997) is the major study, but much information can be gleaned from other sources. Protoceratops is commonly found completely or mostly articulated and are usually oriented parallel to the direction of crossbedding dip. Often the limbs are contracted and the necks pulled back (this death pose may be evidence for desiccation). However, Fastovsky &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (1997) think that death often occurred via suffocation during sand storms. In contrast, the work of Loope &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (1998); Loope &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (1999); Dingus and Loope (2000) and Dingus &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (2008) suggest sudden burial by the collapsing dunes as discussed above. Jerzykiewicz &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (1993, Figure 12) illustrate a complete &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; skeleton in a near-standing position, as if it died while struggling to escape the surrounding sediment. Hone &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (2014) document several juvenile &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; that also represent death by burial in sand storms or dune collapses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most famous Djadochta Formation fossil is a specimen found by the Polish-Mongolian expedition of 1971. This amazing fossil is of a &lt;em&gt;Velociraptor&lt;/em&gt; associated, perhaps during interspecific combat, with a &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt;. This is illustrated in Jerzykiewicz &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (1993, Figure 11). Barsbold (2016) defends the idea that these dinosaurs were rapidly buried in the act of the &lt;em&gt;Velociraptor&lt;/em&gt; attacking the &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt;. While scenarios where the fighting dinosaurs were buried during a dune collapse or sandstorm seem plausible, sudden burial of both animals together underwater does not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-vertebrate-fossils&quot;&gt;Other Vertebrate Fossils&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides _Protoceratops, _there are numerous other dinosaurs and terrestrial vertebrates to be found in the Djadochta Formation (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Djadochta_Formation&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Djadochta_Formation&lt;/a&gt; for a list). Especially important non-dinosaur fossils are the Mesozoic mammals discussed in Kieran-Jaworowska (2013) and elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dinosaur-nests&quot;&gt;Dinosaur Nests&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the major discoveries of American Museum of Natural History’s Third Central Asiatic Expedition were the first recognized examples of dinosaur eggs and nests. These were first misinterpreted as being from the dinosaur &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt;, although the bones of another dinosaur were often found with the nests. This other dinosaur received the name &lt;em&gt;Oviraptor&lt;/em&gt; (egg thief) because of the association, in the mistaken interpretation that it was stealing and eating &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; eggs. It was not until discoveries by scientists working for the American Museum of Natural History in the 1990s that it was determined that these are oviraptor eggs and nests (for popular accounts, see: Clark,1995; Mikhailov, &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;., 1994; Zelenitsky, &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;., 2012); and a well-illustrated juvenile book by Norell and Dingus, 1999). Besides &lt;em&gt;Oviraptor&lt;/em&gt;, a more common oviraptoid named &lt;em&gt;Citipati&lt;/em&gt; is known from numerous Djadochta Formation specimens, including several that are fossilized brooding on their nests (see: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Citipati&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Citipati&lt;/a&gt;)). These are scientifically documented in Norell &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;., 1995; Clark, 1995; and Norell &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;., 2018. The most famous of these oviraptors of the genus &lt;em&gt;Citipai&lt;/em&gt; brooding on its nest is known as the “Big Mamma” specimen and is on display at the American Museum of Natural History (see: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Citipati#/media/File:Citipati_AMNH.jpg&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Citipati#/media/File:Citipati_AMNH.jpg&lt;/a&gt; for a copyright-free photograph). It is difficult to imagine how these oviraptors could have been building nests, laying eggs, then brooding over them in underwater sandslides, as the creationists are bizarrely suggesting. A terrestrial lifestyle and environment of deposition, whether burial in sandstorms or catastrophic collapse of eolian dunes, are reasonable explanations for these remarkable fossils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011, Fastovsky &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. described the first nest from the Djadochta Formation that is actually from &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt;. This nest contains hatchlings of 15 juvenile &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops. _These juveniles are no more than 20 cm long and are all approximately facing the same direction. An oval-shaped margin to one portion of the fossil suggests that this is a portion of a round or oval-shaped nest. The baby _Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt;, although tiny, are larger than would be expected from ones that had immediately hatched. This size, along with the lack of egg shells in the nest, suggest they stayed with the nest and were benefited by at least some level of parental care after hatching. The orientation of the juveniles suggests alignment with a sandstorm. This fossil is not consistent with underwater deposition in an underwater sand dune. Answers in Genesis is aware of this fossil, Mitchell, (No Date, possibly 2011) cites this nest as being evidence for Noah’s Flood, but seems oblivious to the fossil’s actual implications against Flood geology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;insect-borings&quot;&gt;Insect Borings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other taphonomic detail that is inconsistent with an underwater origin of Djadochta Formation dinosaur fossils is the presence of trace fossils consistent with large carrion-feeding insects found in and with the dinosaur skeletons. Kirkland and Bader (2010) and Saneyoshi &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (2011) illustrate and discuss many examples of &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; skeletons, as well as other dinosaur fossils, that have circular holes and damaged areas near their joints. Moreover, there are traces of insect pupation chambers associated with these skeletons. These traces are certainly the result of a large carrion-feeding insect, perhaps similar to modern dermestid beetles, but possibly from another unknown group of beetles. Adult insects would have detected the decaying dinosaurs, burrowed into the unlithified sediment, then fed on the carcasses, eating into the bones and consuming cartilage and any available soft tissue. At some point the insects would have mated and laid eggs within the carcass so their future larvae would have a food source. After feeding and eventually growing to adulthood inside pupae, these larvae would have burrowed to the surface to repeat the process. Duff, 2024 discusses similar, albeit less spectacular, trace fossils associated with Cretaceous dinosaur bones from Mexico described by Serrano-Brana &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (2018) at length as a “Flood geology failure.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saneyoshi &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. (2011) also describe a single, larger (31 mm diameter), burrow in a &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; skeleton that could be interpreted as a small mammal feeding trace. None of these insect burrows and damage to the bones make sense in terms of the deposits forming underwater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;discussion-and-conclusion&quot;&gt;Discussion and Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; display, and several other dinosaur-related displays already at the Creation Museum (see Phelps, 2007), perpetuate the odd creationist claims that their interpretation and conventional interpretations of geology and paleontology are the result of “worldviews.” AiG usually presents this as “God’s Word” versus “Human Reason.” Of course, “human reason” loses every time. This claim is part of what is known as “presuppositional apologetics” in Fundamentalist Christian circles. A typical example is this recent Tweet by Ken Ham (Ham, September 27, 2024) where he states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Did you know that creationists and evolutionists have the same facts? Christians and non-Christians have the same facts? The facts are not what people argue/debate over. It’s the interpretation of the facts that people argue about. And one’s worldview depends on the presuppositions they have. Ultimately, there are only two foundations our worldviews [sic.], God’s Word or man’s word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, and similar arguments for presuppositional apologetics, are often repeated in AiG’s vast output of materials, including this new &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; display. However, this is a rather shallow false equivalence by AiG. As this review of what paleontologists and geologists know about the dinosaur &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; and the rocks it was found in demonstrates, AiG only selectively looks at scientific evidence and often ignores a vast amount of contradictory evidence when comparing their Bible-based dogma to scientific evidence. AiG’s presuppositionalism requires that everything that contradicts their Biblical explanation is wrong and/or is to be ignored by definition (note AiG’s Statement of Faith, cited earlier). The resulting twists of logic from presuppositionsalism can be maddeningly insane. Consider this bizarre statement from 2007 on the AiG website (Answers in Genesis , 2007):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For a person to make the claim that humans and dinosaurs did not coexist, they would have to be able to see all history at exactly the same time, which would make that person omniscient and omnipresent, qualities of God. So, when someone says emphatically that humans and dinosaurs did not exist together in the past, that person is claiming to be a god, while calling God Himself a liar, or, at best, deceptive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, AiG literature usually insist that theirs is &lt;strong&gt;THE&lt;/strong&gt; Biblical worldview, when even the majority of their fellow Christians disagree. And this insistence ignores a vast spectrum of other religious and philosophical views. In some of the photographs on social media of the new &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; display, they show another adjacent display that is labeled “Most Reliable Dating Method.” This display is of a Bible open to the Book of Genesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a YouTube video, Snelling (2022), in an interview with AiG’s Simon Turpin, gives his game away by stating their work is really about religious conversion rather than science:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Andrew Snelling&lt;/strong&gt;: “…as I said to make sure that this is all freely is available to skeptics and you know arming all our people with the evidence. And of course there’ll be further articles in Answers Magazine, on our website, [and] live articles, because &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;we want to be able to explain all this in more lay terms so that the average person can be armed with this information to go out and use it as a witnessing tool&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; because, after all, Simon, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;you know it’s not about winning a scientific argument, you know, it’s about removing stumbling blocks that people raise to listening to the Gospel that people need to respond to. And you know we can argue about the scientific evidence until the cows come home, but the bottom line is you can convince people that there is a Flood, but unless you’re convinced that they need to respond to Jesus Christ as their Savior, they’ll go to Hell.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simon Turpin&lt;/strong&gt;: “Amen Andrew, we’re going to end in a minute.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;[&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Emphasis added by DP&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snelling comes clean by admitting that creationist “science” is all about religious conversion. Creationists reach their conclusions by ignoring large swaths of evidence that is contradictory to their dogma and sticking to predetermined conclusions, the evidence be damned. Actual science, in stark contrast, draws its interpretations from looking at multiple lines of evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;annotated-references-cited&quot;&gt;Annotated References Cited&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ahlbrandt, T., and S. Fryberger, 1982, Introduction to eolian deposits. pp. 11 - 47. &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; Schiller, P., and D. Spearing (eds.), &lt;em&gt;Sandstone Depositional Environments&lt;/em&gt;. American Association of Petroleum Geologists, Tulsa. [Well-illustrated discussion of dune deposits in the rock record.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrews, R. C., 1926, &lt;em&gt;On the Trail of Ancient Man&lt;/em&gt;. G. P. Putman’s Sons, New York.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrews, R. C., W. Granger, C. Pope, and N. Nelson, 1932, &lt;em&gt;The New Conquest of Central Asia: A Narrative of the Explorations of the Central Asiatic Expeditions in Mongolia and China, 1921 - 1930.&lt;/em&gt; Volume 1 of the Natural History of Central Asia. American Museum of Natural History, New York.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers in Genesis (blog post), 2007, An example of circular reasoning, part 3, fossils. [&lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/fossils/circular-reasoning/&quot;&gt;https://answersingenesis.org/fossils/circular-reasoning/&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers in Genesis (YouTube video), 2022 (viewed October, 2024), We had to fight hard to share this discovery with you! &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/live/NeeXMtbPtQE?si=tDwvK3QSKSE_0R5j&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/live/NeeXMtbPtQE?si=tDwvK3QSKSE_0R5j&lt;/a&gt; [YouTube video interview of Andrew Snelling discussing his Grand Canyon “research.” At about 53 minutes in, Snelling admits his work is about giving creationists witnessing tools rather than caring about science (see transcribed comments).]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barsbold, R., 1997, Mongolian Dinosaurs. &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; Currie, P., and K. Padian, (&lt;em&gt;eds&lt;/em&gt;.), &lt;em&gt;The Dinosaur Encyclopedia&lt;/em&gt;. Academic Press, San Diego. pp. 447 - 450.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barsbold, R., 2016,“The Fighting Dinosaurs”: The Position of Their Bodies before and after Death. Paleontological Journal, v. 50, n. 12, pp. 1412 - 1417.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benton, M., M. Shishkin, D. Unwin, and E. Kurochkin (eds.), 2000, &lt;em&gt;The Age of Dinosaurs in Russia and Mongolia&lt;/em&gt;. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bigarella, J., 1972, Eolian environments: their characteristics, recognition, and importance. &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; Rigby, J. and W. Hamblin (&lt;em&gt;eds&lt;/em&gt;.), &lt;em&gt;Recognition of Sedimentary Environments&lt;/em&gt;. Society of Economic Paleontologists and Mineralogists, Special Publication No. 18. [Older paper with many criteria for recognition of windblown sediments in the rock record.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blatt, H., W. Berry, and S. Brande, 1991, &lt;em&gt;Principles of Stratigraphic Analysis&lt;/em&gt;. Blackwell Scientific Publications, Boston. [Textbook with a short section on aeolian deposits.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carpenter, K., 1999, &lt;em&gt;Eggs, Nests, and Baby Dinosaurs, A Look at Dinosaur Reproduction&lt;/em&gt;, Indiana University Press, Bloomington. [Wonderful book with many photos of fossil dinosaur eggs and nests in Mongolia.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clark, J., 1995, An egg thief exonerated. Natural History, June 1995, pp. 56 - 57.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clark, J. A., 1999, An Oviraptoroid skeleton from the Late Cretaceous of Ukhaa Tolgod, Mongolia, preserved in an avian-like brooding position over an Oviraptoroid nest. American Museum Novitates 3269: 1 - 36. [Discussion of a remarkable Oviraptor sitting on its nest.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colbert, E.,1968, &lt;em&gt;Men and Dinosaurs: The Search in Field and Laboratory&lt;/em&gt;, Dutton, New York.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colbert, E., 2000, Asiatic dinosaur rush, &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; Benton, M.,M. Shishkin, D. Unwin, and E. Kurochkin (eds.), &lt;em&gt;The Age of Dinosaurs in Russia and Mongolia&lt;/em&gt;. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creation Museum (Blog post), May 24, 2024, New dinosaur exhibit coming to the Creation Museum. &lt;a href=&quot;https://creationmuseum.org/blog/2024/05/24/new-dinosaur-exhibit-coming-to-creation-museum/&quot;&gt;https://creationmuseum.org/blog/2024/05/24/new-dinosaur-exhibit-coming-to-creation-museum/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Davidson, G., J. Duff, D. Elliot, T. Helbe, C. Hill, S. Moshier, W. Ranney, R. Stearley, B. Tapp, R. Wiens, and K. Wolgemuth (editors), 2016, &lt;em&gt;The Grand Canyon, Monument to an Ancient Earth&lt;/em&gt;. Kregel Publications, Grand Rapids, Michigan. [Wonderful and well-illustrated introductory book refuting creationist attempts at geology with an emphasis on the Grand Canyon.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Davis, B., (ND),_ “ Billions of Dead Things_” audio sample clip of Davis’s song. &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/media/audio/audio-archives/billions-dead-things-sample/&quot;&gt;https://answersingenesis.org/media/audio/audio-archives/billions-dead-things-sample/&lt;/a&gt; . [Creationist country song based on repeating a Ken Ham cultish catchphrase multiple times.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dingus, L., and D. Loope, 2000, Death in the dunes: What killed the famous fossil creatures of the ancient Gobi? Geologists examine the rock-hard evidence. Natural History, v. 109, n. 6, pp. 50 - 55. [Popular summary of their research into sedimentology and depositional environment of the Djadokhta Formation.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dingus, L., D. Loope, D. Dashzeveg, C. Swisher, C. Minjin, M. Novacek, and M. Norell, 2008, The Geology of Ukhaa Tolgod (Djadokhta Formation, Upper Cretaceous, Nemegt Basin, Mongolia). American Museum of Natural History Novitates, n. 3616, p. 1 -40. [Lots of information about depositional environments with many color photos of outcrops and details.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dodson, P., 1996, &lt;em&gt;The Horned Dinosaurs.&lt;/em&gt; Princeton University Press, Princeton. [Good discussion of &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt;, including growth sequence from pp. 206 - 226.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Duff, J., viewed September, 2024, Flood geology failure: beetle bore holes in dinosaur bones. YouTube Video. &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/fFJxmegKoNE?si=j6C7HU-2O5BkhKF3&quot;&gt;https://youtu.be/fFJxmegKoNE?si=j6C7HU-2O5BkhKF3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fastovsky, D. E., D. Badamgarav, H., Ishimoto, M. Watabe, and D. Weishampel, 1997, The paleoenvironments of Tugrikin-Shireh (Gobi Desert, Mongolia) and aspects of the taphonomy and paleoecology of &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; (Dinosauria: Ornithischia). Palaios, v. 12: pp. 59 - 70. [One if the standard papers on the Taphonomy of _Protoceratops, _available at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/3515294&quot;&gt;https://www.jstor.org/stable/3515294&lt;/a&gt;.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fastovsky, D, and D. Weishampel, 2016, &lt;em&gt;Dinosaurs, A Concise Natural History.&lt;/em&gt; 3rd Edition. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge. [Advanced undergraduate textbook aimed at biology and geology majors. Well-illustrated. Includes a photo of a nest of Protoceratops hatchlings on p. 287.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fastovsky, D., D. Weishampel, M. Watabe, M. Barsbold, KH. Tsogtbaatar, and P. Narmandakh, 2011, A Nest of &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops andrewsi&lt;/em&gt;. Journal of Paleontology, v. 85, n. 6. pp. 1035 - 1041. [One of the few known Cretaceous nests from Mongolia that was certainly made by &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; (instead of Oviraptoroid dinosaurs). Nice photo of the nest. URL: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bioone.org/doi/full/10.1666/11-008.1&quot;&gt;http://www.bioone.org/doi/full/10.1666/11-008.1&lt;/a&gt;.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gallenkamp, C., 2001, &lt;em&gt;Dragon Hunter&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Roy Chapman Andrews and the Central Asiatic Expeditions&lt;/em&gt;. Viking Press, New York. [Succinct biography of R. C. Andrews, and a history of the geological/paleontological expeditions to the Gobi Desert in the 1920s.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Galloway, W., and D. Hobday, 1983, &lt;em&gt;Terrigenous Clastic Depositional Systems, Applications to Petroleum, Coal, and Uranium Exploration&lt;/em&gt;. Springer-Verlag, New York. [Chapter 10 discusses characteristics of eolian depositional environments and cites numerous articles in the scientific literature.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granger, W., and W. Gregory, 1923, &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops andrewsi&lt;/em&gt;, a pre-ceratopsian dinosaur from Mongolia. American Museum Novitates, v. 72, p. 1 - 9. [The original scientific description of &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops.&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ham, K. (AiG blog post), July 14, 2024, Exhibit update: most detailed &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; in the World. &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2024/07/14/most-detailed-protoceratops-world/&quot;&gt;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2024/07/14/most-detailed-protoceratops-world/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ham, K. (“X” Twitter post), September 27, 2024. Untitled. [Repeating of the “we have the same facts, but with a creationist worldview” trope].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ham, K. (“X” Twitter post), September 29, 2024, Untitled post on the new &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; display with photos of some of the exhibit’s text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hill, C., and S. Moshier, 2016, Sedimentary structures: clues from the scene of the crime. in Davidson, G., J. Duff, D. Elliot, T. Helbe, C. Hill, S. Moshier, W. Ranney, R. Stearley, B. Tapp, R. Wiens, and K. Wolgemuth (&lt;em&gt;eds&lt;/em&gt;.), 2016, &lt;em&gt;The Grand Canyon, Monument to an Ancient Earth&lt;/em&gt;. Kregel Publications, Grand Rapids, Michigan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hone, D., A. Farke, M. Watabe, S. Shigeru, and K. Tsogtbaatar, 2014, A new mass mortality of juvenile &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; and size-segregated aggregation behaviour in juvenile non-avian dinosaurs. PLOS One, November 26, 2014, pp. 1 - 26. [Available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4245121/&quot;&gt;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4245121/&lt;/a&gt;.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jerzykiewicz, T. D., 1997, The Djadokhta Formation, &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; Currie, P., and K. Padian, (&lt;em&gt;eds&lt;/em&gt;.), &lt;em&gt;The Dinosaur Encyclopedia&lt;/em&gt;. Academic Press, San Diego. pp. 188 - 190.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jerzykiewicz, T. D., 2000, Lithostratigraphy and sedimentary settings of the Cretaceous dinosaur beds of Mongolia. &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; Benton, M.,M. Shishkin, D. Unwin, and E. Kurochkin (eds.),&lt;em&gt;The Age of Dinosaurs in Russia and Mongolia&lt;/em&gt;. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jerzykiewicz, T., and D. Russell, 1991, Late Mesozoic stratigraphy and vertebrates of the Gobi Basin. Cretaceous Research, v. 12, pp. 345 - 377.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jezykiewicz, T., P. Currie, D. Eberth, P. Johnston, 1993, Djadokhta Formation correlative strata in Chinese Inner Mongolia: an overview of the stratigraphy, sedimentary geology, and paleontology and comparisons with the type locality in the pre-Altai Gobi. Canadian Journal of Earth Science, v. 30, pp. 2080 - 2195.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kieran-Jaworowska, Z., 2013, &lt;em&gt;In Pursuit of Early Mammals&lt;/em&gt;. Indiana University Press, Bloomington. [History of early mammal discoveries from Mongolia by a well-published Polish researcher.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kirkland, J., and K. Bader, 2010, Insect trace fossils associated with &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; carcasses in the Djadokhta Fomation (Upper Cretaceous) Mongolia. pp. 509 - 519, &lt;em&gt;in__New Perspectives on Horned Dinosaurs&lt;/em&gt;, Ryan, M., B. Chinnery-Allgeier, and D. Eberth (&lt;em&gt;eds&lt;/em&gt;.), Indiana University Press, Bloomington. [More examples of Protoceratops skeletons associated with burrows, borings, and egg cases of beetles, possibly large dermestids.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lang, V., 2024, Bringing bones to life. Answers News, v. 19, n. 4. [Available as a blog post at &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/answers/magazine/v19-n4/bringing-bones-life/&quot;&gt;https://answersingenesis.org/answers/magazine/v19-n4/bringing-bones-life/&lt;/a&gt;.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loope, D., L. Dingus, C. Swisher, and C. Minjin, 1998, Life and death in a Late Cretaceous dune field, Nemegt Basin, Mongolia. Geology, v. 26, n. 1, pp. 7 - 30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loope. D., J. Mason, and L. Dingus, 1999, Lethal sandslides from eolian dunes. The Journal of Geology, v. 107, pp. 707 - 713. [Slides of dunes during rainfall.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Makovicky, P., 2012, Marginocephalia. pp. 527 - 549., &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; Brett-Surman, M., T. Holtz, and J. Farlow (eds.), &lt;em&gt;The Complete Dinosaur&lt;/em&gt;, 2nd edition, Indiana University Press, Bloomington.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mikhailov, K., K. Sabath, S. Kurzanov, 1994, Eggs and nests from the Cretaceous of Mongolia. &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; Carpenter, K., Hirsch, and J. Horner (&lt;em&gt;eds&lt;/em&gt;.), _Dinosaur Eggs and Babies. _Cambridge University Press, Cambridge. [Great discussion and photos of various dinosaur eggs and nests.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mitchell, E., (No Date, possibly 2011), Group of Infant Dinosaurs Found in Fossilized Nest. Answers in Genesis “News to Know” blog post. &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/dinosaurs/bones/group-infant-dinosaurs-fossilized-nest/&quot;&gt;https://answersingenesis.org/dinosaurs/bones/group-infant-dinosaurs-fossilized-nest/&lt;/a&gt;. [Story about &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; nest with infants. Misrepresents fossil as buried in the Biblical Flood. Fastovsky &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;’s 2011 research is represented as somehow supporting this. Repeats myths about geologists claiming angle of repose always dipping 30 - 34 degrees in dune deposits.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Niedzwiedzki, G., T. Singer, G. Gierlinski, M. Lockley, 2012, A Protoceratopsid skeleton with an associated track from the Upper Cretaceous of Mongolia. Cretaceous Research, v. 33, pp. 7 - 10. [ A single track associated with articulated &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt; skeletons.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norell, M., J. Clark, L. Chiappe, and D. Dashzeveg, 1995, A nesting dinosaur. Nature, v. 378, pp. 774 -776. [An Oviraptoroid fossilized on its nest.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norell, M., A. Balanoff, and D. Barta, 2018, A second specimen of &lt;em&gt;Citipati osmolskae&lt;/em&gt; associated with a nest of eggs from Ukhaa Tolgod, Omnogov Aimag, Mongolia. American Museum Novitates, n. 3899, p. 1 - 44.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norell, M., and L. Dingus, 1999, &lt;em&gt;A Nest of Dinosaurs&lt;/em&gt;. Doubleday, New York.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Novacek, M., M. Norell, M. McKenna, and J. Clark, 1994, Fossils of the Flaming Cliffs. Scientific American, v. 271, n. 6, pp. 60 - 69.
Phelps, D., 2007, The Anti-Museum, an overview and review of the Answers in Genesis Creation “Museum.” NCSE website. [&lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/anti-museum&quot;&gt;https://ncse.ngo/anti-museum&lt;/a&gt;.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prothero, D., 2019, &lt;em&gt;The Story of Dinosaurs in 25 Discoveries&lt;/em&gt;. Columbia University Press, New York. [Several chapters discuss Mongolian dinosaurs, including &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops.&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reineck, H.-E., and I. Singh, 1980, &lt;em&gt;Depositional Sedimentary Environments&lt;/em&gt;. 2nd Revised and Updated Edition. Springer-Verlag, Berlin. [An extensive study of modern sedimentation and geological counterparts. Desert environments are discussed and illustrated on pp. 209 - 240.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russell, D. A., 2004, The Dinosaurian Setting of Primitive Asian Birds. pp. 15 - 34, &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; Currie, P., Koppelhus, E.,Shute, M., and Wright, J., (eds.),&lt;em&gt;Feathered Dragons, Studies on the Transition from Dinosaurs to Birds&lt;/em&gt;, Indiana University Press, Bloomington. [Discussion of the fauna and environments of the Cretaceous Djadokhta Formation of Mongolia.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saneyoshi, M., M. Watabe, S. Suzuki, and K. Tsogtbaatar, 2011, Trace fossils on dinosaur bones from Upper Cretaceous eolian deposits in Mongolia: taphonomic interpretation of paleoecosystems in ancient desert environments. Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology, v. 311, pp. 38 - 47. [Discussion of insect borings, burrows, and larvae pupae cases associated with Mongolian dinosaur fossils as well as a possible mammalian burrow.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serrano-Brana, B. Espinosa-Chavez, S. MacCracken, 2018, Insect damage in dinosaur bones from the Cerro del Pueblo Formation (Late Cretaceous, Campanian), Coahuila, Mexico. Journal of South American Earth Sciences, v. 16, pp. 353 - 365.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shuvalov, V., 2000, The Cretaceous stratigraphy and palaeobiogeography of Mongolia. &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; Benton, M.,M. Shishkin, D. Unwin, and E. Kurochkin (eds.), &lt;em&gt;The Age of Dinosaurs in Russia and Mongolia&lt;/em&gt;. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snelling, A., 1998, Waterborne gravity flows buried Mongolian dinosaurs. Creation &lt;em&gt;Ex Nihilo&lt;/em&gt; Technical Journal, v. 12, n. 2, pp. 133 - 134.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snelling, A., 2009, &lt;em&gt;Earth’s Catastrophic Past&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Volume 2&lt;/em&gt;., New Leaf Publishing and Answers in Genesis, Green Forest, Arkansas and Petersburg, Kentucky, [Discussion of the Djadokhta Formation on pp. 547- 549. Bizarre special pleading and leaves out important details. Available here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://lionandlambapologetics.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Earths-Catastrophic-Past_-Geology-Creation-and-the-Flood-Snelling.pdf&quot;&gt;https://lionandlambapologetics.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Earths-Catastrophic-Past_-Geology-Creation-and-the-Flood-Snelling.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sullivan, C., D. Hone, and Xing Xu, 2012, The search for dinosaurs in Asia. pp. 73 - 105, &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; Brett-Surman, M., T. Holtz, and J. Farlow (eds.), &lt;em&gt;The Complete Dinosaur&lt;/em&gt;, 2nd edition, Indiana University Press, Bloomington. [Extensive history of dinosaur research in Asia, including Mongolia, extensive references cited.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia, viewed October, 2024, &lt;em&gt;Citipati&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Citipati&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Citipati&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia, viewed October, 2024, Djadokhta Formation. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Djadochta_Formation&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Djadochta_Formation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia, viewed October, 2024, Fighting dinosaurs. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fighting_Dinosaurs&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fighting_Dinosaurs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia, viewed October, 2024, &lt;em&gt;Protoceratops&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protoceratops&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protoceratops&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia, viewed October, 2024, Protoceratopsidae. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protoceratopsidae&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protoceratopsidae&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zelenitsky, D., J. Horner, and F. Therrien, 2012, Dinosaur Eggs. pp. 613 - 620, &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; Brett-Surman, M., T. Holtz, and J. Farlow (eds.), &lt;em&gt;The Complete Dinosaur&lt;/em&gt;, 2nd edition, Indiana University Press, Bloomington.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Daniel Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Figure 1. Protoceratops display, comparing &quot;evolutionist&quot; versus creationist explanations of fossilization. From Ken Ham’s blog. Fair use. &amp;nbsp; Since at least May, 2024, the Creation Museum and Ken Ham have been discussing a new display, meant to describe the dinosaur Protoceratops being drowned in the Biblical Flood of Noah (see for example https://creationmuseum.org/blog/2024/05/24/new-dinosaur-exhibit-coming-to-creation-museum/ and https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2024/07/14/most-detailed-protoceratops-world/). This display finally opened in late October, 2024. Figure 1 is this ridiculous display from Ken Ham’s blog. Pictures of the display are available on several Answers in Genesis’ and Ken Ham’s social media pages. Long (2024) describes the artwork going into this new display. Although the artwork depicting the dinosaur itself is excellent, the display has absurd, inaccurate, misleading, and dishonest information on the depositional environment of the surrounding sediment and the taphonomy of Protoceratops and other Cretaceous vertebrate fossils of Mongolia. The Creation Museum and Ark Encounter, both owned by the Young Earth Creationistministry Answers in Genesis (AiG), espouse that the fossil record is a result of Noah’s Flood which occurred in 2348 BC. All employees of AiG must sign off on a “Statement of Faith” (https://answersingenesis.org/about/faith/), that states in part: The great flood of Genesis was an actual historic event, worldwide (global) in its extent and catastrophic in its effects. At one stage during the flood, the waters covered the entire surface of the whole globe with no land surface being exposed anywhere—the flood of Noah is not to be understood as any form of local or regional flood. The Noachian flood was a significant geological event, and most fossiliferous sediments were deposited at that time (Genesis 7:19–20; 2 Peter 3:5–7). And further: No apparent, perceived, or claimed evidence in any field of study, including science, history, and chronology, can be valid if it contradicts the clear teaching of Scripture obtained by historical-grammatical interpretation. Of primary importance is the fact that evidence is always subject to interpretation by fallible people who do not possess all information (Numbers 23:19; 2 Samuel 22:31; Psalm 18:30; Isaiah 46:9–10, 55:9; Romans 3:4; 2 Timothy 3:16). Of course this ends any attempt at science by AiG employees and replaces geology, paleontology, and all other science and history with unchanging religious dogma. Because of their weird dogma, AiG has an unusual take on dinosaurs and other prehistoric life forms. Both the Ark and Creation Museum have problematic displays on dinosaurs. In dioramas, dinosaurs are depicted as living with people, among ancient buildings, in stalls on Noah’s Ark, and most amazingly, fighting with humans and giants in a pre-Flood arena of death (see Figure 3 below). The Creation Museum has a actual skeleton of the dinosaur Allosaurus on display that was donated by white nationalist and neo-Confederate Michael Peroutka (see: https://rightingamerica.net/dinosaur-bones-mark-meadows-neo-confederates-and-the-tawdry-world-of-young-earth-creationism/). This Allosaurus skeleton is depicted as drowning in Noah’s Flood in 2348 BC.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Steatoda triangulosa</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/10/steatoda-triangulosa.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Steatoda triangulosa" /><published>2024-10-28T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-28T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/10/steatoda-triangulosa</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/10/steatoda-triangulosa.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/DSC05741_Spider_Beetle_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Triangular cobweb spider with assassin bug&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, someone pen-named &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ululodes&quot;&gt;Ulolodes&lt;/a&gt;, which I now know is a genus of owl fly, requested more spider pictures. I do not have a whole lot, but here is a snapshot I took this summer of a spider, which I think is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triangulate_cobweb_spider&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Steatoda triangulosa&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – triangular cobweb spider – dining on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reduvius_personatus&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Reduvius personatus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – assassin bug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Two weeks ago, someone pen-named Ulolodes, which I now know is a genus of owl fly, requested more spider pictures. I do not have a whole lot, but here is a snapshot I took this summer of a spider, which I think is Steatoda triangulosa – triangular cobweb spider – dining on Reduvius personatus – assassin bug. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ken Ham's The Lie: What's new (plenty) in the 2024 version</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/10/ken-hams-the-lie.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ken Ham's The Lie: What's new (plenty) in the 2024 version" /><published>2024-10-21T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-21T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/10/ken-hams-the-lie</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/10/ken-hams-the-lie.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Braterman_Lie_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The following is a review of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Lie-Unraveling-Evolution-Millions-Years-ebook/dp/B0DD4YLQRQ/&quot;&gt;The Lie&lt;/a&gt;, by Ken Ham (Master Book, 2024), and a comparison of the 1987, 2012, and 2024 editions. A longer article appeared &lt;a href=&quot;https://3quarksdaily.com/3quarksdaily/2024/10/reviewed-ken-hams-the-lie-unravelling-the-myth-of-evolution-millions-of-years-and-why-we-need-to-pay-attention.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; in 3 Quarks Daily.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me first remind you of the scale of Ken Ham’s political significance. He has among his friends Mike Johnson, Speaker of the US House of Representatives, whose law firm has represented AiG pro bono. And among the contributors to its magazine is Calvin Beisner, director of the Cornwall Alliance, whose entire purpose is to deny the importance of human-caused climate change. Cornwall in turn has direct links to the Heartland Institute and to the Heritage Foundation, authors of Project 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Readers here will be familiar with the destructive and anti-scientific approach of the modern creationist movement in the US. But that’s only half the story. It is not only about the beginning of the world, but about its ending. Genesis is pivotal, but so is Revelation. So are the many hints of the end of the world that are explicit in the New Testament, and can be discovered with sufficient ingenuity in the Old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such thinking underlines the apocalyptic tone, repeatedly echoed in AiG’s material, that underlies current US right-wing politics. If the Earth does not have a deep past, we cannot expect it to have a prolonged future. We should not be concerning ourselves with conservation, but with righteousness. This perspective has political implications, and comparing the 1987 and 2024 versions of &lt;i&gt;The Lie&lt;/i&gt; shows the political aspect becoming increasingly explicit. Otherwise, there is not much difference between the two editions, though The third edition is more repetitious and, where direct comparison is possible, less vigorous in its use of language, and more hectoring, than the original.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-right-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 40px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Braterman_Lie_Bible Mod Sci_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bible and Modern Science cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Cover of an earlier book, &lt;i&gt;The Bible and Modern Science&lt;/i&gt;, by Henry Morris.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A decade before &lt;i&gt;The Genesis Flood&lt;/i&gt;, Henry Morris had written a much shorter book, &lt;i&gt;The Bible and Modern Science&lt;/i&gt;, whose final chapter is devoted to claims that biblical prophecies are being fulfilled in our own times, and are signs of Christ’s imminent return. Prominent among these is the return of Jews to their ancestral homeland. Similar thinking explains why US fundamentalist evangelicals are now among Israel’s most unquestioning supporters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have recently reviewed at length the 1987 (1st ed.) and 2024 (3rd ed.) versions of &lt;i&gt;The Lie&lt;/i&gt;, and the differences between them. Here I will use material from that review to comment on some of the most extraordinary aspects of the work, draw attention to the narrowness of Ham’s portrayal of Christianity, and discuss the changes between the two editions. 

Ham himself  tells us that it was &lt;i&gt;The Lie&lt;/i&gt; that positioned Answers in Genesis as a biblical authority ministry. That’s not true. When it was published in 1987, Ham was still an employee of Morris’ Institute for Creation Research, while his own organization was not incorporated until 1993, amid much unseemly and litigious infighting, and its title, Answers in Genesis, only dates from 1994.
  
Ham’s approach is unsubtle, uncompromising, and unburdened with excess erudition. It is also completely devoid of originality, since all the ideas he expresses are already there in the writings of Henry Morris and his precursors. The book describes itself as concerned with “the foundational nature of the book of Genesis to all Christian doctrine.” By “the book of Genesis,” Ham means a plain literal meaning, with a 6-day 24-hour creation, ignoring two millennia of exegesis and two centuries of literary and archaeological scholarship, and reducing the beautiful, complex, many-layered text to a cardboard cutout.

The title of the first chapter tells us that “Christianity is Under Attack,” or, in the third edition, “Under Massive Attack.” Modern society has moved away from Christ, but the book promises to outline “a Biblical (and therefore successful)” approach.

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Braterman_Lie_Seven Cs_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Seven C's of Ken Ham&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Seven C's of Ken Ham. &lt;small&gt;3rd ed., p. 58, fair use.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt; 

The third edition takes the opportunity to claim victimhood for Christianity, and to attack an unspecified secular wokeness, signaling the book’s political tendency. It then shows the attached figure listing what it regards as our contemporary ills, all caused by a falling away from Ham’s version of Christianity.

This is an extraordinary list. Something very strange is happening when those who call themselves followers of Christ object to the idea of social justice. Of the 16 items on this list, seven (CRT, Inclusion, Identity Politics, Social Justice, Mandates, Intersectionality, and Woke) express political views, with some of which one might have expected a follower of Jesus to sympathise, and none bear any relationship to the book’s ostensive agenda.

It gets worse. The third edition at this point questions the concept of separation of church and state, asserts that the public education system is not neutral, since it teaches naturalistic explanations, quotes Matthew 12:30 that one is either for Christ or against him, and says that

&lt;blockquote&gt;To help parents understand the reality of the situation, I suggest we say “anti-God schools” instead of public (secular) schools to remind us of what these institutions really are.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Since the public school system teaches naturalistic explanation, says Ham, it is indoctrinating into a religion of atheism, thus undermining Christianity and Christian morality

Here we have the reason for creationist advocacy of voucher schemes, designed to use public funds for children to be educated at creationist schools, and for homeschooling. The upsurge in political support for voucher schemes, which incidentally starves the public sector of funds, is now a major problem; see, e.g., here.

The discussion of sexual behavior, especially homosexuality, is a fine example of Ham’s reasoning: We know that homosexuality is wrong because homosexuality is condemned in numerous Bible verses. But without the Bible, we would not have convincing reason for calling it wrong, although it clearly is. Thus homosexuality is wrong because the Bible says so, and the Bible’s condemnation of homosexuality confirms that biblical morality is correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ham uses the familiar creationist argument that the study of the past, as in evolution science, is not science at all. For science involves repeatable observations, and the past is unrepeatable. He boasts of how he used this argument, in his school-teaching days, to undermine his colleagues’ teaching. It is also very attractive argument, since those who accept it believe that they have been granted a superior insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, The third edition tells us that
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the Creation Museum, we summarize biblical history as the Seven C’s of History — Creation, Corruption, Catastrophe, Confusion, Christ, Cross, and Consummation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Susan and William Trollinger point out in their book about the Museum, these 7 C’s are strongly reminiscent of the 7 D’s of dispensationalism, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Premillennialism&quot;&gt;premillennialist&lt;/a&gt; interpretation of history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ham appears completely oblivious of the fact that his own interpretation of Genesis is heavily laden with assumptions. Or if he is, he no doubt attributes them to the operation within him of the Holy Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ham argues that Christians who accept the findings of secular science are being inconsistent. If they choose to accept millions of years, they have succumbed to the disease of naturalism, of which evolutionism is merely a symptom. And naturalism is itself a religion, since by denying God’s role it is a form of atheism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this in the book’s first chapter. The remaining 150 pages add little new, and I will content myself with a few significant points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 3, “Creationism is Religion,” tells us that the Creation took place in six days, and God called it “very good.” It follows that there was no death, all animals were vegetarians, the climate was mild from pole to pole, and there was no bad weather. However, this Edenic state of affairs did not last. Why not?
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because our first parents placed human opinion above God’s word (as we continue to do), struggle and death entered the world and God cursed the creation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wickedness of later generations brought on Flood, and the billions of fossils laid down the Flood sediments (all sediments, we take it, are Flood sediments) remind us of “God’s judgment on sin.” Nonetheless, after the Flood the earth once again became filled with corruption because of human sin. Christ’s death and resurrection conquered death, and through Him we may be born into eternal life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thus as surely as God created the world and judged the world with the Flood, our ungodly world will be destroyed by fire. For those who trust in Jesus, however, there awaits eternal life in the new heavens and new earth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note again the linking of the judgement of the Flood to the coming judgement of fire. This theme is developed further in the concluding chapter, as discussed below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third edition covers the same ground in greater detail, once again invoking the 7 C’s, and presenting Ham’s creative reinterpretations of specific verses as if they were God-given.&lt;sup&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the core of Christianity, as represented by Answers in Genesis, and the movement of which it is part. It is a curious form of Christianity, reducing it almost to a commercial transaction. What you have to do, is trust in Jesus. And He in return will give you eternal life, after this world has been destroyed. Nothing here about love your enemies, turn the other cheek, blessed are the peacemakers, who is my neighbor, I was hungry and you fed me not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A computer scan of the third edition shows 180 references to sin, and just 35 references to love, of which only 8 refer to love between human beings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 4, “The Root of the Problem,” accuses evolution of providing justification for rebellion against God. Moreover, 
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;All the evolutionists have to do is to come up with one piece of evidence that conclusively proves evolution &lt;/i&gt;[emphasis in original]. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I come across this kind of assertion all the time in social media. It is difficult to know how to deal with an argument so confidently presented while being totally at variance with reality (right now, the problem also arises in areas other than evolution). The evidence for the historical fact of evolution was conclusive, by all reasonable standards, over a century ago. Moreover, the time interval between the 1987 and 2024 editions of the book have produced further layers of evidence, based on DNA relationships. The creationist organizations themselves are well aware of these developments. However, as I mentioned earlier, Ham has set up his rules of evidence in advance, in such a way as to be free to ignore them. We see here the rhetorical device of &lt;i&gt;demanding the impossible&lt;/i&gt;. Ham is asking for proof, but has already stated that the relevant evidence is unacceptable. He then uses the absence of proof that he would regard as acceptable, as conclusive evidence that his opponents are arguing in bad faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 5 gives a few other examples of what Ham claims, to my mind completely falsely, to be biblical teaching. For example, Genesis gives us the doctrine of marriage as the union between one man and one woman for life. I am reduced to wondering whether Ham has actually &lt;i&gt;read&lt;/i&gt; Genesis. For if he did, what he would find there is arranged marriage to preserve the bloodline, fathers selling their daughters, concubinage, polygamy, women procuring their slavegirls as breeding stock for their husbands, and levirate marriage, whose purpose is to provide a dead man with an heir.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also says that the Bible tells us that from the point of conception (in the 2024 edition, of course, this becomes the point of fertilization), we are human beings, so that abortion in all instances is killing a human being. Yet the Bible chapters that he himself cites (Psalm 139, Jeremiah 1) speak of the child &lt;i&gt;being formed&lt;/i&gt; in the womb; the very opposite of what he tells us. He objects to women pastors, because (no verse cited) God created men and women for separate roles. There are also vague references, again with no verse cited, to the process of appointing deacons, and strict discipline (I think he means spanking) for children. Ham’s version of biblical Christianity is shot through with such nonbiblical opinions, in all their lamentable fallibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Chapter 6, a great deal is said of the need for clothes, in order to curb sexual arousal, and about humanity’s inherently sinful nature. As further evidence of the growing politicization of AiG, the third edition goes out of its way at this point to mention President Obama’s and President Biden’s support for gay marriage. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 7 tells us that 
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;All who believe in Jesus Christ as Lord and Savior are received back to God to spend eternity with Him. Isn’t that a wonderful message? &lt;i&gt;That is the message of Christianity&lt;/i&gt; [emphasis in original].&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are of course, as I mentioned earlier, other aspects to Christianity, such as loving your neighbor, but the book seems strangely unaware of these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 8 tells us of The Evils of Evolution, which as we have seen include lawlessness, homosexuality, and abortion. 
&lt;p&gt;The third edition now goes out of its way to mention Planned Parenthood, which it describes as “one of the biggest child-killing ‘machines’ in the world,” and mentions in linked paragraphs that its founder, Margaret Sanger, was a fervent eugenicist, and that she promoted the use of birth control. As we have seen, the changes between the first edition and The third edition tells us very plainly how AiG is developing politically, and we must take the reference to birth control very seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, with no sense of irony, Ham tells us in successive paragraphs that evolutionary thinking has been used to defend male chauvinism, and that Christian women should not be deceived by the feminist movement, which is anti-God, since God has given men and women different roles. The third edition even warns us of the danger that “women will abuse their role and want to usurp the authority of the man in regard to headship.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He then summarizes his arguments to date by a cartoon showing two opposing castles. The castle of Christianity is wasting its ammunition by firing at specific targets, while evolution, guided by Satan, attacks the Christian doctrine of creation. Such at least is what we see in the 1987 version of the cartoon, which has been discussed here before. It is one of many such drawings scattered throughout the book, which do have a certain faux naïve charm. The 2024 version, by contrast, looks so bad that I wonder whether it is AI-generated. But notice the reference in the later version to Revelation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Braterman_Lie_Castles_old_600.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100px&quot; alt=&quot;[Old castles figure]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Warring Castles. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;1st ed., p.92, fair use.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Braterman_Lie_Castles_new_600.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100px&quot; alt=&quot;[New castles figure, in color]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Warring Castles, new figure, in color. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;3rd ed. p. 178, fair use.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

Chapter 10, Wake Up, Shepherds! repeats the message that the only sound preaching is based on one particular interpretation of Genesis. Both editions go out of their way to attack and belittle Darwin, as is usual, but the third edition adds a remark so outrageous, that I cannot forbear from comment:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Since the time of Darwin, much research has shown that observational science (e.g., the study of genetics) does not confirm Darwin’s ideas but actually contradicts them.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Ham taught biology, and environmental biology was his degree major. He graduated in the early 1970's, and it is difficult to believe that he was unaware of the way in which the coming together of Mendelian genetics, classical paleontology, and the solving of the genetic code were placing evolution science on an ever-firmer foundation.

Chapter 11, Creation, Flood, and Coming Fire, concludes the book’s central argument by linking the creation of this world to its imminent destruction. It starts with a quotation also used by Henry Morris in his 1951 book, &lt;i&gt;The Bible and Modern Science&lt;/i&gt;, and again in &lt;i&gt;The Genesis Flood&lt;/i&gt;. Ham devotes particular attention to this passage, and so should we:
&lt;blockquote&gt;There is a prophecy in II Peter concerning the last days of this earth’s history, and it very much relates to the whole creation/evolution issue:
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
  
II Peter 3:3-7 (NIV) states: “First of all, you must understand that in the last days scoffers welcome, scoffing and following their own evil desires. They will say, ‘Where is this coming He promised? Ever since our fathers died, everything goes on as it has since the beginning of creation.’ But they deliberately forget that long ago by God’s Word the heavens existed and the earth was formed out of water with water. By water also the world of that time was deluged and destroyed. By the same word the present heavens and earth are reserved for fire, being kept for the day of judgment and destruction of ungodly men.”
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

We see this prophecy being fulfilled in front of our own eyes. The people who tell us that “everything goes on as it has since the beginning of creation” are the evolutionists and deep time geologists. They use the principle that “the present is key to the past,” and invoke the observed present-day processes of sedimentation and mutation in their discussions of geology and evolution.
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

In this, they are “willingly ignorant.” They have deliberately chosen not to believe in the Genesis account of creation, God’s judgement of the world at the time of Noah’s Flood, and coming judgment by fire. If they do not think that the geological record is convincing evidence of the Flood, that is because they do not want to be convinced. And the reason why they do not want to be convinced is that they do not wish to acknowledge God’s authority, obey His rules, and stand in awe of the coming judgment by fire. The very fact that the Biblical account is being questioned is itself a fulfilment of Biblical prophecy, confirming (as if confirmation were required) that the Bible account is true.
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

The sun, moon, and stars are evidence of God’s creation. The sediments are evidence of God’s judgment in the Flood, and Last Day’s prophecies are being fulfilled before our eyes. And, just in case we haven’t got the point, a final quotation in bold from II Peter 3:11-12a:

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;Since everything will be destroyed in this way, what kind of people ought you to be? You ought to live holy and godly lives as you look forward to the day of God and speed its coming &lt;/i&gt;[emphasis in original].&lt;/blockquote&gt;

How we are supposed to speed its coming, it may be wiser not to inquire.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;i&gt;A longer version of this post has appeared on 3 Quarks Daily.&lt;/i&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

Footnote:
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

1. Ham repeatedly imposes his theologically motivated interpretation on the text. For those interested in exegesis, I pedantically present a couple of examples from the third edition, where we are given, in successive paragraphs without explanation,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The very first time the gospel is preached is in Genesis 3:15:
  
&lt;i&gt;And I will put enmity between you and the woman, And between your seed and her Seed; He shall bruise your head, And you shall bruise His heel &lt;/i&gt;[emphasis in original].&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The set up of the sacrificial system and a picture of what was to come in Jesus’ sacrifice on the Cross is found in Genesis 3:21:

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;Also for Adam and his wife the Lord God made tunics of skin, and clothed them &lt;/i&gt;[emphasis in original].&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Ham is imposing, and is expecting his readers to impose, meanings imported from commentaries. In verse 3:15, the serpent has been equated with Satan, the woman’s seed with Jesus, the bruising of the heel refers to Jesus’s suffering in His human aspect, and the bruising of the head is Jesus’ triumph over Satan. The capital H’s correspond to nothing in the Hebrew text, but are inserted because Ham thinks the pronouns refer to Christ. In 3:21, tunics of skin imply that an animal has been killed for the purpose, and for reasons I do not quite understand this is a foreshadowing of the Crucifixion.

If you regard all this as contorted and arbitrary, I quite agree. Or you may regard it as serious exegesis, some at least of which goes back to the Church Fathers. But whatever your opinion, the point is that this is material added to the text, not found within it, and therefore, by Ham’s own criteria, part of man’s thoughts, here misrepresented as God’s.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman</name></author><summary type="html">The following is a review of The Lie, by Ken Ham (Master Book, 2024), and a comparison of the 1987, 2012, and 2024 editions. A longer article appeared here in 3 Quarks Daily. Let me first remind you of the scale of Ken Ham’s political significance. He has among his friends Mike Johnson, Speaker of the US House of Representatives, whose law firm has represented AiG pro bono. And among the contributors to its magazine is Calvin Beisner, director of the Cornwall Alliance, whose entire purpose is to deny the importance of human-caused climate change. Cornwall in turn has direct links to the Heartland Institute and to the Heritage Foundation, authors of Project 2025. Readers here will be familiar with the destructive and anti-scientific approach of the modern creationist movement in the US. But that’s only half the story. It is not only about the beginning of the world, but about its ending. Genesis is pivotal, but so is Revelation. So are the many hints of the end of the world that are explicit in the New Testament, and can be discovered with sufficient ingenuity in the Old. Such thinking underlines the apocalyptic tone, repeatedly echoed in AiG’s material, that underlies current US right-wing politics. If the Earth does not have a deep past, we cannot expect it to have a prolonged future. We should not be concerning ourselves with conservation, but with righteousness. This perspective has political implications, and comparing the 1987 and 2024 versions of The Lie shows the political aspect becoming increasingly explicit. Otherwise, there is not much difference between the two editions, though The third edition is more repetitious and, where direct comparison is possible, less vigorous in its use of language, and more hectoring, than the original.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gnaphosidae</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/10/gnaphosidae.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gnaphosidae" /><published>2024-10-14T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-14T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/10/gnaphosidae</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/10/gnaphosidae.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/DSC05853_Ground_Spider_Gnaphosidae_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ground spider&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ground_spider&quot;&gt;Gnaphosidae&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; ground spider, Boulder, Colorado, July, 2024. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this spider trapped in a porcelain sink from which it could not climb out, so I naturally snapped a few pictures. The people at &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugguide.net&quot;&gt;Bugguide&lt;/a&gt; classified it as a member of the family Gnaphosidae. They warned me that Google Lens is not good at spiders, but, just for fun, I asked. Among the first hits was my very own picture of this very spider &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugguide.net/node/view/2379696&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Gnaphosidae &amp;ndash; ground spider, Boulder, Colorado, July, 2024. I found this spider trapped in a porcelain sink from which it could not climb out, so I naturally snapped a few pictures. The people at Bugguide classified it as a member of the family Gnaphosidae. They warned me that Google Lens is not good at spiders, but, just for fun, I asked. Among the first hits was my very own picture of this very spider here. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cheiracanthium sp</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/cheiracanthium-sp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cheiracanthium sp" /><published>2024-09-30T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-30T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/cheiracanthium-sp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/cheiracanthium-sp.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/DSC05926_Spider_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Yellow sac spider&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheiracanthium&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;Cheiracanthium&lt;/i&gt; sp. &amp;ndash; yellow sac spider, Boulder, Colorado, September, 2024.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this spider inside the house the other day and managed to get a picture showing the 8 eyes. In case you were wondering &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/What_Is_It_Like_to_Be_a_Bat%3F&quot;&gt; what it is like to be a bat&lt;/a&gt;, think about what it must be like to be a spider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spiders have simple eyes, as opposed to compound eyes like those of a dragonfly. Because the eyes are so small, they cannot have good resolution: Even if the eyes were diffraction-limited, their sensors would have to be roughly the same size as the cones in human eyes, for example, and there would be many fewer of them. (In photographic terms, all diffraction-limited F/4 lenses have the same resolution limit, but a longer focal-length lens affords more detail. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.phys.ufl.edu/courses/phy3221/spring10/HaldaneRightSize.pdf&quot;&gt;This paper&lt;/a&gt; by Haldane notes that an eye is not very good until it reaches a certain size, but a colleague of mine has just pointed out that context matters and the spider does not need a better eye.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Wikipedia entry on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spider_vision&quot;&gt;spider vision &lt;/a&gt;, the two central eyes in the lower bank are the &lt;i&gt;principal eyes&lt;/i&gt;, and they do their best to form an image, but the pixels (if you will) are nowhere near the focal point. The spider is thus dreadfully nearsighted, though he must get some imaging due to the depth of field. The other, &lt;i&gt;secondary&lt;/i&gt; eyes are used for light and motion detection, and, for example, polarization detection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Cheiracanthium sp. &amp;ndash; yellow sac spider, Boulder, Colorado, September, 2024. I found this spider inside the house the other day and managed to get a picture showing the 8 eyes. In case you were wondering what it is like to be a bat, think about what it must be like to be a spider. Spiders have simple eyes, as opposed to compound eyes like those of a dragonfly. Because the eyes are so small, they cannot have good resolution: Even if the eyes were diffraction-limited, their sensors would have to be roughly the same size as the cones in human eyes, for example, and there would be many fewer of them. (In photographic terms, all diffraction-limited F/4 lenses have the same resolution limit, but a longer focal-length lens affords more detail. This paper by Haldane notes that an eye is not very good until it reaches a certain size, but a colleague of mine has just pointed out that context matters and the spider does not need a better eye.) According to the Wikipedia entry on spider vision , the two central eyes in the lower bank are the principal eyes, and they do their best to form an image, but the pixels (if you will) are nowhere near the focal point. The spider is thus dreadfully nearsighted, though he must get some imaging due to the depth of field. The other, secondary eyes are used for light and motion detection, and, for example, polarization detection. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry></feed>