<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-04-13T07:08:06-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Scientists fear deportation, withdraw paper on evolution</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/04/scientists-fear-deportation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scientists fear deportation, withdraw paper on evolution" /><published>2025-04-12T13:15:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-04-12T13:15:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/04/-scientists-fear-deportation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/04/scientists-fear-deportation.html">&lt;p&gt;A colleague just alerted us to an article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/science/2025/04/10/evolution-research-deportation-fears/&quot;&gt;Fearing paper on evolution might get them deported, scientists withdrew it&lt;/a&gt;, in the April 10 edition of the Washington Post. According to Mark Johnson, the author of the Post article, the paper “described ways in which evolution unfolds in both living and nonliving systems, a subject relevant to the search for life elsewhere in the universe.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael L. Wong, an astrobiologist and the editor of the paper, confirmed that the paper had been withdrawn because two of the authors who are based in the United States feared retaliation, including possibly deportation. Dr. Wong told the Post,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;“I was so looking forward to reading this paper because I think the ideas in it are potentially transformative,” Wong said. “But the fact that people, scientific researchers, are afraid of just engaging in normal scientific discourse, putting their well thought out ideas into the public sphere so that everybody can see them, read them, come to their own conclusions about them and then debate them ― it is so disheartening.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I suggested in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/04/century-after-scopes.html&quot;&gt;earlier article&lt;/a&gt;, quoting &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/a-century-after-scopes-much-has-not-changed-and-much-has-changed/&quot;&gt;the Righting America blog&lt;/a&gt;, this is where we are, 100 years after the Scopes trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">A colleague just alerted us to an article, Fearing paper on evolution might get them deported, scientists withdrew it, in the April 10 edition of the Washington Post. According to Mark Johnson, the author of the Post article, the paper “described ways in which evolution unfolds in both living and nonliving systems, a subject relevant to the search for life elsewhere in the universe.” Michael L. Wong, an astrobiologist and the editor of the paper, confirmed that the paper had been withdrawn because two of the authors who are based in the United States feared retaliation, including possibly deportation. Dr. Wong told the Post, “I was so looking forward to reading this paper because I think the ideas in it are potentially transformative,” Wong said. “But the fact that people, scientific researchers, are afraid of just engaging in normal scientific discourse, putting their well thought out ideas into the public sphere so that everybody can see them, read them, come to their own conclusions about them and then debate them ― it is so disheartening.” As I suggested in an earlier article, quoting the Righting America blog, this is where we are, 100 years after the Scopes trial. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Century after Scopes, according to Righting America</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/04/century-after-scopes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Century after Scopes, according to Righting America" /><published>2025-04-09T09:15:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-04-09T09:15:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/04/century-after-scopes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/04/century-after-scopes.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/John_Scopes_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;John Scopes&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:John_t_scopes.jpg&quot;&gt;John Scopes&lt;/a&gt;, taken one month before the Tennessee v. John T. Scopes trial. &lt;small&gt;From the Smithsonian Institution Archives. Rotated, cropped, and cleaned by Kaldari. Photographed by Watson Davis. Public domain.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to a recent blog post by Susan Trollinger and William Trollinger, &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/a-century-after-scopes-much-has-not-changed-and-much-has-changed/&quot;&gt;A Century After Scopes: Much Has Not Changed, and Much Has Changed&lt;/a&gt;. I was most interested in their observation that William’s father was a fundamentalist who passionately opposed evolution. But he was also a geologist who searched for oil, believed in an “old earth,” and subscribed to what is known as “day-age theory,” that is, the belief that the “days” in Genesis are not literal, 24-hour days, but rather represent ages. Thus, at the time of the Scopes trial, creationism realistically accepted the vast age of the earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, thanks primarily to Henry Morris, creationists do not accept an old earth and consequently are forced to deny, for example, geological science. Ultimately, they undermine virtually all of science and, according to Trollinger and Trollinger, promote an alternative education system which is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;margin-left: 15px;&quot;&gt;&quot;not just about getting creationism, the Bible, and white Christian nationalism into the public schools. It is also about funding private schools, including fundamentalist schools. It is about expanding the right-wing subculture. It is about taking dominion over the culture.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, they say, is where we are 100 years after the Scopes trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">John Scopes, taken one month before the Tennessee v. John T. Scopes trial. From the Smithsonian Institution Archives. Rotated, cropped, and cleaned by Kaldari. Photographed by Watson Davis. Public domain. According to a recent blog post by Susan Trollinger and William Trollinger, A Century After Scopes: Much Has Not Changed, and Much Has Changed. I was most interested in their observation that William’s father was a fundamentalist who passionately opposed evolution. But he was also a geologist who searched for oil, believed in an “old earth,” and subscribed to what is known as “day-age theory,” that is, the belief that the “days” in Genesis are not literal, 24-hour days, but rather represent ages. Thus, at the time of the Scopes trial, creationism realistically accepted the vast age of the earth. Today, thanks primarily to Henry Morris, creationists do not accept an old earth and consequently are forced to deny, for example, geological science. Ultimately, they undermine virtually all of science and, according to Trollinger and Trollinger, promote an alternative education system which is &quot;not just about getting creationism, the Bible, and white Christian nationalism into the public schools. It is also about funding private schools, including fundamentalist schools. It is about expanding the right-wing subculture. It is about taking dominion over the culture.&quot; This, they say, is where we are 100 years after the Scopes trial. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nephrotoma ferruginea</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/nephrotoma-ferruginea.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nephrotoma ferruginea" /><published>2025-03-31T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-31T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/nephrotoma%20ferruginea</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/nephrotoma-ferruginea.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Ole Lundin&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/lundin_Crane_Fly.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Crane fly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bugguide.net/node/view/11595&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Nephrotoma ferruginea&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; ferruginous tiger crane fly, Englewood, Florida, March, 2014. Thanks to Panda's Thumbelinos John Harshman and M. Kim Johnson for the identification.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Ole Lundin. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Nephrotoma ferruginea &amp;ndash; ferruginous tiger crane fly, Englewood, Florida, March, 2014. Thanks to Panda's Thumbelinos John Harshman and M. Kim Johnson for the identification.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Evolution, Education, and a Century of Scopes</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/evolution-education-scopes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evolution, Education, and a Century of Scopes" /><published>2025-03-22T09:22:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-22T09:22:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/evolution-education-scopes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/evolution-education-scopes.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Evolution_Education_Scopes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frontispiece of video&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you missed it, Skeptical Inquirer Presents has posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://skepticalinquirer.org/video/evolution-education-a-century-of-scopes-john-de-lancie-and-eugenie-scott/&quot;&gt;Evolution, Education, and a Century of Scopes&lt;/a&gt;, a discussion anticipating the &lt;a href=&quot;https://centerforinquiry.org/scopes-trial-centennial-conference/&quot;&gt;Scopes Trial Centennial conference&lt;/a&gt; in Chattanooga, Tennessee, this summer. The discussants are Eugenie Scott, the former executive director of the National Center for Science Education and an expert on creationism vs. evolution, and the actor John de Lancie, who most recently toured the US with a show on the Scopes Monkey Trial and subsequently co-authored an audio play, &lt;i&gt;The Dover Intelligent Design Trial&lt;/i&gt;. Mr. de Lancie was awarded the Clarence Darrow Award in 2018. The video is over an hour long, but I thought it was well worth watching.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">In case you missed it, Skeptical Inquirer Presents has posted Evolution, Education, and a Century of Scopes, a discussion anticipating the Scopes Trial Centennial conference in Chattanooga, Tennessee, this summer. The discussants are Eugenie Scott, the former executive director of the National Center for Science Education and an expert on creationism vs. evolution, and the actor John de Lancie, who most recently toured the US with a show on the Scopes Monkey Trial and subsequently co-authored an audio play, The Dover Intelligent Design Trial. Mr. de Lancie was awarded the Clarence Darrow Award in 2018. The video is over an hour long, but I thought it was well worth watching.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Safeguarding Sound Science, Climate Change Edition</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/safeguarding-sound-science.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Safeguarding Sound Science, Climate Change Edition" /><published>2025-03-21T13:03:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-21T13:03:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/safeguarding-sound-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/safeguarding-sound-science.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Safeguarding_Sound_Science_600.jpg &quot; alt=&quot;Safeguarding Sound Science logo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safeguarding Sound Science combats misinformation, disinformation, and misconceptions about climate change with actual science. In the 7-episode &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/safeguarding-sound-science&quot;&gt;Season One: Climate Change Edition&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.planetary.org/profiles/mat-kaplan&quot;&gt;Mat Kaplan&lt;/a&gt; (Senior Communications Advisor of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.planetary.org/&quot;&gt;Planetary Society&lt;/a&gt; and former host of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.planetary.org/planetary-radio&quot;&gt;Planetary Radio&lt;/a&gt;) talks to scientists, teachers, and other experts to explore who’s behind some of the more insidious efforts to sow distrust in climate science, how those efforts filter down to schools and classrooms, and what is being done to ensure that everyone — especially students — is exposed to accurate climate science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of this writing, the first two installments have been posted: Episode 1: “What Climate Change? Tackling Climate Denial,” with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Mann&quot;&gt; Michael Mann&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glenn_Branch&quot;&gt;Glenn Branch&lt;/a&gt; of the National Center for Science Education; and Episode 2: “A Century of Disinformation: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naomi_Oreskes&quot;&gt;Naomi Oreskes&lt;/a&gt; and the Merchants of Doubt.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Reprinted with permission from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/catalyzing-action/sign-ncse-monitor&quot;&gt;The NCSE Monitor&lt;/a&gt; for March 21, 2025. You may access the podcasts using the Season One link above, or else use &lt;a href=&quot;https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/safeguarding-sound-science/id1797165552&quot;&gt;Apple Podcasts &lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/show/1VENQjGuH2fMycb2lDsT4Q&quot;&gt;Spotify&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Safeguarding Sound Science combats misinformation, disinformation, and misconceptions about climate change with actual science. In the 7-episode Season One: Climate Change Edition, Mat Kaplan (Senior Communications Advisor of the Planetary Society and former host of Planetary Radio) talks to scientists, teachers, and other experts to explore who’s behind some of the more insidious efforts to sow distrust in climate science, how those efforts filter down to schools and classrooms, and what is being done to ensure that everyone — especially students — is exposed to accurate climate science. As of this writing, the first two installments have been posted: Episode 1: “What Climate Change? Tackling Climate Denial,” with Michael Mann and Glenn Branch of the National Center for Science Education; and Episode 2: “A Century of Disinformation: Naomi Oreskes and the Merchants of Doubt.” Reprinted with permission from The NCSE Monitor for March 21, 2025. You may access the podcasts using the Season One link above, or else use Apple Podcasts or Spotify.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Martyn Iles no longer with AIG</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/martyn-iles-no-longer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Martyn Iles no longer with AIG" /><published>2025-03-19T12:58:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-19T12:58:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/martyn-iles-no-longer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/martyn-iles-no-longer.html">&lt;p&gt;Dan Phelps informs us that Martyn Iles is no longer with Answers in Genesis (AIG). Paul Braterman &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/Martyn-Iles-Is-Executive.html&quot;&gt;reported earlier&lt;/a&gt; on PT that Mr. Iles had ascended to the position of “Executive CEO” of AIG. I think we had all assumed that he was the heir apparent. Mr. Phelps asks,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;He was apparently [Ken] Ham's chosen successor. I noticed he didn't do much lately. Was there a dispute, or other trouble? Who will Ham pick to succeed him? Will there be a puff of white smoke above the Ark when the decision is made?&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not know the answers to any of those questions, but it is easy to infer from the Facebook post (reproduced below the fold) that Mr. Iles left AIG before he had an alternative in mind. Mr. Phelps notes further that Mr. Iles’s name had been dropped from the AIG speakers’ biography page by March 13, but it was there on February 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If anyone has any further information, please feel free to comment, but please avoid idle speculation and invective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a screenshot taken by Mr. Phelps on March 19:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Iles_No_Longer_1000.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Iles Facebook post&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Dan Phelps informs us that Martyn Iles is no longer with Answers in Genesis (AIG). Paul Braterman reported earlier on PT that Mr. Iles had ascended to the position of “Executive CEO” of AIG. I think we had all assumed that he was the heir apparent. Mr. Phelps asks, He was apparently [Ken] Ham's chosen successor. I noticed he didn't do much lately. Was there a dispute, or other trouble? Who will Ham pick to succeed him? Will there be a puff of white smoke above the Ark when the decision is made? We do not know the answers to any of those questions, but it is easy to infer from the Facebook post (reproduced below the fold) that Mr. Iles left AIG before he had an alternative in mind. Mr. Phelps notes further that Mr. Iles’s name had been dropped from the AIG speakers’ biography page by March 13, but it was there on February 3. If anyone has any further information, please feel free to comment, but please avoid idle speculation and invective.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pantherophis alleghaniensis-quadrivittatus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/pantherophis-alleghaniensis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pantherophis alleghaniensis-quadrivittatus" /><published>2025-03-17T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-17T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/pantherophis-alleghaniensis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/pantherophis-alleghaniensis.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Denelsbeck_Pantherophis_alleghaniensis_quadrivittata.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Eastern ratsnake&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern_rat_snake&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Pantherophis alleghaniensis-quadrivittatus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; eastern rat snake. You may find a discussion of the scientific name &lt;a href=&quot;https://auth1.dpr.ncparks.gov/reptiles/view.php?checklist_number=103.0&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Al Denelsbeck. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Pantherophis alleghaniensis-quadrivittatus &amp;ndash; eastern rat snake. You may find a discussion of the scientific name here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The President and the Paleontologist: Jimmy Carter’s Dalliance with Creationism and Stephen Jay Gould’s Stumble in Rebutting It</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/president-paleontologist.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The President and the Paleontologist: Jimmy Carter’s Dalliance with Creationism and Stephen Jay Gould’s Stumble in Rebutting It" /><published>2025-03-05T10:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-05T10:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/president-paleontologist</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/president-paleontologist.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Branch_Carter_Gould.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Left, Jimmy Carter. Right, Stephen Jay Gould.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Left, &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Jimmy_Carter_1971_a.jpg&quot;&gt;Jimmy Carter&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;small&gt;Wikimedia. Public domain. Not subject to copyright in the United States.&lt;/small&gt; Right, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Stephen_Jay_Gould_2015,_portrait_(unknown_date).jpg&quot;&gt;Stephen Jay Gould&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;small&gt;Wikimedia. Photograph posted by Wally McNamee. Fair use: copyright owner unknown.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Glenn Branch is deputy director of the National Center for Science Education, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as &lt;/i&gt;Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher, &lt;i&gt;and the &lt;/i&gt;Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics, &lt;i&gt;and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of &lt;/i&gt;Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools (2006). &lt;i&gt; He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Jimmy Carter &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2024/12/29/us/politics/jimmy-carter-dead.html&quot;&gt;died&lt;/a&gt; on December 29, 2024, the nation lost not only its 39th president but also a prominent born-again Christian who accepted evolution. In chapter 5 of his 2005 book &lt;i&gt;Our Endangered Values &lt;/i&gt;, entitled “No Conflict Between Science and Religion,” Carter insisted, “The existence of millions of distant galaxies, the evolution of species, and the big bang theory cannot be rejected because they are not described in the Bible, and neither does confidence in them cast doubt on the Creator of it all.” Yet in the late 1980s, he proposed a creationist argument to no less a figure than the Harvard paleontologist Stephen Jay Gould — whose rebuttal, surprisingly, was inadequate.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Gould related in a postscript to his 1988 essay “In a Jumbled Drawer” (reprinted in his 1991 book &lt;i&gt;Bully for Brontosaurus&lt;/i&gt;), Carter called him out of the blue one day in the late 1980s, “simply to express his good wishes and his hopes for my continued good health” (Gould was in remission from cancer). In gratitude, he then sent Carter a copy of &lt;i&gt;Wonderful Life&lt;/i&gt; (1989), his new book about the Cambrian fauna of the Burgess Shale. As was typical with Gould, the paleontology served as a springboard to explore a larger theme: “the ‘pageant’ of evolution as a staggeringly improbable series of events, sensible enough in retrospect and subject to rigorous explanation, but utterly unpredictable and quite unrepeatable.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having read &lt;i&gt;Wonderful Life&lt;/i&gt; with pleasure while attempting to defuse armed conflicts in the Horn of Africa, Carter nevertheless offered a counterargument:

&lt;blockquote&gt;You seem to be straining mightily to prove that everything that has happened prior to an evolutionary screening period was just an accident, and that if the tape of life was replayed in countless different ways it is unlikely that cognitive creatures [such as humans] would have been created or evolved. It may be that when you raise “one chance in a million” to the 4th or 5th power there comes a time when pure “chance” can be questioned. I presume that you feel more at ease with the luck of 1 out of 10 to the 30th power than with the concept of a creator who/that has done some orchestrating.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gould described Carter’s argument, a bit fulsomely, as “a brilliant riposte ... a brilliant twentieth-century version of natural theology ... fascinating.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he insisted that Carter’s argument was nevertheless wrong, and wrong for the same reason that a similar argument he discussed in “In a Jumbled Drawer,” due to the 19th-century Harvard paleontologist Nathaniel Shaler, was wrong: “because a probability cannot even be calculated for a singular occurrence known only after the fact.” (It’s because of the similarity of Shaler’s and Carter’s arguments that Gould added the postscript to “In a Jumbled Drawer.”) Gould approvingly quoted the 19th-century Harvard philosopher and psychologist William James, as writing, in a letter to Shaler, “Where only one fact is in question, there is no relation of ‘probability’ at all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gould’s answer to Carter thus presupposed that attributions to probability to individual events are not legitimate: it’s wrong to say that the chance that the next toss of a coin will be heads is 1 in 2, or that there’s a 30 percent chance of rain in Chicago tomorrow, or that the probability that a given atom of cobalt-60 will decay in about 5.27 years is 0.5. Such a view is indeed accepted by a few (such as the mathematician Richard von Mises, who famously declared, “The phrase ‘probability of death,’ when it refers to a single person, has no meaning at all for us”), but it is hard to square with the abundance in ordinary life and scientific practice of attributions to probability to individual events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;i&gt;Wonderful Life&lt;/i&gt; itself abounds in such attributions. Early in the book, Gould explained, “This book is about the nature of history and the overwhelming improbability of human evolution under themes of contingency and the metaphor of replaying life’s tape”; toward the end, he mused, with reference to &lt;i&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/i&gt;, “we are an improbable and fragile entity,” and interpolated a new adjective in a familiar Shakespearean line: “O brave — and improbable — new world, that has such people in it!” In light of these and similar passages, it is hardly fair for Gould to have faulted Carter for wanting to discuss the improbability of human existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What should Gould have said to Carter instead? Carter in effect was arguing that because the probability of human existence is very low on the hypothesis of evolution without divine guidance, and humans yet exist, the hypothesis of evolution without divine guidance is therefore false. But the form of inference is incorrect, as the philosopher Elliott Sober (among others) &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1023/A:1019579220694&quot;&gt;observes&lt;/a&gt;. To see why, take a homely example exactly parallel to Carter’s. Suppose that you buy a single Powerball ticket. If the drawing is conducted properly, it is very improbable (about 1 in 300 million) that you hold a jackpot ticket. But if you turn out to hold a jackpot ticket, are you entitled to infer that the drawing was rigged in your favor? Surely not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Endorsement of the incorrect form of inference is not limited to creationists. The biologist Richard Dawkins, who is about as far from creationism as anyone could be, fell into the trap in his discussion of the origin of life in &lt;i&gt;The Blind Watchmaker&lt;/i&gt; (1986), for example. But it is common among creationists, and Carter’s argument was creationist, at least in a broad sense, for he thought that it showed that it was scientifically necessary to appeal to divine guidance in explaining the facts of life. That was apparently a deviation from his settled views on science and religion, however: in &lt;i&gt;Our Endangered Values&lt;/i&gt;, he relates, “I had always understood that we didn’t need scientific proof of the existence or character of God.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It actually isn’t clear what Carter himself thought of Gould’s rebuttal. In &lt;i&gt;Living Faith&lt;/i&gt; (1996), he wrote that Gould “later contradicted my argument — with good humor.” But in his later book &lt;i&gt;Our Endangered Values&lt;/i&gt;, he seemed a little miffed, writing, “He didn’t respond directly, but subsequently quoted and slyly ridiculed my opinion.” Any rancor evidently subsided by the time of &lt;i&gt;Faith: A Journey for All&lt;/i&gt; (2018), in which Carter listed the influences on his thinking about theology and philosophy, ending with Gould. Although he alluded to their arguments “about facts or principles,” he stressed their agreement about science and described Gould’s &lt;i&gt;Rocks of Ages&lt;/i&gt; (1999) as one of his favorite books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, despite his dalliance with the creationist argument he proposed to Gould, Carter was a stalwart defender of the teaching of evolution. In 1980, as the presidential contest was peaking, his challenger Ronald Reagan declared that evolution “is a scientific theory only” and that “the biblical theory of creation” deserved a place in public schools. Carter &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.210.4465.35&quot;&gt;replied&lt;/a&gt;, through his science adviser, that the scientific evidence for evolution was convincing and that schools ought to respect the constitutional separation of church and state. Since creationism was &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.gallup.com/poll/21814/evolution-creationism-intelligent-design.aspx&quot;&gt;favored&lt;/a&gt; by about 44 percent of the American public at the time, Carter’s reply was — typically for him — both principled and courageous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;i&gt;Reprinted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/the-president-and-the-paleontologist-jimmy-carters-dalliance-with-creationism-and-stephen-jay-goulds-stumble-in-rebutting-it/&quot;&gt; Righting America&lt;/a&gt; with the permission of Glenn Branch and William Trollinger.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Glenn Branch</name></author><summary type="html">Left, Jimmy Carter. Wikimedia. Public domain. Not subject to copyright in the United States. Right, Stephen Jay Gould. Wikimedia. Photograph posted by Wally McNamee. Fair use: copyright owner unknown. Glenn Branch is deputy director of the National Center for Science Education, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher, and the Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics, and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools (2006). He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers. When Jimmy Carter died on December 29, 2024, the nation lost not only its 39th president but also a prominent born-again Christian who accepted evolution. In chapter 5 of his 2005 book Our Endangered Values , entitled “No Conflict Between Science and Religion,” Carter insisted, “The existence of millions of distant galaxies, the evolution of species, and the big bang theory cannot be rejected because they are not described in the Bible, and neither does confidence in them cast doubt on the Creator of it all.” Yet in the late 1980s, he proposed a creationist argument to no less a figure than the Harvard paleontologist Stephen Jay Gould — whose rebuttal, surprisingly, was inadequate.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Spatula clypeata</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/spatula-clypeata.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spatula clypeata" /><published>2025-03-03T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-03T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/spatula-clypeata</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/spatula-clypeata.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/P1031480_Northern_Shoveler_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Northern shoveler&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Northern_Shoveler/overview&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Spatula clypeata&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; northern shoveler, East Boulder (Colorado) Community Center, February, 2025. It was hard to get a halfway decent picture of this pair, because they kept swimming around in circles with their bills in the water, almost as if they were filter feeding. According to the link, in fact they &lt;i&gt;were&lt;/i&gt; filter feeding: &quot;Shovelers eat tiny crustaceans, other aquatic invertebrates, and seeds which they filter out of the water with comblike projections (called lamellae) along the edge of the bill.&quot; You may see a nice picture of the lamellae &lt;a href=&quot;https://roadsendnaturalist.com/2016/02/24/meandering-at-mattamuskeet/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Spatula clypeata &amp;ndash; northern shoveler, East Boulder (Colorado) Community Center, February, 2025. It was hard to get a halfway decent picture of this pair, because they kept swimming around in circles with their bills in the water, almost as if they were filter feeding. According to the link, in fact they were filter feeding: &quot;Shovelers eat tiny crustaceans, other aquatic invertebrates, and seeds which they filter out of the water with comblike projections (called lamellae) along the edge of the bill.&quot; You may see a nice picture of the lamellae here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">State Police Proselytized during K9 Training at Ark Park; No Word on How Dogs Reacted</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/state-police-proselytized.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="State Police Proselytized during K9 Training at Ark Park; No Word on How Dogs Reacted" /><published>2025-03-01T14:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-01T14:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/state-police-proselytized</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/state-police-proselytized.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_KSP_Ark_Fig_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kentucky trooper with dog&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2020, the Kentucky State Police (KSP) were embroiled in a controversy after it was discovered that a &lt;a href=&quot;https://manualredeye.com/90096/news/local/police-training-hitler-presentation/&quot;&gt;training PowerPoint presentation&lt;/a&gt; quoted Adolf Hitler and advocated ruthless violence.  In spite of this horrendous exception, the Kentucky State Police is well-respected and noted for their professionalism and devotion to duty. Imagine my surprise when I learned that the KSP paid Answers in Genesis (AIG) to send an officer on a K9 training class on February 1 to 4, 2025, at the Ark Encounter. Besides K9 training, the class included Fundamentalist Christian and Christian Nationalist propaganda. With the government agencies and politicians increasingly becoming entangled Christian Nationalism, this incident is particularly disturbing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On February 7, 2025, Ken Ham &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2025/02/07/aig-impacts-law-enforcement-k-9-conference/&quot;&gt;bragged&lt;/a&gt; in his daily blog that the AIG Department of Public Safety had hosted numerous law enforcement organizations in K9 training at the Ark. Photos indicated a Kentucky State Police officer was there with his vehicle, as were several other regional law enforcement agencies. Moreover, an organization known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://tacticaministries.org/&quot;&gt;TACTICA Ministries&lt;/a&gt; (Teaching Authorities Christian Truth in Central America) was also present. My curiosity was immediately piqued by the presence of the KSP trooper. The questions I immediately had were, “Why is a major law enforcement organization being trained by AIG?” and “Why isn’t AIG going to a major organization like the KSP for training instead?” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then wrote a Kentucky Open Records Act (KORA) request. Surprisingly, perhaps as a delaying tactic, my initial request was rejected. The rejection claimed I was not a Kentucky resident, even though I specifically said I was a resident in the KORA request. (I was born here and have owned a house which I have lived in in Lexington for more than 20 years. Many of my ancestors came to the state with Daniel Boone in the late 18th Century.) I resubmitted the request and received a small number of documents. Some of the requested information was not available; no mileage records were kept, and the KSP trooper did not save all of his training materials. Additional withheld information included the redaction of the identities of all third-party instructors “…due to sensitivity of their respective jobs and the need for anonymity.” Were these third-party instructors members of government law enforcement? We may never know. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The open records information showed that Kentucky taxpayers paid approximately $225 for the training of one officer. This doesn’t include money spent by other Kentucky law enforcement agencies. Kentucky law enforcement from Villa Hills Police Department and the Boone County Sheriff’s Office participated. Some out-of-state regional law enforcement that participated included the Genesee County Ohio, Twinsburg (Ohio) Police Department, and the Collier County (Florida) Sheriff’s Department. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event included several breakfasts and lunches, as well as one diner that was sponsored by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nutramaxlabs.com/our-passion&quot;&gt; Nutramax Laboratories&lt;/a&gt; (a company that produces supplements for pets and does a lot of evangelism on the side). Interestingly, the event Welcome Package showed that each lunch included “testimony.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_KSP_Ark_Attachment.pdf&quot;&gt;Welcome Package&lt;/a&gt; for the event also included a message from AIG’s Department of Public Safety’s Sgt. Adam Witherspoon: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also, AIG Dept of Public Safety makes no effort to hide who we are. We care deeply about your working relationship with your dog and want to do everything we can to help you improve as a K9 team. More importantly though we care about you as an individual. God created all of us in His image. Due to our sin, and we are all sinners, Romans 3:23-24. 23. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;...for all have sinned and fall short of the glory of God, 24. being justified as a gift by His grace through the redemption which is in Christ Jesus; we are condemned to spend eternity
separated from God. Jesus Christ however took our punishment on the Cross. Our most sincere prayer is that if you don’t know Jesus Christ as your savior, come and talk to us. We
would love to share with you the Good News of the Gospel, which grants us eternity with God in heaven. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let’s get to some great training, enjoy some great food, fellowship, and learning, and I look forward to meeting and getting to know each one of you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In His Service,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; Sgt Adam Witherspoon &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_KSP_Ark_Fig_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tactica ministries hat&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_KSP_Ark_Fig_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Memorization Card&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt; A presentation at the K9 training (and a major vendor/sponsor) was by a Michigan-based TACTICA Ministries. This ministry apparently gives police/paramilitary training plus substantial religious instruction to police forces in Central and South American countries. Disturbingly, there are numerous YouTube videos available of TACTICA paramilitary training set to high energy Christian music (see: https://youtu.be/x7PKZ7_KA3w?feature=shared, https://youtu.be/SAwjK4QzLUM?si=xvhnvOajsXJ4X53I, and https://youtu.be/ZoHRcZ4SmP0?si=cowgfvsRRT4D-yqi). Figure 2 is a hat that TACTICA Ministries sells. Apparently, part of the TACTICA “training” at the event included memorization of Bible verses on a “Memorization Card.” What do any of these verses have to do with K9 training? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TACTICA Ministries is run by Ryan Rought. At least one presentation was done by Mr. Rought. The training documents give this biography and description of Rought’s work: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ryan is a man fervently committed to his Christian faith, his family, and serving others. His energy is contagious as he is unashamedly committed to investing in the public safety community through high quality training, relationship building, and Gospel centered teaching. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several other participants' biographies mention going on mission trips and long term training in with TACTICA Ministries, including Marty Buffenbarger (2.5 years with TACTICA in Costa Rica), Chris Carpenter of Livingston Security Solutions (several training mission trips), and Bill and Cindy Gruppen (also of Association of Baptists for World Evangelism). The Gruppens' bios indicate that their “mission is to share God's good news through creative and impactful avenues.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the itinerary, a good deal of the first day of training (14:00 to 19:00) involved signing in and “roaming” the Ark. This visitation combined with the speakers' bios and other activities, such as lunchtime “testimonials” show that religious instruction and evangelism of law enforcement officers was a substantial portion of the K9 training. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_KSP_Ark_Fig_4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot; Officer Charity, a K9 dog&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is some evidence that the KSP and other Kentucky law enforcement has participated in similar past events. On July 9, 2024, conservative Republican Kentucky Attorney General Russell Coleman posted pictures of “K9 Officer Charity” in front of the Ark Encounter. Officer Charity is a K9 with the Attorney General’s Office’s Department of Criminal Investigations. This sweet doggie has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/officercharity_k9/&quot;&gt; her own Instagram page&lt;/a&gt;. (The Attorney General’s post mentions that the KSP and the Boone County Sheriff’s Office participated in K9 training at the Ark in early July 2024. The instruction in February 2025 is probably one of several similar events that have used taxpayer money for an odd combination of training and evangelism.) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More disturbing than the use of taxpayer funding to evangelize law enforcement is the likelihood of the officers being indoctrinated in Christian Nationalism. Answers in Genesis is becoming more and more an advocate for far-right politics. On February 25, 2025, Founder CEO of Answers in Genesis, Ken Ham, posted an essay on his blog titled “&lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2025/02/25/what-happens-when-your-god-dies/&quot;&gt;What Happens When Your God Dies&lt;/a&gt;.” In this political essay he attacks “wokeness,” “racist” DEI hiring, pronoun use, and transgender ideology while praising the new administration and attacking Democrats. This theme is common throughout AIG’s online publications. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_KSP_Ark_Fig_5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;God's religion, according to AIG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On July 15, 2023, Bodie Hodge (Ken Ham’s son-in-law) had an essay on AIG’s page called “The Religion of Sexual Humanism” (you may now find it on the Wayback Machine &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20250114135356/https://answersingenesis.org/culture/religion-sexual-humanism/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). In this post, Hodge claims what he and AIG represent is “God’s Religion” while most other people belong to “Not God’s Religion.” Note that “Not God’s Religion” has a sub-section “Counterfeits of Biblical Christianity” that includes Roman Catholics, Seventh Day Adventists, Mormons, Jehovah’s Witnesses, Unitarians, “Moonies,” and even more bizarrely (if possible) Jews, Muslims, Freemasons, and Satanists (isn’t that special?) among many others. Eastern religions and secularism are given separate categories in this incredible (in the literal sense of the word) chart. I almost find this chart comical, but considering the very real possibility of Christian Nationalism becoming an arm of the government, the graphic is simply horrifying. AIG is very well-connected in state politics and apparently is looking to expand their reach. At one point Ken Ham was scheduled to speak at an event on April 24 along with Secretary of Defense Pete Hegseth and Franklin Graham. Recently, Hegseth backed out, presumably because of other duties, but a list of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20250117152827/https://www.dayspringchristian.com/remember-america/speaker-series/&quot;&gt;originally scheduled speakers is available on the Internet Wayback Machine&lt;/a&gt; as recently as January 17, 2025. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every July the Tri-State Freethinkers have a protest near the entrance to Ark Encounter to protest the fake science plus the sales-tax rebate incentives and other handouts that the Ark has received from state, county, and Williamstown governments. I have avoided participating in this event in the past because of concerns about the event’s effectiveness and the possibility of a creationist provocateur causing a disruption. I was recently asked to speak at this event. I am frankly very hesitant. I have to wonder whether law enforcement will look the other way if the protest is attacked, actively disrupt the protest, or find another way of punishing or harassing the participants. In any case the government should not be paying to give their employees religious instruction especially when the employees are in a position where fairness and equanimity should be standard. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Back in 2020, the Kentucky State Police (KSP) were embroiled in a controversy after it was discovered that a training PowerPoint presentation quoted Adolf Hitler and advocated ruthless violence. In spite of this horrendous exception, the Kentucky State Police is well-respected and noted for their professionalism and devotion to duty. Imagine my surprise when I learned that the KSP paid Answers in Genesis (AIG) to send an officer on a K9 training class on February 1 to 4, 2025, at the Ark Encounter. Besides K9 training, the class included Fundamentalist Christian and Christian Nationalist propaganda. With the government agencies and politicians increasingly becoming entangled Christian Nationalism, this incident is particularly disturbing. On February 7, 2025, Ken Ham bragged in his daily blog that the AIG Department of Public Safety had hosted numerous law enforcement organizations in K9 training at the Ark. Photos indicated a Kentucky State Police officer was there with his vehicle, as were several other regional law enforcement agencies. Moreover, an organization known as TACTICA Ministries (Teaching Authorities Christian Truth in Central America) was also present. My curiosity was immediately piqued by the presence of the KSP trooper. The questions I immediately had were, “Why is a major law enforcement organization being trained by AIG?” and “Why isn’t AIG going to a major organization like the KSP for training instead?”</summary></entry></feed>