<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-08-11T04:41:34-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Archilestes grandis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/archilestes-grandis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Archilestes grandis" /><published>2025-08-04T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-08-04T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/archilestes-grandis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/archilestes-grandis.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Joel Eissenberg&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Eissenberg_Archilestes grandis.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Damselfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_spreadwing&quot;&gt;Archilestes grandis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; great spreadwing damselfly spotted at the Denver zoo. Prof. Eissenberg notes that &quot;the resemblance between the damselfly and the twig to which it is clinging shows mimicry.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Joel Eissenberg. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Archilestes grandis &amp;ndash; great spreadwing damselfly spotted at the Denver zoo. Prof. Eissenberg notes that &quot;the resemblance between the damselfly and the twig to which it is clinging shows mimicry.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Worst Scopes Article Ever</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/worst-scopes-article-ever.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Worst Scopes Article Ever" /><published>2025-08-03T08:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-08-03T08:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/worst-scopes-article-ever</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/worst-scopes-article-ever.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Braterman_Darrow_Interrogating_Bryan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Darrow interrogating Bryan out-of-doors&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/0d/Tennessee_v._John_T._Scopes_Trial-_Outdoor_proceedings_on_July_20%2C_1925%2C_showing_William_Jennings_Bryan_and_Clarence_Darrow._%282_of_4_photos%29_%282898243103%29_crop.jpg&quot;&gt;William Jennings Bryan (seated, left) being cross-examined by Clarence Darrow&lt;/a&gt;, the trial having been moved outside because of the heat. Photograph by Watson Davis. Public domain.&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a close run thing. I would narrowly give second place to Answers in Genesis, which blames Bryan’s humiliation on &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2025/06/13/partnering-with-faithful-fathers/&quot;&gt;his willingness to contemplate an ancient Earth&lt;/a&gt;. But first place, to Mike Mueller, writing for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icr.org/article/scopes-monkey-trial-battle-worldviews/&quot;&gt;Creation Research International&lt;/a&gt; (CRI), which takes on the interesting task of seeing how well the scientific evidence has held up, gets every single detail wrong, and tells more than the usual number of lies in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early on: “Eventually the Butler Act was overturned.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Eventually” means in 1967! Forty-two years after the trial, seventeen years after the establishment of the National Science Foundation, and six years after the publication of &lt;i&gt;The Genesis Flood&lt;/i&gt; led to the resurgence of young Earth creationism. And it was not “overturned,” but repealed. This matters because of ongoing creationist complaints about judicial activism; it was a decision by the State Governor, rather than the outcome of a lawsuit, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Butler_Act&quot;&gt;although&lt;/a&gt; it was indeed a pending freedom of speech lawsuit that forced the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;[S]upposed experts presented some of the following topics as proof. Many are still used, but the scientific evidence actually supports creation, not evolution. Consider the claims and our brief responses.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “supposed” experts included half a dozen professors of geology, zoology, agriculture, and education from the Universities of Chicago, New Jersey, and Missouri, Johns Hopkins, and Harvard, as well as the State Geologist of Tennessee (the location of the trial), and, for good measure, a rabbi. Their combined testimony, available &lt;a href=&quot;https://profjoecain.net/scopes-monkey-trial-1925-complete-trial-transcripts/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, runs to 35 closely argued pages. It is an admirable document, including among other things the use of molecular biology (in the form of serology) to show that whales are related to hoofed animals. And of course none of it was “presented” at the trial, but merely deposited without being presented to jury, since the judge (in a sense, correctly) regarded it as irrelevant to whether Scopes had broken the law. But consider now the individual claims as summarized and allegedly refuted by CRI:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Claim&lt;/strong&gt;: Evolution from simple cells to complex life, bacteria to man, is a fact.

&lt;strong&gt;Response&lt;/strong&gt;: The trial experts admitted they didn’t know where the first cell came from and weren’t clear on the process or method evolution uses. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, we don’t know the origins of life. So what? We don’t know the origins of language, either, but we do know an enormous amount about how languages have evolved. As for not being clear on process or method, we are as would be expected a lot clearer now than we were a hundred years ago. Again, so what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, Mueller makes reference to a new theory being developed by Randy Giulizza, which he describes as based on engineering approach. This asserts that organisms have an inbuilt ability to modify their development in the face of new environmental challenges. Lamarckism, combined with the gift of prophecy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Claim&lt;/strong&gt;: Ape-to-human evolution is demonstrated by fossils.

&lt;strong&gt;Response&lt;/strong&gt;: The so-called missing links between ape and man are still missing. No discoveries show that humans descended from primates, and the fossil specimens presented in the trial and since have turned out to be fully human, fully ape or animal, a mixture of human and animal, or fraudulent.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The specimens described at the trial were Java Man (now classified as &lt;i&gt;Homo erectus&lt;/i&gt;, which branched off from our own line of descent some 2 million years ago); Heidelberg Man (now regarded as ancestral to both Neanderthal Man and anatomically modern humans); Piltdown Man, concerning which Professor Horatio Hackett Newman stated in his deposition that “there has been a great deal of controversy as to their significance. Until the experts arrive at an agreement about this type it might be well for others to reserve judgment”; Neanderthal Man (whose status as a close but distinct sister species to us is of course now well established); Rhodesia Man (regarded as related to Heidelberg Man); and a then recently discovered child’s skull which we now classify as &lt;i&gt;Australopithecus africanus&lt;/i&gt;. So there were already an impressive collection of “missing links,” which could not really be classified either as fully human or as fully ape, and the only fraud in the bunch came with a warning label. What we have learned since has greatly added to the number of ancestral species and sister lines of descent. As for any attempted division into “fully human” or “fully ape,” that is simply a pathology of rigid binary thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Claim&lt;/strong&gt;: The geological record proves evolution because simple life forms are buried in the deepest geological layers.

&lt;strong&gt;Response&lt;/strong&gt;: The fossil record documents the ecological zones that were progressively flooded and buried in the global Flood of Genesis. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All geological layers display a full range of ecological zones, to the point that we can compare extinct species with modern species showing similar lifestyles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Claim&lt;/strong&gt;: The earth is millions of years old, allowing for evolution to have occurred.

&lt;strong&gt;Response&lt;/strong&gt;: Many dating methods used to assign millions-of-years ages to rock specimens are based on unprovable assumptions and/or produce inconsistent results. Most evidence clearly supports a young earth and coincides with the biblical timeframe of around 6,000 years.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creationist list of “unprovable assumptions,” namely amount of daughter material initially present, the possible mobility of isotopes, and the constancy of radioactive decay constants, is cut-and-paste from classical papers on the subject, dating back to around 1910. My favorite account of how these problems have been overcome is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.asa3.org/ASA/resources/Wiens2002.pdf&quot;&gt;Radiometric dating; a Christian perspective&lt;/a&gt;, by Roger Wiens at Los Alamos, himself an evangelical Christian. Simply put, the first two problems are overcome by looking at more than two isotopes, and where possible at rock grains within which the initial incorporation of daughter would have been impossible, while the radioactive decay constants depend on fundamental laws that must have been the same when the rocks were laid down, or we would never have had such rocks. As for “Most evidence,” this refers to methods based on such things as the thickness of sediments or the salinity of the oceans, which consider the rate of deposition of substances but not their removal. These were in any case regarded, until superseded by radiometric dating, as indicating an age of the earth of around 100 million years. I’m not aware of any method that supports 6,000 years, except for recent geological phenomena such as Niagara Falls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Claim&lt;/strong&gt;: The tailbone, appendix, wisdom teeth, and other organs are vestigial features.

&lt;strong&gt;Response&lt;/strong&gt;: Parts of organisms once thought to be useless evolutionary leftovers are today known to have important functions. They were designed according to God’s plan.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If evolution is correct, we would expect organs that had lost their initial function to undergo one of two fates: total disappearance (in which case we would not see them now even as vestiges) or, an interesting possibility clearly realized by Darwin, modification with change of function. Thus the human appendix is now thought to act as a useful refugium for essential gut bacteria, while the whale’s residual hind limbs serve to anchor muscles used, I have read, to hold the parties together during sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Claim&lt;/strong&gt;: Genetic similarity and breeding results support evolution.

&lt;strong&gt;Response&lt;/strong&gt;: Human and ape DNA are now known to be 84% similar, not 98% as initially claimed. And variation between plant and animal species can be managed by controlled genetic breeding. This is not evidence of gradual change driven by random mutations over millions of years.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been known for a very long time that roughly 15% of human and chimpanzee DNA is not directly comparable, because of major deletions and inversions, while the 98% similarity refers to that part of the genome where direct comparison is possible. Every so often, some new analysis reminds creationists of these familiar facts, and they gleefully point out that 84% is less than 98%, thus to their satisfaction refuting the argument from genetic similarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Claim&lt;/strong&gt;: Embryonic development and comparative embryology between animals prove that living organisms came from a common ancestor because their developing embryos echo evolutionary stages.

&lt;strong&gt;Response&lt;/strong&gt;: This idea was popularized in 1866 by Ernst Haeckel. He was later reprimanded for using fraudulent drawings. Unfortunately, students are still told that developing babies go through evolutionary history with gill slits, a tail, and yolk sacs, even though this is false. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all dishonest creationist arguments, this is the one that I find most annoying. There is no way in which our present knowledge of embryology is affected by possible dishonesty in Haeckel’s work over 150 years ago. Human embryos do indeed “go through evolutionary history with gill slits, a tail, and yolk sacs,” as is evident in the freely viewable images of weeks 6 and 7 on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.babycenter.com/pregnancy/week-by-week&quot;&gt;the Babycenter site&lt;/a&gt;. As spelled out in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.280.5366.983c&quot;&gt;a key paper&lt;/a&gt; by the very author that creationists most frequently quote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;On a fundamental level, Haeckel was correct: All vertebrates develop a similar body plan (consisting of notochord, body segments, pharyngeal pouches, and so forth). This shared developmental program reflects shared evolutionary history. It also fits with overwhelming recent evidence that development in different animals is controlled by common genetic mechanisms.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a fundamental level, I have questions of my own. Are the CRI scientists, some with reputable training, knowingly telling lies? Or do they think that they are legitimately simplifying complex matters to make them clearer to a lay audience? Or are their cognitive filters and biases so well developed that they can see only what confirms their case, even when looking directly at information that refutes it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficult questions, but relevant to the choice of counter-tactics, and on which I would much appreciate readers’ opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Braterman_Embryo_Stage_12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Human embryo, stage 12&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Human embryo, stage 12, Shigehito Yamada and Tetsuya Takakuwa, &lt;i&gt;The Human Embryo&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footnote: The freely downloadable book chapter, &lt;i&gt;Developmental Overview of the Human Embryo&lt;/i&gt;,  DOI &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.5772/38232&quot;&gt;10.5772/38232&lt;/a&gt;, by Shigehito Yamada and Tetsuya Takakuwa, in the book &lt;i&gt;The Human Embryo&lt;/i&gt; (Intech Open, 2012), gives an excellent detailed account of developmental stages, with gill pouches, tail, and yolk sac clearly visible at 28 days, as shown.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman</name></author><summary type="html">William Jennings Bryan (seated, left) being cross-examined by Clarence Darrow, the trial having been moved outside because of the heat. Photograph by Watson Davis. Public domain. It’s a close run thing. I would narrowly give second place to Answers in Genesis, which blames Bryan’s humiliation on his willingness to contemplate an ancient Earth. But first place, to Mike Mueller, writing for Creation Research International (CRI), which takes on the interesting task of seeing how well the scientific evidence has held up, gets every single detail wrong, and tells more than the usual number of lies in the process. Early on: “Eventually the Butler Act was overturned.” “Eventually” means in 1967! Forty-two years after the trial, seventeen years after the establishment of the National Science Foundation, and six years after the publication of The Genesis Flood led to the resurgence of young Earth creationism. And it was not “overturned,” but repealed. This matters because of ongoing creationist complaints about judicial activism; it was a decision by the State Governor, rather than the outcome of a lawsuit, although it was indeed a pending freedom of speech lawsuit that forced the issue.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy Lamarck day</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/HappybirthdayLamarck.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy Lamarck day" /><published>2025-08-01T13:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2025-08-01T13:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/HappybirthdayLamarck</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/HappybirthdayLamarck.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Buffon2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Not Lamarck but instead Buffon]&quot; /&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Not actually Lamarck, but instead 
his superior, Buffon.&lt;br /&gt; Painting by François-Hubert Drouais. From Wikimedia.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, it is the birthday (August 1st) of Jean Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet, the Chevalier de 
Lamarck.  He was the first major evolutionary biologist (as far as I am concerned).  He drew some of 
the first evolutionary trees, and suggested mechanisms for evolution, including adaptation. (His mechanisms 
were wrong, of course).  He was also a major pioneer of invertebrate biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On past birthdays I have covered many aspects of Lamarck’s life and work, down to and including the 
avenue and Paris Metro station named after him.  This time, allow me to digress to the life of 
his patron Buffon, who also has a claim to be an early evolutionist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Georges-Louis Leclerc, Comte de Buffon (1707-1788) was a sometime-aristocrat who was 
interested in many scientific and mathematical questions.  Among other investigations, he had 
his employees measure the rate of cooling of a metal sphere after it was taken out of a 
furnace, and from this estimated the age of the Earth as almost 75,000 years.  This is much 
more than the biblical figure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was most famous for writing a 39-volume &lt;em&gt;Histoire Naturelle&lt;/em&gt; which surveyed many 
aspects of natural history, and was widely read.  In the course of this, he raised the issue of evolutionary 
change, and argued that it was due to degeneration of forms from an original continuum of 
life.  He was actually forced by Paris academicians to recant his views because they 
conflicted with the biblical account.  He gave no mechanism for the evolution of adaptation, 
however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His connection with Lamarck was direct.  When Lamarck started writing on the flora of 
France, Buffon, who was head of the royal botanical garden, was impressed and gave him 
a job there.  When I visited the garden, which now contains the museum of natural 
history as well, I saw an impressive 18th century mansion there.  On it was a 
plaque announcing that Buffon has lived in it and had died there, and so had Lamarck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without Buffon, Lamarck would probably not have accomplished much of what he did. 
Perhaps Buffon’s cleverest achievement was that he died one year before the start 
of the French Revolution.  So here’s a toast to Buffon, and thus indirectly to Lamarck.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Not actually Lamarck, but instead his superior, Buffon. Painting by François-Hubert Drouais. From Wikimedia. &amp;nbsp; Once again, it is the birthday (August 1st) of Jean Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet, the Chevalier de Lamarck. He was the first major evolutionary biologist (as far as I am concerned). He drew some of the first evolutionary trees, and suggested mechanisms for evolution, including adaptation. (His mechanisms were wrong, of course). He was also a major pioneer of invertebrate biology. On past birthdays I have covered many aspects of Lamarck’s life and work, down to and including the avenue and Paris Metro station named after him. This time, allow me to digress to the life of his patron Buffon, who also has a claim to be an early evolutionist.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Evolution News finds the problem with the evolution of mimicry</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/olearymimicry.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evolution News finds the problem with the evolution of mimicry" /><published>2025-07-28T13:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-28T13:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/olearymimicry</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/olearymimicry.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Butterflyfish.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[The Four-eyed Butterflyfish]&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Four-eyed Butterflyfish, &lt;em&gt;Chaetodon capistratus&lt;/em&gt;, 
with the real pair of eyes obscured by stripes, allowing the large spots 
to be mistaken for eyes. From Wikimedia.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Discovery Institute’s &lt;em&gt;Evolution News&lt;/em&gt; website is the foremost site for 
advocacy of Intelligent Design.  We should therefore expect its arguments to 
be technically sound and convincing.  An extraordinary example of their 
standards appeared recently there.  On the 23rd of July, Denyse O’Leary,
who posts there often, explained why: 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2025/07/for-darwinism-here-is-the-problem-with-butterfly-mimicry/&quot;&gt;For Darwinism, Here Is the Problem with Butterfly Mimicry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She starts by noting a scientific paper which examined the evolution of 
a type of mimicry in which what look like large eyespots occur near the 
rear end of butterfly wings.  A similar example in butterflyfish will be 
seen in the image above.  These false eyespots might tempt a predator to 
attack that end of the butterfly rather than its actual head.  The 
paper examines such color patterns across many butterfly species, and 
finds that the elements of the pattern evolve together in different 
parts of the evolutionary tree, multiple times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors of that paper conclude that this repeated correlated evolution 
is most likely the result of natural selection for mimicry.
Not so Denyse O’Leary.  She sees a big problem: the fallacy of 
“the five percent solution”.  If the pattern is only five 
percent present, how can it be favored by natural selection?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charles Darwin (uncredited by O’Leary) gave a convincing 
argument for how eyes in animals could evolve, starting 
with a mere light-sensitive spot.  O’Leary argues that 
no such argument can be made for the false eyespots:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I call this the “five percent solution” because of a question asked in the article at PBS above, “What good is five percent of an eye?” And a reasonable answer is: Some good. Even a light-sensitive spot is better than no vision at all.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But Now What about the Five Percent Problem?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The dead leaf butterfly’s challenge — to take one example — is quite different from the one a blind worm faces. The blind worm is better off with five percent of visual information, as opposed to none at all.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;But a method of deception that is only five percent persuasive is not a first step on a road to a solution. Looking only five per cent like a dead leaf would likely prove fatal to the insect that relied on it. The false head butterfly would face the same problem: If the wing spots looked only a bit like a head for aeons, the gradually evolving insect would need a different method of self-protection for quite a long time. And, under the circumstances, why would either the dead leaf or false head mimicry continue to evolve?
There really isn’t an adequate answer to this problem because Darwinian evolution is not thought to show foresight. The usual response has been to Cancel the question instead. That submerges the question but doesn’t make it go away.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not convinced. &lt;!--more--&gt; O’Leary assumes an all-or-nothing view of adaptation.  Either a 
species is fully adapted, so that the mimicry is fully effective, or it has 
no adaptation at all.  But encounters between predators and prey occur in many 
different circumstances, sometimes with predators having a good view of the 
potential prey for a long time, and sometimes with them having only a brief 
and obscured glimpse for just a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A prey individual may be covered with irregular blotches, as a means of 
cryptic coloration.  And these blotches may occasional strike the predator 
as eyes.  If that can cause the predator to misdirect its attack, this 
pattern may have a small increase in fitness.  The resulting small 
selection pressure can gradually make the pattern of blotches more like 
a pair of eyes. (I should add another possibility – that the false eyes 
make the prey look like the head of a larger species, such as a 
snake.  That would tend to deter the predator from attacking.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Invoking the 5% problem and assuming that only a 100% mimicry can have 
any effect on fitness follows a common argument of opponents of 
natural selection.  Both of the two main ID arguments, complex specified 
information and irreducible complexity, seek to do away with the 
possibility that effective adaptations could arise step by step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The common thread in all this is that advocates of ID and/or creationism 
simply don’t understand how natural selection works in populations. 
Any noise, uncertainty, or weakness of selection pressure is assumed to 
prevent adaptation from being achieved at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denyse O’Leary’s argument, like most others she makes, reveal a 
thorough misunderstanding of evolutionary biology.  They end up 
being astonishingly weak arguments.  They reveal that the DI, in 
Evolution News, is willing to endorse absurd arguments as meeting 
its supposedly-high standards.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">The Four-eyed Butterflyfish, Chaetodon capistratus, with the real pair of eyes obscured by stripes, allowing the large spots to be mistaken for eyes. From Wikimedia. &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The Discovery Institute’s Evolution News website is the foremost site for advocacy of Intelligent Design. We should therefore expect its arguments to be technically sound and convincing. An extraordinary example of their standards appeared recently there. On the 23rd of July, Denyse O’Leary, who posts there often, explained why: For Darwinism, Here Is the Problem with Butterfly Mimicry. She starts by noting a scientific paper which examined the evolution of a type of mimicry in which what look like large eyespots occur near the rear end of butterfly wings. A similar example in butterflyfish will be seen in the image above. These false eyespots might tempt a predator to attack that end of the butterfly rather than its actual head. The paper examines such color patterns across many butterfly species, and finds that the elements of the pattern evolve together in different parts of the evolutionary tree, multiple times. The authors of that paper conclude that this repeated correlated evolution is most likely the result of natural selection for mimicry. Not so Denyse O’Leary. She sees a big problem: the fallacy of “the five percent solution”. If the pattern is only five percent present, how can it be favored by natural selection? Charles Darwin (uncredited by O’Leary) gave a convincing argument for how eyes in animals could evolve, starting with a mere light-sensitive spot. O’Leary argues that no such argument can be made for the false eyespots: I call this the “five percent solution” because of a question asked in the article at PBS above, “What good is five percent of an eye?” And a reasonable answer is: Some good. Even a light-sensitive spot is better than no vision at all. But Now What about the Five Percent Problem? The dead leaf butterfly’s challenge — to take one example — is quite different from the one a blind worm faces. The blind worm is better off with five percent of visual information, as opposed to none at all. But a method of deception that is only five percent persuasive is not a first step on a road to a solution. Looking only five per cent like a dead leaf would likely prove fatal to the insect that relied on it. The false head butterfly would face the same problem: If the wing spots looked only a bit like a head for aeons, the gradually evolving insect would need a different method of self-protection for quite a long time. And, under the circumstances, why would either the dead leaf or false head mimicry continue to evolve? There really isn’t an adequate answer to this problem because Darwinian evolution is not thought to show foresight. The usual response has been to Cancel the question instead. That submerges the question but doesn’t make it go away.” I’m not convinced.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Booster Shots, book by Adam Ratner</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/booster-shots-book.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Booster Shots, book by Adam Ratner" /><published>2025-07-28T09:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-28T09:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/booster-shots-book</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/booster-shots-book.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Ratner_Booster_Shots_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book Cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This splendid little book (202 pp. not counting the notes) is ostensibly about measles, but it covers a lot more, not least how we are probably unprepared for the next pandemic. I learned two main things: Vaccines do not prevent disease; &lt;i&gt;vaccinations&lt;/i&gt; prevent disease. And successful campaigns against contagious diseases contain within them the seeds of their own destruction. The first of these is perhaps obvious; the second, perhaps less so, but once a disease is eradicated or nearly eradicated, people forget, become complacent, possibly exaggerate the side effects of immunization, and sometimes tragically fail to get their vaccinations. Later in the book, the author discusses the libertarian conceit that individual rights take precedence over obligations to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first things first. The book is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/670274/booster-shots-by-adam-ratner-md-mph/&quot;&gt;Booster Shots&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://nyulangone.org/doctors/1972558187/adam-j-ratner&quot;&gt;Adam Ratner&lt;/a&gt;, a specialist in infectious pediatric diseases at New York University’s Grossman School of Medicine. He is also, judging by the contents of his book, a good historian and a talented writer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;History first. I was fascinated by the story of Peter Panum, a Norwegian doctoral student (!), who was sent with his fellow student August Manicus, to the Faroe Islands in 1846 to study an outbreak of measles. The Faroes had never suffered from measles and were sparsely populated. The two facts together made them a “natural laboratory” and enabled Panum to, in effect, invent the science of epidemiology and also show that measles was a contagious disease and not caused by a “miasma,” or bad air, as from a swamp. Panum went on to a distinguished career and according to Ratner contributed to immunology, physiology, nutrition, and binocular vision, as well as integrating Scandinavian medicine with European medicine. He worked about a decade before John Snow, who found the origin of the cholera epidemic in London, but Panum is not well known, at least in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ratner’s detailed history also brought home that measles is not a childhood disease. When the population is dense, however, everyone who is not a child has already had the disease and is immune or has died from it, so children are almost the only ones who contract the disease today. Contrary to what many think, measles is a serious disease with a mortality rate of a few per thousand cases. In the early twentieth century, the disease was exacerbated by the architecture of the tenements in which the urban poor typically lived. Even today, mortality in the industrialized nations is higher among the poor than among the rich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The eradication of smallpox is well and widely known, but Ratner’s telling is nevertheless interesting. Cotton Mather, whom Ratner calls “ostensibly a man of God,” lost much of his family to measles, but then promoted variolation to prevent smallpox. For his pains he was sent a Molotov cocktail (fortunately, a dud) along with a note, “Cotton Mather, You Dog, Dam you: I’ll inoculate you with this, with a Pox to you.” Anti-vaxxers have a longer history than I ever imagined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonas Salk and Albert Sabin developed polio vaccines based on the work of John Enders and colleagues. Polio was virtually wiped out in the United States. Why not measles, for which Enders developed a vaccine that was licensed around a decade after polio? It is complicated, but I well remember how frightened parents were during the polio epidemic, whereas measles (and mumps and whooping cough) were considered “just” childhood diseases. Also, says Ratner, there was no plan for purchasing and distributing measles vaccine. There were two measles vaccines, and it was unclear which one was preferred. Ratner’s lessons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;that messages matter, that policy decisions about vaccine availability and recommendations matter, and that early confusion on the part of parents and pediatricians can prove difficult to overcome….&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still have not learned all those lessons with regard to Covid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even so, we eventually came close to wiping out measles, but then the anti-vaxx movement hit and combined with our collective amnesia to result in a substantial number of unvaccinated children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do people fear vaccination (Ratner politely calls them vaccine-hesitant)? He tells us early on: “fear of vaccines and minimization of the real dangers of the diseases that those vaccines protect against.” Ethical lapses, such as the infamous Tuskegee experiment, also did not help. Ratner stresses, correctly, I think, that the vaccine-hesitant are not fools, and their concerns need to be taken seriously and addressed sympathetically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will not go into detail, but Ratner describes the situation in Texarkana, a city that straddles the border between Texas and Arkansas. The two halves of the city are evidently completely integrated, but Arkansas required vaccination for measles, whereas Texas did not. You can guess what is coming next: in a measles outbreak in 1970, 96 % of all cases in Texarkana were found among people who lived in Texas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ratner is almost unfailingly polite; remember, he advised approaching vaccine-hesitant patients sympathetically. He shows no sympathy for Robert F. Kennedy Jr. who, he says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;traveled to Samoa to meet with the prime minister and local activists, ghoulishly spreading unfounded anti-vaccine messages in an attempt to ensure that no tragedy would go to waste.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book was almost certainly submitted for publication before Kennedy lied to a congressional committee and set about destroying the National Institutes of Health and other agencies under his purview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ratner worries that we made mistakes letting measles back in. We similarly made mistakes with Covid, but these were more mistakes of ignorance than of omission. He worries that we will not be ready for the next pandemic, whatever it is and wherever it strikes. He is, however, optimistic that we can eliminate measles if we put our minds to it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">This splendid little book (202 pp. not counting the notes) is ostensibly about measles, but it covers a lot more, not least how we are probably unprepared for the next pandemic. I learned two main things: Vaccines do not prevent disease; vaccinations prevent disease. And successful campaigns against contagious diseases contain within them the seeds of their own destruction. The first of these is perhaps obvious; the second, perhaps less so, but once a disease is eradicated or nearly eradicated, people forget, become complacent, possibly exaggerate the side effects of immunization, and sometimes tragically fail to get their vaccinations. Later in the book, the author discusses the libertarian conceit that individual rights take precedence over obligations to others. But first things first. The book is Booster Shots by Adam Ratner, a specialist in infectious pediatric diseases at New York University’s Grossman School of Medicine. He is also, judging by the contents of his book, a good historian and a talented writer.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Garrulus glandarius</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/garrulus-glandarius.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Garrulus glandarius" /><published>2025-07-21T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-21T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/garrulus-glandarius</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/garrulus-glandarius.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Philip Abrams&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Abrams_Eurasian_Jay_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Eurasian jay.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wildlondon.org.uk/wildlife-explorer/birds/crows-and-shrikes/jay&quot;&gt;Garrulus glandarius&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; Eurasian jay, 16 June 2025, in a narrow lane in Chelsea, London SW3, iPhone 15. Mr. Abrams notes, &quot;This juvenile, judging by size,  Eurasian jay was sheltering in a doorway from attacks by a couple of adult magpies (&lt;i&gt;Pica pica&lt;/i&gt;).  Once they’d been driven off it let me approach quite close &amp;ndash; within a couple of metres.  Unsurprisingly, it was panting, so I assume it felt stressed.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Philip Abrams. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Garrulus glandarius &amp;ndash; Eurasian jay, 16 June 2025, in a narrow lane in Chelsea, London SW3, iPhone 15. Mr. Abrams notes, &quot;This juvenile, judging by size, Eurasian jay was sheltering in a doorway from attacks by a couple of adult magpies (Pica pica). Once they’d been driven off it let me approach quite close &amp;ndash; within a couple of metres. Unsurprisingly, it was panting, so I assume it felt stressed.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Teach Your Dog Quantum Mechanics: book report</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/hot-to-teach-your-dog.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Teach Your Dog Quantum Mechanics: book report" /><published>2025-07-19T12:45:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-19T12:45:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/hot-to-teach-your-dog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/hot-to-teach-your-dog.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Orzel_Physics_Dog_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I accidentally came across &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/How-Teach-Quantum-Physics-Your-ebook/dp/B002ZJCQT2/&quot;&gt;this little book&lt;/a&gt;, originally published in 2009, a short while ago and thought it deserved a review in Amazon. It is a little bit off-task here, but it is a solid science book and still deserves some publicity. This report, which you will find below the fold, is necessarily a little technical. If you cannot understand it, read the book!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dog was a little cutesy at times, but on the whole I thought this was a splendid book. Not that it exactly explained why quantum will mechanics is the way it is – I have a feeling we will never know the answer to that question – but rather it was breezy yet got into surprising depth. The dog and the bunnies she always chased turned out to be a good device for explaining why we do not see quantum effects in the macroscopic world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the realists among us, Orzel explains that the wave-particle duality is real, and the particle truly does not have a definite state until it is “observed.” Likewise, Heisenberg’s uncertainty principle is a purely quantum effect and has no classical analog. It is good for an experimental physicist like me to be reminded of that every now and then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orzel spends considerable time with the Copenhagen and the many-worlds interpretations. He does not like the Copenhagen interpretation, but if he embraces the many-worlds interpretation, he did not convince me. That we cannot understand quantum mechanics does not mitigate our desire for an explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quantum Zeno effect was vaguely familiar to me, and Orzel explains it well. Oversimplified slightly, if you repeatedly make measurements immediately after you start a transition, you repeatedly put the system back into the initial condition, and the system never completes the transition. In classical mechanics, the system would keep going, perhaps with small perturbations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quantum tunneling is nothing to someone who is used to electromagnetic waves, but entanglement can drive a naïve realist crazy. The book was published in 2009, and I think entangled photons have since been discovered over much greater distances than described in the book. Unless I completely misunderstand, one of two entangled photons could travel to Alpha Centauri, while the other one went back and forth to Jupiter a zillion times.* As soon as we measure the second photon, the state of the Alpha Centauri photon will be determined instantly (in our reference frame), but we will have to wait several years to receive a telephone call at the speed of light.†&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chapter on quantum teleportation might be a little too “hairy” for the casual reader, but I had not realized that a particle is not literally teleported; rather, another particle down the road somewhere is prepared, with some difficulty, in the same state as the initial particle (sort of, but not precisely, the way a fax machine sends a copy of an original).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The attraction between, say, an electron and a proton is caused by an exchange of virtual particles. These particles are exceedingly short-lived and are never observed. They may sound like woo, but in fact they are the basis for the most precise calculations in physics (or anywhere else).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last chapter of the book discusses misuses of quantum physics by quacks who promise free energy from something known as zero-point energy; quantum healing, which is so convoluted that you will have to read it to believe it was written by someone with an advanced degree; healing at a distance, supposedly based on a unified field theory, which does not exist, or entanglement, or something; and homeopathy, which evidently has taken up entanglement since I last studied it. Such a lot of nonsense! As Orzel notes, quantum mechanics is not magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;I had a relatively few quibbles, most of which I will not detail here. I thought that the Dirac bracket, &amp;lt;a&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;b&amp;gt;, should have been defined more clearly. Physicists may not be “widely admired for their ability to think up clever names,” but Dirac very cleverly divided his brackets into two segments, &amp;lt;a&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;and&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;b&amp;gt;, and called them bras and kets. (I had a professor in the 1960’s who said that it took him several years before he could say “bra” without blushing, but in fact the Dirac bra was invented before the brassiere.)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not know why Orzel used gamma, rather than the usual lambda, for the wavelength of light. A mirror that is “not quite perfect” would have better been described as a partially reflecting or transmitting mirror. You do not send a laser through a crystal; you send a &lt;i&gt;laser beam&lt;/i&gt;. And finally, never, as I once did, let a philosopher hear you say that virtual particles annihilate each other &lt;i&gt;in order to satisfy the uncertainty principle&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* I will take this opportunity to point out (a) that the book uses far, far too many footnotes in order to include material that mostly should have been written into the text, and (b) that entanglement is very, very fussy, and it would be very difficult in reality for a photon to travel all the way to Alpha Centauri without having an interaction that destroys the entanglement. Such an interaction brings about decoherence, which is covered in some detail in the book. Decoherence is arguably one reason we do not see quantum effects with macroscopic objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;† Unfortunately, we cannot use entanglement to send messages instantaneously to Alpha Centauri, because if we knew the state of “our” photon before sending it off, it would be a different experiment, with no entanglement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Judah Levine for providing helpful comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I accidentally came across this little book, originally published in 2009, a short while ago and thought it deserved a review in Amazon. It is a little bit off-task here, but it is a solid science book and still deserves some publicity. This report, which you will find below the fold, is necessarily a little technical. If you cannot understand it, read the book!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Echium candicans</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/echium-candicans.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Echium candicans" /><published>2025-07-14T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-14T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/echium-candicans</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/echium-candicans.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;John Trawick&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Runner-up&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Trawick_Apis_mellifera_Echium_candicans.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pride of Madeira with honeybee.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smgrowers.com/products/plants/plantdisplay.asp?plant_id=543&quot;&gt;Echium candicans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; pride of Madeira. Mr. Trawick notes, &quot;Pride of Madeira is rare in its native Madeira but has become very common in California, especially the San Diego area. Though very pretty, the sap is toxic. These attract a lot of honeybees (&lt;i&gt;Apis mellifera&lt;/i&gt;) when blooming.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by John Trawick. Photography Contest, Runner-up. Echium candicans &amp;ndash; pride of Madeira. Mr. Trawick notes, &quot;Pride of Madeira is rare in its native Madeira but has become very common in California, especially the San Diego area. Though very pretty, the sap is toxic. These attract a lot of honeybees (Apis mellifera) when blooming.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Human and Chimpanzee: 15% or 1% Genetic Difference? How Creationism Misleads the Public</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/human_and_chimpanzee.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Human and Chimpanzee: 15% or 1% Genetic Difference? How Creationism Misleads the Public" /><published>2025-07-12T12:45:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T12:45:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/human_and_chimpanzee</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/human_and_chimpanzee.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Neukamm_Frontispiece.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Human, chimpanzee shaking hands&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://depositphotos.com/de/photo/handshake-between-human-hand-and-monkey-hand-10880064.html&quot;&gt;Photograph by lifeonwhite&lt;/a&gt;, depositphoto license.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In academic circles, various figures are cited regarding the genetic similarity between humans and chimpanzees. Some studies estimate the differences to be around 1% to 5%, while others suggest they might be as high as 13% to 15% or more. Creationists claim that recent research has debunked the so-called “1% myth.” In doing so, they aim to cast doubt on the evolutionary relationship between humans and other primates, and accuse evolutionary biology of clinging to outdated dogmas. However, in order to make their argument persuasive, they deliberately omit crucial information. Casey Luskin of the evangelical think tank Discovery Institute even went so far as to crop a graphic published in the scientific journal &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt;, intentionally removing key data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;header&gt;&lt;h4&gt;
Are Human and Chimpanzee Genes Really 99% Identical?
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few scientific discoveries have shaken humanity’s self-image as profoundly as Darwin’s insight that our origins lie within the animal kingdom. The idea that we are not uniquely created beings standing above nature, but instead share a common ancestry with chimpanzees, gorillas, and other primates, remains intellectually challenging for many. This notion is particularly unsettling for religious individuals who view humans as the “crown of creation.” The fear of losing a sense of human uniqueness runs deep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The realization that only 1.2% of our genes differ from those of chimpanzees hit like a bombshell; our shared evolutionary history becomes unmistakably clear. It’s no surprise that evolution deniers—broadly speaking, creationists—who reject our ancestral roots in the animal world, constantly question, downplay, and attack this close genetic relationship, branding it the “1% myth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent studies, however, appear to support the creationist narrative. Some no longer report 95% or 99% genetic similarity, but instead present significantly lower numbers—sometimes as low as 85%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent study published in the journal &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt; (YOO et al., 2025) confirms this approximate figure. An international research team offers a comprehensive reassessment of the genomic similarity between humans, chimpanzees, and other primate species, based on complete genome sequencing and comparative analysis of multiple primate genomes. The study combines high-resolution sequencing technologies with advanced bioinformatic methods to systematically detect both point mutations and structural genomic differences. The result: the total genome-wide difference between humans and chimpanzees is between approximately 13.3% and 14.9%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;header&gt;&lt;h4&gt; Creationism Claims Victory: The 1% Myth Has Been Debunked?
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first glance, the recent figures suggesting a greater genetic difference between humans and chimpanzees appear to represent a dramatic revision of earlier estimates—and they are eagerly embraced by opponents of evolution. In creationist circles, the claim that humans and chimpanzees differ by only 1% genetically is now regarded as outdated or disproven. This claim is used to argue against a close genetic relationship between the two species. For instance, BORGER alias TERBORG (2019) writes (translated into English by MN):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The data of the 21st century show that the genetic gap between humans and chimpanzees is far greater than previously assumed and popularized by the media. When the media still claim that there is only a 1–2% genetic difference between humans and chimpanzees, they are relying on outdated knowledge that falsely implies humans are merely highly evolved apes.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The topic is discussed with astonishing frequency and freaky redundancy by the evangelical U.S.-based Discovery Institute. Between May 20 and June 26, 2025, the conservative Christian think tank published no fewer than &lt;i&gt;sixteen&lt;/i&gt; articles focused solely on this very issue, with particular emphasis on the aforementioned &lt;i&gt;Nature study&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Casey Luskin, Associate Director of the Center for Science and Culture at the Discovery Institute, adds a noticeably moralistic tone to his critique of the “1% myth.” He writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;For now, we can safely say that this latest study shows that the human and chimp genomes are at least 14.9 percent different. This means that the human and chimp genomes are at least &lt;i&gt;a full order of magnitude&lt;/i&gt; more dissimilar than the public is typically told.  … These are all groundbreaking findings — and it’s a shame that &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt; would not report the data clearly and would make all of this so hard to find — using jargon that most non-experts won’t understand. Why did they do this?” (LUSKIN 2025)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luskin expresses indignation that the figure showing the genomic similarities was “buried” deep in the supplementary materials of the study. He speculates that the “groundbreaking” nature of the findings may have motivated &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt; to present them as opaquely as possible. After all, the implications are significant: they challenge the supposed uniqueness of humans and call the 1% myth into question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But have these newer studies truly debunked the so-called 1% myth? Does a genetic difference of 15% really demand a re-evaluation of human origins? Or is creationism simply engaging in a game of obfuscation—cherry-picking half-truths while omitting crucial context and key information?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;header&gt;&lt;h4&gt; What Creationists Don’t Say
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the attention the recent &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt; study by YOO et al. (2025) has received, the figure included in the appendix of the paper does not actually reveal novel insights. The reported 15% difference refers to the fact that only about 85% of the human and chimpanzee genomes can be aligned base by base—that is, with exact positional correspondence of DNA sequences (see Fig. 1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for this discrepancy lies in larger insertions and deletions within the genomes, known as &lt;i&gt;InDels&lt;/i&gt;. These are stretches of DNA that have no direct counterpart in the other species’ genome—only gaps can be assigned in their place. Another factor is &lt;i&gt;translocations&lt;/i&gt;, in which entire segments of chromosomes have shifted to new positions, disrupting the linear alignment between the two genomes. These changes are the result of chromosomal mutations, which can affect dozens or even thousands of DNA bases at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Extended repeats&lt;/i&gt;—DNA base sequences (nucleotides) that occur multiple times consecutively in the genome—can also disrupt sequence alignment. These repeats can arise and expand due to errors during DNA replication (known as replication slippage) and mistakes in DNA repair. Mobile genetic elements, such as transposons, also contribute to the accumulation of repetitive sequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Transposable elements&lt;/i&gt; account for approximately 45% of the human genome, making them extremely common. Way above 90% of these elements have no function (MORAN 2023). They are predominantly found in non-coding regions, where they are less subject to negative selection. As a result, they have accumulated relatively freely over the course of evolution. These elements often affect larger segments of DNA at once, are highly dynamic, and show considerable variation even within a single species. &lt;i&gt;For these reasons, the gaps they cause in sequence alignments are generally not counted as individual nucleotide differences when assessing genetic similarity between species.&lt;/i&gt; Since such events usually affect entire blocks of nucleotides, each gap is typically counted as a single difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Tandem repeats&lt;/i&gt; are generally excluded from genome comparisons because their length is highly variable—even between closely related individuals. For example, every person carries &lt;i&gt;several thousand&lt;/i&gt; more differences in the tandem repeat regions of their genome than their parents. While this high variability makes tandem repeats useful for fine-scale analyses of genetic relatedness, they are unsuitable for comparing entire species. Similarly, &lt;i&gt;low-complexity regions&lt;/i&gt; (LCRs) are often ignored in genome comparisons. These regions can distort sequence alignments and lead to spurious homologies that do not reflect true evolutionary relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Neukamm_Fig_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Fig. 1: In a linear sequence comparison (sequence alignment), DNA sequences are arranged—and, if necessary, adjusted with gaps—so that as many bases as possible align with one another. In the example shown, the sequences differ at a single base position (the third position from the left). The insertion found in the human sequence (highlighted in red) is missing in the chimpanzee sequence and therefore appears as a gap in the alignment. 

Inserted or missing segments (InDels) are typically caused by a single mutation event—either an insertion or a deletion. For this reason, they are counted as a single difference. If the total sequence length is 60 bases, this corresponds to a difference of 3.3% (number of mutation events divided by sequence length). However, if all differing base positions—including the length of the gap—are considered, the difference amounts to 10 base positions, or 16.7%. Both values are correct in their own way, but when determining evolutionary distances, the number of individual mutation events is the decisive factor.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, contrary to creationist claims, the established methods for measuring genetic similarity—such as applying special rules for handling gaps—are well-founded and purposeful. These approaches are designed to account for the biological realities of genome structure and evolution. By selectively excluding certain sequence features (like tandem repeats or low-complexity regions), scientists aim to avoid misleading results and ensure that genetic comparisons accurately reflect evolutionary relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crucial point is this: In those regions where a direct comparison is possible and purposeful, analyses have consistently shown, for decades, a genetic similarity between humans and chimpanzees of 95 to 99%. The exact figure depends on which parts of the genome are being compared—whether coding regions (which produce proteins), introns (non-coding regions within genes), or intergenic regions (the DNA between genes). These values have been consistently confirmed by more recent scientific literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, KRONENBERG et al. (2018) divided the genomes of various primates into segments of one million bases each. They then examined the differences among these segments at the level of single nucleotide variants (SNVs)—that is, single-base changes. For each segment, they calculated how many of these SNVs differed from the human genome. The result: 1.27% of the DNA bases differ between humans and chimpanzees. For humans and gorillas, the difference is 1.61%, and for humans and orangutans, it rises to 3.12%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, SUNTSOVA &amp;amp; BUZDIN (2020) found that human-specific single-nucleotide changes account for approximately 1.23% of the human genome, while larger insertions and deletions (InDels) account for about 3%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;header&gt;&lt;h4&gt; Large Differences in Gene Regulation, Small Evolutionary Distance
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TERBORG (2019), writing from a creationist perspective, emphasizes that the differences between humans and chimpanzees are much greater at the level of gene regulation. According to him, it is not primarily the protein-coding genes that determine an organism’s characteristics, but rather the promoter regions of homologous genes (the “gene switches”) and regulatory elements such as miRNAs and HAR transcripts (human accelerated regions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, ironically, it is in the brain—arguably the most complex and uniquely human organ—where gene expression differences between humans and chimpanzees are particularly minimal, as shown by KHAITOVICH et al. (2005).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, larger differences in gene regulation do not negate the close genetic relationship or the evolutionary proximity between the species. A single mutation in a cis-regulatory element, or the duplication or variation of a miRNA gene can alter the activity of many genes at once. That regulatory divergence can result in significant phenotypic changes—without a corresponding increase in the number of actual mutational events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As explained in Fig. 1, it is not regulatory effects that count when determining evolutionary distances but &lt;i&gt;mutation events&lt;/i&gt;. That is why the oft-cited 1.2% difference remains the decisive metric. A single chromosomal mutation may impact thousands of base pairs, but it still counts as one event. It therefore makes little sense to claim “thousands of differences” when referring to what, in evolutionary terms, is one mutation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only when every base in a gap (alignment gap) is counted as a separate difference does one arrive at figures like 15%. This clearly illustrates how misleading creationist presentations can be. By pitting different measurement methods against one another, they create the impression that an earlier scientific claim (e.g., 99% similarity) has been disproven by more recent data (e.g., 85% similarity).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This narrative is simply false.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;header&gt;&lt;h4&gt; Up to 13.8% Genetic Difference – Within Gorillas Alone
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One key point creationists usually fail to mention: if you compare the genomes of different primate species and count every base, including those in alignment gaps, not only do the genome-wide differences between humans and chimpanzees increase—but so do the differences within a single species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to YOO et al. (2025), chimpanzees exhibit a genetic diversity of 8.8% within their own species. Even more striking: gorilla genomes differ from one another by up to 13.8%—within the same species!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even worse: If you consider only the gap divergence (without SNV differences), as is the case in the &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt; paper, you end up with a 13.3% difference between chimps and humans—&lt;i&gt;which is actually lower than the genetic variability found in gorillas!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that such vast diversity can exist within a species, the 15% difference between humans and chimpanzees is not only unsurprising—it is entirely expected, especially considering that their evolutionary lineages diverged roughly 7 million years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the genetic difference between chimpanzees and gorillas—both of which are considered “apes”—exceeds the 15% difference between humans and chimpanzees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These findings are evidently so inconvenient for creationists that they are not just ignored or omitted, but—as Daniel Stern Cardinale demonstrates in a YouTube video (https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VNs_lgWM6R8)— are intentionally obscured by LUSKIN (2025) (see Fig. 2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;header&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Do the Ends Justify the Means?
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luskin presents a figure from YOO et al. (2025) that illustrates the degree of genomic difference between humans and other primates. The figure counts each nucleotide within gaps as a separate difference. However, when one compares the image he shows with the original publication, a striking omission becomes immediately apparent: Luskin displays only the upper portion of the figure, which highlights the genetic differences between species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Neukamm_Fig_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Fig. 2: Left: Image from YOO et al. (2025), Supplementary Figure III.12. The data illustrate both the genetic differences between humans and various primate species and the intraspecific genetic variations. Right: Heavily cropped version of the figure as presented by LUSKIN (2025). The lower portion of the graphic, which shows intraspecies variation, was precisely cut out—without any acknowledgment. Luskin also moved the caption (“Gap difference in 1MB segment”) upward, creating the misleading impression that the figure is shown in full. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lower portion of the graphic—depicting intraspecific genetic variation—has been deliberately cropped out (see Fig. 2). The exposure of this tactic is revealing for two key reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the complete presentation of the data fundamentally undermines the creationist argument. If the gap divergence—within chimpanzees already amount to nearly 9%, and within gorillas to 14%, then the 13.3% difference between humans and chimpanzees suddenly appears remarkably small by comparison—unless the Discovery Institute seriously wants to claim that gorillas do not share a common ancestor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luskin was able to advance his argument only by withholding this crucial piece of information from his readers. &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, Luskin calls into question the integrity of evolutionary biology. He accuses the editors of the journal &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt; of deliberately hiding the “groundbreaking” findings deep within the supplementary material—implying manipulative intent. Yet, the opposite is true: the data are neither new nor revolutionary, nor do they constitute the central focus of the cited study. Luskin’s own manipulation of figures to obscure critical information lends an almost ironic twist to his critique. While his defense of purported higher truths may motivate the actions of this “design” advocate, the question remains whether the ends ever justify the means. &lt;sup&gt;ii&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;header&gt;&lt;h4&gt; Summary
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the method of comparison, the genetic difference between humans and chimpanzees is approximately 1.2% or around 15%. Evolution deniers deliberately emphasize the higher figure to portray the so-called “1% myth” as debunked. In doing so, they cast doubt on the genetic closeness between humans and other primates, and accuse evolutionary biology of clinging to outdated concepts. However, they overlook that the higher figure is based on a different methodology, which does not diminish the significance of the 1.2% estimate in any way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is even more troubling is their silence on the fact that this altered comparative approach also dramatically increases the measured genetic differences within primate species. For example, a recent study published in &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt; (YOO et al. 2025) reveals that, by the same method, the gorilla genome exhibits up to 14% variation within the species, and chimpanzees up to 9%. Against this backdrop, nothing has changed regarding the close genetic relationship between humans and chimpanzees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To obscure this fact, the Discovery Institute removed crucial data from a figure—showing a clear intention to deceive the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;header&gt;&lt;h4&gt; References
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/header&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KHAITOVICH, P.; HELLMANN, I.; ENARD, W. et al. (2005). Parallel patterns of evolution in the genomes and transcriptomes of humans and chimpanzees. Science 309, 1850–1854.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KRONENBERG, Z. N.; FIDDES, I. T.; GORDON, D. et al. (2018). High-resolution comparative analysis of great ape genomes. Science 360: eaar6343.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LUSKIN, C. (2025). Fact check: New “complete” chimp genome shows 14.9 percent difference from human genome. Available at: https://evolutionnews.org/2025/05/fact-check-new-complete-chimp-genome-shows-14-9-percent-difference-from-human-genome [Accessed 07 July 2025].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MORAN, L. (2023). What is in your genome? 90 % of your genome is junk. Aevo UTP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SUNTSOVA, M. V. &amp;amp; BUZDIN, A. A. (2020). Differences between human and chimpanzee genomes and their implications in gene expression, protein functions and biochemical properties of the two species. BMC Genomics 21: 535.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TERBORG, P. (2019). The genome of humans and chimpanzees: How close is the genetic relationship really? Studium Integrale Journal 26, 4–10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;YOO, D.; RHIE, A.; HEBBAR, P. et al. (2025). Complete sequencing of ape genomes. &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt; 641, 401–418.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;i&lt;/sup&gt; Luskin (2025) has since replaced the cropped image with the original version. In an addendum, he explains that the earlier omission was merely for the sake of “simplification purposes,” arguing that “intraspecific genetic differences” are “irrelevant” to his point. He writes: “My argument is not that human-ape genetic differences necessary [sic] refute evolution; it’s that evolutionists who for decades have claimed humans are only 1 percent genetically different from apes were wrong.” In my view, this addendum fails to conceal either Luskin’s intent to manipulate or the flaws of his reasoning. Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, he simply repeats the false claim that the 1% difference has been disproven. Second, the substantial intraspecific genetic variation in chimps and gorillas undermines the supposed “groundbreaking finding” of the 15% difference between humans and chimpanzees. This figure is neither “radical” nor does it carry meaningful “implications for human exceptionalism.” On the contrary, it aligns perfectly with what one would expect from an evolutionary perspective, considering that genetic diversity—when counting every base in the alignment gaps—reaches 9% in chimpanzees and 14% in gorillas. That alone discredits Luskin’s impertinent insinuation that evolutionary scientists had a motive to present their own data in a deliberately obscure way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luskin thus had every reason to conceal this additional information and crop the figure. His justification of “simplification” rings hollow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, his strong emphasis on the 15% difference clearly serves a rhetorical purpose: to cast doubt on the scientific consensus that humans are highly evolved apes. If this were not the underlying goal, the degree of genetic similarity between humans and chimpanzees would not be such a persistent point of contention for the Discovery Institute. The claim that this is not about challenging common ancestry (“refute evolution,” in his own words) is, quite plainly, a smokescreen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as Cardinale convincingly demonstrates in this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G1c7Z8DpJT4&quot;&gt;YouTube video&lt;/a&gt;, this addendum can conceal neither Luskin’s manipulative intent nor the flaws in his reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;ii &lt;/sup&gt; Unfortunately, this strategy is not an isolated case: In order to falsely accuse the anthropologist Owen Lovejoy of having manipulated a fossil, the Discovery Institute cut and edited a video documentary in a highly misleading way to serve their propagandistic aims. Crucial segments, including an audio track that explained Lovejoy’s methodology, were deliberately omitted. For a detailed account of this remarkable case, see this YouTube-Video of Dave Farina (Min. 8:40): https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HRxq1Vrf_Js&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Machine-translated and edited by the author from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ag-evolutionsbiologie.de/html/2025/mensch-schimpanse-genetischer-unterschied.html&quot;&gt;original German&lt;/a&gt;, and lightly edited and formatted by Matt Young.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Neukamm</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by lifeonwhite, depositphoto license. In academic circles, various figures are cited regarding the genetic similarity between humans and chimpanzees. Some studies estimate the differences to be around 1% to 5%, while others suggest they might be as high as 13% to 15% or more. Creationists claim that recent research has debunked the so-called “1% myth.” In doing so, they aim to cast doubt on the evolutionary relationship between humans and other primates, and accuse evolutionary biology of clinging to outdated dogmas. However, in order to make their argument persuasive, they deliberately omit crucial information. Casey Luskin of the evangelical think tank Discovery Institute even went so far as to crop a graphic published in the scientific journal Nature, intentionally removing key data. Are Human and Chimpanzee Genes Really 99% Identical? Few scientific discoveries have shaken humanity’s self-image as profoundly as Darwin’s insight that our origins lie within the animal kingdom. The idea that we are not uniquely created beings standing above nature, but instead share a common ancestry with chimpanzees, gorillas, and other primates, remains intellectually challenging for many. This notion is particularly unsettling for religious individuals who view humans as the “crown of creation.” The fear of losing a sense of human uniqueness runs deep. The realization that only 1.2% of our genes differ from those of chimpanzees hit like a bombshell; our shared evolutionary history becomes unmistakably clear. It’s no surprise that evolution deniers—broadly speaking, creationists—who reject our ancestral roots in the animal world, constantly question, downplay, and attack this close genetic relationship, branding it the “1% myth.” Recent studies, however, appear to support the creationist narrative. Some no longer report 95% or 99% genetic similarity, but instead present significantly lower numbers—sometimes as low as 85%. A recent study published in the journal Nature (YOO et al., 2025) confirms this approximate figure. An international research team offers a comprehensive reassessment of the genomic similarity between humans, chimpanzees, and other primate species, based on complete genome sequencing and comparative analysis of multiple primate genomes. The study combines high-resolution sequencing technologies with advanced bioinformatic methods to systematically detect both point mutations and structural genomic differences. The result: the total genome-wide difference between humans and chimpanzees is between approximately 13.3% and 14.9%.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The 100th Anniversary of the Scopes Monkey Trial is Here!</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/Scopes100_in_Nashville.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 100th Anniversary of the Scopes Monkey Trial is Here!" /><published>2025-07-09T18:01:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-09T18:01:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/Scopes100_in_Nashville</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/Scopes100_in_Nashville.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Matzke_Scopes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Nick Matzke at the Dayton County Courthouse, site of the 1925 Scopes Monkey Trial]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Nick Matzke at the Dayton County Courthouse where the Scopes Trial was held in 1925. (photo from ~2014)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One-hundred years ago, on a hot and humid summer day in the Tennessee River Valley in southeast Tennessee, teacher John Scopes, the ACLU, Clarence Darrow, and various lawyers and scientists tried to challenge the state of Tennessee’s ban on teaching human evolution. The national press descended on Dayton, and the audio was broadcast across the country in the first “Trial of the Century.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expert testimony was blocked, and Darrow, Scopes’s defense attorney, in frustration, asked to call prosecutor William Jennings Bryan (leader of the anti-evolution crusade, three-time presidential candidate, former Secretary of State, and populist politician) as a witness. Somehow this was allowed, and due to the heat, the proceedings were moved out onto the lawn. Darrow examined Bryan on the Bible and evolution, Bryan held his own, both sides concluded they were right, the national press lampooned the fundamentalists, but Scopes was convicted and fined (overturned on a technicality in 1927), and Bryan’s laws against teaching evolution remained on the books in many states and local jurisdictions until overturned by the 1968 &lt;i&gt;Epperson v. Arkansas&lt;/i&gt; Supreme Court case. The term “creation science” emerged right around then (Matzke 2009), rebranding Flood Geology and young-earth creationism as science. As that strategy failed in the 1981 &lt;i&gt;McLean vs. Arkansas&lt;/i&gt; case, creationists began work on a book called “Creation Biology”, which later became &lt;i&gt;Of Pandas and People&lt;/i&gt;, the original vehicle promoting “intelligent design” in schools.  The history of &lt;i&gt;Pandas&lt;/i&gt; was uncovered in the 2005 &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover&lt;/i&gt; case, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2005/11/missing-link-cd.html&quot;&gt;covered right here on the Panda’s Thumb blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so here we are in 2025! Today, I am finishing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hfsp.org/aam&quot;&gt;2025 Human Frontier Science Program (HFSP) meeting&lt;/a&gt; in Melbourne, Australia, where myself and collaborators talked about our research (my bit: a &lt;a href=&quot;http://phylo.wikidot.com/local--files/nicholas-j-matzke/Matzke_2025_HFSP_poster_v5.pdf&quot;&gt;Structural Phylogenetics of the Bacterial Flagellum&lt;/a&gt; poster). And I am getting on the plane and flying to Dallas, then Nashville, for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/KvDv19.html&quot;&gt;Scopes 100th meeting at Vanderbilt&lt;/a&gt;, which will also have a bunch of the people involved in &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover&lt;/i&gt;. While the antievolution issue has receded somewhat, challenges to science and science education are ever-present and can come from either political side, so I think the lessons of the Scopes Trial and its descendants are ever present. The main question is whether or not we will learn from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all of that, I am flying to Oklahoma to visit my 101-year old grandmother, who was born before the Scopes Trial and has seen everything since. Ironically she played a nontrivial role in my personal history, as it was my grandmother that sent me creationist books when I was a kid, which (as I eventually worked out) meant there were two radically different views of the history of life and humans out there. I remember being interested enough that I read Doug Futuyma’s (1982) &lt;i&gt;Science on Trial: The Case for Evolution&lt;/i&gt; in high school (perhaps 1991 or so). So when I got to college and took a course on Postmodernism and Science (in 1995), and discovered that the fundamentalists in the class actually really liked postmodernism even though it was a Leftist idea, I was well-prepared to make the case for evolution and science for both sides. In 1996, Behe’s book &lt;i&gt;Darwin’s Black Box&lt;/i&gt; was published and the ID movement was taking off. Around 1999 I got heavily involved in the online pro-evolution groups, and got to know (online) such talk.origins stalwarts as Wes Elsberry, John Wilkins, and Ian Musgrave.  In 2002 and 2003 I wrote some weighty talk.origins and talkdesign.org FAQs on favorite ID arguments, this lead to my working at NCSE, then the &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller&lt;/i&gt; case happened, then I got into Berkeley and got a Ph.D., then a series of postdocs and eventually I somehow got a job in New Zealand and occasionally find myself involved in not entirely dissimilar debates there. And also somehow found collaborators that wanted to work on the bacterial flagellum, and somehow happened on some new methods using protein structure to enhance phylogenies that are letting us make progress that was previously not imaginable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been quite a ride and I can’t quite believe it all happened the way it did. It seems like it would be a halfway-decent book, but as I now have 3 young daughters, good luck with that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I will try to blog the high points of the Scopes meeting and get some photos of participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S.: There has been some great press coverage of the &lt;i&gt;Scopes&lt;/i&gt; 100th, here are some of the links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NPR story on 100 years after Scopes, quoting Ken Miller
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/player/embed/nx-s1-5430760/nx-s1-5513367-1?fbclid=IwY2xjawLckNVleHRuA2FlbQIxMABicmlkETA2RDJLcDFaOGJFV1hueVVaAR4OSnbXt6oKbnutC83LrsdVgIKcYz8zSgJL0e958GUIS0hDTxn7v4HHaAw4CQ_aem_9Qj38T4Fq9IB3W8NP2pm_Q&quot;&gt;https://www.npr.org/player/embed/nx-s1-5430760/nx-s1-5513367-1?fbclid=IwY2xjawLckNVleHRuA2FlbQIxMABicmlkETA2RDJLcDFaOGJFV1hueVVaAR4OSnbXt6oKbnutC83LrsdVgIKcYz8zSgJL0e958GUIS0hDTxn7v4HHaAw4CQ_aem_9Qj38T4Fq9IB3W8NP2pm_Q&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NPR stories on 80 years after &lt;i&gt;Scopes&lt;/i&gt;, quoting…Ken Miller!
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/series/4726537/the-scopes-monkey-trial-80-years-later&quot;&gt;https://www.npr.org/series/4726537/the-scopes-monkey-trial-80-years-later&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some amazing video clips of the the &lt;i&gt;Scopes&lt;/i&gt; Trial, which I had forgotten existed, have been posted to Twitter, e.g.: &lt;a href=&quot;https://x.com/frad_fradi/status/1943268572634968422&quot;&gt;https://x.com/frad_fradi/status/1943268572634968422&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;b&gt;A century after a man was convicted of teaching evolution, the debate on religion in schools rages&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://apnews.com/article/religion-schools-church-state-scopes-monkey-trial-054773ed76ef36836e2f180d8d8d2802?utm_source=twitter&amp;amp;utm_medium=share&quot;&gt;https://apnews.com/article/religion-schools-church-state-scopes-monkey-trial-054773ed76ef36836e2f180d8d8d2802?utm_source=twitter&amp;amp;utm_medium=share&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
100 years after Scopes ‘Monkey Trial,’ religion in public schools hits courts again&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pennlive.com/nation-world/2025/07/100-years-after-scopes-monkey-trial-religion-in-public-schools-hits-courts-again.html?utm_campaign=pennlive_sf&amp;amp;utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_source=twitter&quot;&gt;https://www.pennlive.com/nation-world/2025/07/100-years-after-scopes-monkey-trial-religion-in-public-schools-hits-courts-again.html?utm_campaign=pennlive_sf&amp;amp;utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_source=twitter&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
Though a brief legal circus, the trial inflamed social divisions. Conservatives and fundamentalists in the Midwest and South felt mocked by those they considered liberal, East Coast elites. “They were humiliated,” Tuttle says. “That’s internalized, and it carries through.”
&lt;br /&gt;
In the 1940s, tensions flared with a school funding case before the Supreme Court. They returned in the 1960s when the justices ruled against school-sponsored prayer and Bible readings. It was upsetting, Tuttle says, to conservative Christians who saw schools as a source of morality.
&lt;br /&gt;
“The link you see with the Scopes case is a sense of alienation and devaluing of what civic experience means to them,” he says.
&lt;br /&gt;
Suzanne Rosenblith, an expert on religion in public education at the University at Buffalo in New York, sees the wave of court cases as primarily First Amendment tensions.
&lt;br /&gt;
“Your argument for removing something can be seen as ensuring that Congress makes no law respecting the establishment of religion. And my wanting something included, that’s my way of exercising my right to religious freedom,” she says. “And it could be on the same issue.”
&lt;br /&gt;
A lesson to be learned from the last 100 years, Rosenblith says, is that America remains a pluralist democracy and needs to be approached as such.
&lt;br /&gt;
“All sides are going to win some and lose some,” she says. “But how can we treat each other, especially those with whom we disagree on these significant issues, how do we treat each other more seriously?”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;b&gt;100 years after Scopes Monkey Trial, a new religious culture war emerges in Oklahoma&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
https://www.oklahoman.com/story/news/education/2025/07/10/ryan-walters-oklahoma-culture-war-religious-charter-school-bible-mandate/84076370007/
&lt;br /&gt;
A century after the famed Scopes Monkey Trial in Tennessee brought the concept of teaching evolution in public schools into a courtroom, thus testing cultural and religious norms of that era, another state is pushing to put the Bible back into the regular classroom rotation.
&lt;br /&gt;
Led by firebrand state schools Superintendent Ryan Walters, Oklahoma is forcing courts — as they did in Tennessee in 1925 — to wrestle with the thorny question of just how much religion is permissible in public schools.
&lt;br /&gt;
From a U.S. Supreme Court case involving what would have been the first public religious charter school in the nation, to a Bible-teaching edict issued for schools by Walters, to new social studies academic standards infused with references to Christianity and 2020 election-denial language, Oklahoma — a ruby-red state politically — is at the center of a national conversation about Christian nationalism being taught to students.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Science, scripture &amp;amp; Scopes: 100 years since Dayton, Tennessee trial captivated the nation&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://chattanoogacw.com/news/local/science-scripture-and-scopes-100-years-later-evolution-creationism-debate-darwin-schools-rhea-county-tennessee-1925-inherit-the-wind-clarence-darrow-william-jennings-bryan-john-scopes-schoolteacher&quot;&gt;https://chattanoogacw.com/news/local/science-scripture-and-scopes-100-years-later-evolution-creationism-debate-darwin-schools-rhea-county-tennessee-1925-inherit-the-wind-clarence-darrow-william-jennings-bryan-john-scopes-schoolteacher&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

[This story has lots of great photos / videos, and quotes from locals]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;b&gt;Trial of the century: Why 100 years later, the Scopes case still matters&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tennessean.com/story/news/education/2025/07/10/scopes-monkey-trial-100th-anniversary-dayton-tennessee/83395548007/&quot;&gt;https://www.tennessean.com/story/news/education/2025/07/10/scopes-monkey-trial-100th-anniversary-dayton-tennessee/83395548007/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

The trial that followed was heated. Spectators swarmed in from around the country to see the legendary lawyers battle over creationism, evolution and the role of religion in government.&lt;br /&gt;

The courtroom was so overcrowded at one point that town officials warned the building might collapse, prompting the judge to set up a temporary court outside to appease the masses.&lt;br /&gt;


Audiences across the country tuned in to the trial as well, both through radio and newspaper. The trial was the first to be broadcast live on radio in American history, with Chicago's WGN Radio spending $1,000 a day — equivalent to over $18,000 a day in today's economy — to run cables from Chicago, Illinois to Dayton, Tennessee to provide live gavel-to-gavel coverage of the &quot;trial of the century.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;

Famous journalist and commentator Henry Louis “H.L.” Mencken, who wrote for the Baltimore Sun at the time of the trial, wrote daily columns for the paper covering the ordeal and famously dubbed the proceedings as &quot;The Monkey Trial.”&lt;br /&gt;

The expansive audience placed pressure on the lawyers. After facing significant roadblocks in his defense, Darrow changed tactics and called Bryan to the stand in an attempt to prove Bryan’s literal interpretation of the Bible was unfit to base laws on.&lt;br /&gt;

Clarence Darrow questions William Jennings Bryan in Scopes trial.
“Bryan had a lot of difficulty with (Darrow’s questions), and many of them were not very subtle or sophisticated questions,” Branch said. “One of the questions that Darrow asked was ‘Where did Cain, the second son of Adam and Eve, find his wife?’ And Bryan had no kind of answer for this. He said ‘I leave the atheist to look for her.’”&lt;br /&gt;

The grueling examination left Bryan scrambling and humiliated.&lt;br /&gt;

“Darrow was quite relentless, and in many people's opinion, especially the big city reporters, Bryan came across not only as ignorant, but as complacent about his ignorance,” Branch said.&lt;br /&gt;


In Darrow’s closing arguments, he asked the jury to return a guilty verdict so he could try the case on appeal — where he would have more room to argue the law itself was unconstitutional. And in a clever legal maneuver, Darrow denied Bryan the chance to give his own closing argument that he had been anticipating for weeks.&lt;br /&gt;

After only nine minutes of deliberation, the jury returned the desired guilty verdict. And while Scopes got away with paying a $100 fine, about $1,800 in today's dollars, Bryan left the court disgraced. He died just five days later on a Sunday afternoon − in Dayton.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;b&gt;How Theater Helps Us Remember the Scopes Monkey Trial 100 Years Later&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;https://time.com/7294045/theater-scopes-monkey-trial-100-years/
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
One hundred years ago today, live radio began broadcasting what would be soon termed the “trial of the century.”&lt;br /&gt;

The state of Tennessee had charged a high school biology teacher, John Scopes, with violating the Butler Act, which prohibited “the teaching of the Evolution Theory in all...public schools.”&lt;br /&gt;

Americans remember the Scopes Trial, or the “Monkey Trial,” as it was popularly dubbed, as a landmark fight for freedom of thought and a heroic stance against “ignorance” (as defense attorney Clarence Darrow put it). The trial resonated nationally because it brought the question of the place of science and religion in education to the forefront of public debate. Science, as defended by Scopes' legal team for 11 days, made the more compelling case to radio listeners across the country.&lt;br /&gt;

What is often forgotten, however, is that Scopes lost, personally and legally. State legislators didn’t repeal the Butler Act until 1967 and he never taught again in Tennessee or anywhere else. When Scopes tried to earn a PhD, as he recounted in his memoirs, the president “of one of most respected universities” wrote: “Your name has been removed from consideration...you can take your atheistic marbles and play elsewhere.”&lt;br /&gt;

The selective public memory reflects how two Ohio playwrights, Jerome Lawrence and Robert E. Lee, rewrote the history for their 1955 play Inherit the Wind. They transformed the Scopes trial from a specific historical moment into a legendary and heroic dissent from mainstream orthodoxy. The play is a reminder of theater’s power to demonstrate the meanings inherent in our daily lives by bringing structure and intent to what we experience as a chaotic jumble of events. Inherit the Wind is a perfect example of how theater can change the distant past into a very relevant and urgent present.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there are some essays. Here, the New York Times tries to give advice to Democrats. It actually suggests bringing back some Bryan-style populism. I’m not sure that’s the right lesson. I’d look more to Darrow – be rigorously skeptical of everything, even “your own” side, and acknowledge that public disagreement and debate are good, not bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;b&gt;This ‘Trial of the Century’ Is 100. Its Lessons Could Save the Democrats.&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2025/07/10/opinion/scopes-monkey-trial-democrats.html?smid=nytcore-ios-share&amp;amp;referringSource=articleShare&quot;&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2025/07/10/opinion/scopes-monkey-trial-democrats.html?smid=nytcore-ios-share&amp;amp;referringSource=articleShare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is a less-good piece, it points out the historical inaccuracies of Inherit the Wind (but these have been pointed out many times before), but then it claims that William Jennings Bryan was against eugenics, which is actually incorrect; Bryan endorsed eugenics in the early 1920s, and it was the cynical civil libertarian activist Clarence Darrow that came out hard and early against eugenics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;b&gt;Modernist Folklore: Sowing The Narrative and Inheriting The Wind&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://decadentserpent.com/2025/07/10/modernist-folklore-sowing-the-narrative-and-inheriting-the-wind/&quot;&gt;https://decadentserpent.com/2025/07/10/modernist-folklore-sowing-the-narrative-and-inheriting-the-wind/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author doesn’t like “modernism”, presumably he’s coming from a conservative religious viewpoint, although ironically you can see quite similar arguments on the postmodernist part of the Left.  I kind of like modernism and its morality plays like &lt;i&gt;Inherit the Wind&lt;/i&gt;. We could (and have) done worse. Sue me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;References&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matzke et al. (2025). Structural Phylogenetics of the Bacterial Flagellum. Poster at the 2025 annual meeting of the Human Frontier Science Program, 2025-07-08. &lt;a href=&quot;http://phylo.wikidot.com/local--files/nicholas-j-matzke/Matzke_2025_HFSP_poster_v5.pdf&quot;&gt;http://phylo.wikidot.com/local–files/nicholas-j-matzke/Matzke_2025_HFSP_poster_v5.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matzke, N. (2009). “But Isn’t It Creationism? The beginnings of ‘intelligent design’ and Of Pandas and People in the midst of the Arkansas and Louisiana litigation.” But Is It Science?: The Philosophical Question in the Creation/Evolution Controversy, Updated Edition, edited by Robert Pennock and Michael Ruse. Prometheus Books, Amherst, New York, pp. 377-413. 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://phylo.wdfiles.com/local--files/nicholas-j-matzke/Matzke_2009_ID_origins_But_Is_It_Science.pdf&quot;&gt;https://phylo.wdfiles.com/local–files/nicholas-j-matzke/Matzke_2009_ID_origins_But_Is_It_Science.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vanderbilt-university-scopes-trial-symposium-july-12-13-2025&quot;&gt;Vanderbilt University, Scopes Trial Symposium, July 12-13, 2025&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/2025-07-12_Scopes_Trial_Symposium_at_Vanderbilt.png&quot; alt=&quot;[Vanderbilt Scopes Trial Symposium schedule, July 12-13, 2025]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Vanderbilt Scopes Trial Symposium schedule, July 12-13, 2025&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vanderbilt.edu/evolution/scopes-symposium/&quot;&gt;Scopes &quot;Monkey&quot; Trial Centennial Symposium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Vanderbilt University, July 12-13, 2025&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vanderbilt.edu/evolution/scopes-symposium/&quot;&gt;https://www.vanderbilt.edu/evolution/scopes-symposium/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
...following on from...&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;ISEMPH 2025 Meeting&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
International Society for Evolution, Medicine, and Public Health&lt;br /&gt;
Vanderbilt University, July 8-10, 2025&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The weekend following the ISEMPH conference (7/12/25 – 7/13/25), we will host an academic symposium featuring dozens of wonderful guest speakers from around the world. This event is sponsored in part by the National Center for Science Education. Leading experts (Ed Larson, Randy Moore, and Adam Laats) on all things Scopes will speak about the history of the trial. Next, we’ll hear about issues facing teachers today as they try to navigate teaching evolution (Barbara Forrest, Kenneth Miller, Amanda Townley). Then, we will hear from folks at the forefront of their evolution-focused fields about their research (Sean Carroll, Jonathan Losos, Marlene Zuk, Stephen Brusatte, and Briana Pobiner). We’ll finish off Day 1 with a roundtable discussion on evolutionary science in the 21st century.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Day 2 will kick off with evolutionary research in fields other than biology, such as medicine (Paul Turner), agriculture (Sophien Kamoun), and the law (Owen Jones). After that, we’ll have another section on teaching evolution in a broader sense (Gale Sinatra, Patricia Hawley, Corrie Moreau, Riley Black, and Joseph Graves, Jr.). Our last proper session will be on the relationship of evolution and religion (Jamie Jensen, Katy Hinman, Liz Barnes and Lee Meadows). We’ll end with a second roundtable discussion on the future of evolution education.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Matzke</name></author><summary type="html">Nick Matzke at the Dayton County Courthouse where the Scopes Trial was held in 1925. (photo from ~2014) One-hundred years ago, on a hot and humid summer day in the Tennessee River Valley in southeast Tennessee, teacher John Scopes, the ACLU, Clarence Darrow, and various lawyers and scientists tried to challenge the state of Tennessee’s ban on teaching human evolution. The national press descended on Dayton, and the audio was broadcast across the country in the first “Trial of the Century.” The expert testimony was blocked, and Darrow, Scopes’s defense attorney, in frustration, asked to call prosecutor William Jennings Bryan (leader of the anti-evolution crusade, three-time presidential candidate, former Secretary of State, and populist politician) as a witness. Somehow this was allowed, and due to the heat, the proceedings were moved out onto the lawn. Darrow examined Bryan on the Bible and evolution, Bryan held his own, both sides concluded they were right, the national press lampooned the fundamentalists, but Scopes was convicted and fined (overturned on a technicality in 1927), and Bryan’s laws against teaching evolution remained on the books in many states and local jurisdictions until overturned by the 1968 Epperson v. Arkansas Supreme Court case. The term “creation science” emerged right around then (Matzke 2009), rebranding Flood Geology and young-earth creationism as science. As that strategy failed in the 1981 McLean vs. Arkansas case, creationists began work on a book called “Creation Biology”, which later became Of Pandas and People, the original vehicle promoting “intelligent design” in schools. The history of Pandas was uncovered in the 2005 Kitzmiller v. Dover case, covered right here on the Panda’s Thumb blog. And so here we are in 2025! Today, I am finishing the 2025 Human Frontier Science Program (HFSP) meeting in Melbourne, Australia, where myself and collaborators talked about our research (my bit: a Structural Phylogenetics of the Bacterial Flagellum poster). And I am getting on the plane and flying to Dallas, then Nashville, for the Scopes 100th meeting at Vanderbilt, which will also have a bunch of the people involved in Kitzmiller v. Dover. While the antievolution issue has receded somewhat, challenges to science and science education are ever-present and can come from either political side, so I think the lessons of the Scopes Trial and its descendants are ever present. The main question is whether or not we will learn from them.</summary></entry></feed>