<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-11-18T16:02:51-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Counterexample to Mark Champneys’ argument about natural selection: more technical details</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/counterexample-to-mark-champneys-details.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Counterexample to Mark Champneys’ argument about natural selection: more technical details" /><published>2020-11-14T01:17:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-11-14T01:17:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/counterexample-to-mark-champneys-details</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/counterexample-to-mark-champneys-details.html">&lt;p&gt;This post will supply some more technical details of my counterexample to
Mark Champneys’ arguments that approach of physical and biological systems
to equilibrium prevents natural selection from being effective.  The counterexample is explained in &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/does-approach-toward-higher-probability.html&quot;&gt;my previous post&lt;/a&gt;.  Below I
provide the relevant equations and some simulation results showing what
the effect of genetic drift will be.  To avoid taking up too much space on the
site’s front page, I will put most of that content “below the fold” …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Population genetics theory&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The model had a very large (effectively infinite) population of haploid organisms, for which we are following 100 sites in their DNA.  Mutation is symmetrical among all
four possible nucleotides at rate  &lt;em&gt;u&lt;/em&gt;, with each mutational event equally likely
to result in each of the other 3 possible bases.  We are following the frequency
of the C allele at each site.  It has fitness a fraction &lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt; greater than the three other nucleotides, which have fitness &lt;em&gt;1&lt;/em&gt;.  So the fitness of C is &lt;em&gt;1+s&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each generation starts by producing a large number of offspring, with mutation
happening at that time.  So if the fraction of all copies of the site that have C is
&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;, after mutation a fraction &lt;em&gt;u&lt;/em&gt; of those have changed to another base, and
a fraction &lt;em&gt;u/3&lt;/em&gt; of the non-C bases have changed and become C.  Thus the
frequency of allele C is then &lt;em&gt;p’&lt;/em&gt;, where&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p’ =  p(1-u) + (u/3)(1-p)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then these individuals undergo natural selection.  &lt;em&gt;(1-p’)&lt;/em&gt; of the copies are
non-C bases, and &lt;em&gt;p’&lt;/em&gt; of the copies are C.  As these have fitnesses &lt;em&gt;1&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;1+s&lt;/em&gt;,
their numbers after selection will be proportional to  &lt;em&gt;(1-p’)&lt;/em&gt;  and  &lt;em&gt;p’(1+s)&lt;/em&gt;,
so that the fraction of copies that are C will then become&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p’(1+s) / ((1-p’) + p’(1+s)),&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p’(1+s) / (1 + p’ s).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applying these two formulas in that order, we get after a full generation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(p(1-u) + (u/3)(1-p)) (1+s) / (1 + (p(1-u) + (u/3)(1-p)) s )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we have reached the equilibrium gene frequency, this is again &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;, so
that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p  =  (p(1-u) + (u/3)(1-p) )(1+s) / (1 + (p(1-u) + (u/3)(1-p)) s ).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multiplying through by the denominator and collecting terms, after some struggle
we end up with the quadratic equation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;s(1-(4/3)u) p^2  +  p( (4u/3) - s + (5/3)us)  - (u/3)(1+s)  = 0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solving this for  &lt;em&gt;u = 0.0001&lt;/em&gt; and  &lt;em&gt;s = 0&lt;/em&gt;, we get  &lt;em&gt;p = 1/4&lt;/em&gt;, the obvious answer from
the symmetry of the mutational model.  When &lt;em&gt;s = 0.005&lt;/em&gt;, the equation becomes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;0.004999333 p^2 - 0.00486583333 p - 0.0000335  =  0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;whose positive root is the equilibrium frequency,  &lt;em&gt;p = 0.980133157&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simulations showing the effect of genetic drift&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the 100 sites are far enough apart to have noticeable levels of recombination
between them, and if their fitnesses combine multiplicatively, then each site can be regarded as evolving independently.  If the population size is not infinite but, say, 20,000 then we can use a single-locus genetic simulation program such as the teaching program PopG produced by my laboratory.  It is a Java application that can be downloaded from the site  &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution.gs.washington.edu/popg/popg.html&quot;&gt;https://evolution.gs.washington.edu/popg/popg.html&lt;/a&gt; at our webserver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program is for a diploid population, but by making the diploid population size be
10,000 and making the fitnesses of the genotypes be powers of &lt;em&gt;(1+s)&lt;/em&gt;, it will give the same results as a haploid population twice the size and with fitnesses &lt;em&gt;(1+s) ; 1&lt;/em&gt;.  So I ran the program with 5 independent populations and 10,000 diploid individuals per population, and fitnesses of &lt;em&gt;AA&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Aa&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;aa&lt;/em&gt; of  &lt;em&gt;1.010025 : 1.005 : 1&lt;/em&gt;, and this is equivalent to having &lt;em&gt;20,000&lt;/em&gt; haploid individuals with fitnesses &lt;em&gt;1.005 : 1&lt;/em&gt; for &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
We have mutation rate from &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; to non-&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; of 0.0001 and from non-&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; of one-third that value,
&lt;em&gt;0.000033333&lt;/em&gt;.  Note that in these cases allele A stands in for the selectively favored base, C.
The figure below shows two runs, each with 5 populations, which is equivalent to following 5 sites:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/champneys3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see the mutational equilibrium in the absence of natural selection on the left,
and the effect of selection with mutation in the figure on the right.  The smooth blue
curve shows what would have happened without genetic drift.  With a larger population
the individual sites would have remained closer to the smooth blue curves.
The 50 individual sites will vary in gene frequency, as these 5 do,  The result will
be distributions a bit wider than the original  binomial distributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Without genetic drift&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a very large population, where we can ignore genetic drift, each site has the
frequency of the C allele change.  At any generation, all 100 sites will have equal
gene frequencies.  Thus the distribution of the numbers of C’s in the haploid
genomes will follow the binomial distribution, with 100 trials, each with a probability
of C that is 1/4 (if there is no natural selection) or each with a probability of C
that is 0.980133157.  The state of the population will be a binomial distribution of
the number of C’s,  and this distribution will either approach an average of 25 C’s or an average of 98.0133157 C’s, depending on whether there is not or is natural selection.  Like an idealized gas, the individuals will vary randomly, but the distribution of their properties will be a distribution that changes deterministically, from generation to generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like gas in a container that is evenly distributed when there is no gravity, but collects at the bottom of the container if the whole thing is placed in a strong gravitational field, the population approaches an equilibrium which is different whether there is or is not natural selection.  And that simple fact disproves the statements Mark Champneys made in his video about movement towards equilibrium preventing natural selection from having any long-term effect.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">This post will supply some more technical details of my counterexample to Mark Champneys’ arguments that approach of physical and biological systems to equilibrium prevents natural selection from being effective. The counterexample is explained in my previous post. Below I provide the relevant equations and some simulation results showing what the effect of genetic drift will be. To avoid taking up too much space on the site’s front page, I will put most of that content “below the fold” …</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Less than optimistic view of Pfizer vaccine</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/Pfizer-vaccine.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Less than optimistic view of Pfizer vaccine" /><published>2020-11-11T11:11:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-11-11T11:11:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/Pfizer-vaccine</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/Pfizer-vaccine.html">&lt;p&gt;I heard an interview with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laurie_Garrett&quot;&gt;Laurie Garrett&lt;/a&gt; last night on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.democracynow.org/&quot;&gt;Democracy Now&lt;/a&gt;. Ms. Garrett, a distinguished science journalist and the author of the apparently prescient 1995 book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Coming-Plague-Emerging-Diseases-Balance/dp/0140250913&quot;&gt;The Coming Plague: Newly Emerging Diseases in a World out of Balance&lt;/a&gt;, is not quite as optimistic as the stock market regarding Pfizer’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pfizer.com/news/press-release/press-release-detail/pfizer-and-biontech-announce-vaccine-candidate-against&quot;&gt;recent announcement&lt;/a&gt; of a potentially successful coronavirus vaccine. So I looked up Ms. Garrett’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://foreignpolicy.com/2020/11/10/the-vaccine-news-is-good-heres-the-bad-news/&quot;&gt;recent article in &lt;em&gt;Foreign Policy&lt;/em&gt; magazine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms. Garrett seems generally pessimistic, because cases are surging, the United States has roughly one-fifth of known cases worldwide, and possibly one-third (!) of the population will probably refuse a vaccine, once one is available. Though optimistic that President-Elect Biden has appointed a Covid task force, she also notes that the present lame-duck administration will be in charge for more than two months and the presidential scientific advisor, Scott Atlas, advocates “what amounts to a do-nothing approach to Covid-19 control” (as we noted &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/are-creationists-dictating.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Ms. Garrett foresees a “mass exodus” of health officials from the government this fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about the vaccine? Ms. Garrett says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But let’s be clear about what this Pfizer study shows so far: For 90 percent of the volunteers who got the vaccine (as opposed to a placebo), SARS-CoV-2 infection did not occur for a study period of seven days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Seven days&lt;/em&gt;. Nothing more is known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If that protection turns out to be durable for, say, a full year, the Pfizer vaccine might be deemed a spectacular success. But nobody is going to wait a year to find out. The moment the FDA approves the product, Pfizer says in its press release, “we expect to produce globally up to 50 million vaccine doses in 2020 and up to 1.3 billion doses in 2021.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vaccine, however, is made of messenger RNA and as such “is unlike any vaccine ever used, for any disease.” It requires storage at a temperature of -103 °F (or -75 °C in God’s units) – well below typical refrigeration temperatures, and there is apparently a shortage of dry ice (-78 °C).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://cspinet.org/news/beyond-the-curve/causes-for-hope&quot;&gt;generally positive article&lt;/a&gt; praising President-Elect Biden’s Covid-19 task force and also his plan to ensure, among other things, that “public health decisions are made by public health professionals,” Peter Lurie of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cspinet.org/&quot;&gt;Center for Science in the Public Interest&lt;/a&gt; observes that the claimed 90 % is well beyond the minimum requirement of the FDA. He wants to know, however,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How many cases were in the treated and placebo groups? How serious were the cases? How many people have been followed in the trial and for how long? How big is the vaccine’s safety database and what does it show?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and, in particular, he notes that Pfizer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;pointedly declined support from Operation Warp Speed, [and] may not be subject to the same constraints upon pricing that those who signed up for the program might feel obligated to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I heard an interview with Laurie Garrett last night on Democracy Now. Ms. Garrett, a distinguished science journalist and the author of the apparently prescient 1995 book, The Coming Plague: Newly Emerging Diseases in a World out of Balance, is not quite as optimistic as the stock market regarding Pfizer’s recent announcement of a potentially successful coronavirus vaccine. So I looked up Ms. Garrett’s recent article in Foreign Policy magazine. Ms. Garrett seems generally pessimistic, because cases are surging, the United States has roughly one-fifth of known cases worldwide, and possibly one-third (!) of the population will probably refuse a vaccine, once one is available. Though optimistic that President-Elect Biden has appointed a Covid task force, she also notes that the present lame-duck administration will be in charge for more than two months and the presidential scientific advisor, Scott Atlas, advocates “what amounts to a do-nothing approach to Covid-19 control” (as we noted here). Ms. Garrett foresees a “mass exodus” of health officials from the government this fall. What about the vaccine? Ms. Garrett says,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pyronia tithonus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/Pyronia-tithonus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pyronia tithonus" /><published>2020-11-09T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-11-09T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/Pyronia-tithonus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/Pyronia-tithonus.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Marilyn Susek&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photogaphy Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Susek_Gatekeeper-Butterfly.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Butterfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ukbutterflies.co.uk/species.php?species=tithonus&quot;&gt;Pyronia tithonus&lt;/a&gt;, gatekeeper butterfly. The photographer writes, &quot;This photograph was taken at my garden in Rotherham, S. Yorkshire, UK. I noticed that the under wing of this gatekeeper is not the same as other photos of gatekeeper butterflies. It is sitting on an Echinacea.&quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Marilyn Susek. Photogaphy Contest, Honorable Mention. Pyronia tithonus, gatekeeper butterfly. The photographer writes, &quot;This photograph was taken at my garden in Rotherham, S. Yorkshire, UK. I noticed that the under wing of this gatekeeper is not the same as other photos of gatekeeper butterflies. It is sitting on an Echinacea.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Are creationists dictating Covid policy?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/are-creationists-dictating.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are creationists dictating Covid policy?" /><published>2020-11-04T10:24:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-11-04T10:24:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/are-creationists-dictating</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/are-creationists-dictating.html">&lt;p&gt;Are creationists dictating Covid policy? We just received an article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rightwingwatch.org/post/exclusive-far-right-creationists-are-setting-trumps-virus-response/&quot;&gt;Far-Right Creationists Are Setting Trump’s Virus Response&lt;/a&gt;, by Matthew Sheffield, which suggests precisely that. Mr. Sheffield’s article is posted in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rightwingwatch.org/&quot;&gt;Right Wing Watch&lt;/a&gt;, a “project” of the progressive organization People For the American Way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Sheffield begins by noting that Mark Meadows, Mr. Trump’s chief of staff, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/2020/10/25/politics/mark-meadows-controlling-coronavirus-pandemic-cnntv/index.html&quot;&gt;told Jake Tapper of CNN&lt;/a&gt;, “We are not going to control the pandemic … because it’s a contagious virus” (does he think we could control it better if it were a non-contagious virus?). Mr. Meadows may or may not be a creationist, but he is certainly a fellow traveler: At one time, he &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/news/news-desk/mark-meadows-and-the-undisclosed-dinosaur-property&quot;&gt;purchased a piece of property&lt;/a&gt; on which an &lt;em&gt;Allosaurus&lt;/em&gt; specimen had been discovered (supposedly by some home-schooled children). He then sold the property to Answers in Genesis, arguably in order to keep the fossils under the control of young-earth creationists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Vice-President, Mike Pence, heads the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_House_Coronavirus_Task_Force&quot;&gt;White House Coronavirus Task Force&lt;/a&gt;. On August 8, 2016, Mr. Sheffield reminds us, Mr. Pence said, in a somewhat rambling &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.c-span.org/video/?c4617037/user-clip-mike-pence-evolution&quot;&gt;speech on the floor of the House&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I believe that God created the known universe, the earth, and everything in it, including man. And I also believe that some day scientists will come to see that only the theory of intelligent design provides [an] even remotely rational explanation for the known universe, but until that day comes and [sic] I have no fear of science. I believe that the more we study the science, the more the truths of faith will become apparent. I just would humbly ask, as new theories of evolution find their ways into the newspapers and into the textbooks, let us demand that educators around America teach evolution not as fact but as theory. And an interesting theory to boot.
But let’s also bring into the minds of all of our children all of the theories about the unknowable that some bright day in the future, through science and perhaps through faith, we will find the truth from whence we come[.] [Lightly edited from a user clip, not recorded by C-Span.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be hard to argue that Mr. Pence was not a creationist, though conceivably not a young-earth creationist. In the statement above, contrary to Mr. Sheffield, he did not claim “that science is too changeable to be trusted, and that schools should also teach that humans were ‘created’ by God in their current form,” though he certainly mentioned all the old creationist shibboleths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://profiles.stanford.edu/scott-atlas&quot;&gt;Scott Atlas&lt;/a&gt;, the White House’s advisor on Covid-19, appears to have been a fairly prolific neuroradiologist before he joined the Hoover Institution, a right-wing think tank. Mr. Sheffield is impressed by the fact that Dr. Atlas is in turn impressed by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the COVID-19 mitigation proposals of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Gilder&quot;&gt;George Gilder&lt;/a&gt;, co-founder of the Discovery Institute, a Seattle-based think tank that specializes in promoting supply-side economics, climate science denial, and “intelligent design,” a spit-polished version of creationism which focuses more on attacking “Darwinism” than promoting biblical fundamentalism. According to Atlas, Gilder’s recommendation to “defer as much as possible to the principles of freedom” was “right on target.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Sheffield details how Mr. Gilder “has also applied his particular blend of junk economics and junk science” elsewhere, but I want to concentrate on Dr. Atlas. Dr. Atlas is not a virologist, an infectious-disease specialist, or an epidemiologist. Nevertheless, he has been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/09/02/us/politics/trump-scott-atlas-coronavirus.html&quot;&gt;advising the White House&lt;/a&gt; to let the virus run its course and rely on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-02948-4&quot;&gt;herd immunity&lt;/a&gt;, while protecting “vulnerable populations.” As far as I can determine, no true experts, not least Anthony Fauci, Deborah Birx, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/stanford-colleagues-warn-dr-scott-atlas-fosters-falsehoods/story&quot;&gt;78 of his former colleagues&lt;/a&gt; at Stanford Medical School agree with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he is he a creationist? Neither the &lt;em&gt;Times&lt;/em&gt; article nor his Wikipedia entry hints that he is a creationist of any kind, let alone a young-earth creationist, which I think is what we mean when we use the term unadorned. At most, Mr. Sheffield has established, in his case, a kind of guilt by association, and the association is mostly with Mr. Gilder and the Discovery Institute, not Mr. Meadows and Mr. Pence. Even so, it seems to me that a creationist is not necessarily wrong about everything else, nor is every so-called libertarian necessarily in favor of inaptly applying a political position, such as “the principles of freedom,” to a medical problem, such as Covid-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, Mr. Meadows and Mr. Pence may be creationists, depending on your definition. But if Mr. Sheffield is trying to connect Dr. Atlas to creationism, broadly construed, it seems to me that he is on the wrong track: the connection is both tenuous and irrelevant to Dr. Atlas’s position on Covid-19. I think that Dr. Atlas is wrong because he is wrong, and not because he has colleagues who are creationists. And I think I will leave it at that.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Are creationists dictating Covid policy? We just received an article, Far-Right Creationists Are Setting Trump’s Virus Response, by Matthew Sheffield, which suggests precisely that. Mr. Sheffield’s article is posted in Right Wing Watch, a “project” of the progressive organization People For the American Way. Mr. Sheffield begins by noting that Mark Meadows, Mr. Trump’s chief of staff, told Jake Tapper of CNN, “We are not going to control the pandemic … because it’s a contagious virus” (does he think we could control it better if it were a non-contagious virus?). Mr. Meadows may or may not be a creationist, but he is certainly a fellow traveler: At one time, he purchased a piece of property on which an Allosaurus specimen had been discovered (supposedly by some home-schooled children). He then sold the property to Answers in Genesis, arguably in order to keep the fossils under the control of young-earth creationists. The Vice-President, Mike Pence, heads the White House Coronavirus Task Force. On August 8, 2016, Mr. Sheffield reminds us, Mr. Pence said, in a somewhat rambling speech on the floor of the House,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Behe likens Dover trial to Kafka's The Trial</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/behe-likens-dover.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Behe likens Dover trial to Kafka's The Trial" /><published>2020-10-31T08:33:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-31T08:33:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/behe-likens-dover</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/behe-likens-dover.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Behe_Swamidass.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Interview&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Interview, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ltmhpG8fydM&quot;&gt;Michael Behe: Kafka at the Dover trial&lt;/a&gt; with Joshua Swamidass and Michael Behe.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our colleague Joshua Swamidass &lt;a href=&quot;https://peacefulscience.org/dover-behe/&quot;&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt; on the blog Peaceful Science that he was interviewed yesterday along with Michael Behe. I have not yet had a chance to watch the interview, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ltmhpG8fydM&quot;&gt;Michael Behe: Kafka at the Dover trial&lt;/a&gt; (actually, I am hoping for a transcript), so I will merely note that Dr. Behe apparently compared the Dover trial to the book &lt;em&gt;The Trial&lt;/em&gt; by Franz Kafka. I have read &lt;em&gt;The Trial&lt;/em&gt; and also much of the transcript of the Dover trial, and I find that claim astonishing though, as I said, I have not actually seen the interview yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At any rate, here is part of what Dr. Swamidass has to say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…The Dover Trial was one of the central and defining events of my time in graduate school. So this was a remarkable opportunity for me, a chance to talk directly with one of the key participants in this moment of history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mike and I certainly have our disagreements. Nathan H. Lents, Richard Lenski, and I reviewed his last book, &lt;em&gt;Darwin Devolves&lt;/em&gt;, a couple years ago. It was not a positive review. But I actually agree with Behe on more than most people expect. In the end, Intelligent Design looks like a “garden path” to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The tension between our agreement, on the on hand, and our disagreement, on the other, makes conversation with Mike exciting for me. We are both Christians that believe God created humans through a providentially governed process of common descent. We also do not see clear biochemical evidence for God’s guidance in human evolution. So where exactly do we disagree? Honestly, on human evolution, I am not exactly sure. Maybe you can help us figure out that puzzle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The exchange in this conversation was fun. We discussed Irreducible Complexity too. I explain why I’m not convinced by his argument, and Behe agreed to give [a] look at and respond to what I’ve written about this in the past. We wondered about the meaning of Darwinism, and tussled over the right understanding of “exaptation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…The Dover Trial was a flash point of conflict, but this dialogue certainly seemed like peaceful science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then he adds, “Kafkaesque indeed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the quotations above, I have omitted several links, but you may get them from the link in the first line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the Peaceful Science post contains a link to another interaction between Drs. Behe and Swamidass, this one at Texas A&amp;amp;M, entitled “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wXU2Z3GVNFM&quot;&gt;God and/or Evolution?&lt;/a&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Interview, Michael Behe: Kafka at the Dover trial with Joshua Swamidass and Michael Behe. Our colleague Joshua Swamidass reports on the blog Peaceful Science that he was interviewed yesterday along with Michael Behe. I have not yet had a chance to watch the interview, Michael Behe: Kafka at the Dover trial (actually, I am hoping for a transcript), so I will merely note that Dr. Behe apparently compared the Dover trial to the book The Trial by Franz Kafka. I have read The Trial and also much of the transcript of the Dover trial, and I find that claim astonishing though, as I said, I have not actually seen the interview yet. At any rate, here is part of what Dr. Swamidass has to say:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pheucticus melanocephalus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/Pheucticus-melanocephalus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pheucticus melanocephalus" /><published>2020-10-26T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-26T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/Pheucticus-melanocephalus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/Pheucticus-melanocephalus.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Mark Lee&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Lee_BlackheadedGrosbeak.JPEG&quot; alt=&quot;Grosbeak&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Black-headed_Grosbeak/id&quot;&gt;Pheucticus melanocephalus&lt;/a&gt;, black-headed grosbeak, Palo Duro Canyon State Park, Texas.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Mark Lee. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Pheucticus melanocephalus, black-headed grosbeak, Palo Duro Canyon State Park, Texas.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Does approach to higher probability block natural selection?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/does-approach-toward-higher-probability.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does approach to higher probability block natural selection?" /><published>2020-10-25T00:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-25T00:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/does-approach-toward-higher-probability</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/does-approach-toward-higher-probability.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/gf.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his video, which we have discussed &lt;em&gt;ad nauseam&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/are-evolutionary-biologists-ignoring-science.html&quot;&gt;our
extremely long recent thread&lt;/a&gt; Mark Champneys claims that
scientists are ignoring science when they claim that natural selection can
result in functional information increasing in the genome.  In the subsequent
discussion, Champneys insisted that there was a generalized form of the Second
Law which made such increase impossible, insisted that it applied not just to
isolated systems but to non-isolated populations of organisms, and that it
did prevent natural selection from achieving long-term improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In this post, I hope to show a very simple example, and to get away from
the issue of whether this has anything to do with the Second Law.  If we
can focus on discussing whether the approach of a stochastic process to its
equilibrium prevents natural selection from having effect, maybe we
can avoid having 1,600-plus comments and actually discuss the matter at hand.
&lt;p&gt;
Let's try for that focus and relevance.  Surely someone who wants scientists
to actually grapple with the science must agree with that goal.  Right?  Let's
see ...
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;The example&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My simple example will be a large population of organisms, haploid ones, for
simplicity.  We will follow 100 sites in their DNA.  At each site there are
four possible bases, A, C, G and T.  There will be a simple mutational
process which changes symmetrically among the four possible bases
(technically, a Jukes-Cantor model of change).  Each base has the same
probability of mutating, and when it mutates it changes to one of the other
three bases, chosen at random.  We'll take the probability of mutation to be
0.0001 per base per generation, a fairly high value.
&lt;o&gt;
No matter what the population of sequences is, as mutations accumulate,
the population proceeds towards its equilibrium.  Each site becomes
equally likely to have all four bases, and this happens independently
at all 100 sites.  The equilibrium has all 4^(100) possible sequences,
equally frequent.  If we were to follow only how many copies of one of the
four bases, say C, the sequence has, each site has a 25% chance of having a
C.  So on average there will be 25 Cs.  It will be like coin tosses of a
biased coin, with 100 tosses, on average 25% of which are Heads.  This is a
binomial distribution.  In the figure above, it is the orange histogram,
which varies around 25.  If having lots of Cs were somehow desirable, with
only mutation, the sequences are stuck in the vicinity of 25, forever.
&lt;p&gt;
The process of change of these sequences is a random process (a stochastic
process), and it has a single equilibrium distribution toward which it
proceeds.  In technical terminology, this is an ergodic process.
So far things look as if they follow Mark Champneys' rules.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;With natural selection&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But notice what is left out -- natural selection.  So let's consider
another case, which puts it in.  Suppose that at a site, having a C
improves the fitness of the individual by 0.005, which is one part
in 200, or 0.5%.  And suppose that this happens at all the sites.
For simplicity we'll suppose that the higher fitness is always
for C, with all three other bases having the equal, slightly lower fitness.
The fitnesses at the different sites combine by multiplying.  So
the fitness of a 100-base genotype is 1.005, raised to the power
of the number of Cs in those sites.
&lt;p&gt;
It will not be a big surprise that Cs increase at each of the
sites.  I'll leave out the algebra, but can supply it on request.
Starting out with a population gene frequency of 0.25 at all 100
sites, the gene frequencies are always the same at all of the sites,
but they rise gradually.  After about 5,000 generations. they
rise almost to 1, settling in to an equilibrium gene frequency
of 0.9801332.  They don't get all the way to 1, because mutation
has continued, and Cs keep mutating away from C as well as being
selected towards it.
&lt;p&gt;
In the figure, the result is the green histogram.  There are an
average of 98.01332 Cs in these 100 sites.  The number varies around that
from genome to genome, just as tosses of 100 coins would that have a Heads
probability of 0.9801332.  It is possible to show that the average
fitness of genomes in that equilibrium distribution is 1.630472.
Natural selection shifts the equilibrium distribution dramatically
to the right.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Mark Champneys is right (and also wrong)&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yes, in both of these cases the random process results in an equilibrium
distribution, toward which the process moves.  But note -- &lt;em&gt;they
aren't the same distribution in the two cases.&lt;/em&gt;  Natural
selection has a dramatic effect on what the equilibrium
distribution is.  So the movement towards an equilibrium does
not mean that natural selection is ineffective.
&lt;p&gt;
I will be interested in seeing whether Mark Champneys agrees with
this.  His video gives the distinct impression that
both cases are expected to have the same equilibrium distribution,
with natural selection therefore being ineffective.  That would
seem to require some changes in the video, and some acknowledgement
that maybe evolutionary biologists are not quite as ignorant
of science as Mark Champneys said they were.


&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/o&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">In his video, which we have discussed ad nauseam in our extremely long recent thread Mark Champneys claims that scientists are ignoring science when they claim that natural selection can result in functional information increasing in the genome. In the subsequent discussion, Champneys insisted that there was a generalized form of the Second Law which made such increase impossible, insisted that it applied not just to isolated systems but to non-isolated populations of organisms, and that it did prevent natural selection from achieving long-term improvement. In this post, I hope to show a very simple example, and to get away from the issue of whether this has anything to do with the Second Law. If we can focus on discussing whether the approach of a stochastic process to its equilibrium prevents natural selection from having effect, maybe we can avoid having 1,600-plus comments and actually discuss the matter at hand. Let's try for that focus and relevance. Surely someone who wants scientists to actually grapple with the science must agree with that goal. Right? Let's see ...</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gold of the gaps</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/gold-of-the-gaps.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gold of the gaps" /><published>2020-10-16T09:43:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-16T09:43:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/gold-of-the-gaps</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/gold-of-the-gaps.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2020/10/does-gold-have-a-purpose-science-hints-at-answers/&quot;&gt;Does gold have a purpose?&lt;/a&gt; asks an unnamed author in &lt;em&gt;Evolution News &amp;amp; Science Today&lt;/em&gt;. The author goes on to observe that there is more gold on earth than astrophysicists can account for and also that gold has risen to the surface of the earth faster than might be expected. They go on to note the “availability of many essential elements at the surface of the earth …” and also discuss the use of gold in medicine. They are somewhat breathless at the discovery that the body can metabolize gold:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Gold nanoparticles, which are &lt;strong&gt;supposed to be stable&lt;/strong&gt; in biological environments, &lt;strong&gt;can be degraded inside cells&lt;/strong&gt;, [boldface in original]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;even though, as they note, gold salts have been used for decades in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At any rate, the article stresses the “mystery of biological gold” and claims several hints why gold may have a purpose: its abundance and seemingly unlikely transport to the surface of the earth, the ability of cells to “metabolize” [sic] gold, the fact that gold persists in the body, and the usefulness of gold for therapeutics. The conclusion of the article is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since ID advocates are better equipped to think outside the box than are the paradigm-locked materialist scientists, they are more free to consider a positive answer — showing once again that intelligent design is not a “science stopper” but a fruitful way to pursue interesting questions. If the answer is “Yes, gold has a purpose,” the applications could be profound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Au boy! The author seems a little Au-struck by what seem to me relatively unrelated scientific discoveries and is trying Au-fully hard to weave them together into a fine-tuning argument. Here is my translation of the conclusion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since intelligent-design creationists are desperately searching for “hints” of design, they are more likely than empirically based scientists to come up with a positive answer — showing once again that intelligent-design creationists can pretend that any unanticipated scientific discovery leads to “interesting questions.” If the answer is, “Yes, gold has a purpose,” no practical applications will result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, the answer to the question is, “Yes, gold, like anything else, has whatever purposes we assign to it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Glenn Branch, who apparently reads Evolution News, so I generally do not have to.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Does gold have a purpose? asks an unnamed author in Evolution News &amp;amp; Science Today. The author goes on to observe that there is more gold on earth than astrophysicists can account for and also that gold has risen to the surface of the earth faster than might be expected. They go on to note the “availability of many essential elements at the surface of the earth …” and also discuss the use of gold in medicine. They are somewhat breathless at the discovery that the body can metabolize gold: Gold nanoparticles, which are supposed to be stable in biological environments, can be degraded inside cells, [boldface in original] even though, as they note, gold salts have been used for decades in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. At any rate, the article stresses the “mystery of biological gold” and claims several hints why gold may have a purpose: its abundance and seemingly unlikely transport to the surface of the earth, the ability of cells to “metabolize” [sic] gold, the fact that gold persists in the body, and the usefulness of gold for therapeutics. The conclusion of the article is Since ID advocates are better equipped to think outside the box than are the paradigm-locked materialist scientists, they are more free to consider a positive answer — showing once again that intelligent design is not a “science stopper” but a fruitful way to pursue interesting questions. If the answer is “Yes, gold has a purpose,” the applications could be profound. Au boy! The author seems a little Au-struck by what seem to me relatively unrelated scientific discoveries and is trying Au-fully hard to weave them together into a fine-tuning argument. Here is my translation of the conclusion: Since intelligent-design creationists are desperately searching for “hints” of design, they are more likely than empirically based scientists to come up with a positive answer — showing once again that intelligent-design creationists can pretend that any unanticipated scientific discovery leads to “interesting questions.” If the answer is, “Yes, gold has a purpose,” no practical applications will result. Actually, the answer to the question is, “Yes, gold, like anything else, has whatever purposes we assign to it.” Thanks to Glenn Branch, who apparently reads Evolution News, so I generally do not have to.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Platalea ajaja L.</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/Platalea-ajaja.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Platalea ajaja L." /><published>2020-10-12T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-12T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/Platalea-ajaja</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/Platalea-ajaja.html">&lt;p&gt;Roseate spoonbill, by &lt;strong&gt;C. Joseph Long&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Long_roseate_spoonbill.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Roseate spoonbill&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roseate_spoonbill&quot;&gt;Platalea ajaja L.&lt;/a&gt;, roseate spoonbill, with young. The photographer writes, &quot;This shot was taken at the Alligator Farm in St. Augustine, Florida.  This is a popular place (among the birds, as well as humans) because, while nestlings that fall to the surface are lost, the nests are safe from such predators as raccoons, bobcats, and snakes due to the inaccessibility of the trees’ bases.  The color is due, as in flamingos, to carotenoids in the diet.  According to Wikipedia, the roseate’s closest relative is the yellow-billed spoonbill, which is found in southeast Australia.  They do get around.&quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Roseate spoonbill, by C. Joseph Long. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Platalea ajaja L., roseate spoonbill, with young. The photographer writes, &quot;This shot was taken at the Alligator Farm in St. Augustine, Florida. This is a popular place (among the birds, as well as humans) because, while nestlings that fall to the surface are lost, the nests are safe from such predators as raccoons, bobcats, and snakes due to the inaccessibility of the trees’ bases. The color is due, as in flamingos, to carotenoids in the diet. According to Wikipedia, the roseate’s closest relative is the yellow-billed spoonbill, which is found in southeast Australia. They do get around.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Protein chimeras are evidence against ID claims!</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/protein-chimeras.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Protein chimeras are evidence against ID claims!" /><published>2020-10-11T12:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-11T12:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/protein-chimeras</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/protein-chimeras.html">&lt;p&gt;Where do novel functional proteins come from? It has become something of a staple of the ID-creationism movement that proteins with novel functions and structures are practically impossible to evolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? In part because functional protein sequences, that is, protein sequences &lt;em&gt;with functions that are useful to living organisms&lt;/em&gt; (such as protecting DNA from damage or promoting essential chemical reactions), are supposedly hyper-astronomically rare among all &lt;em&gt;possible&lt;/em&gt; protein sequences. So rare, ID-creationists argue, that even with unrealistically huge population sizes and rates of mutation, not a single functional protein sequence could be expected to evolve in the entire history of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The intended message is, of course, that since we know of millions of functional protein sequences within the diversity of life on Earth, and since supposedly none of them could have evolved, Intelligent Design becomes the only other plausible explanation for why they exist. And so, you know, evolution must be false and there must be an Intelligent Designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main champions of this claim is ID-creationist and researcher Douglas Axe, who is one among few ID-creationists with actual qualifications in biochemistry. Back in 2004 he &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2004.06.058&quot;&gt;published a paper&lt;/a&gt; in the journal Molecular Biology and Evolution detailing some experiments he did on a protein enzyme 150 amino acids in length. In this paper he concludes that functional protein enzyme sequences of a similar size (150 amino acids) are so rare among all possible proteins, that they are found at the astonishingly low frequency of approximately 1 in 10&lt;sup&gt;77&lt;/sup&gt;. This number is frequently cited in the ID literature, ranging from Stephen Meyer’s book &lt;em&gt;Darwin’s Doubt&lt;/em&gt;, through &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2016/10/imagine_60_mill/&quot;&gt;being bandied about&lt;/a&gt; on the Discovery Institute’s pro-ID blog Evolution News &amp;amp; Science Today, to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519320302071?via%3Dihub&quot;&gt;recent pro-ID paper&lt;/a&gt; published in the Journal of Theoretical Biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now 1 in 10&lt;sup&gt;77&lt;/sup&gt; is certainly a very low frequency, and all the way back in January of 2007, Panda’s Thumb contributor Arthur Hunt wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2007/01/92-second-st-fa.html&quot;&gt;a post detailing good reasons&lt;/a&gt; why Axe’s work is incapable of supporting this 10&lt;sup&gt;-77&lt;/sup&gt; frequency. And while I will not reiterate those reasons here, in a future post I intend to revisit some of the conclusions ID-creationists draw from Axe’s work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather, given that Axe’s work is once again being cited and is doing the rounds in ID-creationist circles, I thought this would be as good a time as any to visit some work in experimental molecular biology that massively contradicts Axe’s number. And to not beat around the bush too much, we’re talking &lt;em&gt;a 72 order-of-magnitude discrepancy&lt;/em&gt; between Axe’s frequency of 1 in 10&lt;sup&gt;77&lt;/sup&gt; and what other experiments in probing protein sequence space reveal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will give an account of experiments done to probe a particular process of novel protein evolution, called gene fusion, which turned out to be able to find functional proteins at a rate of 1 in 3.3×10&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;. To put the magnitude of the discrepancy into context, it’s 1 followed by 72 zeroes, which is a number that seems to fit in the arena concerning things like the number of atoms in the observable universe (estimated at ~10&lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;). Quite a margin of error!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question of how novel protein-coding genes have arisen by evolutionary processes throughout life’s history has many possible answers, ranging from processes such as mutational divergence of duplicate genes, through emergence by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frameshift_mutation&quot;&gt;frameshift mutation&lt;/a&gt;, to proteins evolving &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; from non-coding DNA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another idea is that novel protein-coding genes can arise by recombination of smaller fragments of already existing genes, resulting in chimeric sequences with the potential for new functions. An example of how such a chimeric gene can arise is depicted in Figure 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Rasmussen_Fig1_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Origin of chimeric gene&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt;: Overview of a step-wise process by which a chimeric gene can arise by what is in essence analogous to a copy-and-paste mechanism operating on DNA sequences. A piece of an organism’s chromosome is depicted with intergenic DNA represented by black horizontal lines, separated by colored bars representing the protein-coding genes A and B. (1) A small segment of chromosomal DNA is copied. (2) This copy is inserted back into the chromosome, this time inside the functional gene B. (3) This insertion results in a novel hybrid gene A/B. (4) All three genes A, B, and hybrid gene A/B, are expressed within the cell.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put very succinctly, take two (or more) pieces of already existing genes and combine them into a new gene which is a hybrid of the two. Since for the purposes of this post I am defining a gene as a piece of DNA that encodes a protein, the resulting hybrid protein consists of fragments of other existing proteins, and potentially has novel and useful biological functions, possibly facilitated by folding into a novel 3-dimensional structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve come across an interesting PhD thesis, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ourarchive.otago.ac.nz/handle/10523/9772&quot;&gt;Exploring the protein universe: a study of subdomain driven evolution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, by Gabriel Rawcliffe, detailing experiments to explore the evolution of novel functional proteins, by a version of this process of combining pieces of different genes, which the author calls “subdomain driven evolution.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rawcliffe sought to determine whether this process of generating hybrid genes by combining pieces of existing genes was capable of finding novel functional proteins. To do so, Rawcliffe performed his experiments using 107 different genetically engineered &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auxotrophy&quot;&gt;auxotrophic strains&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; bacteria. Each strain had only one of 107 different genes rendered nonfunctional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get some terminology down, an auxotrophic organism is a mutant variant of the same species that has lost the ability to biosynthesize a key organic compound that is essential for growth. Think of how we as humans have lost the ability to synthesize our own vitamin C, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pseudogene&quot;&gt;due to the pseudogenization&lt;/a&gt; (mutations have rendered a gene nonfunctional, turning into a so-called pseudogene) of a key gene in the vitamin C biosynthesis pathway. This means we need vitamin C in our diet to survive since we can’t make it within our own bodies. The particular gene that has mutated and become nonfunctional is found in humans and many of our close primate cousins and is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L-gulonolactone_oxidase&quot;&gt;known as GULOP&lt;/a&gt; (we inherited this nonfunctional gene from a distant primate common ancestor).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar principle goes for the &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; bacteria used in Rawcliffe’s experiments. He used 107 different auxotrophic strains, that is, 107 variants of &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt;, each of which carried a single genetically engineered mutation that made that strain unable to biosynthesize one of 107 different organic compounds the bacteria need to grow and divide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This compound could be anything from a particular sugar or amino acid, to lipids used in the cell membrane, or other essential constituents of &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt;. Experiments of this nature are also known as “knock-out” experiments, denoting that the experiment is performed with an organism carrying a gene that has been “knocked out” of function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rawcliffe’s strategy was then to find out whether it was possible to find a novel hybrid gene that was capable of performing a function that compensated for any one of the 107 different knocked out genes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He went on to screen a library of 1.65 million different hybrid genes created (using a molecular biology protocol called &lt;a href=&quot;https://experiments.springernature.com/articles/10.1007/978-1-4939-1053-3_16&quot;&gt;ITCHY&lt;/a&gt;) from what was essentially random fragments of existing genes, to see whether one of these millions of new hybrid genes could perform a function that could compensate for one of the 107 different dysfunctional mutant genes. It’s important to note here that the novel hybrid gene might not perform &lt;em&gt;the same&lt;/em&gt; function as the gene that was knocked out, but it is still able to rescue the strain by performing some other compensating function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The protocol he employed to detect whether such a function existed among his millions of random chimeric genes is depicted in this Figure 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Rasmussen_Fig2_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Plasmids carrying hybrid genes&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt;: On the right: circles with colored segments represent DNA &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plasmid&quot;&gt;plasmids&lt;/a&gt; carrying hybrid genes (created using the ITCHY protocol). These plasmids are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transformation_(genetics)&quot;&gt;transformed&lt;/a&gt; (a process by which bacteria can take in and use foreign DNA) into auxotrophic *E. coli* bacteria, and the transformed bacteria are then transferred to a Petri dish to see if they are able to grow and divide by employing the hybrid gene. If they can, a bacterial colony will become visible on the Petri dish, which can then be isolated and analyzed. On the left: Same strains of bacteria are used, but without the plasmid DNA carrying the hybrid genes. &lt;small&gt;Image credit: Figure 4.10 of Rawcliffe, G. (2019). Exploring the protein universe: a study of subdomain driven evolution. Reproduced with permission. &lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To elaborate a bit, what Rawcliffe does is first and foremost to use some rather technical molecular biology methods (the &lt;a href=&quot;https://experiments.springernature.com/articles/10.1007/978-1-4939-1053-3_16&quot;&gt;ITCHY protocol&lt;/a&gt;) to generate a huge library of random gene hybrids. Due to various technical limitations, his hybrid genes are restricted to consist of only two fragments at most, each derived from a different gene (essentially similar to that A/B hybrid depicted in Figure 1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rawcliffe generated a library of ~1.65 million different such hybrid genes that met the specifications for his experimental protocol. Rawcliffe then went on to use this library of ~1.65 million hybrid genes in a process called bacterial transformation, which basically means he gets his 107 different auxotrophic strains of &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; to transport the DNA encoding the novel hybrid genes inside themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the DNA is inside the bacterial cells, these same bacteria can now “read and decode” the DNA and thereby produce the novel hybrid gene. And here comes the crucial part: if by chance this novel hybrid gene can perform a function that compensates for the “knocked out” gene, the bacteria will be able to grow in a Petri dish on agar that otherwise lacks the essential nutrient. If any of Rawcliffe’s auxotrophic strains can grow and form a colony on a Petri dish, it is known as a rescue clone (because the inserted DNA “rescued” its ability to grow despite having a gene knocked out).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, having a negative control is important if we are to conclude that the bacteria grow &lt;em&gt;because they received a novel hybrid gene&lt;/em&gt; (instead of gaining this ability through some other spontaneous mutation, or perhaps having his culture cross-contaminated with bacteria that do not carry “knock out” mutations), so, crucially, Rawcliffe also tested his auxotrophic bacteria &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; giving them any of the DNA containing novel hybrid genes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so what did Rawcliffe find? He has this table summarizing his findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Rasmussen_Table1_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Table of results&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Table 4.2 from Rawcliffe, G. 2019. Ibid.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically what Rawcliffe found was that among his ~1.65 million hybrids, there were six different genes capable of performing a function that rescued one of his 107 auxotrophic strains (listed under the Hybrid column). Reading the table we see, for example, the hybrid gene Sgbe147/MioC82, being derived from a fusion of fragments from the genes Sgbe147 and MioC82, rescued a strain of &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; having the gene cysN knocked out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rawcliffe goes into more detail in his thesis, analyzing the particular strains that were rescued, what function was initially knocked out, and from which genes the fragments that constitute the rescuing hybrid gene was derived. One of his six rescue clones turned out to be a case of “self-rescue,” which means that a piece of the gene that was originally knocked out was also found as part of the hybrid gene that performed the rescue function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly the self-rescue is not a fully intact version of the original knocked out gene, being partially constituted of a smaller fragment from it, but is nevertheless able to carry out its function, at least while fused to a fragment of another gene. Rawcliffe writes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4.3.2.4 Rescue of E. coli ΔguaB&lt;/strong&gt;
The rescue of &lt;em&gt;E. coli ΔguaB&lt;/em&gt; represents a partial self-rescue; it was rescued by the hybrid YdjO257/GuaB283, a combination of 257 amino acids of YdjO and 283 amino acids of GuaB. The full length GuaB is 488 amino acids, meaning that ~60% of GuaB, fused to an almost full length YdjO (267 amino acids), seemingly performed the function of GuaB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of this post we can discount a partial self-rescue. What we need to know here is only that among Rawcliffe’s original ~1.65 million hybrid genes, there were 5 novel ones capable of performing a function essential for life in a real living organism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means we now have a number to compare to the number that gets bandied about in the ID-creationist literature, that functional proteins are found at the hyper astronomically low frequency of about 1 in 10&lt;sup&gt;77&lt;/sup&gt;. The number we have is ~1.65 million divided by 5 = ~330 000. So we have a frequency of functional proteins of 1 in 330 thousand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rawcliffe didn’t have to search through 10&lt;sup&gt;77&lt;/sup&gt; random combinations to find a new functional protein, and apparently truncated fragments of already existing protein sequences, when fused together, were capable of performing other functions. Thus, Axe’s estimate is in error, as noted above, by something on the order of &lt;em&gt;72 orders of magnitude&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Axe DD. Estimating the prevalence of protein sequences adopting functional enzyme folds. J Mol Biol. 2004;341(5):1295-1315. doi:10.1016/j.jmb.2004.06.058&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rawcliffe, G. (2019). Exploring the protein universe: a study of subdomain driven evolution (Thesis, Doctor of Philosophy). University of Otago. Retrieved from http://hdl.handle.net/10523/9772&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mikkel Nif Rasmussen</name></author><summary type="html">Where do novel functional proteins come from? It has become something of a staple of the ID-creationism movement that proteins with novel functions and structures are practically impossible to evolve. Why? In part because functional protein sequences, that is, protein sequences with functions that are useful to living organisms (such as protecting DNA from damage or promoting essential chemical reactions), are supposedly hyper-astronomically rare among all possible protein sequences. So rare, ID-creationists argue, that even with unrealistically huge population sizes and rates of mutation, not a single functional protein sequence could be expected to evolve in the entire history of the universe. The intended message is, of course, that since we know of millions of functional protein sequences within the diversity of life on Earth, and since supposedly none of them could have evolved, Intelligent Design becomes the only other plausible explanation for why they exist. And so, you know, evolution must be false and there must be an Intelligent Designer.</summary></entry></feed>