<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-02T16:07:24-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Daniel Phelps wins Paleontological Society Award, 2</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/09/daniel-phelps-paleontological-society-award-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Daniel Phelps wins Paleontological Society Award, 2" /><published>2022-09-02T09:41:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-09-02T09:41:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/09/daniel-phelps-paleontological-society-award-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/09/daniel-phelps-paleontological-society-award-2.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Dan_Phelps_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Daniel Phelps&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our colleague Daniel Phelps reminds us,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Last year, I won the Paleontological Society’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/daniel-phelps-paleontological-society-award.html&quot;&gt;Strimple Award&lt;/a&gt; [which recognizes outstanding achievement in paleontology by someone who does not make a living full-time from paleontology]. The Journal of Paleontology just published &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1017/jpa.2022.63&quot;&gt;Colin Sumrall’s presentation&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1017/jpa.2022.64&quot;&gt;my acceptance&lt;/a&gt; as open access papers. Someone let Ken Ham know.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we reported the award over a year ago, we decided to post the texts as a separate item.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Our colleague Daniel Phelps reminds us, &quot;Last year, I won the Paleontological Society’s Strimple Award [which recognizes outstanding achievement in paleontology by someone who does not make a living full-time from paleontology]. The Journal of Paleontology just published Colin Sumrall’s presentation and my acceptance as open access papers. Someone let Ken Ham know.&quot; Because we reported the award over a year ago, we decided to post the texts as a separate item.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ICR argues that science refutes junk DNA</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/ICR-junkdna.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ICR argues that science refutes junk DNA" /><published>2022-08-31T19:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-08-31T19:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/ICR-junkdna</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/ICR-junkdna.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/ICRjunkdna.png&quot; alt=&quot;[Screen shot of ICR junk DNA video]&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;ICR junk DNA video (screenshot above, for video &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=I0dPntyyCpU&quot;&gt;click here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that most molecular biologist and genomicists have concluded (erroneously) that the notion of “junk DNA” was a mistake, 
  here comes the Institute for Creation Research to crow about how wrong the scientists were and how the real science shows that humans are descended 
  from Adam and Eve only thousands of years ago.  Above you will find the ICR video (click on the link in the caption, the figure is only 
  a screenshot).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=37148773&amp;amp;postID=5192215128092575421&quot;&gt;It's been suggested&lt;/a&gt; by a commenter at Sandwalk that we do a crowdsourced critique of this video here at Panda's Thumb.  Fortunately, a response has already been done
  by Daniel Stern Cardinale. See below ... &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cardinale, who teaches at Rutgers University, critiques the ICR video in detail in a YouTube video in his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/c/CreationMyths&quot;&gt;“Creation Myths” YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;.  (Take a look at the other videos, there is a lot of good stuff there).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/DSCjunkdna.png&quot; alt=&quot;[Screen shot of Daniel Stern Cardinale response to ICR junk DNA video]&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Daniel Stern Cardinale reply to ICR junk DNA video (screenshot above, for video &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FOXrsaCpt-A&quot;&gt;click here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoughts?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">ICR junk DNA video (screenshot above, for video click here) Now that most molecular biologist and genomicists have concluded (erroneously) that the notion of “junk DNA” was a mistake, here comes the Institute for Creation Research to crow about how wrong the scientists were and how the real science shows that humans are descended from Adam and Eve only thousands of years ago. Above you will find the ICR video (click on the link in the caption, the figure is only a screenshot). It's been suggested by a commenter at Sandwalk that we do a crowdsourced critique of this video here at Panda's Thumb. Fortunately, a response has already been done by Daniel Stern Cardinale. See below ...</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Buteo swainsoni jamaicensis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/buteo-swainsoni.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buteo swainsoni jamaicensis" /><published>2022-08-29T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-08-29T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/buteo-swainsoni</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/buteo-swainsoni.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/DSC05010_Red-tailed_Hawk_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Red-tailed hawk&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Red-tailed_Hawk/overview&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Buteo &lt;strike&gt;swainsoni&lt;/strike&gt; jamaicensis&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Red-tailed hawk, Walden Ponds, Boulder, Colorado, May, 2022. One of 2 hawks searching for lunch or maybe dinner for their young. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Buteo swainsoni jamaicensis &amp;ndash; Red-tailed hawk, Walden Ponds, Boulder, Colorado, May, 2022. One of 2 hawks searching for lunch or maybe dinner for their young.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ulster Museum declines to respond to FOI request for empirical evidence</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/ulster-museum-declines.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ulster Museum declines to respond to FOI request for empirical evidence" /><published>2022-08-23T12:01:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-08-23T12:01:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/ulster-museum-declines</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/ulster-museum-declines.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Ulster_Museum_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ulster Museum&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Headline and frontispiece of article in the Belfast Telegraph.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An alert reader (who must subscribe to every newspaper on the planet) alerted us to this article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.belfasttelegraph.co.uk/news/northern-ireland/ulster-museum-could-end-up-in-court-over-freedom-of-information-request-41926500.html&quot;&gt;Ulster Museum could end up in court over stance on evolution&lt;/a&gt;, by Ciaran O’Neill in the Belfast (Northern Ireland) Telegraph. It is not clear that the Ulster Museum will end up in court, but the fact is that an unnamed citizen submitted a Freedom of Information (FOI) request for “‘empirical evidence and hard science’ used to support the museum’s ‘endorsement of the origins of the human species,’” according to the Telegraph article. Instead of, as a colleague put it, giving the person a link to the Smithsonian, the Museum evidently elected to ignore the request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK, it turns out, has an &lt;a href=&quot;https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-freedom-of-information/complaints/&quot;&gt;Information Commissioner&lt;/a&gt;, and the citizen complained to the Commission. Without going into detail, the commission gave the museum 20 days, then, after a hearing, an additional 35 days to respond to the FOI request. So far, the museum has been silent. They could be held in contempt of court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that the request is overbroad, asking for “e-mails, letters, notes and references, … &lt;i&gt;in paper format&lt;/i&gt;,” and I do not understand why the museum has not responded. By making an issue of this frankly nonsensical request, they may encourage other creationists to harass other museums. Let us hope that those museums find a way to simply brush them off.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Headline and frontispiece of article in the Belfast Telegraph. An alert reader (who must subscribe to every newspaper on the planet) alerted us to this article, Ulster Museum could end up in court over stance on evolution, by Ciaran O’Neill in the Belfast (Northern Ireland) Telegraph. It is not clear that the Ulster Museum will end up in court, but the fact is that an unnamed citizen submitted a Freedom of Information (FOI) request for “‘empirical evidence and hard science’ used to support the museum’s ‘endorsement of the origins of the human species,’” according to the Telegraph article. Instead of, as a colleague put it, giving the person a link to the Smithsonian, the Museum evidently elected to ignore the request. The UK, it turns out, has an Information Commissioner, and the citizen complained to the Commission. Without going into detail, the commission gave the museum 20 days, then, after a hearing, an additional 35 days to respond to the FOI request. So far, the museum has been silent. They could be held in contempt of court. It is clear that the request is overbroad, asking for “e-mails, letters, notes and references, … in paper format,” and I do not understand why the museum has not responded. By making an issue of this frankly nonsensical request, they may encourage other creationists to harass other museums. Let us hope that those museums find a way to simply brush them off.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Icterus bullockii</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/icterus-bullockii.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Icterus bullockii" /><published>2022-08-15T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-08-15T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/icterus-bullockii</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/icterus-bullockii.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/IMG_0127_Bullocks_Oriole_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bullock's oriole&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Bullocks_Oriole/overview&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Icterus bullockii&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Bullock's oriole, Wonderland Lake, Boulder, Colorado, May, 2022.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Icterus bullockii &amp;ndash; Bullock's oriole, Wonderland Lake, Boulder, Colorado, May, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Meyer and Thaxton ask one question and answer another</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/thaxton-and-meyer-switcheroo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meyer and Thaxton ask one question and answer another" /><published>2022-08-14T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-08-14T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/thaxton-and-meyer-switcheroo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/thaxton-and-meyer-switcheroo.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Tolstoy_and_chekhov2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Photo of Chekhov and Tolstoy discussing literature]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Chekhov(L) and Tolstoy(R).  Were they discussing the origin of the book?&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An article at the Discovery Institute’s
website Evolution News &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2022/08/from-intelligent-cause-to-intelligent-design-my-debt-to-charles-thaxton/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;reprints a tribute&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
that Stephen Meyer paid to Charles Thaxton,
in a preface Meyer wrote to a memoir
by Thaxton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;During a session on the origin of life, the scientists 
discussed a question I had never considered: 
Where did the information stored in the DNA molecule 
come from?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;….&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On February 10, 1985, I learned I wasn’t the only one. On 
that day I found myself sitting in front of 
eight world-class scientists, who were 
discussing the vexing scientific and 
philosophical question: How did the first life on earth arise?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Um, different question!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “information stored in the DNA molecule” is of course the precise sequence of bases.  Not the existence of the molecule
in the first place.  And there are well-known evolutionary processes that are capable of putting adaptive information into
the molecule by choosing particular bases at each site.  They continue to happen long after the origin of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me explain:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very much like someone saying that to explain the information stored in some computer memory, what we have to discuss
is how the computer came to exist.  No, we don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we compare a novel by Leo Tolstoy to a set of short stories by Anton Chekhov, what is of interest is not how books
came to be invented, or how the particular binding, fonts, and physical format were chosen.  The two works might be
very much the same in those respects, but they of course will be very different in the sequence of letters in the
books.  And that is where the information is that makes them different, and makes both of them remarkable.  In the
photo above we see Chekhov(L) with Tolstoy(R), when Tolstoy visited Chekhov’s dacha in 1900.  The two authors 
had much to discuss about their writings, and those of others.  But I doubt they spent much of that time discussing 
how and where books first arose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of Meyer’s piece concentrates on the origin of life, and does not at all discuss how the information in the 
DNA got there.  Why does Meyer insist on describing that as the issue? Is there some big mystery?  Are the ordinary processes of evolution, such as natural selection and 
mutation somehow incapable, in principle, of putting into the DNA information that leads to the organism being well-adapted?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Differences in the sequences in DNA (or RNA) genomes can lead to differences in phenotype.  And those differences in 
phenotype can lead to differences in function, and thus differences in fitness.  The sequences with higher fitness will 
tend to increase in frequency.  The genotypes in the population come to be better adapted.  When we use the scale of 
fitness as a specification, the functional information in the genome then increases.  There is no mystery as to how 
this can happen, no proof that improved adaptation is somehow impossible in principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;misunderstanding-or-misdirection&quot;&gt;Misunderstanding or misdirection?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advocates of ID and creationists often avoid talking about how changes of DNA sequence by mutation and by changes of 
gene frequency of the resulting DNA sequences increase the functional information in the DNA.  They usually immediately 
change the subject to the Origin Of Life.  I like to call this change of topic OTOOL (Off To the Origin Of Life), or
STOOL (Switch To the Origin Of Life).  It is moving to a much-less-well-understood topic, one where Design Intervention 
can be invoked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They often say that they do not question the processes of “microevolution”, including mutation, natural selection, 
gene flow, and genetic drift.  Yet these processes can easily be shown to put functional information into the pool of 
genomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what Stephen Meyer does in the Preface to Thaxton’s book, the one quoted in his piece in Evolution News.  It’s the 
old switcheroo once again.  When Meyer raises the issue of how the information comes to be in the DNA, he immediately does the
old familiar change-of-topic.  If he does not mean to deliberately switch the topic, then he is giving a strong indication 
that he simply does not understand what the functional information in DNA is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-the-echo-chamber&quot;&gt;In the echo chamber&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, as usual,
at Uncommon Descent, the Meyer/Thaxton article is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/at-evolution-news-from-intelligent-cause-to-intelligent-design-my-debt-to-charles-thaxton/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;taken very seriously&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and quoted at length, with no
recognition that the origin of the information in
the DNA might be a different issue from the origin of the first DNA molecule.  The post is authored by “Caspian”, who the
site identifies as its regular poster, physicist Eric Hedin.  He ought to have a good grasp of
information theory.  Is it too much 
to ask whether the site might someday distinguish between these two questions?  Apparently so.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Chekhov(L) and Tolstoy(R). Were they discussing the origin of the book? An article at the Discovery Institute’s website Evolution News reprints a tribute that Stephen Meyer paid to Charles Thaxton, in a preface Meyer wrote to a memoir by Thaxton. During a session on the origin of life, the scientists discussed a question I had never considered: Where did the information stored in the DNA molecule come from? …. On February 10, 1985, I learned I wasn’t the only one. On that day I found myself sitting in front of eight world-class scientists, who were discussing the vexing scientific and philosophical question: How did the first life on earth arise? Um, different question! The “information stored in the DNA molecule” is of course the precise sequence of bases. Not the existence of the molecule in the first place. And there are well-known evolutionary processes that are capable of putting adaptive information into the molecule by choosing particular bases at each site. They continue to happen long after the origin of life. Let me explain:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Myers, Phelps dissect creationist video</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/myers-phelps-dissect.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Myers, Phelps dissect creationist video" /><published>2022-08-14T09:33:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-08-14T09:33:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/myers-phelps-dissect</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/myers-phelps-dissect.html">&lt;p&gt;I am right now watching an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lU3SgSc4j38&quot;&gt;unnamed video&lt;/a&gt; in which &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PZ_Myers&quot;&gt;PZ Myers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/friend-darwin-daniel-j-phelps&quot;&gt;Dan Phelps&lt;/a&gt; dissect a creationist video by Answers in Genesis functionary &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/bios/tim-chaffey/&quot;&gt;Tim Chaffey&lt;/a&gt;. The format is essentially that Prof. Myers plays a bit of the Chaffey video, then pauses and – I was going to say they dissect it, but demolish may be the better word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original video is rather odd: it appears to have been speeded up, and all the pauses have been eliminated. It is as if they want to get through their arguments so fast that you cannot understand or refute them. (See also: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gish_gallop&quot;&gt;Gish gallop&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not finished watching the video yet, but one thing that caught my attention was this: Mr. Chaffey is at pains to demonstrate that the Ark was big enough to hold all the “kinds” necessary. Apart from his risible contention that sea creatures needed no saving from a flood that could carve the Grand Canyon, Mr. Chaffey seems to think that the Ark had enough space to house the necessary land creatures. In rebuttal, Prof. Myers cleverly looked up the land areas and numbers of species of several zoos, not to mention the number of employees. Suffice to say that the zoos occupied more area than the Ark and had more employees than Noah and his family. (Yes, I know, the zoos need room for visitors. Fine, cut the area and the number of employees by 5 and compare that to the Ark.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will watch the rest of the video later on, but please feel free to comment, and do not worry about spoilers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I am right now watching an unnamed video in which PZ Myers and Dan Phelps dissect a creationist video by Answers in Genesis functionary Tim Chaffey. The format is essentially that Prof. Myers plays a bit of the Chaffey video, then pauses and – I was going to say they dissect it, but demolish may be the better word. The original video is rather odd: it appears to have been speeded up, and all the pauses have been eliminated. It is as if they want to get through their arguments so fast that you cannot understand or refute them. (See also: Gish gallop.) I have not finished watching the video yet, but one thing that caught my attention was this: Mr. Chaffey is at pains to demonstrate that the Ark was big enough to hold all the “kinds” necessary. Apart from his risible contention that sea creatures needed no saving from a flood that could carve the Grand Canyon, Mr. Chaffey seems to think that the Ark had enough space to house the necessary land creatures. In rebuttal, Prof. Myers cleverly looked up the land areas and numbers of species of several zoos, not to mention the number of employees. Suffice to say that the zoos occupied more area than the Ark and had more employees than Noah and his family. (Yes, I know, the zoos need room for visitors. Fine, cut the area and the number of employees by 5 and compare that to the Ark.) I will watch the rest of the video later on, but please feel free to comment, and do not worry about spoilers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ark Park displays giant palm frond</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/giant-palm-frond.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ark Park displays giant palm frond" /><published>2022-08-13T12:35:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-08-13T12:35:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/giant-palm-frond</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/giant-palm-frond.html">&lt;p&gt;I was forwarded a press release from Answers in Genesis the other day. They tout a new addition to their collection, a giant palm frond:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Giant_Palm_Frond_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Palm frond&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Giant palm frond on display at Ark Park. &lt;small&gt; Credit: AIG press release.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;Meanwhile, the Ark Encounter continues to make major additions. On the third deck of the massive ship [sic], a large exhibit highlighting a giant plant fossil is now on display. This unique 10’7” palm frond fossil was discovered in the well-known Green River Formation of Wyoming. &lt;/p&gt;  
 
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Dr. Andrew Snelling, head of the research department at AiG, declared: 'It is a phenomenal, world-class fossil. It is not millions of years old. The palm frond was buried catastrophically as a result of the global flood of Noah’s day about 4,500 years ago.' A family in Wisconsin made the fossil’s donation possible.&quot; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The palm frond, we note, is in very good condition for something that was buried catastrophically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, Green River Shale fossils are actually common and well-studied, so this display isn’t hurting scientific research as badly as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2015/06/will-aig-return.html&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Allosaurus&lt;/i&gt; specimen they received from the neo-Confederate Michael Peroutka&lt;/a&gt;.  Magnificent specimens like these are very expensive. This one was probably prepared by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.greenriverstone.com/&quot;&gt;Green River Stone Company&lt;/a&gt;, a commercial excavator and preparation company that is concerned exclusively with making sales (one of many problems with the commercial fossil market; sales do not necessarily benefit scientific research).  Ham’s Wisconsin donors must have deep pockets. I hope the donors and the costs are revealed on a future AiG or Crosswater Canyon IRS Form 990. I will be looking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Matt Young will be the principal moderator of this thread. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">I was forwarded a press release from Answers in Genesis the other day. They tout a new addition to their collection, a giant palm frond: Giant palm frond on display at Ark Park. Credit: AIG press release. &quot;Meanwhile, the Ark Encounter continues to make major additions. On the third deck of the massive ship [sic], a large exhibit highlighting a giant plant fossil is now on display. This unique 10’7” palm frond fossil was discovered in the well-known Green River Formation of Wyoming. &quot;Dr. Andrew Snelling, head of the research department at AiG, declared: 'It is a phenomenal, world-class fossil. It is not millions of years old. The palm frond was buried catastrophically as a result of the global flood of Noah’s day about 4,500 years ago.' A family in Wisconsin made the fossil’s donation possible.&quot; The palm frond, we note, is in very good condition for something that was buried catastrophically. Fortunately, Green River Shale fossils are actually common and well-studied, so this display isn’t hurting scientific research as badly as the Allosaurus specimen they received from the neo-Confederate Michael Peroutka. Magnificent specimens like these are very expensive. This one was probably prepared by the Green River Stone Company, a commercial excavator and preparation company that is concerned exclusively with making sales (one of many problems with the commercial fossil market; sales do not necessarily benefit scientific research). Ham’s Wisconsin donors must have deep pockets. I hope the donors and the costs are revealed on a future AiG or Crosswater Canyon IRS Form 990. I will be looking. Matt Young will be the principal moderator of this thread.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lamarck rides again?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/lamarck-rides-again.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lamarck rides again?" /><published>2022-08-10T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-08-10T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/lamarck-rides-again</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/lamarck-rides-again.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Giraffes_male_necking2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Image of male giraffes &amp;quot;necking&amp;quot;, from Wikimedia Commons]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Male giraffes &quot;necking&quot;.  From Wikimedia Commons&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous post, I argued that modern-day critics of the Modern Evolutionary 
Synthesis who think that they are putting forth a Lamarckian theory most likely
aren’t doing that, as they do not actually believe that the direction of change 
toward adaptation comes from use and disuse of organs.  To Lamarck, the 
directionality was not due to external environmental effects being inherited, 
it was actually the effort made by the individual to use particular organs more or use them 
less that somehow altered its genetic makeup and it was those changes that were inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now comes Dennis Noble.  A leader of the Extended Evolutionary Synthesis 
group and one of the main organizers of the notorious 2016 meeting on New Trends 
in Evolutionary Biology brought about by misguided biologists, philosophers, and
historians who talked the Royal Society into endorsing it, he has published 
another outburst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noble, an eminent physiologist, points to exosome vesicles that can cross the 
barrier between the somatic cells and the germ cells in animals, ones that can
contain mRNA.  These, he argues, can serve as the basis for the effects of use 
and disuse to alter the herditary material.  He does not actually show that this 
is what they do.  A critical issue is whether the effects on the somatic cells 
then induce in the germ cells a genetic change that is adaptive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But don’t listen to me.  Jerry Coyne has lost his temper and published a 
critique at his blog &lt;em&gt;Why Evolution Is True&lt;/em&gt;. He tears strips off Noble in a rather 
disrespectful way.  Which seems to me to be appropriate.  When Jerry gets into 
a high Evolutionary Synthesis dudgeon, he is well worth reading.  You will 
find his piece &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2022/08/07/denis-noble-goes-after-darwinian-evolution-again-scores-own-goal/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  Noble’s original cri de couer was published  &lt;a href=&quot;https://iai.tv/articles/denis-noble-the-broken-paradigm-of-neo-darwinism-auid-2210&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To see comments on this post, click on the title of the post, above.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Male giraffes &quot;necking&quot;. From Wikimedia Commons In the previous post, I argued that modern-day critics of the Modern Evolutionary Synthesis who think that they are putting forth a Lamarckian theory most likely aren’t doing that, as they do not actually believe that the direction of change toward adaptation comes from use and disuse of organs. To Lamarck, the directionality was not due to external environmental effects being inherited, it was actually the effort made by the individual to use particular organs more or use them less that somehow altered its genetic makeup and it was those changes that were inherited. And now comes Dennis Noble. A leader of the Extended Evolutionary Synthesis group and one of the main organizers of the notorious 2016 meeting on New Trends in Evolutionary Biology brought about by misguided biologists, philosophers, and historians who talked the Royal Society into endorsing it, he has published another outburst. Noble, an eminent physiologist, points to exosome vesicles that can cross the barrier between the somatic cells and the germ cells in animals, ones that can contain mRNA. These, he argues, can serve as the basis for the effects of use and disuse to alter the herditary material. He does not actually show that this is what they do. A critical issue is whether the effects on the somatic cells then induce in the germ cells a genetic change that is adaptive. But don’t listen to me. Jerry Coyne has lost his temper and published a critique at his blog Why Evolution Is True. He tears strips off Noble in a rather disrespectful way. Which seems to me to be appropriate. When Jerry gets into a high Evolutionary Synthesis dudgeon, he is well worth reading. You will find his piece here. Noble’s original cri de couer was published here. To see comments on this post, click on the title of the post, above.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy birthday, Lamarck</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/happy-birthday-lamarck.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy birthday, Lamarck" /><published>2022-08-01T13:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2022-08-01T13:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/happy-birthday-lamarck</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/08/happy-birthday-lamarck.html">&lt;p&gt;Happy birthday, Jean-Baptiste!  On this day, August 1, in 1744 Jean-Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet, the Chevalier de Lamarck, was born.  Had he lived he would now be a sprightly 
278 years old.  It is time for my annual birthday post.  He was the first evolutionary biologist.  In addition to world-class work in invertebrate taxonomy he argued for common descent and put forward a mechanism to account for adaptation.  No not inheritance of acquired characters – everyone always knew that it was true.  The mechanism was Use and Disuse. Organisms tried to solve their problems by using (or disusing) their organs, and the resulting changes would be adaptive and of course would be passed on to the next generation.  Lamarck also believed that,
in addition, there was an overall force in descent of organisms in nature leading to an increase of complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is Lamarckism dead now?  Well, yes and no.  Let me explain …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are people who have evolutionary theories that they think are Lamarckian.  A prime example is Dr. Eva Jablonka, an evolutionary biologist at the Cohn Institute for the History of Philosophy of Science and Ideas at Tel Aviv University. 
She declares herself a Lamarckian, invoking epigenetic changes of DNA as her mechanism (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eva_Jablonka&quot;&gt;her Wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does that mean she believes that, in addition to the known physical laws, that there is an inherent complexifying force in nature?  I don’t think so.  And does she believe that use and disuse of organs, together with epigenetic inheritance, explains adaptations?  I can’t see that she does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She does identify her views as Lamarckian in her web page at the Third Way of Evolution website (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thethirdwayofevolution.com/people/view/eva-jablonka&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).  She is also a member of the Extended Evolutionary Synthesis group (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://extendedevolutionarysynthesis.com/person/eva-jablonka/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).  She has written many books, and you can easily find YouTube videos of lectures where she advocates views she calls Lamarckian. For a critical review of her arguments, see Bruce Walsh’s book review in volume 50, number 5, 1996 in &lt;em&gt;Evolution&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/epdf/10.1111/j.1558-5646.1996.tb03600.x&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving aside her main concerns, which are to vindicate the importance of epigenetic phenomena in evolution, and to place them in the context of other forms of non-Mendelian inheritance, we can ask whether Lamarck would recognize her views as his own.  I can’t see that he would.  “Lamarckian” evolutionary phenomena may be repeatedly invoked by a generation of skeptics of the Modern Evolutionary Synthesis.  But in their view evolutionary changes that involve epigenetic variations in populations come from natural selection acting on those variations.  By contrast, use and disuse is different: a kind of directed mutation.  Lamarck’s theory invoked, in effect, directed mutation, and did not depend on selecting among variations in the population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lamarck is being invoked against the Modern Synthesis.  But his theories of change are not.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Happy birthday, Jean-Baptiste! On this day, August 1, in 1744 Jean-Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet, the Chevalier de Lamarck, was born. Had he lived he would now be a sprightly 278 years old. It is time for my annual birthday post. He was the first evolutionary biologist. In addition to world-class work in invertebrate taxonomy he argued for common descent and put forward a mechanism to account for adaptation. No not inheritance of acquired characters – everyone always knew that it was true. The mechanism was Use and Disuse. Organisms tried to solve their problems by using (or disusing) their organs, and the resulting changes would be adaptive and of course would be passed on to the next generation. Lamarck also believed that, in addition, there was an overall force in descent of organisms in nature leading to an increase of complexity. Is Lamarckism dead now? Well, yes and no. Let me explain …</summary></entry></feed>