<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-07-09T04:03:05-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Daniel Phelps wins Paleontological Society award</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/daniel-phelps-paleontological-society-award.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Daniel Phelps wins Paleontological Society award" /><published>2021-07-07T14:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-07T14:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/daniel-phelps-paleontological-society-award</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/daniel-phelps-paleontological-society-award.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Dan_Phelps_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Daniel Phelps&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniel Phelps of Lexington, Kentucky, is the recipient if the 2021 Strimple Award of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.paleosoc.org/who-we-are&quot;&gt;Paleontological Society&lt;/a&gt;, an international nonprofit organization devoted exclusively to the advancement of the science of paleontology. The Strimple Award recognizes outstanding achievement in paleontology by someone who does not make a living full-time from paleontology. Contributions may be an outstanding record of research and publication, making outstanding collections, safeguarding unique paleontological materials through public service, teaching activities in the area of paleontology, and collaborations with others working in paleontology. The award will be given online as part of the Geological Society of America annual meeting in Portland, Oregon on October 12.*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Paleontological Society is the world’s leading scientific organization for studying invertebrate and vertebrate paleontology, micropaleontology, and paleobotany. The Society has membership in 40 countries and consists of professional paleontologists, academicians, science editors, earth-science teachers, museum specialists, and undergraduate and graduate students and postdoctoral scholars, as well as avocational paleontologists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniel Phelps is well known to readers of PT. He is President and founder of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.uky.edu/OtherOrgs/KPS/&quot;&gt;Kentucky Paleontological Society&lt;/a&gt;. He is a retired environmental geologist for the Commonwealth of Kentucky. He has also taught geology part-time in Kentucky’s Community College system and once worked for a major petroleum company’s Plano, Texas, research center. Dan is also Vice-President of Kentuckians for Science Education. He was a major participant in the documentary “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webelieveindinosaurs.net&quot;&gt;We Believe in Dinosaurs&lt;/a&gt;,” which aired on PBS’s series Independent Lens in February, 2020 (see, for example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2016/12/we-believe-in-dinosaurs.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/04/reviews-of-documentary.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* Full disclosure: based almost entirely on a press release.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Daniel Phelps of Lexington, Kentucky, is the recipient if the 2021 Strimple Award of the Paleontological Society, an international nonprofit organization devoted exclusively to the advancement of the science of paleontology. The Strimple Award recognizes outstanding achievement in paleontology by someone who does not make a living full-time from paleontology. Contributions may be an outstanding record of research and publication, making outstanding collections, safeguarding unique paleontological materials through public service, teaching activities in the area of paleontology, and collaborations with others working in paleontology. The award will be given online as part of the Geological Society of America annual meeting in Portland, Oregon on October 12.* The Paleontological Society is the world’s leading scientific organization for studying invertebrate and vertebrate paleontology, micropaleontology, and paleobotany. The Society has membership in 40 countries and consists of professional paleontologists, academicians, science editors, earth-science teachers, museum specialists, and undergraduate and graduate students and postdoctoral scholars, as well as avocational paleontologists. Daniel Phelps is well known to readers of PT. He is President and founder of the Kentucky Paleontological Society. He is a retired environmental geologist for the Commonwealth of Kentucky. He has also taught geology part-time in Kentucky’s Community College system and once worked for a major petroleum company’s Plano, Texas, research center. Dan is also Vice-President of Kentuckians for Science Education. He was a major participant in the documentary “We Believe in Dinosaurs,” which aired on PBS’s series Independent Lens in February, 2020 (see, for example, here and here). * Full disclosure: based almost entirely on a press release.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest ends in &amp;lt;2 days</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/photography-contest-xiii-ends-2-days.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest ends in &amp;lt;2 days" /><published>2021-07-05T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-05T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/photography-contest-xiii-ends-2-days</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/photography-contest-xiii-ends-2-days.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/DSC03625_Wasp_Xoridinae_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wasp&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;Ichneumonid wasp, subfamily &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xoridinae&quot;&gt;Xorinidae&lt;/a&gt;, female with ovipositor, September, 2020, Boulder, Colorado.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;Reminder: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/photography-contest-xiii.html&quot;&gt;Photography Contest XIII&lt;/a&gt; ends in &amp;lt;2 days, on Wednesday, July 7, at noon, UTC – 6 h.&lt;/big&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, unless we decide to extend it for a week because of the July 4 holiday in the US. Stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Ichneumonid wasp, subfamily Xorinidae, female with ovipositor, September, 2020, Boulder, Colorado. Reminder: Photography Contest XIII ends in &amp;lt;2 days, on Wednesday, July 7, at noon, UTC – 6 h. Well, unless we decide to extend it for a week because of the July 4 holiday in the US. Stay tuned.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest Ends in 5 Days</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/photography-contest-xiii-ends-5-days.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest Ends in 5 Days" /><published>2021-07-02T16:32:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-02T16:32:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/photography-contest-xiii-ends-5-days</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/photography-contest-xiii-ends-5-days.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/DSC03820_Wasp_Mischocyttarus_flavitarsis_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wasp&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mischocyttarus_flavitarsis&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt; Mischocyttarus_flavitarsis&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; paper wasp, November, 2020, Boulder, Colorado.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;Reminder: Photography Contest XIII ends in 5 days, on Wednesday, July 7, at noon, UTC – 6 h.&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Mischocyttarus_flavitarsis &amp;ndash; paper wasp, November, 2020, Boulder, Colorado. Reminder: Photography Contest XIII ends in 5 days, on Wednesday, July 7, at noon, UTC – 6 h.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Q and A on phylogeny for the skeptic</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/Phylogeny-Q-and-A-for-the-skeptic.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Q and A on phylogeny for the skeptic" /><published>2021-07-01T10:48:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-01T10:48:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/Phylogeny-Q-and-A-for-the-skeptic</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/07/Phylogeny-Q-and-A-for-the-skeptic.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions by Josh Swamidass, the rest by John Harshman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/cladograms.png&quot; alt=&quot;figure 1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

The most powerful evidence in favor of common descent is what’s called the nested hierarchy of life. Other scientists may have their own candidates for most powerful evidence, and might say that the most powerful evidence comes from within their fields. A paleontologist might point to the fossil record. But I’m a phylogeneticist and I’m writing this, so nested hierarchy it is. Also, since I work with molecular data, I’m going to talk most often about DNA sequences. But what I say applies to all sorts of other data too: proteins, anatomy, behavior, whatever heritable features an organism has.
&lt;p&gt;

 &quot;Nested hierarchy”, stated most simply, means that species can be organized into a branching tree: species at the ends of the twigs, meeting in branches, that themselves meet other branches, and finally coming down to a meeting of all branches at the root of the tree. Further, the tree represents the actual pattern of branching descent, with each joining of branches representing the common ancestor of all the species above it.
&lt;p&gt;

But of course the tree diagram itself is evidence of nothing; you can draw a tree for any combination of species, and in fact you can draw any number of different trees connected in different ways for the same combination. What makes the tree evidence is that you use data to determine the tree, lots of data, and that different samples of data consistently determine a particular tree rather than a bunch of wildly different ones. For example, consider a very simple tree of four species: human, chimpanzee, gorilla, and orangutan. How do we know those species are related by common descent? There are fifteen possible ways to arrange these four species into a tree, and the one supported by most evidence is tree #1 in the figure above.
&lt;p&gt;

We also need some way to decide which tree the data fit. I’m going to use a very simple criterion, parsimony. Other criteria are more complex, but the way they are used is the same. Under parsimony, the tree that most simply accounts for the similarities and differences among the species is the one that fits. Consider, for example, the two characteristics (characters, for short) shown in the figure above, character #1 in blue and character #2 in red. Each of them has two possible values, or states, that we name A and B. In the tree at left, look at character #1 (again, in blue); the human and chimp both have the state A, and the gorilla and orangutan share state B. That’s  most simply explained by a change in character state, from B to A, happening in one branch of the left-hand tree. But the same character would require two changes to explain the distribution of A and B among species on the right-hand tree. For that reason we say that character supports the left-hand tree but not the right-hand tree. (Character B, the one in red, supports the right-hand tree but not the left-hand tree) If we collect a great many characters and they all support the left-hand tree, that’s good evidence of a true nested hierarchy and thus a true tree of descent.
&lt;p&gt;

Any questions? 

&lt;!--more--&gt;
 
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;em&gt;1. What would it look like for data not to fit the tree?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

There are many possible measurements of the fit of data to a tree, and they aren’t all or nothing. Data would fit the tree to a greater or lesser degree, and the degree of fit would not just be to the tree itself but to the tree and the model of change you attach to it. But forgetting all those complexities, let's consider one simple model, parsimony: data fit the tree if they can be explained by the smallest possible number of evolutionary changes. If there are two possible states of a character, as in the figure above, the smallest possible number of changes is one, and the character fits the tree perfectly if only one change is needed to account for the distribution of states in the included species, as the left-hand tree did for character #1. If two or more changes are needed, as for character #2 on the left-hand tree, the character doesn’t fit the tree, or at least not perfectly. Character #2 fits the right-hand tree instead. If we have a large collection of characters, a data set, the data set fits the tree perfectly if each character requires only one change on that tree. If a few characters require two (or even more) changes, the data set fits the tree pretty well. If we look at all possible trees, we say the data fit the left-hand tree  if most of the characters are like the character #1, requiring one change on that tree and two or more changes on other trees. If, on the other hand, different pieces of data prefer different trees, with no clear winner, that would show that the data set does not fit the tree.
&lt;p&gt;
 
&lt;em&gt;2. If common descent is true, do we expect violations in the tree in evolution? When and why?&lt;/em&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;

Yes, we do. There are several reasons why characters would be expected not  to fit the tree. The simplest is homoplasy: the same state arising twice at different spots on the tree. If changes are randomly sprinkled throughout the genome, we would expect a certain proportion of those changes to happen twice, on different branches of the tree. The resulting pattern of character states wouldn’t fit the tree on which they had actually occurred. Other possible reasons are incomplete lineage sorting and horizontal transfer.
 &lt;p&gt;

Homoplasy is most likely to happen when branches are long (that is, a long time has passed) and the number of possible states of a character is limited. In DNA sequence data, there are only four possible states of a character: A, C, G, or T. And there’s no way to tell by looking at them whether two A’s resulted from the same ancestral mutation (homology) or two different ones (homoplasy). Worse, changes between A and G or C and T, called transitions, are much more common than other changes, so in the short run, there are more like two states than four. So purely by chance, we expect some homoplasy from common descent. After a long enough time has passed, in fact, the data will have become randomized and will have lost all information about the tree.
 &lt;p&gt;

A second source of homoplasy is adaptive convergence: two distantly related species in similar environments may find similar adaptations, which might be interpreted by researchers as the same character state. The more complex a character and the more possible different adaptations might serve the same function, the less likely the researcher is to be fooled by convergence. Squid and fish, for example, are streamlined in superficially similar ways, because they are both adapted to minimizing drag in high speed swimming. But the fish swims forward while the squid swims backwards, so no one would confuse those as the same state. In DNA data, a single site might easily converge due to selection, but a long sequence of sites is much less likely to do so.
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/ILS.png&quot; alt=&quot;figure 2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
 
Another common event is incomplete lineage sorting. Since populations are not uniform but contain genetic variation, some of that variation can be long-lasting enough to be maintained across multiple branchings of species. When that variation is eventually sorted out, as must eventually happen, different species may retain different variations. In such cases, the actual tree of descent of the characters may differ slightly from the tree of the species they reside in and from the trees of other characters. 
 &lt;p&gt;

Incomplete lineage sorting is most likely to happen when branching events (speciations) are close in time to each other, i.e. branches are short, and the population is large. You can think of lineages as pipes in which the frequencies of different character states (alleles) are fluctuating. In the figure above, the top edge of the pipe represents 100% frequency for one allele (represented by gray), and the bottom 100% frequency for the other (represented by white). The jagged line between gray and white is the current frequency at that point in the pipe. If the frequency line hits the top or bottom side, one allele has become fixed (which just means that it has reached 100% frequency). The larger the population, the wider the pipe, and the more time, on average, it takes for the randomly varying frequency to hit either side. If there’s speciation, a branching of the pipe, before one allele is fixed, each new pipe will probably inherit some of each allele. And if there’s a short enough time until the next branching of the pipe, fixation still won’t have happened, and both alleles may be inherited by those new species too. Eventually, one allele will inevitably become fixed in each species, and the different alleles may not reflect the history of the species, though they do reflect the true history of the alleles themselves. In the figure, The white allele is the original allele, inherited by the orangutan. The gray allele begins in the common ancestor of human, chimp, and gorilla, and lasts along with the white allele through two successive branchings of the tree. The gray allele has become fixed in human and gorilla, while the white allele has become fixed in the chimp. The true phylogeny of the gene shown contradicts the true phylogeny of the species it contains, and a tree based on this gene would show humans and gorillas as closest relatives.
 &lt;p&gt;

A third source of violations of the tree is horizontal transfer, resulting from genetic exchange between species. It’s most common between closely related species whose populations are in contact or from infection by viruses that transfer their genetic material to the host.
 &lt;p&gt;

So how do we deal with characters that conflict with the tree? If we’re lucky, homoplasy and other sources of conflict are rare and affect few characters. If homoplasy is common but random, different characters showing homoplasy will disagree on what tree to support, leaving the characters without homoplasy to show a consistent signal that stands out from the noise, even if collectively the noise is louder than the signal.
 &lt;p&gt;

&lt;em&gt;3. Are the species misleadingly cherry picked to match the attributes to minimize homoplasy?&lt;/em&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;

No. The species in phylogenetic studies are picked to answer the questions the researcher is interested in. If you want to know relationships of humans within primates, you pick species from all the various groups of primates, and perhaps a rodent or two for an outgroup. If you want to know whether humans really are primates, you pick species from various other groups of mammals as well as a collection of primates. And generally you don’t know in advance how much homoplasy you will encounter.
 &lt;p&gt;

There are cases in which you might choose to leave out some species: those at the end of very long branches may have accumulated so much homoplasy that they cause problems for the analysis. Leaving them out is one solution, but another would be to add more species that break up that long branch. However, that’s not always possible, as such species may not exist.
 &lt;p&gt;

&lt;em&gt;4. Are attributes cherry-picked, such that other attributes would not fit the tree? What is a fair way to pick attributes?&lt;/em&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;

Not usually. Attributes are picked because they show a reasonable amount of variation. If a character doesn’t vary across the tree, it can’t disagree with any tree, and so is useless for a test. If a character varies wildly within species, it doesn’t provide evidence for variation between species. There’s a middle ground that provides the most efficient source of data, enough variation to be useful but not enough to dissolve into noise, and that middle ground may be different depending on what collection of species you want to study. More recent events may be best investigated using fast-evolving DNA sequences such as introns, while very ancient events may be best investigated using amino acid sequences of slowly evolving proteins. Importantly, when choosing a sequence of DNA to include in a data set, we don’t know in advance what tree it will support, and we use all of the sequence we gather, so cherry-picking is unlikely. With anatomical data, cherry-picking is possible, but scientists make every effort to sample a variety of characters so as to avoid this, and again without regard to what sort of tree they might support. 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>John Harshman</name></author><summary type="html">Questions by Josh Swamidass, the rest by John Harshman The most powerful evidence in favor of common descent is what’s called the nested hierarchy of life. Other scientists may have their own candidates for most powerful evidence, and might say that the most powerful evidence comes from within their fields. A paleontologist might point to the fossil record. But I’m a phylogeneticist and I’m writing this, so nested hierarchy it is. Also, since I work with molecular data, I’m going to talk most often about DNA sequences. But what I say applies to all sorts of other data too: proteins, anatomy, behavior, whatever heritable features an organism has. &quot;Nested hierarchy”, stated most simply, means that species can be organized into a branching tree: species at the ends of the twigs, meeting in branches, that themselves meet other branches, and finally coming down to a meeting of all branches at the root of the tree. Further, the tree represents the actual pattern of branching descent, with each joining of branches representing the common ancestor of all the species above it. But of course the tree diagram itself is evidence of nothing; you can draw a tree for any combination of species, and in fact you can draw any number of different trees connected in different ways for the same combination. What makes the tree evidence is that you use data to determine the tree, lots of data, and that different samples of data consistently determine a particular tree rather than a bunch of wildly different ones. For example, consider a very simple tree of four species: human, chimpanzee, gorilla, and orangutan. How do we know those species are related by common descent? There are fifteen possible ways to arrange these four species into a tree, and the one supported by most evidence is tree #1 in the figure above. We also need some way to decide which tree the data fit. I’m going to use a very simple criterion, parsimony. Other criteria are more complex, but the way they are used is the same. Under parsimony, the tree that most simply accounts for the similarities and differences among the species is the one that fits. Consider, for example, the two characteristics (characters, for short) shown in the figure above, character #1 in blue and character #2 in red. Each of them has two possible values, or states, that we name A and B. In the tree at left, look at character #1 (again, in blue); the human and chimp both have the state A, and the gorilla and orangutan share state B. That’s most simply explained by a change in character state, from B to A, happening in one branch of the left-hand tree. But the same character would require two changes to explain the distribution of A and B among species on the right-hand tree. For that reason we say that character supports the left-hand tree but not the right-hand tree. (Character B, the one in red, supports the right-hand tree but not the left-hand tree) If we collect a great many characters and they all support the left-hand tree, that’s good evidence of a true nested hierarchy and thus a true tree of descent. Any questions?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pygoscelis papua</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/Pygoscelis-papua.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pygoscelis papua" /><published>2021-06-28T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-06-28T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/Pygoscelis-papua</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/Pygoscelis-papua.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Jerry Coyne&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/P1050167_Coyne_Penguins_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gentoo penguin&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gentoo_penguin&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Pygoscelis papua&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; gentoo penguin, Antarctica, November, 2019.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today is one of the middle Mondays of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/photography-contest-xiii.html&quot;&gt;Photography Contest&lt;/a&gt;, and I want to display a photograph sent to us by Jerry Coyne. Professor Coyne is the proprietor of the popular blog, &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/&quot;&gt;Why Evolution Is True&lt;/a&gt;. He publishes a daily readers’ wildlife photo feature, which can include travel or street photography, and he likes to get batches of around ten photos. He requests that any PT readers who have &lt;i&gt;good&lt;/i&gt; photographs submit them to j-coyne@uchicago.edu. Professor Coyne is an &lt;a href=&quot;https://ecologyandevolution.uchicago.edu/people/emeritus-faculty&quot;&gt;Emeritus Professor of Ecology and Evolution&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Chicago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think he must have considered my photographs to be acceptable, because he graciously posted eight of them the other day. You may see them &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2021/06/26/readers-wildlife-photos-1336/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, if you have not already seen some of them on PT.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Jerry Coyne. Pygoscelis papua &amp;ndash; gentoo penguin, Antarctica, November, 2019. Today is one of the middle Mondays of the Photography Contest, and I want to display a photograph sent to us by Jerry Coyne. Professor Coyne is the proprietor of the popular blog, Why Evolution Is True. He publishes a daily readers’ wildlife photo feature, which can include travel or street photography, and he likes to get batches of around ten photos. He requests that any PT readers who have good photographs submit them to j-coyne@uchicago.edu. Professor Coyne is an Emeritus Professor of Ecology and Evolution at the University of Chicago. I think he must have considered my photographs to be acceptable, because he graciously posted eight of them the other day. You may see them here, if you have not already seen some of them on PT.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bill Dembski has thoughts about COVID-19</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/Dembskipandas.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bill Dembski has thoughts about COVID-19" /><published>2021-06-22T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-06-22T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/Dembskipandas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/Dembskipandas.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Devilbat.png&quot; alt=&quot;Devil Bat movie&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  Are killer bat experiments by mad scientists only the stuff of B movies?
  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although William Dembski is no longer a prominent figure in the Intelligent Design movement he helped found, he does remain among its proponents and occasionally writes about it on his blog.  A recent entry entitled &lt;a href=&quot;https://billdembski.com/intelligent-design/how-to-cover-up-design-inferences/&quot;&gt;&quot;How to Cover Up a Design Inference: The Coronavirus as a Case Study&quot;&lt;/a&gt; draws some unexpected, and unintentionally revealing, connections between ID and the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;He begins with a brief summary of his ID argument:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;(My) method took the form of an inference—specifically, an inference to the best explanation. Thus the method asserted that if an event, object, or structure conforms to an independently given pattern (i.e., a specification) and if in the absence of intelligence the probability of matching that pattern is small (i.e., improbability), then a design inference is warranted. Simply put, specified improbability constitutes a method for inferring design. Moreover, things that exhibit specified improbability are best explained as the product of intelligence.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dembski then refers to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/the-science-suggests-a-wuhan-lab-leak-11622995184&quot;&gt;recent article in the Wall Street Journal&lt;/a&gt; by medical doctor Stephen Quay and physics professor Richard Muller supporting the belief that SARS-CoV-2, the virus responsible for COVID-19, did not arise naturally in an animal host as most experts believe but, rather, was artificially engineered in a Chinese lab.  In support of this belief, they claim that SARS-CoV-2 contains the sequence CGG-CGG which “in the entire class of coronaviruses that includes CoV-2… has never been found naturally.”  However, according to them, it is commonly used in “gain of function” viral experiments in the laboratory.  Their conclusion is that the presence of this sequence demonstrates that SARS-CoV-2 did not have a zoonotic origin but, instead, was created by human scientists.  Dembski's response to this argument is, “If this is not a full design inference in the sense of my Cambridge University Press monograph, it’s close.”  And while he does qualify his position by saying he is not a conspiracy theorist and has not studied this issue in depth, Dembski clearly considers the possibility that the Chinese manufactured the virus to be at least highly plausible.&lt;p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he then goes beyond even that and suggests that the Chinese government may now be engaged in an elaborate cover up operation involving the artificial creation of even more viruses that resemble the transitional forms the would be expected to exist if the virus had arisen naturally.  These would then be used to infect bats and other animals.  (I must say, I have spent some time reading up on the COVID-19 lab leak theory, but have not encountered anyone else suggesting this further diabolical aspect of the alleged plot, in which pandemics are not only being caused in humans, but in bats and other innocent creatures.  The only source Dembski cites is a tweet from a former Fox News reporter who now runs a wine business.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does one respond to all this?  Well, to begin with this entire argument regarding the CGG-CGG sequence has been definitively debunked.  While it is true that this sequence is not found in any of the other known SARS-like coronaviruses, that is a cohort of only three.  Among coronaviruses as a whole the sequence is not at all uncommon.  Virologist Kristian Anderson, one of the scientists involved in identifying SARS-CoV-2 and sequencing its genome, has provided &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/beingwell/nobel-winning-virologist-eats-wuhan-crow-1709ba20ef7d&quot;&gt;a detailed explanation&lt;/a&gt; of how the virus shows no signs of having arisen through anything other than natural processes. So right out of the block, Dembski is just blowing someone else’s hot air without having bothered to verify whether the claims have any merit, something that would have only required that he take a few quick moments from his “day job as a businessman” to do a Google search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, that aside, I do believe Dembski’s article reveals more than he intends about his particular take on ID.  His rather detached attitude to the question of the virus’s origin is curious given his self-proclaimed status as one of the world’s leading experts in detecting “design” in nature.  It would seem if he really believed his own promotional material, he would be volunteering his services and expertise to help answer a question that has been at the forefront of the single gravest issue facing humanity at this moment:  Where did SARS-CoV-2 come from?  Surely Bill Dembski can delay his quest to become a cryptocurrency billionaire for just a few days while he helps save the human race, no?  Bruce Wayne and Tony Stark do it all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same question applies to the ID movement as a whole.  It’s not as if they have not had anything to say about COVID-19.  But their previous efforts were primarily focused on &lt;a href=&quot;https://thefederalist.com/2020/05/14/trump-needs-to-recruit-a-medical-red-team-to-challenge-lockdown-manic-governors/&quot;&gt;reversing lockdowns and other public health measures&lt;/a&gt; that, they feared, would jeopardize Donald Trump’s re-election by harming the economy.  Almost a year ago, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.americanscientist.org/blog/macroscope/did-intelligent-design-just-miss-its-corona-moment&quot;&gt;an article in American Scientist&lt;/a&gt; asked if ID had missed its “corona moment.” With the lab leak theory rearing its head yet again, that moment has returned, but ID is still missing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is, if ID actually had anything of value to contribute to the detection of “design” in biology.  But, on the contrary, I believe Dembski’s article only serves to accentuate why ID fails even at the theoretical level.  As I have said, the argument that the virus’s double CGG sequence is evidence of design is unsound because it turns out this sequence exists in viruses that have evolved naturally.  However, the logic of the general argument itself is valid.  That is to say, if one &lt;i&gt;were&lt;/i&gt; to identify sequences in the virus that do not occur in nature but which are commonly found in viruses that are manufactured in a lab, then that would indeed be strong evidence that SARS-CoV-2 had been manufactured. And, I would argue, this is how we determine whether or not something is designed in all other cases.  We do not determine this through measuring &lt;a href=&quot;http://users.fred.net/tds/lab/papers/ev/dembski/specified.complexity.html&quot;&gt;“complex specified information”&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/review-michael-behes-darwins-black-box&quot;&gt;&quot;irreducible complexity&quot;&lt;/a&gt;, by employing an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.talkdesign.org/faqs/theftovertoil/theftovertoil.html&quot;&gt;“explanatory filter”&lt;/a&gt; nor through appeal to any of the other vapid buzz words devised by the ID movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather, the question of whether something was designed is answered through empirically derived knowledge regarding which things arise through natural processes, and which only arise through being created by intelligent designers.  Since bacteria who possess flagella arise thru the natural process of reproduction, we do not conclude that the bacterial flagellum was designed.  But since the outboard motor of a boat is not something that arises in nature, but is only manufactured by human beings, we know that it was designed. Without this background knowledge (which is not at all difficult to obtain), there is nothing inherent in the objects themselves that betrays their origin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many ID proponents argue that one of the chief hallmarks of “design” is the impossibility of the existence of functional transitional forms between one functional system and another.  So it is very odd that Dembski does not indicate he believes there would be any difficulty whatsoever in creating a series of transitional viruses leading up to SARS-CoV-2.  It would appear that, as Dembski sees it, the project would only be limited by the mendacity and cunning of the Chinese government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If one were to present this argument to Dembski or any other proponent of ID, of course, they would almost certainly reject it.  However, their actions speak louder than their words.  When an opportunity arises that seems tailor-made for the practical application of their “theories”, it does not even cross their mind to take it.  And that suggests to me that, deep down, even they realize their ideas are worthless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Faizal Ali</name></author><summary type="html">Are killer bat experiments by mad scientists only the stuff of B movies? Although William Dembski is no longer a prominent figure in the Intelligent Design movement he helped found, he does remain among its proponents and occasionally writes about it on his blog. A recent entry entitled &quot;How to Cover Up a Design Inference: The Coronavirus as a Case Study&quot; draws some unexpected, and unintentionally revealing, connections between ID and the COVID-19 pandemic. He begins with a brief summary of his ID argument: (My) method took the form of an inference—specifically, an inference to the best explanation. Thus the method asserted that if an event, object, or structure conforms to an independently given pattern (i.e., a specification) and if in the absence of intelligence the probability of matching that pattern is small (i.e., improbability), then a design inference is warranted. Simply put, specified improbability constitutes a method for inferring design. Moreover, things that exhibit specified improbability are best explained as the product of intelligence. Dembski then refers to a recent article in the Wall Street Journal by medical doctor Stephen Quay and physics professor Richard Muller supporting the belief that SARS-CoV-2, the virus responsible for COVID-19, did not arise naturally in an animal host as most experts believe but, rather, was artificially engineered in a Chinese lab. In support of this belief, they claim that SARS-CoV-2 contains the sequence CGG-CGG which “in the entire class of coronaviruses that includes CoV-2… has never been found naturally.” However, according to them, it is commonly used in “gain of function” viral experiments in the laboratory. Their conclusion is that the presence of this sequence demonstrates that SARS-CoV-2 did not have a zoonotic origin but, instead, was created by human scientists. Dembski's response to this argument is, “If this is not a full design inference in the sense of my Cambridge University Press monograph, it’s close.” And while he does qualify his position by saying he is not a conspiracy theorist and has not studied this issue in depth, Dembski clearly considers the possibility that the Chinese manufactured the virus to be at least highly plausible.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest XIII</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/photography-contest-xiii.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest XIII" /><published>2021-06-21T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-06-21T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/photography-contest-xiii</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/photography-contest-xiii.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/DSC04337_Sekonic_Light_Meter_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Light meter&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Sekonic light meter designed to fit on accessory shoe for 35-mm camera. This is perhaps somewhat off-task, but I cannot find a date for the meter. The accessory shoe, soon to evolve into a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hot_shoe&quot;&gt;hot shoe&lt;/a&gt;, was developed in the 1970's, so the meter probably predates 1970. The highest ASA (ISO) speed is 3200, so the meter probably cannot date as early as the 1940's or even 1950's (Kodak Royal X Pan came out around 1957 with an astronomical ASA daylight speed of 1250). The meter is worth about $30 US, used.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For the uninitiated, you set the ASA speed by rotating the inner ring. In this case the ASA speed is 80. The meter reads &quot;3,&quot; so rotate the outer ring till the tick is opposite the &lt;i&gt;red&lt;/i&gt; 3. Then read the exposure &amp;ndash; for example, F/11 and 1/100&amp;nbsp;s. Now set your camera accordingly and take the picture. If your camera uses exposure values (EV), then use the number next to the black ASA speed (the black and red numbers are used to avoid crowding).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The meter is photovoltaic, which means that (a) it is not as sensitive as a battery-powered photoconductive meter, but (b) it still works. You may convert the meter to an incident-light meter by opening the little door on the upper edge of the case.

&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 13th annual Panda’s Thumb Photography Contest begins now, Monday, June 21, at 12:00 p.m., MDT (MDT = UTC(GMT) – 6 h). Entries will be accepted between now and Wednesday, July 7, at 12:00 p.m., MDT. The rules are precisely the same as &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/photography-contest-xii.html&quot;&gt;last year’s&lt;/a&gt;, except, obviously, that the dates have been updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We encourage entries in a single, general category, which includes pictures of just about anything of scientific interest: any object of experimentation or observation, from single-celled organisms, through nematodes, fruit flies, rats, chimpanzees, and college sophomores to volcanoes, stars, and galaxies. In order not to omit theoreticians, we will consider computer-generated pictures and also photographs of equipment. Photomicrographs and electron micrographs are likewise welcomed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since rumor has it that the pandemic encouraged macro photography, we may, if we receive enough entries, establish a “macro” category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winner and the runner-up will receive a copy of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/534976/improbable-destinies-by-jonathan-b-losos/&quot;&gt;Improbable Destinies&lt;/a&gt; by Jonathan Losos, generously donated by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.com/&quot;&gt;National Center for Science Education&lt;/a&gt;, and a copy of one of my own books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we get enough entries, consistently with Rules 11 and 12, we may add categories and award additional prizes, presuming, of course, that we can find more prizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rules of the contest are simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We will consider any photograph that displays scientific interest – biological, paleontological, geological, or astronomical, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Submit photographs in JPEG format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Reduce photographs to an information content of 600 pixels horizontally. If creationists require a definition of information, they may apply in writing to the management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Photographs may be enhanced but may not be montages. High dynamic range photographs are, however, accepted. Submit a maximum of 3 photographs (or 5 photographs per family) to thousandwords@pandasthumb.org.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Submit the photographs as attachments to an e-mail (not embedded in the body of the e-mail). The subject line to the e-mail must have the form YourLastName_PhotographyContest. The filenames for the photographs must have the form YourLastName_Descriptor as, for example, Young_Oxytropis_sericea or Young_Table_Mountain, as appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In your e-mail, identify the subject of the photograph: common and biological name, mineral type, or geological formation, for example. Provide a link that will allow a reader to learn more about the subject. You may add descriptive text in the body of the e-mail if you like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Depending on the number of photographs submitted, we may post the best submissions and ask our readers to vote for the best photograph. Likewise, we may establish several categories with separate entries and separate ballots. In particular, students 16 and under should so identify themselves; if we receive enough entries, we will establish a student category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By submitting a photograph, you stipulate that you are the owner of the copyright and grant The Panda’s Thumb a nonexclusive license to publish the photograph on its blog. The photograph will be subject to a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-No Derivatives license.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Regular contributors to The Panda’s Thumb are not eligible to enter the contest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The decision of the judges is irrevocable. The judges remain irrepressibly and irreducibly irascible, irreverent, and irredeemable, irregardless and irrespective, but not, we hope, irrational or irritable. We hope for a veritable irruption of entries this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Even though we are getting fairly good at running contests, we reserve the right to change any of the rules, or add or subtract rules at any time at our discretion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will choose a number of finalists and open voting for the winner at 12:00 p.m., Monday, July 12. Voting will end Friday, July 23, at 12:00 noon, and the winner will be announced om Monday, July 26, at 12:00.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Sekonic light meter designed to fit on accessory shoe for 35-mm camera. This is perhaps somewhat off-task, but I cannot find a date for the meter. The accessory shoe, soon to evolve into a hot shoe, was developed in the 1970's, so the meter probably predates 1970. The highest ASA (ISO) speed is 3200, so the meter probably cannot date as early as the 1940's or even 1950's (Kodak Royal X Pan came out around 1957 with an astronomical ASA daylight speed of 1250). The meter is worth about $30 US, used. For the uninitiated, you set the ASA speed by rotating the inner ring. In this case the ASA speed is 80. The meter reads &quot;3,&quot; so rotate the outer ring till the tick is opposite the red 3. Then read the exposure &amp;ndash; for example, F/11 and 1/100&amp;nbsp;s. Now set your camera accordingly and take the picture. If your camera uses exposure values (EV), then use the number next to the black ASA speed (the black and red numbers are used to avoid crowding). The meter is photovoltaic, which means that (a) it is not as sensitive as a battery-powered photoconductive meter, but (b) it still works. You may convert the meter to an incident-light meter by opening the little door on the upper edge of the case. The 13th annual Panda’s Thumb Photography Contest begins now, Monday, June 21, at 12:00 p.m., MDT (MDT = UTC(GMT) – 6 h). Entries will be accepted between now and Wednesday, July 7, at 12:00 p.m., MDT. The rules are precisely the same as last year’s, except, obviously, that the dates have been updated. We encourage entries in a single, general category, which includes pictures of just about anything of scientific interest: any object of experimentation or observation, from single-celled organisms, through nematodes, fruit flies, rats, chimpanzees, and college sophomores to volcanoes, stars, and galaxies. In order not to omit theoreticians, we will consider computer-generated pictures and also photographs of equipment. Photomicrographs and electron micrographs are likewise welcomed. Since rumor has it that the pandemic encouraged macro photography, we may, if we receive enough entries, establish a “macro” category. The winner and the runner-up will receive a copy of Improbable Destinies by Jonathan Losos, generously donated by the National Center for Science Education, and a copy of one of my own books.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nature Photography Day</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/nature-photography-day.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nature Photography Day" /><published>2021-06-15T15:20:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-06-15T15:20:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/nature-photography-day</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/nature-photography-day.html">&lt;p&gt;Today, according to the American Association for the Advancement of Science, is Nature Photography Day. You can see some of the photographs that were submitted to the AAAS on their Facebook page &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/AAAS.Science/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and many more &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/hashtag/naturephotographyday&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, while we are on the topic, please do not forget the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/hashtag/naturephotographyday&quot;&gt;Panda’s Thumb Photography Contest&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Today, according to the American Association for the Advancement of Science, is Nature Photography Day. You can see some of the photographs that were submitted to the AAAS on their Facebook page here and many more here. And, while we are on the topic, please do not forget the Panda’s Thumb Photography Contest!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Waiting time problem” and imaginary hurdles for evolution</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/ID-and-imaginary-hurdles.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Waiting time problem” and imaginary hurdles for evolution" /><published>2021-06-12T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-06-12T10:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/ID-and-imaginary-hurdles</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/ID-and-imaginary-hurdles.html">&lt;p&gt;ID-creationists Ola Hössjer, Günter Bechly, and Ann Gauger have managed to get a paper published &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519321000795&quot;&gt;(Hössjer et al. 2021)&lt;/a&gt; in the Journal of Theoretical Biology, in which they argue that a complex adaptation would take a very long time to evolve given certain imaginary conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/JTBHBG2021.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;JTB IDcreationist paper&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They never give any evidence that any known complex adaptation had to evolve through their imaginary scenario, so the relevance of their paper to real biology is only that, imaginary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the paper does sort of casually mention by name a number of complex adaptations that evolved in a (geologically speaking) short amount of time, Hössjer et al. never give any evidence that any of these adaptations actually evolved or &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to evolve through their imaginary scenario. Only this short section of the paper is what appears to try to connect their hypothetical scenario to the real world:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For more complex adaptations of a species, it is necessary that several genes are modified in a &lt;em&gt;coordinated&lt;/em&gt; manner, either through mutations in the coding sequence, or through changed expression of these &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt; genes. For instance, the fossil record is often interpreted as having long periods of stasis (Voje et al., 2018), interrupted by more abrupt changes and “explosive” origins (Bechly and Meyer, 2017). These changes include, for instance, the evolution of life (Bell et al., 2015), photosynthesis (Hecht, 2013), multicellularity and the “Avalon Explosion” (Shen et al., 2008), animal body plans and the “Cambrian Explosion” (Erwin and Valentine, 2013), complex eyes (Paterson et al., 2011), vertebrate jaws and teeth (Fraser et al., 2010), terrestrialization (e.g., in vascular plants, arthropods, and tetrapods) (Bateman et al., 1998), insect metamorphosis (Labandeira, 2011), animal flight and feathers (Wu et al., 2018, Yang et al., 2019), reproductive systems, including angiosperm flowers, amniote eggs, and the mammalian placenta (Chuong, 2013, Doyle, 2012, Roberts et al., 2016, Sauquet, 2017, Specht and Bartlett, 2009), echolocation in whales (Churchill et al., 2016, Park et al., 2016) and bats (Simmons et al., 2008), and even cognitive skills of modern man (Neubauer et al., 2018). Based on radiometric dating of the available windows of time in the fossil record, these genetic changes are believed to have happened very quickly on a macroevolutionary timescale. In order to evaluate the chances for a neo-Darwinian process to bring about such major phenotypic changes, it is important to give rough but reasonable estimates of the time it would take for a population to evolve so that the required multiple genetic changes occur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we read carefully with comprehension we see that none of these references even remotely indicate that the complex adaptations listed would have to evolve through the scenario Hössjer et al. go on to model. 
They start by simply asserting (my bold) that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For more complex adaptations of a species, &lt;strong&gt;it is necessary&lt;/strong&gt; that &lt;em&gt;several genes&lt;/em&gt; are modified in a &lt;em&gt;coordinated&lt;/em&gt; manner, either through mutations in the coding sequence, or through changed expression of these &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt; genes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They give no reference to substantiate that it is &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; for any of their following list of complex adaptations to have evolved with &lt;em&gt;“multiple genes”&lt;/em&gt; being modified in a &lt;em&gt;coordinated manner&lt;/em&gt; like the one they model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is really all one needs to say about this paper with respect to its relevance to real biology. It’s a typical example of GIGO, where the conclusion you derive from your calculation is entirely dictated by the reality of the assumptions you base them on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also another example of creationist papers focused on so-called “waiting time problems” with evolution, which are typically based on the entirely imaginary - and totally dubious premise - that there are “target sequences” that evolution must find and evolve towards without any input by natural selection, by mutating incrementally from some random ancestral sequence until the correct (or almost correct) “target” sequence is produced by the chance accumulation of mutations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To nobody’s surprise, the longer the target sequence is, the longer it will take before chance mutations happen to produce it or something very near to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for creationists, this imaginary scenario has next to nothing to do with how potential new genes gain regulatory promoter sequences. In real biology the background low-level affinities between DNA binding proteins and DNA sequences ensures that there’s almost always &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; activity for selection to act on to improve the binding between a transcription factor and a promoter sequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than try to calculate the probability of evolving this interaction with “targets” that have to match near-perfectly - from some random ancestor - with zero real chemical or biophysical input, biochemists have done even better and experimentally evolved promoters in the lab.  It turns out this is surprisingly easy for evolution. In an experiment with E coli &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-018-04026-w&quot;&gt;(Yona et al. 2018)&lt;/a&gt; approximately &lt;strong&gt;~60%&lt;/strong&gt; of random DNA sequences are &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; mutation away from turning into a selectively useful transcriptional promoter, and &lt;strong&gt;~10%&lt;/strong&gt; of random DNA sequences are functional promoters just by chance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Random sequences rapidly evolve into de novo promoters&lt;/strong&gt;
Avihu H. Yona, Eric J Alm &amp;amp; Jeff Gore&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;
How new functions arise de novo is a fundamental question in evolution. We studied de novo evolution of promoters in Escherichia coli by replacing the lac promoter with various random sequences of the same size (~100 bp) and evolving the cells in the presence of lactose. We find that ~60% of random sequences can evolve expression comparable to the wild-type with only one mutation, and that ~10% of random sequences can serve as active promoters even without evolution. Such a short mutational distance between random sequences and active promoters may improve the evolvability, yet may also lead to accidental promoters inside genes that interfere with normal expression. Indeed, our bioinformatic analyses indicate that E. coli was under selection to reduce accidental promoters inside genes by avoiding promoter-like sequences. We suggest that a low threshold for functionality balanced by selection against undesired targets can increase the evolvability by making new beneficial features more accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hössjer O, Bechly G, Gauger A. On the waiting time until coordinated mutations get fixed in regulatory sequences.Â &lt;em&gt;J Theor Biol&lt;/em&gt;. 2021;524:110657. doi:10.1016/j.jtbi.2021.110657&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yona AH, Alm EJ, Gore J. Random sequences rapidly evolve into de novo promoters.Â &lt;em&gt;Nat Commun&lt;/em&gt;. 2018;9(1):1530. Published 2018 Apr 18. doi:10.1038/s41467-018-04026-w&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mikkel Nif Rasmussen</name></author><summary type="html">ID-creationists Ola Hössjer, Günter Bechly, and Ann Gauger have managed to get a paper published (Hössjer et al. 2021) in the Journal of Theoretical Biology, in which they argue that a complex adaptation would take a very long time to evolve given certain imaginary conditions. They never give any evidence that any known complex adaptation had to evolve through their imaginary scenario, so the relevance of their paper to real biology is only that, imaginary.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest XIII Begins in 10 days</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/photography-contest-xiii-begins.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest XIII Begins in 10 days" /><published>2021-06-11T15:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-06-11T15:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/photography-contest-xiii-begins</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/photography-contest-xiii-begins.html">&lt;p&gt;Announcing the nth Panda’s Thumb Photography Contest, where n = 13. The contest will begin on Monday, June 21, 12:00, noon, Mountain Daylight Time (MDT = UTC - 6). The rules will be the same as &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/photography-contest-xii.html&quot;&gt;last year’s&lt;/a&gt;, give or take a few modifications. We will accept entries till Wednesday, July 7, also at 12:00 MDT. As in the past, we will post finalists on Monday, July 12, at 12:00. Voting will remain open till Friday, July 23, at 12:00. And we will post the winner on July 26 at 12:00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will not establish formal categories, but we reckon that a lot of our readers may have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dpreview.com/forums/post/64689925&quot;&gt;taken up macro photography as a result of the pandemic&lt;/a&gt;. Consequently, if we receive enough macro photographs, we may decide to establish two categories, “macro” and “ general.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will announce prizes on June 21.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Announcing the nth Panda’s Thumb Photography Contest, where n = 13. The contest will begin on Monday, June 21, 12:00, noon, Mountain Daylight Time (MDT = UTC - 6). The rules will be the same as last year’s, give or take a few modifications. We will accept entries till Wednesday, July 7, also at 12:00 MDT. As in the past, we will post finalists on Monday, July 12, at 12:00. Voting will remain open till Friday, July 23, at 12:00. And we will post the winner on July 26 at 12:00. We will not establish formal categories, but we reckon that a lot of our readers may have taken up macro photography as a result of the pandemic. Consequently, if we receive enough macro photographs, we may decide to establish two categories, “macro” and “ general.” We will announce prizes on June 21.</summary></entry></feed>