<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-02-14T12:31:44-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Does the genetic code reveal a Wow! signal? A team of scientists claim evidence for &quot;intelligent design&quot;</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/genetic-code-wow-signal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does the genetic code reveal a Wow! signal? A team of scientists claim evidence for &quot;intelligent design&quot;" /><published>2021-02-07T16:28:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-02-07T16:28:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/genetic-code-wow-signal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/genetic-code-wow-signal.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Neukamm_Wow_signal.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wow! sig-nal&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term “Wow! signal” represents a decade-long mystery in astronomy: In 1977, the astrophysicist Jerry Ehman received a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wow!_signal&quot;&gt;strong narrowband radio signal&lt;/a&gt; on the frequency of the 21 cm line of hydrogen with the gigantic big-ear radio telescope in Delaware in the US state of Ohio. There seemed to be no natural explanation for the persisting 72 s signal from the Sagittarius constellation, which was 30 standard deviations above the background noise. The profile of the strong, narrow-band signal corresponds to that of a communication antenna. Its discoverer highlighted the signal on the printout with a red circle and added an expression of astonishment by noting “Wow!” In the period that followed, there was a lively debate among experts as to whether it was an artificially generated or a natural signal. Although objects like pul-sars seem to be a possible source, the controversy continues to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, a team of Kazakh scientists published a &lt;a href=&quot;www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0019103513000791&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; claiming to have discovered a Wow! signal in the genetic code of living beings. The code structure, so they claimed, is statistically so striking that its origin could be explained only by the presumption of an intelligent actor. The paper, published in Icarus, was somewhat off-topic since Icarus is a journal for planetary science rather than molecular biology or evolution. Since then, the paper has been celebrated as evidence for the extraterrestrial origin of the genetic code by support-ers of ancient astronauts and by the intelligent design movement; see, for example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2013/03/a_wow_signal_of/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/extraterrestrial-life-genetic-code-as-wow-signal/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discovery.org/id/peer-review/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, as well as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.si-journal.de/index2.php?artikel=jg22/heft2/sij222-2.html&quot;&gt;this arti-cle&lt;/a&gt; in a German creationist journal. What’s it all about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ominous divisor 37 as a design signal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors of the paper are the mathematician Vladimir shCherbak from Al-Farabi University in Kazakhstan and the physicist Maxim Makukov from the Fessenkow Astrophysical Institute. The publisher of Icarus, a refereed journal, is the American Astronomical Society (AAS), an association of professional astronomers. The journal is mainly de-voted to initial publications in planetary scienceand is neither esoteric nor religious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to track down the alleged Wow! signal, shCherbak and Makukov first divided the 20 genetically encoded amino acids into two groups: In the first group, they listed all amino acids that are sufficiently defined by the first two bases of a base triplet (meaning that any change of the third base would not change the amino acid) (Fig. 1). A base triplet or codon is a sequence of three bases (“letters”) on the genetic molecule DNA (or on the RNA) coding for a specific amino acid. The authors placed the remaining amino acids into a second group. Then they calculated the nucleon number (molecular weight) of every amino acid in both groups, as well as the nucleon number of every amino acid basic structure (“block nucleons”) and side chain. Finally, they sorted the numbers and added them up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this operation, shCherbak and Makukov came across numerical ratios in which the divisor 37 appears again and again: In the first group, the nucleon sum of all side chains is 333 (= 37 x 3&lt;sup&gt;²&lt;/sup&gt;), that of all “block nucleons” 592 (= 37 x 4&lt;sup&gt;²&lt;/sup&gt;), and the total 925 = (37 x 5&lt;sup&gt;²&lt;/sup&gt;). Moreover: “With 037 cancelled out, this leads to 3&lt;sup&gt;²&lt;/sup&gt; + 4&lt;sup&gt;²&lt;/sup&gt; = 5&lt;sup&gt;²&lt;/sup&gt; – representation of the Egyptian triangle…” (p. 6). The number 37 also appears in the second group; the total number of nucleons in the amino acids is 1110 (= 30 x 37).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Neukamm_Figure_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Side chains&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Fig. 1. Structure of the side chains of those eight amino acids which are clearly defined by their first two codon bases. Side chains and their nucleon numbers (molecular weights) are shown in ascending order. The total is 333. However, this requires targeted manipulation (here: with proline). Further explanation in the text.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;shCherbak and Makukov discuss various other examples using different sorting and exchange operations. Another one is discussed in Fig. 2. In all those cases, the divisor 37 appears prominently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Neukamm_Figure_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Codons&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fig. 2 There are 24 codons, each with three very different bases (A, T, G, and C). shCherbak and Makukov arranged those codons in such a way that their nucleic bases are interchanged according to certain rules: Within each “block” of 3 codons, the first nucleic base is shifted from one row to the next one onto the third position. From block to block, A is exchanged for G, and T for C (and vice versa). On the left and right column, the codons are arranged mirror-imaged. Next to each codon, it is noted which amino acid it codes for, and the molecular weight of the side chains and whole molecules is noted. In total, there are numbers that are completely divisible by 37. Source: shCherbak and Makukov, p. 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the authors, the frequent appearance of “37”, the emergence of “Egyptian triangles”, etc. are far beyond the statistical significance of randomly generated patterns. Thus, these appearances cannot  be explained by natural processes since they are not relevant for biological function. The number “0” is also represented, as a corresponding symbol for start/stop codons. The authors claim: “Nature is indifferent to numerical languages contrived by intelligence to represent quantities, including zero”. Such a “privileged numerical system is therefore a reliable sign of artificiality” (p. 4). Ergo: “Whatever the actual reason behind the decimal system in the code, it appears that it was invented outside the solar system already several billions [of] years ago” (p. 8).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A method reminiscent of the Bible Code&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Neukamm_Figure_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bible code&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Fig. 3. The Bible Code. For detailed explanations see text. &lt;small&gt;Source: https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bibelcode. See  also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/No-Sense-Obligation-Religion-Impersonal/dp/0759610894/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, pp. 102-104.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/UFOs-Chemtrails-Aliens-What-Science/dp/025302692X&quot;&gt;Prothero and Callahan&lt;/a&gt; (p. 127) note that the approach of the authors shows clear similarities with the method of the so-called Bible code, which is as also called &lt;em&gt;equidistant letter spacing&lt;/em&gt; (ELS). It serves to track down presumed “hidden messages” and prophecies in biblical texts. How does this method work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To recognize the “message”, a rectangular grid with a constant but arbitrary number of columns and rows is placed over the text, and a freely selectable number of letters is skipped from a starting point in the horizontal and vertical direction. Then meaningful words or word constellations are sought (Fig. 3). According to this method, world historical events such as the Holocaust or 9/11 are said to have been predicted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is: Since the dimensions of the grid and the number of letters skipped when reading were freely defined, the “researchers”  most likely would have come up with different messages, had they chosen the width of the grid differently. Nobody read and verified relevant information that had not already been known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prothero and Callahan criticize the fact that the authors use the same subjective method to track down the presumed design signals in the genetic code. shCherbak and Makukov have also freely (meaning: arbitrarily) defined the logical criteria for dividing the amino acids into certain groups as well as the transformation and exchange rules according to which the “magic” sums appear. For example, if we would exchange A for T and G for C (rather than A for G and T for C) in Fig. 2, we would receive completely different sums and divisors. In other words, the authors get only results that they have already produced by their own rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interpretation of start/stop codons as a symbol for numerical 0 is just as arbitrary. And of course, if we interpret start and stop codons as numerical 0 on metaphysical grounds, it is not surprising, that we  “discover” a “privileged numerical system”, including 0. Garbage in, garbage out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice of molecular weights (nucleon numbers) of side chains, basic structures and whole molecules as an object of investigation is also arbitrary. It is as arbitrary as the determination of a certain number of letters to be skipped in the Bible code, which is needed to find meaningful word combinations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design signals generated by targeted manipulations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is another, more serious objection to shCherbak and Makukov’s method, which Prothero and Callahan do not mention: It works frequently only by a trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amino acid proline does not fit into the scheme, so the authors modify it. To do so, they formally remove an H atom from the side chain of proline and transfer it to the secondary amino group (see Fig. 4). This makes proline the primary amino acid. The purpose of this operation is to formally “standardize” the basic structures of all amino acids, as the authors mention. This is because proline is the only secondary amino acid in the genetic code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But “standardizing” means nothing other than purposefully changing facts to introduce the divisor 37 through the back door! In contrast to the other amino acids, the molecular weight of the proline basic structure (73) cannot be divided exactly by 37. This also applies, as discussed in Fig. 1, for the nucleon sum of the side chains. That undesirable fact only changes through the appropriate manipulation of numbers. Without it, the authors would never come up with the “magic” numbers 333 and 592. Strictly speaking, none of the examples in which the amino acid proline occurs, works “smoothly” in the sense of the authors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make matters worse, this formal H transfer would lead to an impossible molecule (see Fig. 4). The authors even implicitly admit this by stating that the H transfer in proline “can be simulated only in the mind of a recipient to achieve the array of amino acids with uniform structure. Such nucleon transfer thus appears artificial”. However, exactly this artificial operation, so the authors continue, “seems to be its destination: it protects the patterns from any natural explanation” (p. 3). In other words, targeted manipulations generate artifacts whose origin logically eludes any natural explanation! If that’s not a fatal circular argument, what then?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Neukamm_Figure_4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Clever trick&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Fig. 4 The clever trick of “standardizing” the nucleon number of proline: The authors formally transfer an H atom from the side chain to the secondary amino group (A). Thus, the molecule becomes the primary amino acid with a basic structure whose mo-lecular weight (74) is completely divisible by 37. Also, the side chain is open and has the “desired” molecular weight of 41 (B). But the molecule would now be in a chemically impossible state with an electron sextet on the terminal carbon atom (indicated by the two dots). Only on the basis of this extremely unstable carbene molecule, the nucleon sums are completely divisible by 37 (Fig. 1). Correctly, the authors should either have added two H atoms to the side chain – or left it as it is. By the way: They could have removed an H atom also from the alpha C atom of the basic structure (C, D). In none of these cases their method would have worked. This shows that the alleged “Wow! signal” is just an artifact of the authors. Without their manipulation, there would be no “magic” numbers.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The power of numerology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, it is not surprising that in the (numerical) cosmos, which functions under certain rules and laws, certain order patterns like Egyptian triangles, golden triangles, Fibonacci numbers, ascending numerical sequences, prime numbers, etc. can be found which, as brute facts, neither allow an explanation nor even demand one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s, for example, look at the natural three-digit numbers with identical digits and form their digit sums (111 = 3, 222 = 6, 333 = 9, etc.). If we divide these numbers by their digit sums, the result is in all cases … 37. Another example: 81 stable chemical elements exist. 81 may be represented formally as a “prime number cross” (3 x 3&lt;sup&gt;³&lt;/sup&gt;). The reciprocal of the number 81 can in turn be approximated by the decimal fraction 0.0123456789 (10) (11) (12)… (here, 10, 11, 12 are the next digits; the parentheses are for convenience). And if we look at Romanesco broccoli, we’ll see that its appearance is strictly mathematical: Its conical turrets are copies of the entire inflorescence, which is known as self-similarity or a fractal structure. Each of those turrets is also a so-called Fibonacci spiral, a sequence of numbers that ensures that one turret of vegetables never grows vertically above another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why should these pretty patterns, of which we could construct endless examples, represent design signals? Does it even make sense to ask how probable their “accidental” emergence is? Why 37 rather than 38 or 42? Why not π or e? Why not an alternating sequence of numbers? What if the laws were different? And what message are the “signals” supposed to convey? Shall we assume that a creator liked to line the world up with the number 3 or π and to introduce Fibonacci numbers into the cosmos? Such metaphysical interpretations cannot seriously pass as empirical arguments! All such patterns have no more objectively recognizable meaning (or semantic content) than the “Egyptian triangle” or the “appearance” of 37 in the genetic code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least: The more often we try out different mathematical transformations, the higher is the likelihood to find any mathematical pattern. We neither know the total set of possibilities nor how many unsuccessful trials the authors made to find their patterns. We only know that the number of potential mathematical transformations is infinite. Any number of counterexamples without any pattern can be constructed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a word, the approach of shCherbak and Makukov is pure number mysticism. They could only read an intelligent pattern from those numbers after they inserted it into the genetic code by convenient operations, targeted manipulations and reckless interpretations. Therefore, we have to agree with Prothero and Callahan (p. 128), who summarize:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The result is a paper that, despite the impressive credentials of its authors and the soundness of the journal it was printed in, is essentially without substance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mathematician Underwood Dudley (1997) shows in his book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Numerology-What-Pythagoras-Wrought-Spectrum/dp/0883855240&quot;&gt;Numerology&lt;/a&gt; in an entertaining way what nonsense can be done with such number games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Martin Neukamm is a German chemist and managing editor of the “AG Evolutionsbiologie” (www.ag-evolutionsbiologie.de), a German scientific association that deals with evolutionary biology and creationism. He has published various articles and books on evolution and creationism in the German language. Matt Young is the moderator of this post.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Neukamm</name></author><summary type="html">The term “Wow! signal” represents a decade-long mystery in astronomy: In 1977, the astrophysicist Jerry Ehman received a strong narrowband radio signal on the frequency of the 21 cm line of hydrogen with the gigantic big-ear radio telescope in Delaware in the US state of Ohio. There seemed to be no natural explanation for the persisting 72 s signal from the Sagittarius constellation, which was 30 standard deviations above the background noise. The profile of the strong, narrow-band signal corresponds to that of a communication antenna. Its discoverer highlighted the signal on the printout with a red circle and added an expression of astonishment by noting “Wow!” In the period that followed, there was a lively debate among experts as to whether it was an artificially generated or a natural signal. Although objects like pul-sars seem to be a possible source, the controversy continues to this day. A few years ago, a team of Kazakh scientists published a paper claiming to have discovered a Wow! signal in the genetic code of living beings. The code structure, so they claimed, is statistically so striking that its origin could be explained only by the presumption of an intelligent actor. The paper, published in Icarus, was somewhat off-topic since Icarus is a journal for planetary science rather than molecular biology or evolution. Since then, the paper has been celebrated as evidence for the extraterrestrial origin of the genetic code by support-ers of ancient astronauts and by the intelligent design movement; see, for example, here, here, and here, as well as this arti-cle in a German creationist journal. What’s it all about?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">We Believe in Dinosaurs Not on YouTube</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/we-believe-in-dinosaurs-on-youtube.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We Believe in Dinosaurs Not on YouTube" /><published>2021-02-07T10:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-02-07T10:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/we-believe-in-dinosaurs-on-youtube</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/we-believe-in-dinosaurs-on-youtube.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Dinosaurs_Amazon_Ratings.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Amazon ratings&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Amazon ratings of &quot;We believe in Dinosaurs,&quot; showing unusual bimodal distribution.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;strike&gt;We received an e-mail today from our penpal Dan Phelps, informing us that the Independent Lens version of We Believe In Dinosaurs is available on YouTube [link removed]. Mr. Phelps asks that we&lt;/strike&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh dear, we jumped on this message too fast. Mr. Phelps now tells us,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It looks as if the site is a well-done fake. Please don’t promote it. The copyright people at the distribution company are on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may still, however,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[c]onsider &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/aw/reviews/B081S9Y898&quot;&gt;rating it on Amazon&lt;/a&gt; since creationists have been leaving inaccurate and negative reviews there misrepresenting the film indicating they probably didn’t watch it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of them obviously watched it, some plainly did not, and some read into it what they wanted to see. I resisted reviewing the film on Amazon until over the summer, when I saw a spate of 1-star reviews by people who had plainly not seen the film. In case anyone is interested, I will post my own 5-star Amazon review, posted on August 25, below the fold:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I initially decided not to review this splendid movie. I am penpals with two of its principal subjects, David MacMillan and Dan Phelps, and was peripherally involved with promoting the movie, as when I detailed its progress in The Panda’s Thumb blog. The film has been well received by critics and initially earned a respectable number of 5-star reviews here [on Amazon]. Since early July, however, a number of 1-star reviews began to show up, many of them one-liners by people who had probably never seen the film and others that are simply irrelevant to the actual film. In short, these reviews suggest the possibility of a coordinated effort to lower the average rating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I thought that the film was an excellent documentary, clear and evenhanded. The film shows how hard and irrefutable evidence forced David MacMillan to evolve from a young-earth creationist and a charter member of the Creation Museum to a scientist, though he remains a committed Christian (contrary to at least one review). Doug Henderson, a lead designer for the Ark is a dedicated creationist who seems to think that he is doing God’s work; he is shown with at least as much sympathy as is given to MacMillan. So are the merchants of downtown Williamstown, which was left desolate after the Ark opened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This movie is not a hatchet job on the Ark Encounter, creationism, Ken Ham, Christianity, or anything else. It is not a liberal screed, much less an atheist screed. It is a fair depiction of the design, construction, and (shall we say) chaotic opening of the Ark. You may buy it or rent it here, or see it in slightly abridged form on PBS’s Independent Lens, provided that you are a member of a local station. Watch it for yourself and do not believe any overwrought depictions in 1-star reviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Revised 2:10 MST.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Amazon ratings of &quot;We believe in Dinosaurs,&quot; showing unusual bimodal distribution. We received an e-mail today from our penpal Dan Phelps, informing us that the Independent Lens version of We Believe In Dinosaurs is available on YouTube [link removed]. Mr. Phelps asks that we Oh dear, we jumped on this message too fast. Mr. Phelps now tells us, It looks as if the site is a well-done fake. Please don’t promote it. The copyright people at the distribution company are on it. You may still, however, [c]onsider rating it on Amazon since creationists have been leaving inaccurate and negative reviews there misrepresenting the film indicating they probably didn’t watch it. Some of them obviously watched it, some plainly did not, and some read into it what they wanted to see. I resisted reviewing the film on Amazon until over the summer, when I saw a spate of 1-star reviews by people who had plainly not seen the film. In case anyone is interested, I will post my own 5-star Amazon review, posted on August 25, below the fold:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is creationism a conspiracy theory?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/creationism-conspiracy-theory.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is creationism a conspiracy theory?" /><published>2021-02-04T12:28:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-02-04T12:28:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/creationism-conspiracy-theory</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/creationism-conspiracy-theory.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Ark_On_Opening_Day.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ark on opening day&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Photograph courtesy of Dan Phelps.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is creationism a conspiracy theory? Our colleague &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Braterman&quot;&gt;Paul Braterman&lt;/a&gt; of the University of Glasgow thinks so: In an article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/why-creationism-bears-all-the-hallmarks-of-a-conspiracy-theory-153831&quot;&gt;Why creationism bears all the hallmarks of a conspiracy theory&lt;/a&gt;, he notes creationist&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;claims that the scientific establishment promoting evolution is an arrogant and morally corrupt elite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This so-called elite supposedly conspires to monopolise academic employment and research grants. Its alleged objective is to deny divine authority, and the ultimate beneficiary and prime mover is Satan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Creationism,” he adds, “re-emerged in this form in reaction to the mid-20th century emphasis on science education.” “Creationists go to great lengths to demonise the proponents of evolution, and to undermine the overwhelming evidence in its favour.” Further, they “immunise themselves from fact-based criticism. They label the study of the past as based on unprovable assumptions, thus disqualifying in advance the plain evidence of geology.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can add only that creationists have to think that everyone else thinks as they do, in terms of vast conspiracies; otherwise, it would be hard to imagine 99 % of the world’s biologists engaged in a gigantic conspiracy. But if &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; is involved in a conspiracy, ….&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph courtesy of Dan Phelps. Is creationism a conspiracy theory? Our colleague Paul Braterman of the University of Glasgow thinks so: In an article, Why creationism bears all the hallmarks of a conspiracy theory, he notes creationist claims that the scientific establishment promoting evolution is an arrogant and morally corrupt elite. This so-called elite supposedly conspires to monopolise academic employment and research grants. Its alleged objective is to deny divine authority, and the ultimate beneficiary and prime mover is Satan. “Creationism,” he adds, “re-emerged in this form in reaction to the mid-20th century emphasis on science education.” “Creationists go to great lengths to demonise the proponents of evolution, and to undermine the overwhelming evidence in its favour.” Further, they “immunise themselves from fact-based criticism. They label the study of the past as based on unprovable assumptions, thus disqualifying in advance the plain evidence of geology.” I can add only that creationists have to think that everyone else thinks as they do, in terms of vast conspiracies; otherwise, it would be hard to imagine 99 % of the world’s biologists engaged in a gigantic conspiracy. But if everyone is involved in a conspiracy, ….</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lochmaeus manteo</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/Lochmaeus-manteo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lochmaeus manteo" /><published>2021-02-01T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/Lochmaeus-manteo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/Lochmaeus-manteo.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Denelsbeck.Lochmaeus_manteo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Moth larva.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Lochmaeus manteo&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&quot;http://bugguide.net/node/view/418&quot;&gt;variable oakleaf caterpillar moth larva&lt;/a&gt;. Mr. Denelsbeck writes, &quot;I was doing closeup images of the head of what was possibly a variable oakleaf caterpillar moth larva, when the flash brought up something curious. Apparently, between the translucent exoskeleton and the light angle, I got a glimpse of the internal anatomy of the caterpillar, but whether that is the actual brain or not I cannot say. I just liked the comic-book nuclear effect. The caterpillar measured 25&amp;nbsp;mm overall, with the head being just 2.5&amp;nbsp;mm in width.&quot; I stared at Mr. Denelsbeck's photo for a long time, incidentally, before I realized that the body is in the upper left, and the mouthparts, I think, in the lower right. If that is wrong, take me to task in the Comments.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Al Denelsbeck. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Lochmaeus manteo &amp;ndash; variable oakleaf caterpillar moth larva. Mr. Denelsbeck writes, &quot;I was doing closeup images of the head of what was possibly a variable oakleaf caterpillar moth larva, when the flash brought up something curious. Apparently, between the translucent exoskeleton and the light angle, I got a glimpse of the internal anatomy of the caterpillar, but whether that is the actual brain or not I cannot say. I just liked the comic-book nuclear effect. The caterpillar measured 25&amp;nbsp;mm overall, with the head being just 2.5&amp;nbsp;mm in width.&quot; I stared at Mr. Denelsbeck's photo for a long time, incidentally, before I realized that the body is in the upper left, and the mouthparts, I think, in the lower right. If that is wrong, take me to task in the Comments.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lunar Meteorite</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/lunar-meteorite.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lunar Meteorite" /><published>2021-02-01T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/lunar-meteorite</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/lunar-meteorite.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Dan Phelps&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Phelps_Meteorite_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Meteorite&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Phelps writes, “This is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lunar_meteorite&quot;&gt;lunar meteorite&lt;/a&gt; about the size of a thumbnail. Most of the white mineral clasts are anorthite feldspar. The darker minerals include olivine, pyroxenes, chromite and spinel.  There could be minor amounts other minerals as well. The rock is described as a feldspathic regolith breccia. Basically, the rock is fragments of the lunar highlands (the feldspar), mixed in with other lunar material such as mare basalts via asteroid impacts. These meteorites are the only lunar samples legally obtainable by the general public. This specimen is North West Africa (NWA) 11273. It was excavated in Morocco or Algeria and bought by western dealers. It was obtained from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meteoritemarket.com/&quot;&gt;meteorite dealer Eric Twelker&lt;/a&gt;.  For more details, including specific minerals and geochemistry, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lpi.usra.edu/meteor/metbull.php?code=66064&quot;&gt;The Meteoritical Society page for NWA 11273&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Dan Phelps. Mr. Phelps writes, “This is a lunar meteorite about the size of a thumbnail. Most of the white mineral clasts are anorthite feldspar. The darker minerals include olivine, pyroxenes, chromite and spinel. There could be minor amounts other minerals as well. The rock is described as a feldspathic regolith breccia. Basically, the rock is fragments of the lunar highlands (the feldspar), mixed in with other lunar material such as mare basalts via asteroid impacts. These meteorites are the only lunar samples legally obtainable by the general public. This specimen is North West Africa (NWA) 11273. It was excavated in Morocco or Algeria and bought by western dealers. It was obtained from meteorite dealer Eric Twelker. For more details, including specific minerals and geochemistry, see The Meteoritical Society page for NWA 11273.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Report: ID experts mistakenly think evolutionary trees cannot be reconstructed</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/ID-experts-think-trees-cannot-be-reconstructed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Report: ID experts mistakenly think evolutionary trees cannot be reconstructed" /><published>2021-01-30T16:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-01-30T16:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/ID-experts-think-trees-cannot-be-reconstructed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/ID-experts-think-trees-cannot-be-reconstructed.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Seedplants.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;tiny&gt;One of the figures from Louca and Pennell's 2020 paper.  From the Biorxiv server, courtesy of Matt Pennell.&lt;/tiny&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It is rather easy to find examples of misconceptions about evolution and misinterpretations of scientific results. All you need to do is look at the latest articles at the Discovery Institute's site &quot;Evolution News &amp;amp; Science Today&quot;.  Case in point: their take on a recent paper by Stilianos Louca and Matt Pennell in &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; last spring.  The paper is
this one:
&lt;p&gt;
Louca, S. and Pennell, MW. (2020). Extant timetrees are consistent with a myriad of diversification histories. &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi:10.1038/s41586-020-2176-1&quot;&gt;doi:10.1038/s41586-020-2176-1&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It is behind a paywall, but the preprint version of the paper is
freely available at the Biorxiv preprint server here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/719435v2.full&quot;&gt;
https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/719435v2.full&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Discovery Institute's site is quite excited about this paper.  Their
report on 12 January (&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2021/01/controversy-arising-timetrees-unconstrained/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) announced that the paper announced something very dramatic:
&lt;blockquote&gt; Two theorists have caused a stir in evolutionary circles, claiming to have proven that Darwinian phylogeny efforts (tree-building) cannot be constrained to one “best” answer. In fact, any proposed tree is no better than an infinity of other trees. They can’t see the tree for the forest.  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now if true, this would call phylogenies (evolutionary trees) seriously
into question.  Can it be that Louca and Pennell have undermined the
foundation of reconstruction of evolutionary trees?  Or is it possible
instead that the folks at EN&amp;amp;ST have misread Louca and Pennell's paper?
&lt;p&gt;
Guess which is more likely? ...
&lt;!--more--&gt;
(no points for guessing from the title of this post that it is the EN&amp;amp;ST people who are wrong)
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;What the paper's authors assert&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Reading the Conclusions of the Louca and Pennell paper, we immediately see that
&lt;blockquote&gt;
We have shown that for virtually any candidate birth-death process, suspected of having generated some extant timetree, there exists an infinite number of alternative and markedly dierent birth-death processes that could have generated the timetree with the same likelihood. Without further information or prior constraints on plausible diversification scenarios, extant timetrees alone cannot be used to reliably infer speciation rates (except at present-day), extinction rates or net diversification rates, raising serious doubts over a multitude of previous estimates of past diversification dynamics.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In other words, the authors have a timetree, a tree for a set of species, with the
branching events on a time scale.  Their assumption is actually that the tree is entirely correct -- they are then evaluating from it what are the underlying rates of speciation (&quot;birth&quot; rates of lineages) and extinction (&quot;death rates&quot; of lineages). These rates are the &quot;diversification
scenario&quot;, not the tree itself.  Louca and Pennell argue that any one true tree is compatible with many different birth-death processes, and does not distinguish between them.
&lt;p&gt;
This is a somewhat shocking result, as it does call into question our ability to 
use a correct tree to infer the birth and death rates of lineages.  
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;What the Discovery Institute thought the paper meant&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Reading the coverage in Evolution News and Science Today, you'd get a very different impression: the paper is supposed to show that we cannot tell the difference between
phylogenies from the usual biological data used to infer them.  The paper does not
at all say that -- it says that the inferences that can be drawn from an entirely-correct tree do not specify the underlying speciation and extinction rates as narrowly as
previously thought.
&lt;p&gt;
EN&amp;amp;ST quotes the University of Oregon press release about the paper.  The U of O press release does get
the issue wrong, talking about &quot;flaws in how scientists build trees of life&quot; and how there are limits on how scientists can &quot;reconstruct evolution's path&quot;.  But the &quot;path&quot;
referred to is not the timetree itself -- it is the combinations of underlying birth and death rates of species that are compatibile with the correct tree.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt; Uncommon Descent chimes in &lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The website Uncommon Descent, which is a cheering section for the Discovery Institute, of course cheered the DI's interpretation (in a post &lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/darwinian-time-trees-dont-really-work/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). The UD post is signed by their commentator News, who is identified by UD as being Denyse O'Leary.  She is paid to generate posts for discussion there.  O'Leary, a skilled specialist in invective,
has some oft-repeated themes:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Science is mostly wrong, and so cannot be trusted, as demonstrated by publication scandals, failures of the
peer review process, failure to replicate statistically significant results, and particularly by scientists finding unexpected results of any kind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Scientific results, particularly any unexpected ones, show that &quot;Darwinism&quot; is wrong, and they can entirely be trusted when they do that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

Even though UD lately has been spending most of its time on arguing that the U.S. presidential elections were
rigged, that the Covid-19 pandemic will not be serious and that hydroxyquinone is all that is needed, that Quantum Mechanics and Relativity validate the Shroud of Turin, that
consciousness cannot possibly be explained by evolution, that G&amp;ouml;del's mathematics proves the existence of God, etc., they did deign to take time out from these extraordinary efforts to
cheer &quot;News&quot; when she said that &quot;Darwinian timetrees don't really work&quot;, and that they are &quot;deeply flawed&quot;.  
&lt;p&gt;
In the ensuing discussion, commenter Orthomyxo repeatedly calls their attention to what the Louca and Pennell paper actually is about, that the EN&amp;amp;ST conclusion was not warranted, that the timetrees in Luca and Pennell's paper were in fact being taken as completely correct, and that the questions
Louca and Pennell raised were only about what could be known from correct trees about underlying birth-death rates.
&lt;p&gt;
But they will have none of it, pointing to the EN&amp;amp;ST post and to the University of Oregon press release, which appears to support that post.  None of them check Orthomyxo's assertions by actually going back to read the Louca and Pennell paper.  UD's commenters EDTA, Martin_r, PaV, Ralph David Westfall, ET, and EugeneS pile on, Orthomyxo sounding inreasingly astonished at their obtuseness.  In the last few comments the UD commenters fall back on taunting Orthomyxo about the obvious election conspiracy and the falseness of official statements about the Covid-19 pandemic.
&lt;p&gt;
Which is an ironic coda to their total misunderstandings about the Louca and Pennell paper.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">One of the figures from Louca and Pennell's 2020 paper. From the Biorxiv server, courtesy of Matt Pennell. It is rather easy to find examples of misconceptions about evolution and misinterpretations of scientific results. All you need to do is look at the latest articles at the Discovery Institute's site &quot;Evolution News &amp;amp; Science Today&quot;. Case in point: their take on a recent paper by Stilianos Louca and Matt Pennell in Nature last spring. The paper is this one: Louca, S. and Pennell, MW. (2020). Extant timetrees are consistent with a myriad of diversification histories. Nature doi:10.1038/s41586-020-2176-1 It is behind a paywall, but the preprint version of the paper is freely available at the Biorxiv preprint server here: https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/719435v2.full The Discovery Institute's site is quite excited about this paper. Their report on 12 January (here) announced that the paper announced something very dramatic: Two theorists have caused a stir in evolutionary circles, claiming to have proven that Darwinian phylogeny efforts (tree-building) cannot be constrained to one “best” answer. In fact, any proposed tree is no better than an infinity of other trees. They can’t see the tree for the forest. Now if true, this would call phylogenies (evolutionary trees) seriously into question. Can it be that Louca and Pennell have undermined the foundation of reconstruction of evolutionary trees? Or is it possible instead that the folks at EN&amp;amp;ST have misread Louca and Pennell's paper? Guess which is more likely? ...</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Assembly Required: book review</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/some-assembly-required.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Assembly Required: book review" /><published>2021-01-21T14:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-01-21T14:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/some-assembly-required</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/some-assembly-required.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Shubin_Cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just finished reading the latest book by Neil Shubin, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Some-Assembly-Required-Decoding-Billion/dp/1101871334/&quot;&gt;Some Assembly Required&lt;/a&gt;. I thought it was a splendid book and, besides this recommendation, will offer a few comments. If you want a detailed synopsis of the book, I suggest the &lt;a href=&quot;https://3quarksdaily.com/3quarksdaily/2020/03/some-assembly-required-by-neil-shubin-review.html&quot;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; by my colleague Paul Braterman on the blog 3 Quarks Daily. 
&lt;em&gt;Some Assembly Required&lt;/em&gt; is a history of evolutionary biology from Darwin to the present, from fossils to DNA. Shubin takes a biographical or historical approach (or a biographical/historical approach) in much of the book, but his topic is largely an answer to the question famously posed by Darwin’s contemporary St. George Jackson Mivart: what would be the use, for example, of an incipient wing? How, for that matter, could a fish evolve fins for walking and lungs for breathing at the same time? As Shubin puts it,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If entire bodies have to change for any great transformation, and many features need to change simultaneously, then how could major transitions happen gradually?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That states the central problem of book, and Shubin spends the rest of his time solving it. The book is at root a science book, but sometimes it reads almost like a historical novel. I enjoyed the capsule biographies of many of the scientists, some of whom were familiar names and some of whom were not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was particularly interested in a segment about Linus Pauling and his colleague Emile Zuckerkandl. I found the chemistry somewhat hard to understand, particularly when Shubin referred to amino acid molecules as being charged (I understand now that they may have charged arms and of course they ionize in solution, but I still do not know precisely what charge was referred to). At any rate, Zuckerkandl, through a series of “connections,” not least a connection to Einstein, managed to escape Nazi Germany and ultimately to collaborate with Pauling, who was by then already well known. Pauling set Zuckerkandl to work on the proteins in hemoglobin. Zuckerkandl measured the mass and charge of various proteins and deduced that human hemoglobin was more closely related to ape hemoglobin than to frog or fish hemoglobin. He hypothesized that the similarity between human and ape hemoglobin was the result of evolution. Indeed, Pauling and Zuckerkandl inferred that “the more proteins of two species differed from each other, the longer the time those species have been evolving independently from a common ancestor.” If proteins evolved at a constant rate, then they could deduce when two species diverged; they had discovered the molecular clock, a concept that Shubin says was “utterly outrageous when it was first proposed[.]” The more I read, the more I wondered why I had never heard of Zuckerkandl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Zuckerkandl and his molecular clock were ignored, they were not alone. When Barbara McClintock enrolled in Cornell University, women were not allowed to major in genetics. Instead, she majored in horticulture and discovered her now-famous jumping genes in corn. Shubin shows that jumping genes are of critical importance for evolution, but no one paid attention when McClintock discovered them. Similarly, Lynn Margulis proposed that the organelles in eukaryotic cells were originally freely swimming bacteria or algae. According to Shubin, her paper received 15 rejections. Science eventually caught up with her, when it turned out that the DNA in mitochondria and chloroplasts was unrelated to the nuclear DNA of the cell itself. Francisco Mojica was likewise ignored when he discovered a mechanism that bacteria use to protect themselves against virus infections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like salamanders and personal essays, you will love the chapter called “Loaded Dice” (I did). Shubin uses the concept of convergent evolution (a term he never actually uses) and shows that, for example, unrelated lizards on isolated islands develop similar morphologies and, as is more well-known, marsupials in Australia have evolved into marsupial wolves, flying squirrels, moles, and groundhogs, and even extinct lions, wolves, and saber-toothed tigers. He concludes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The history of life is not wholly a crapshoot of contingent events. The dice are loaded by the ways genes and development build bodies, by the physical constraints of environments, and by history. In each generation, organisms have inherited recipes – written in their genes, cells, and embryos – to build organs and bodies. This inheritance … can make certain pathways of change more likely than others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, in Stephen Jay Gould’s terminology, if we replayed (actually, re-recorded) the tape of life, we would get the same result. Here, I think he did not convince me; he rewound the tape only to, roughly speaking, the extinction of the dinosaurs. From then on, I grant, even if the asteroid had never struck, creatures similar to those we see today may have evolved, though I am less certain about technological beings. But what if we wound the tape back to the time before some eukaryote assimilated an algal cell, and that event never happened? Creatures today, I daresay, would look very different. Shubin quotes Lillian Hellman, “Nothing, of course, begins at the time you think it did.” I think perhaps he did not apply her dictum rigorously enough to the question of contingency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also rather taken by the story of Susumu Ohno, a musician who likes to translate the structure of proteins into concert pieces. Ohno photographed chromosomes of mammals from shrews to giraffes, cut them out, and compared the chromosomes of these diverse species.  He noted that the numbers of chromosomes varied widely from species to species.  Then he got the idea to weigh the paper cutouts and discovered that the total weight of the chromosomes of each species was the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mostly, I thought that the science in the book was straightforward, and (apart from the discussion of amino acids) I understood it without difficulty. I was somewhat surprised when Shubin wrote that we have all descended from a sea squirt; surely that was too much of an oversimplification and he should have said common ancestor. In the same way, there was no need to avoid such terms as convergent evolution, exaptation, and maybe trace fossil; without those terms it might be hard for an inexperienced reader to seek further information. And, finally, I truly enjoyed the drawings by Kalliopi Monoyios; I thought some of them, however, such as the figures on pages 79 and 99, needed further explanation, possibly including labels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The editor in me thought there were very few puzzling or infelicitous comments or sentences, but I stumbled over the statement that the Jurassic was named “for its distinctive features.” It was actually named after the Jura Mountain range in France. The story of how &lt;em&gt;Archaeopteryx&lt;/em&gt; found its way into the British Museum was one of the more interesting anecdotes in the book, but I keep wondering who “the doctor” was.  I would not have minded another figure here and there, as when he describes “the classic pattern of one bone, two bones, wrist bones, and digits.” Words like metamorphosis and development should have been defined, not to mention decidual stromal cell.  A single, anodyne sentence regarding Linus Pauling and vitamin C seemed inadequate.  Shubin’s use of the term “selfish gene” was not precisely the same as the definition used by Richard Dawkins, and I thought that Shubin might have made a comment to that effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that I will leave with the final paragraph, which you might consider the bottom line,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When you know how to look, you can see billions of years inside the organs, cells, and DNA in all living things and relish our connections to the rest of life on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgment.&lt;/strong&gt; Many thanks to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo&quot;&gt;National Center for Science Education&lt;/a&gt; for providing a review copy of the book.  NCSE is currently offering &lt;em&gt;Some Assembly Required&lt;/em&gt; as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/donate&quot;&gt;donation premium&lt;/a&gt; for donations of $100 or $10/month. In addition, John Harshman, Andrew Petto, Joe Felsenstein, Paul Braterman, Stephen Matheson, and Nick Matzke helped me understand a couple of murky concepts. If I still do not understand, it is not their fault.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I just finished reading the latest book by Neil Shubin, Some Assembly Required. I thought it was a splendid book and, besides this recommendation, will offer a few comments. If you want a detailed synopsis of the book, I suggest the review by my colleague Paul Braterman on the blog 3 Quarks Daily. Some Assembly Required is a history of evolutionary biology from Darwin to the present, from fossils to DNA. Shubin takes a biographical or historical approach (or a biographical/historical approach) in much of the book, but his topic is largely an answer to the question famously posed by Darwin’s contemporary St. George Jackson Mivart: what would be the use, for example, of an incipient wing? How, for that matter, could a fish evolve fins for walking and lungs for breathing at the same time? As Shubin puts it,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Questions of Race and Evolution</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/questions-race-evolution.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Questions of Race and Evolution" /><published>2021-01-18T14:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-01-18T14:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/questions-race-evolution</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/questions-race-evolution.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/ML_King_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Martin Luther King, Jr.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://abc7news.com/mlk-martin-luther-king-jr-nobel-prize-lecture/1163922/&quot;&gt;Rev. Martin Luther King, Jr.&lt;/a&gt; delivering his Nobel Peace Prize acceptance speech. &lt;small&gt;ABC News, Channel 7, San Francisco; Associated Press.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today is Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. Day in the United States. This day, we remember the courage that was required to engage with racism in our society. The history here is both hopeful and discouraging. For all the progress made, much is left undone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some question why we should even address race on &lt;em&gt;The Panda’s Thumb&lt;/em&gt;, a blog devoted to defending evolutionary science. Perhaps this will just end into a contentious debate about the scientific particulars about the biological meaning of race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to talk about race. Still, we should find the courage to engage. The questions matter here. There are important things that can and should be said by us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to follow Todd Wood’s example. This summer, this young earth creationist asked, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://discourse.peacefulscience.org/t/todd-wood-is-evolution-racist/11287&quot;&gt;Is Evolution Racist?&lt;/a&gt;” Knowing this genre well, we should expect a diatribe of race-baiting, but that is not what Wood did. Instead, he took an honest look at his camp’s own history of racism, explaining how creationism has been used to justify racism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wood’s approach displays obvious integrity. His direct explanation of the history of racism in his own camp, to his own community, was not easy. It was not costless. He demonstrated courage, and in doing so sets an important example for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, much of the same reality is true of evolution too. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientific_racism&quot;&gt;There is a complex and troubled history of racism among evolutionary scientists&lt;/a&gt;. Evolution has often been used to justify false understandings of race and the evil of racism. It serves the common good to acknowledge this, to teach its history, and to model how to move past it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is difficulty in reckoning our history here. Dr. King has words for us. He was a theologian by training, but he also discussed science. In fact, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/alexknapp/2014/01/20/martin-luther-king-jr-on-science-and-religion&quot;&gt;he said quite a bit about science&lt;/a&gt;. In his Nobel Prize lecture, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/peace/1964/king/lecture/&quot;&gt;King observes&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Yet, in spite of these spectacular strides in science and technology, and still unlimited ones to come, something basic is missing…We have learned to fly the air like birds and swim the sea like fish, but we have not learned the simple art of living together as brothers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be disagreements with the particulars of what he said of science and religion. Still, it seems that we should agree with him here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been more than 50 years since MLK was murdered. Over that half century, we certainly have not learned how to live together as a common family. Now, it is legal to integrate; the law does not force us to segregate. In that sense, we are desegregated. Yet we still live apart from one another. We have not managed well what MLK called the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.faculty.umb.edu/lawrence_blum/courses/318_11/readings/king_ethical_demands.pdf&quot;&gt;ethical demands for integration&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evolutionary science is important, in part because it brings us to grand questions about who we are and where we came from. Origins, at its best, brings us to the grand question of what it means to be human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this front, looking past our disagreements, it seems there is broad consensus among evolutionary scientists on these points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. There are &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/phc3.12468&quot;&gt;many definitions of race&lt;/a&gt;, especially if we include &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/epdf/10.1111/phc3.12467&quot;&gt;folk and historical definitions&lt;/a&gt;. For that reason, we have to be careful about equivocation in the term &quot;race.&quot; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. Evolutionary science certainly &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; rule out many understandings of biology race, but perhaps not all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3. Some of the versions of &quot;race&quot; ruled out were quite prevalent in the past, including among evolutionary scientists. It is worth understanding why they were wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4. We now know that the human species is far more linked by interbreeding that we realized even just 50 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5. Even if biological races are real in some sense, that reality would not grant moral legitimacy to racism. Even as we debate the legitimacy of certain understanding of race, recognizing differences would not legitimize dehumanizing people based on those differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6. There is, regrettably, a near total absence of African American scientists in evolutionary science, and in the biological sciences as a whole. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is much more I could say here, but these points of agreement seem like a good place to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our points of disagreement, also, are important. I want to work through them. A full telling of evolutionary science includes the questions of race. These questions are difficult, in part &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; they extend beyond evolutionary science. The payoff is worth the trouble. The science here is interesting, and it can serve the common good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps, in a conversation among scientists, we can find a better way. The conversation is difficult for obvious reasons. We are faced with questions about our moral worth, dignity, and place in society. How we think about race matters. Scientists can and should be a model community for navigating the complexity here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>S. Joshua Swamidass</name></author><summary type="html">Rev. Martin Luther King, Jr. delivering his Nobel Peace Prize acceptance speech. ABC News, Channel 7, San Francisco; Associated Press. Today is Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. Day in the United States. This day, we remember the courage that was required to engage with racism in our society. The history here is both hopeful and discouraging. For all the progress made, much is left undone. Some question why we should even address race on The Panda’s Thumb, a blog devoted to defending evolutionary science. Perhaps this will just end into a contentious debate about the scientific particulars about the biological meaning of race. It is difficult to talk about race. Still, we should find the courage to engage. The questions matter here. There are important things that can and should be said by us. I want to follow Todd Wood’s example. This summer, this young earth creationist asked, “Is Evolution Racist?” Knowing this genre well, we should expect a diatribe of race-baiting, but that is not what Wood did. Instead, he took an honest look at his camp’s own history of racism, explaining how creationism has been used to justify racism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Great Sand Dunes</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/great-sand-dunes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Great Sand Dunes" /><published>2021-01-18T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-01-18T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/great-sand-dunes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/great-sand-dunes.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;C. Joseph Long&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Long_great_sand_dunes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Great Sand Dunes&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/grsa/learn/nature/index.htm&quot;&gt;Great Sand Dunes National Park and Preserve&lt;/a&gt;.  Mr. Long writes, “Dunes up to 200 m are formed where wind sweeping across the cold semi-desert of southern Colorado’s San Luis Valley is funneled toward Mosca Pass in the Sangre de Cristo range on the eastern edge of the southern Rocky Mountains.  The valley itself is a deep graben toward the upper end of the Rio Grande Rift with no surface drainage in its northern reaches.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by C. Joseph Long. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Great Sand Dunes National Park and Preserve. Mr. Long writes, “Dunes up to 200 m are formed where wind sweeping across the cold semi-desert of southern Colorado’s San Luis Valley is funneled toward Mosca Pass in the Sangre de Cristo range on the eastern edge of the southern Rocky Mountains. The valley itself is a deep graben toward the upper end of the Rio Grande Rift with no surface drainage in its northern reaches.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Does op-doc unintentionally tout Ark Park?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/does-op-doc-tout-ark.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does op-doc unintentionally tout Ark Park?" /><published>2021-01-07T14:55:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-01-07T14:55:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/does-op-doc-tout-ark</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/01/does-op-doc-tout-ark.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Times_Ark_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;aerial view of Ark&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Aerial view of the “Ark,” from the op-doc. &lt;small&gt; Credit: &lt;i&gt;Super Deluxe Films&lt;/i&gt;. Fair use.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Times&lt;/em&gt; the other day posted an “op-doc,” or an op-ed in documentary-film format, concerning the “Ark” Park in Kentucky. I have received a handful of communications about this op-doc, and I have decided to plagiarize all of them. I will not identify the authors, but if they feel like identifying themselves, they can do so in the comments. The op-doc is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2021/01/05/opinion/noahs-ark-kentucky.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It is behind a pay wall, but you may be entitled to access a few pages each month without a subscription. At any rate, I found a range of opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first person to contact me noted that the piece had been posted in the &lt;em&gt;Times&lt;/em&gt; and called it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[a]n uncritical free ad for the Ark Park disguised as an op-ed “documentary.” The NYT let this in as an “opinion” piece. It is directed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jeremyseifert.com/&quot;&gt;Jeremy Seifert&lt;/a&gt;. Seifert’s other work doesn’t appear to be aligned with fundamentalism; he does seem to have directed or produced a film attacking GMO foods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remainder of the comments come from a listserv I subscribe to. A second person wrote, 
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The documentary doesn’t state a point of view overtly, but subtly conveys the incongruities of the place as a tourist attraction, as well as the silliness of the exhibits. It also conveys the humanity of the locals. Doing those things together is a pretty neat trick. And there’s more to the film than I’m saying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a third person:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Basically, it seems to make it clear that there was no “secular intent” in the approval and promotion of the Ark by proponents in Williamstown or in Grant County.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This was, for them, a part of their expression of faith and evangelism – the “tourist attraction” and economic development bits were a secondary motive, though they were used to justify putting a lot of public money and resources into the construction and infrastructure (and it is also clear that the economic boom never happened).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is also clear that there is a shared culture in the region – such that the people in the film cite biblical stories and recite passages that only make sense if people are already familiar with the biblical passages. The one that struck me was the mention of the 3 holy children[,]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mechon-mamre.org/p/pt/pt34.htm&quot;&gt;Daniel&lt;/a&gt; 3. I certainly did not see all of that in that film, and I thought that Person 3 might be reading more into it because of prior knowledge. At any rate, he then added,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I don’t entirely disagree with [the first person]. It is clearly uncritical of the whole operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But what it does do, IMHO, is to make clear that the support for the Ark and Creation Museum in Grant County, Williamstown, and Kentucky &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; religiously motivated and that the “economic development/tourism” promotion was little more than a cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The economic legacy of the projects makes that clear – the “secular” authorities are still strongly in support despite the fact that none of the economic predictions have come to pass (and [Ken] Ham et al. backtracked on the issue, saying – I think this is made clear in &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/04/reviews-of-documentary.html&quot;&gt;We Believe in DInosaurs&lt;/a&gt; – that they never really &lt;em&gt;promised&lt;/em&gt; that these economic outcomes would happen).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But one would have to have context to see that underneath all the testimonials – and the film clearly does not provide such.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, you may see a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/11/we-believe-on-PBS.html&quot;&gt;slightly shortened version&lt;/a&gt; of the film &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/independentlens/films/we-believe-in-dinosaurs/&quot;&gt;We Believe in Dinosaurs&lt;/a&gt; on PBS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If other people read things into the op-doc or thought it was kind of an anodyne commercial for the “Ark” Park, another person asked,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Is it just me? I thought it was crude and indeed insulting satire of a creationist. &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/environmental-science/climate-change/im-climate-change-alarmist/&quot;&gt;Ham does believe in the fire to come&lt;/a&gt;, but do we want to go there?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reference is to a web page where Ken Ham acknowledges the reality of climate change and then avers that “Jesus will return and the earth (and whole universe) will be judged with fire and God will make a new heavens and earth.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I was directed to &lt;a href=&quot;https://friendlyatheist.patheos.com/2021/01/06/this-short-film-about-ark-encounter-functions-as-an-unintentional-advertisement/&quot;&gt;This Short Film about Ark Encounter Functions as an Unintentional Advertisement&lt;/a&gt;, by Hemant Mehta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Mehta’s article is somewhat more wide-ranging than the title suggests, but he concludes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ultimately, it functions as an unintentional advertisement for the Ark precisely because there’s nothing critical about it in the film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me? I did not read much into the film. I thought it was somewhat tedious and completely uncritically showed various people quoting the Bible, not to mention a mannequin. Granted that it was short, perhaps one-quarter the length of “We Believe in Dinosaurs,” but it seemed to me that it lacked the analysis and the counterpoint that we saw in “We Believe in Dinosaurs.” All in all, yes, an unintentional ad for the fake Ark. My Wife and Harshest Critic, however, thinks it was deliberately favorable, if not an intentional ad: It was not just uncritical, but downright laudatory, and it did not explore any of the implications of locating the “Ark” near Williamstown. A talented musician, she did not think the music helped the film along and was unimpressed when I told her that it was credited to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arvo_P%C3%A4rt&quot;&gt;Arvo Pärt&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Aerial view of the “Ark,” from the op-doc. Credit: Super Deluxe Films. Fair use. The Times the other day posted an “op-doc,” or an op-ed in documentary-film format, concerning the “Ark” Park in Kentucky. I have received a handful of communications about this op-doc, and I have decided to plagiarize all of them. I will not identify the authors, but if they feel like identifying themselves, they can do so in the comments. The op-doc is available here. It is behind a pay wall, but you may be entitled to access a few pages each month without a subscription. At any rate, I found a range of opinions. The first person to contact me noted that the piece had been posted in the Times and called it [a]n uncritical free ad for the Ark Park disguised as an op-ed “documentary.” The NYT let this in as an “opinion” piece. It is directed by Jeremy Seifert. Seifert’s other work doesn’t appear to be aligned with fundamentalism; he does seem to have directed or produced a film attacking GMO foods. The remainder of the comments come from a listserv I subscribe to. A second person wrote,</summary></entry></feed>