<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-06-29T10:11:06-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest XVI: Finalists</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/Photography-Contest-XVI-Finalists.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest XVI: Finalists" /><published>2025-06-23T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-23T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/Photography%20Contest-XVI-Finalists</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/Photography-Contest-XVI-Finalists.html">&lt;p&gt;Here are the finalists of the 2025 photography contest. It was nice to see some old friends, though new names would have been welcome. With assistance from Our Wife and Harshest Critic, we chose 7, which we display below the Figurative Fold. We chose the photographs more on the basis of their pictorial quality than on their scientific interest. Any text submitted by the photographers has been omitted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The finalists are presented in alphabetical order of last name. Please look through their photographs before voting for your favorite. Polling will close Sunday, July 6 (the 4th being a holiday in the US), at approximately noon MDT, and we will display the winner at noon Monday, July 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please remember that this is a photography contest, not a popularity contest, and discourage your friends from enlisting others specifically to vote for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Philip Abrams&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Abrams_Eurasian_Jay_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Eurasian jay&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wildlondon.org.uk/wildlife-explorer/birds/crows-and-shrikes/jay&quot;&gt;Garrulus glandarius&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; Eurasian jay, Chelsea, London, iPhone 15.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Denelsbeck_Ginkgo_biloba.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ginkgo leaf&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ginkgo_biloba&quot;&gt;Ginkgo biloba&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; ginkgo leaf after a heavy rain, Canon 7D.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Joel Eissenberg&lt;/strong&gt;.

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Eissenberg_Archilestes grandis.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Damselfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_spreadwing&quot;&gt;Archilestes grandis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; damselfly spotted at the Denver zoo.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;John Harshman&lt;/strong&gt;.
  
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Harshman_Anhinga.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Anhinga (bird)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oriental_darter&quot;&gt;Anhinga melanogaster&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; Oriental darter, Keoladeo National Park, Rajasthan, India.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;C. Joseph Long&lt;/strong&gt;.

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Long_Antigone_canadensis.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sandhill crane&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandhill_crane&quot;&gt;Antigone (formerly Grus) canadensis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; sandhill crane, Bernardo State Wildlife Refuge, Rio Grande Valley, New Mexico.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Malcolm Schongalla&lt;/strong&gt;.

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Schongalla_Rangifer_tarandus_skull.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Caribou skull&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barren-ground_caribou&quot;&gt;Rangifer tarandus groenlandicus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; barren-ground caribou, Russell Glacier on the West Coast of Greenland, June, 2022.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;John Trawick&lt;/strong&gt;.

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Trawick_Apis_mellifera_Echium_candicans.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;ldquo;Pride of Madeira&amp;rdquo; (flower)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smgrowers.com/products/plants/plantdisplay.asp?plant_id=543&quot;&gt;Echium candicans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; &quot;Pride of Madeira,&quot; with &lt;i&gt;Apis mellifera&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; European honeybee.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLScYL25zz4LVzQz7di3g-UIJI1vtyLfr93nZFXbC36fO59v_HA/viewform?embedded=true&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;650&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot;&gt;Loading…&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Here are the finalists of the 2025 photography contest. It was nice to see some old friends, though new names would have been welcome. With assistance from Our Wife and Harshest Critic, we chose 7, which we display below the Figurative Fold. We chose the photographs more on the basis of their pictorial quality than on their scientific interest. Any text submitted by the photographers has been omitted. The finalists are presented in alphabetical order of last name. Please look through their photographs before voting for your favorite. Polling will close Sunday, July 6 (the 4th being a holiday in the US), at approximately noon MDT, and we will display the winner at noon Monday, July 7. Please remember that this is a photography contest, not a popularity contest, and discourage your friends from enlisting others specifically to vote for you.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pipilo maculatus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/pipilo-maculatus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pipilo maculatus" /><published>2025-06-16T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-16T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/pipilo-maculatus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/pipilo-maculatus.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/P1031649_Towhee_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spotted towhee&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spotted_towhee&quot;&gt;Pipilo maculatus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; spotted towhee, not exactly in his natural environment.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Please do not forget &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;header&gt;&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/photography-contest-xvi.html&quot;&gt;Photography Contest XVI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/header&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contest remains open for entries through &lt;i&gt;this coming Friday&lt;/i&gt;, June 20.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Pipilo maculatus &amp;ndash; spotted towhee, not exactly in his natural environment. Please do not forget Photography Contest XVI The contest remains open for entries through this coming Friday, June 20.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Agave neomexicana</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/agave-neomexicana.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Agave neomexicana" /><published>2025-06-09T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-09T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/agave-neomexicana</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/agave-neomexicana.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/P1031638_Yucca_Agave_neomexicana_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;New Mexico century plant&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agave_americana&quot;&gt;Agave neomexicana&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; New Mexico century plant (also known as &lt;i&gt;Agave parryi&lt;/i&gt; ssp. &lt;i&gt;neomexicana&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; Parry's agave. The &lt;i&gt;H. sapiens&lt;/i&gt; in the picture, Ron Wittmann, tells us that some botanists recognize it as a distinct species, whereas others do not). The plant has not bloomed in at least 25 years. The pointy, gray-green leaves at the bottom of the stalk are the agave leaves.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Please do not forget &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;header&gt;&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/photography-contest-xvi.html&quot;&gt;Photography Contest XVI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/header&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contest remains open for entries through Friday, June 20.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Agave neomexicana &amp;ndash; New Mexico century plant (also known as Agave parryi ssp. neomexicana &amp;ndash; Parry's agave. The H. sapiens in the picture, Ron Wittmann, tells us that some botanists recognize it as a distinct species, whereas others do not). The plant has not bloomed in at least 25 years. The pointy, gray-green leaves at the bottom of the stalk are the agave leaves. Please do not forget Photography Contest XVI The contest remains open for entries through Friday, June 20.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest XVI</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/photography-contest-xvi.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest XVI" /><published>2025-06-02T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-02T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/photography-contest-xvi</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/photography-contest-xvi.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/DSC05994_OM1_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Olympus OM-1, with assorted paraphernalia&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olympus_OM-1&quot;&gt;Olympus OM-1&lt;/a&gt; – as far as I know the first smallish 35-mm SLR. I used mine from 1976 till 2003, when I bought a digital camera. I have had my present digital camera since 2015, so it has a long way to go. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 16th annual Panda’s Thumb Photography Contest begins now, Monday, June 2, at 12:00 p.m., MDT (MDT = UTC(GMT) – 6 h). Entries will be accepted between now and Friday, June 20, at 12:00 p.m., MDT. The rules are precisely the same as previous years’, except, obviously, that the dates have been updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We encourage entries in a single, general category, which includes pictures of just about anything of scientific interest: any object of experimentation or observation, from single-celled organisms, through nematodes, fruit flies, rats, chimpanzees, and college sophomores to volcanoes, stars, and galaxies. In order not to omit theoreticians, we will consider computer-generated pictures and also photographs of equipment. Photomicrographs and electron micrographs are likewise welcomed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since rumor has it that the pandemic encouraged macro photography, we may, if we receive enough entries, establish a “macro” category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winner will receive a choice between &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/stores/Matt-Young/author/B001HPILDU/&quot;&gt;Why Intelligent Design Fails, A Scientific Critique of the New Creationism&lt;/a&gt;, edited by Taner Edis and me; and Mark Isaak’s 2007 classic &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ucpress.edu/books/the-counter-creationism-handbook/paper&quot;&gt;The Counter-Creationism Handbook&lt;/a&gt;, generously contributed once again by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/&quot;&gt;NCSE&lt;/a&gt;. The runner-up will receive the remaining book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we get enough entries, consistently with Rules 11 and 12, we may add categories and award additional prizes, presuming, of course, that we can find more prizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rules of the contest are simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;We will consider any photograph that displays scientific interest – biological, paleontological, geological, or astronomical, for example.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Submit photographs in JPEG format. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Reduce photographs to an information content of 600 pixels horizontally. If creationists require a definition of information, they may apply in writing to the management. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Photographs may be enhanced but may not be montages. High dynamic range photographs and focus-stacked photographs are, however, accepted. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Submit a maximum of 3 photographs (or 5 photographs per family) to ProfessorSteveSteve@gmail.com. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Submit the photographs as attachments to an e-mail (not embedded in the body of the e-mail). The subject line to the e-mail must have the form YourLastName_PhotographyContest. The filenames for the photographs must have the form YourLastName_Descriptor as, for example, Young_Oxytropis_sericea or Young_Table_Mountain, as appropriate. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;In your e-mail, identify the subject of the photograph: common and biological name, mineral type, or geological formation, for example. Provide a link that will allow a reader to learn more about the subject. You may add descriptive text in the body of the e-mail if you like. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Depending on the number of photographs submitted, we may post the best submissions and ask our readers to vote for the best photograph. Likewise, we may establish several categories with separate entries and separate ballots. In particular, students 16 and under should so identify themselves; if we receive enough entries, we will establish a student category. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;By submitting a photograph, you stipulate that you are the owner of the copyright and grant The Panda’s Thumb a nonexclusive license to publish the photograph on its blog. The photograph will be subject to a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-No Derivatives license. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Regular contributors to The Panda’s Thumb are not eligible to enter the contest. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;The decision of the judges is irrevocable. The judges remain irrepressibly and irreducibly irascible, irreverent, and irredeemable, irregardless and irrespective, but not, we hope, irrational or irritable. So do not be irresolute; irradiate your sensors. We hope for a veritable irruption of entries this year. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Even though we are getting fairly good at running contests, we reserve the right to change any of the rules, or add or subtract rules at any time at our discretion. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will choose a number of finalists (or a winner) and open voting for the winner at 12:00 p.m. MDT, Monday, June 23.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Olympus OM-1 – as far as I know the first smallish 35-mm SLR. I used mine from 1976 till 2003, when I bought a digital camera. I have had my present digital camera since 2015, so it has a long way to go. The 16th annual Panda’s Thumb Photography Contest begins now, Monday, June 2, at 12:00 p.m., MDT (MDT = UTC(GMT) – 6 h). Entries will be accepted between now and Friday, June 20, at 12:00 p.m., MDT. The rules are precisely the same as previous years’, except, obviously, that the dates have been updated. We encourage entries in a single, general category, which includes pictures of just about anything of scientific interest: any object of experimentation or observation, from single-celled organisms, through nematodes, fruit flies, rats, chimpanzees, and college sophomores to volcanoes, stars, and galaxies. In order not to omit theoreticians, we will consider computer-generated pictures and also photographs of equipment. Photomicrographs and electron micrographs are likewise welcomed. Since rumor has it that the pandemic encouraged macro photography, we may, if we receive enough entries, establish a “macro” category. The winner will receive a choice between Why Intelligent Design Fails, A Scientific Critique of the New Creationism, edited by Taner Edis and me; and Mark Isaak’s 2007 classic The Counter-Creationism Handbook, generously contributed once again by NCSE. The runner-up will receive the remaining book.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lepisma saccharinum</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/05/lepisma-saccharinum.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lepisma saccharinum" /><published>2025-05-26T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-05-26T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/05/lepisma-saccharinum</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/05/lepisma-saccharinum.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/DSC05981_Silverfish_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Silverfish&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silverfish&quot;&gt;Lepisma saccharinum&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; silverfish, Boulder, Colorado, May, 2025. Do not let the date fool you: I have had them in a below-grade bathroom since I brought them home from Nist on a backpack, probably in the 1990's. It is what you get for working in a building that was put up during the Eisenhower administration. Mostly I do not see them in the rest of the house, but this one decided to hang around on a plate in the kitchen, apparently begging to be photographed.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;** &lt;strong&gt;PHOTOGRAPHY CONTEST BEGINS NEXT MONDAY, JUNE 2&lt;/strong&gt; **&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be the XVIth – who’da thunk it?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Lepisma saccharinum &amp;ndash; silverfish, Boulder, Colorado, May, 2025. Do not let the date fool you: I have had them in a below-grade bathroom since I brought them home from Nist on a backpack, probably in the 1990's. It is what you get for working in a building that was put up during the Eisenhower administration. Mostly I do not see them in the rest of the house, but this one decided to hang around on a plate in the kitchen, apparently begging to be photographed. ** PHOTOGRAPHY CONTEST BEGINS NEXT MONDAY, JUNE 2 ** It will be the XVIth – who’da thunk it?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Silver Cord Cascade</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/05/silver-cord-cascade.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Silver Cord Cascade" /><published>2025-05-12T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-05-12T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/05/silver-cord-cascade</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/05/silver-cord-cascade.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Jim Kocher&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Kocher_Silver_Cord_Cascade_YNP.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silver_Cord_Cascade&quot;&gt;Silver Cord Cascade&lt;/a&gt;. Mr Kocher writes, &quot;View is from the Seven Mile Hole trail and shows only the upper part of the falls. Colorful rock outcrops are hydrothermally altered rhyolite flows. These flows filled emplaced on the floor of the Yellowstone Caldera (~640 ka).  Photographed with Kodak Instamatic 120, June, 1981.&quot; See also, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silver_Cord_Cascade&quot;&gt;Silver Cord Cascade&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Jim Kocher Photography contest, Honorable Mention Silver Cord Cascade. Mr Kocher writes, &quot;View is from the Seven Mile Hole trail and shows only the upper part of the falls. Colorful rock outcrops are hydrothermally altered rhyolite flows. These flows filled emplaced on the floor of the Yellowstone Caldera (~640 ka). Photographed with Kodak Instamatic 120, June, 1981.&quot; See also, Silver Cord Cascade.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Giant sunspot</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/05/giant-sunspot.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Giant sunspot" /><published>2025-05-05T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-05-05T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/05/giant-sunspot</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/05/giant-sunspot.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/DSC05967_Sunspot_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Giant sunspot&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://earthsky.org/sun/sun-news-activity-solar-flare-cme-aurora-updates&quot;&gt;Giant sunspot&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This picture is 180 degrees out of phase with our usual biweekly posts, but you do not see a giant sunspot every day. (You may see a more or less ordinary sunspot at about 4:30 on an imaginary clock, provided that the hour hand is short.) EarthSky at the link above discusses the sunspot in the picture:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;NOAA just released its April 2025 solar data. The monthly sunspot number climbed to 140.6, up from 134.2 in March, a clear signal that we remain firmly in solar maximum for Solar Cycle 25. This peak phase could continue for several more months before experts call the downturn. Leading the charge is AR4079, a behemoth sunspot region now dominating the sun’s northeast quadrant. Stretching six to seven Earths wide, it’s easily visible with eclipse glasses (always use proper eye protection!)....&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They further note that the sunspot “carries serious flare potential, [though f]or now, it’s been surprisingly calm[.]” They add, “Eyes on the sun!” But please, as they advise, with proper protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took the picture using the same setup I used to photograph the 2017 solar eclipse &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2017/08/total-eclipse.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. There is no truth to the rumor that I never throw anything away.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Giant sunspot. This picture is 180 degrees out of phase with our usual biweekly posts, but you do not see a giant sunspot every day. (You may see a more or less ordinary sunspot at about 4:30 on an imaginary clock, provided that the hour hand is short.) EarthSky at the link above discusses the sunspot in the picture: NOAA just released its April 2025 solar data. The monthly sunspot number climbed to 140.6, up from 134.2 in March, a clear signal that we remain firmly in solar maximum for Solar Cycle 25. This peak phase could continue for several more months before experts call the downturn. Leading the charge is AR4079, a behemoth sunspot region now dominating the sun’s northeast quadrant. Stretching six to seven Earths wide, it’s easily visible with eclipse glasses (always use proper eye protection!).... They further note that the sunspot “carries serious flare potential, [though f]or now, it’s been surprisingly calm[.]” They add, “Eyes on the sun!” But please, as they advise, with proper protection. I took the picture using the same setup I used to photograph the 2017 solar eclipse here. There is no truth to the rumor that I never throw anything away.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Intelligent Design advocates buy into Platonic nonsense</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/05/platonic-nonsense.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intelligent Design advocates buy into Platonic nonsense" /><published>2025-05-05T01:00:33-07:00</published><updated>2025-05-05T01:00:33-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/05/platonic-nonsense</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/05/platonic-nonsense.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/PlatoAristotle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Sculpture of Plato and Aristotle arguing]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Sculpture of Plato and Aristotle arguing.  Is Plato the one on the right?  &quot;The Art of Philosophy&quot;  by  Luca della Robbia (1400-1480), in 
the Museo dell'Opera del Duomo (Museum of Works of the Cathedral), Florence, Italy.  Image: Wikimedia Commons.  The original sculptor's copyright on the work itself expired in about 1550.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Discovery Institute’s “Evolution News” is always a great place to look for tenuous and dubious arguments against evolutionary 
biology.  Lately they have been touting a book by EN journalist David Klinghoffer, published by Discovery Press, 
the DI’s house publisher.  The book is “&lt;a href=&quot;https://discovery.press/b/platos-revenge/&quot;&gt;Plato’s Revenge: The New Science of the Immaterial Genome&lt;/a&gt;”.   Emily Sandico, a DI staff writer, has &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2025/04/platos-revenge-intelligent-design-in-real-time/&quot;&gt;a piece calling attention to the book&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book by Klinghoffer describes the views of Richard Sternberg.  Sternberg has two 
Ph.D. degrees, one in molecular evolution and another in systems science.  His
own web page (&lt;a href=&quot;https://richardsternberg.com/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) explains that, in his view&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Evolutionary genetics leaves open the central issue of how the one dimensional genotype can specify the four dimensional phenotype. The approach I am taking to this problem is a variant of structural realism, by which I mean that biological phenomena are manifestations of logico-mathematical structures. This perspective is orthogonal to the origins debate, if you will, because all historical actualities are understood to be space-time instances of pre-existing non-temporal possibilities. Within this context one can accept all that is empirically valid in evolutionary biology, while not axiomatically dismissing the position that structures as well as their “real” instantiations have an intelligent cause. My position asserts that the cosmos is fundamentally intelligible in such a way that it can be logically, mathematically, and scientifically recognized to be such; and moreover–following Proclus–that the universe emanates from Nous (mind). In this sense my thinking is compatible with intelligent design broadly defined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sternberg’s site also links to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discovery.org/f/54005/&quot;&gt;a PDF&lt;/a&gt; explaining in more detail how he came to his views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To Klinghoffer, as quoted by Sandico’s post&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When Dr. Sternberg thinks of ID, he’s thinking of the here and now. With echoes in the ancient philosophy of Plato, which pointed to immaterial “forms” shaping life, he finds scientific evidence of agency at work in the formation of every embryo, the development of every organism in the womb, and in the ongoing operation of every cell. The genome is not a material entity alone — DNA — but one that transcends space and time, employing DNA as an instrument, right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which he calls “intelligent design in real time”.  Andrew McDiarmid, EN’s head of podcasts, has interviewed Klinghoffer (&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2025/05/platos-revenge-the-next-scientific-revolution/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) about his book on Sternberg’s views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me this all sounds a bit strange.  Plato argued that real organisms were but imperfect reflections of ideal forms, which existed in some other realm. 
What evidence do Sternberg, Klinghoffer, Sandico, and McDiarmid have that this is so?  Let’s look at an example …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example is explained by Daniel Witt, in an EN post (&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2025/02/biologist-michael-levin-a-farewell-to-physicalism/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), where he explains and interprets the views of Michael Levin, a biologist at Tufts University who works on developmental algorithms.  According to Witt’s explanation,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is important information in the DNA, of course. But organisms seem to develop with a goal in mind, so to speak, and are able reach that goal in spite of shifting and inherently unpredictable circumstances. This is significant, because if the circumstances and the developmental pathways necessary to adapt to them are unpredictable, then those pathways cannot have been programmed into the organism in advance. They have to be invented on-the-fly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another, more recent EN post about Levin’s views is by cancer researcher Steven Iacoboni (&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2025/04/life-itself-in-michael-levins-platonism-teleology-advances/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).
Levin gives his own summary of his views in a preprint available &lt;a href=&quot;https://osf.io/preprints/psyarxiv/5g2xj_v2&quot;&gt;from the Open Science Foundation site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Levin does invoke Platonism, and proposes that “mind” rather than physical entities are fundamental in nature.  Andreas Wagner, in his book “The Arrival of the Fittest” also ends up invoking Platonism and proposes that there may be “a library of forms” in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;telos&quot;&gt;Telos?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Evolution News posters view Levin’s and Wagner’s views as evidence for “telos” (goal-directedness) in nature, and argue that this is evidence for supernatural processes.  Levin and Wagner do not go that far.
A central argument at EN seems to be that if an organism can compensate for developmental accidents, and end up changing so as to achieve a desirable form, then this is only possible if there is telos, teleological change.
In particular, if organisms can anticipate the future and correct accidents of development, to these platonists this cannot be the result of mere physical changes in DNA sequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;no-nous&quot;&gt;No nous&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it could, and it’s not hard see how such a capability could evolve, without any overall plans that refer to platonic 
ideals.  Organisms exist in populations. Owing to processes such as mutation, recombination, and some types of 
natural selection, the members of the population vary genetically. Consider a worm developing, and an individual 
suffers damage around its mouth.  Different genotypes will differ in what happens after that.  Some of them 
will change in a direction that brings the worm closer to having a functional mouth. Many others will lead to 
an increasingly less functional mouth.  So different genotypes will vary in how fit the organism will be 
when affected by that damage.   Natural selection will of course favor the genotypes that are more fit when 
damage like that occurs.  No need to look up the ideal form in the Platonic encyclopedia in a supernatural 
realm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever organisms develop to anticipate future environments, ID advocates tend to regard this as 
evidence for supernatural intervention, or plans inserted into the species by Design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, they 
argue, a material organism can only react to present conditions, and thus could not in principle 
develop so as to predict future environments, and how well various forms could cope with 
them.  But this is not necessary.  Consider a plant that sprouts from a seed in the spring, 
and grows for some months before flowering at an appropriate time in the summer.  Does doing 
that require supernaturally inserted algorithms, which push the plant towards its Platonic 
ideal life cycle. No. All that is necessary is some feedback from fitness to the 
genotypes.  And that of course is what natural selection does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So no Nous is good news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-library-of-forms-in-the-real-world&quot;&gt;A library of forms in the real world?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biologists that the DI platonists refer to are less clearly referring to any 
supernatural processes.  Michael Levin comes closest:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;(1) instances	of	embodied	cognition	likewise	ingress	from	a	Platonic	space,	which	contains	not	only	low-agency	patterns	like	facts	about	triangles	and	prime	numbers,	but	also	higheragency	ones	such	as	kinds	of	minds;	(2) we	take	seriously	for	developmental,	synthetic,	and	behavioral	biologythe	 kinds of	 non-physicalist	 ideas	 that	 are	 already	 a	 staple	 of	 Platonist	mathematics; (3)	what	evolution	(and	bioengineering,	and	possibly AI)	produces	are	pointers	into	that	Platonic	space	–physicalinterfaces that	enable	the	ingression	of	specific	 patterns of	 body&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To	recap,	the	first	pillar	of	the	proposed	framework	is	that	Platonic	forms	inject	information	and	influence	into	physical	events,	such	as	the	growth	and	form	of	biological	bodies.	The	second	is	that	this	latent	space	contains	not	only	boring,	low-agency	forms	such	as	facts	about	integers	and	geometric	shapes,	but	also	a	wide	range	of	increasingly	high-agency	patterns,	some	of	which	we	call	“kinds	of	minds”.	Thus,	I	propose	that	minds,	as	patterns	that	ensoul	somatic	embodiments,	are	of	exactly	the	kind	(but	not	in	degree)	of	non-physical	nature	as	the	patterns	that	inhabit	and	guide	the	behavior	of	biological	tissue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andreas Wagner instead &lt;a href=&quot;https://aeon.co/essays/without-a-library-of-platonic-forms-evolution-couldn-t-work&quot;&gt;proposes&lt;/a&gt; that to understand evolution, 
a conceptual collection of all possible genome 
sequences, with the forms each sequence produces, is fundamental to understanding
evolution:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So nature’s libraries and their sprawling networks go a long way towards explaining life’s capacity to evolve. But where do they come from? You cannot see them in the glass lizard or its anatomy. They are nowhere near life’s visible surface, nor are they underneath this surface, in the structure of its tissues and cells. They are not even in the submicroscopic structure of its DNA. They exist in a world of concepts, the kind of abstract concepts that mathematicians explore.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Does that make them any less real?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Nature’s libraries are the fountains of biological innovation that Darwin was looking for. And unlike the realm of abstract forms that Plato envisioned, they are richer, more diverse, and more complex than the visible world. They harbour enough innovations for all the species Darwinian evolution has created – and could create. No planet would be large enough to explore all of them. The legless lizard and the rest of the living world, in all their glory, are just faint shadows of this Platonic realm of the possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stuart Kauffman has also insisted that evolutionary theory should incorporate 
descriptions of the connectedness of graphs describing organisms, in order 
to understand which complex structures might come, not from natural 
selection, but instead from random happenstance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;platonism&quot;&gt;Platonism?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Levin and Wagner make the connection to Plato, but they do not seem to be 
describing a supernatural realm, rather a reconceived or extended reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Discoverosphere at Evolution News takes their views as 
endorsing a dualism which has a supernatural world directing 
the natural world.  It is less than clear whether Levin or 
Wagner would agree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a blistering rejection of neo-platonic ideas as 
relevant to biological evolution, see also &lt;a href=&quot;https://nautil.us/the-neo_platonic-argument-for-evolution-couldnt-be-more-wrong-236176/&quot;&gt;Massimo 
Pigliucci’s 2016 essay&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is more to say about this, but others are better at the 
philosophy of biology, so I will look forward to what our commenters have to say, below.  The 
authors from Evolution News are of course welcome to participate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Sculpture of Plato and Aristotle arguing. Is Plato the one on the right? &quot;The Art of Philosophy&quot; by Luca della Robbia (1400-1480), in the Museo dell'Opera del Duomo (Museum of Works of the Cathedral), Florence, Italy. Image: Wikimedia Commons. The original sculptor's copyright on the work itself expired in about 1550. &amp;nbsp; The Discovery Institute’s “Evolution News” is always a great place to look for tenuous and dubious arguments against evolutionary biology. Lately they have been touting a book by EN journalist David Klinghoffer, published by Discovery Press, the DI’s house publisher. The book is “Plato’s Revenge: The New Science of the Immaterial Genome”. Emily Sandico, a DI staff writer, has a piece calling attention to the book. The book by Klinghoffer describes the views of Richard Sternberg. Sternberg has two Ph.D. degrees, one in molecular evolution and another in systems science. His own web page (here) explains that, in his view Evolutionary genetics leaves open the central issue of how the one dimensional genotype can specify the four dimensional phenotype. The approach I am taking to this problem is a variant of structural realism, by which I mean that biological phenomena are manifestations of logico-mathematical structures. This perspective is orthogonal to the origins debate, if you will, because all historical actualities are understood to be space-time instances of pre-existing non-temporal possibilities. Within this context one can accept all that is empirically valid in evolutionary biology, while not axiomatically dismissing the position that structures as well as their “real” instantiations have an intelligent cause. My position asserts that the cosmos is fundamentally intelligible in such a way that it can be logically, mathematically, and scientifically recognized to be such; and moreover–following Proclus–that the universe emanates from Nous (mind). In this sense my thinking is compatible with intelligent design broadly defined. Sternberg’s site also links to a PDF explaining in more detail how he came to his views. To Klinghoffer, as quoted by Sandico’s post When Dr. Sternberg thinks of ID, he’s thinking of the here and now. With echoes in the ancient philosophy of Plato, which pointed to immaterial “forms” shaping life, he finds scientific evidence of agency at work in the formation of every embryo, the development of every organism in the womb, and in the ongoing operation of every cell. The genome is not a material entity alone — DNA — but one that transcends space and time, employing DNA as an instrument, right now. which he calls “intelligent design in real time”. Andrew McDiarmid, EN’s head of podcasts, has interviewed Klinghoffer (here) about his book on Sternberg’s views. To me this all sounds a bit strange. Plato argued that real organisms were but imperfect reflections of ideal forms, which existed in some other realm. What evidence do Sternberg, Klinghoffer, Sandico, and McDiarmid have that this is so? Let’s look at an example …</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Safeguarding Sound Science, Climate Change Edition</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/05/safeguarding-sound-science.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Safeguarding Sound Science, Climate Change Edition" /><published>2025-05-02T15:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-05-02T15:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/05/safeguarding-sound-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/05/safeguarding-sound-science.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Sound_Science_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Reproduced from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/&quot;&gt;NCSE&lt;/a&gt; Monitor, with permission. Original article by Glenn Branch.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/safeguarding-sound-science&quot;&gt;Safeguarding Sound Science&lt;/a&gt; — NCSE’s new podcast, intended to combat misinformation, disinformation, and misconceptions with actual science — recently completed its first season, with all seven episodes now available:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Episode 1: &quot;What Climate Change? Tackling Climate Denial&quot; with Michael E. Mann and NCSE's Glenn Branch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Episode 2: &quot;A Century of Disinformation: Naomi Oreskes and the Merchants of Doubt&quot; with Naomi Oreskes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Episode 3: &quot;Miseducation in the USA: How Our Kids Are Too Often Denied Climate Facts&quot; with Katie Worth and Melissa Lau&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Episode 4: &quot;Zombie Theories Must Die! A Conversation with Climate Communicator Marshall Shepherd&quot; with J. Marshall Shepherd&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Episode 5: &quot;Today's Forecast: Climate Change, Trusted Sources, and a Sprinkling of Local Relevance&quot; with Bernadette Woods Placky and Edward Maibach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Episode 6: &quot;Making Every Classroom a Climate Classroom&quot; with NCSE's Amanda L. Townley and Bertha Vazquez&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Episode 7: &quot;Hope in the Face of the Climate Crisis: Youth Activism and Leadership&quot; with three youth climate activists&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All episodes are hosted by Mat Kaplan and all are now available via all your favorite podcasting platforms, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/safeguarding-sound-science/id1797165552&quot;&gt;Apple Podcasts&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/search/safeguarding%20sound%20science/podcastAndEpisodes&quot;&gt;Spotify&lt;/a&gt;. If you like what you hear, consider making a &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/sound-science-podcast&quot;&gt;special donation&lt;/a&gt; to support the future of Safeguarding Sound Science!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Reproduced from NCSE Monitor, with permission. Original article by Glenn Branch. Safeguarding Sound Science — NCSE’s new podcast, intended to combat misinformation, disinformation, and misconceptions with actual science — recently completed its first season, with all seven episodes now available: Episode 1: &quot;What Climate Change? Tackling Climate Denial&quot; with Michael E. Mann and NCSE's Glenn Branch Episode 2: &quot;A Century of Disinformation: Naomi Oreskes and the Merchants of Doubt&quot; with Naomi Oreskes Episode 3: &quot;Miseducation in the USA: How Our Kids Are Too Often Denied Climate Facts&quot; with Katie Worth and Melissa Lau Episode 4: &quot;Zombie Theories Must Die! A Conversation with Climate Communicator Marshall Shepherd&quot; with J. Marshall Shepherd Episode 5: &quot;Today's Forecast: Climate Change, Trusted Sources, and a Sprinkling of Local Relevance&quot; with Bernadette Woods Placky and Edward Maibach Episode 6: &quot;Making Every Classroom a Climate Classroom&quot; with NCSE's Amanda L. Townley and Bertha Vazquez Episode 7: &quot;Hope in the Face of the Climate Crisis: Youth Activism and Leadership&quot; with three youth climate activists All episodes are hosted by Mat Kaplan and all are now available via all your favorite podcasting platforms, including Apple Podcasts and Spotify. If you like what you hear, consider making a special donation to support the future of Safeguarding Sound Science!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Prunella vulgaris</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/04/prunella-vulgaris.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Prunella vulgaris" /><published>2025-04-28T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-04-28T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/04/prunella-vulgaris</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/04/prunella-vulgaris.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Marilyn Susek&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Susek_Prunella_Vulgaris.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Prunella vulgaris&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prunella_(plant)&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Prunella vulgaris&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; self-heal, heal-all. Ms. Susek writes, &quot;I decided not to mow the lawn in May this year [2021] as suggested by the professional gardeners to see what grew as well as the grass. I knew I would get some daisies and plantain and some self-heal. I always look forward to self-heal as a lot is said about its healing properties.  It is known as an herb that is said to be good for health when dried and used to make tea.&quot; The University of Arkansas Extension service &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uaex.uada.edu/yard-garden/resource-library/plant-week/prunella-vulgaris-heal-all-02-12-2016.aspx&quot;&gt;discusses the medicinal properties&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;i&gt;P. vulgaris&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Marilyn Susek Photography contest, Honorable Mention Prunella vulgaris &amp;ndash; self-heal, heal-all. Ms. Susek writes, &quot;I decided not to mow the lawn in May this year [2021] as suggested by the professional gardeners to see what grew as well as the grass. I knew I would get some daisies and plantain and some self-heal. I always look forward to self-heal as a lot is said about its healing properties. It is known as an herb that is said to be good for health when dried and used to make tea.&quot; The University of Arkansas Extension service discusses the medicinal properties of P. vulgaris.</summary></entry></feed>