<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-01-15T14:04:10-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Creationists have wrong-handed DNA</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/icr-logo-wrong-handed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creationists have wrong-handed DNA" /><published>2022-01-11T11:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-01-11T11:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/icr-logo-wrong-handed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/icr-logo-wrong-handed.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/ICR_New_Logo_403.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Logo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/01/10/the-institute-for-creation-research-has-a-new-logo/&quot;&gt;The DNA in the helix spirals the wrong way.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Institute for Creation Research has just &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icr.org/article/icr-announces-new-logo/&quot;&gt;announced a new logo&lt;/a&gt;, above. Evidently the helix spirals the wrong way. I wonder if they are all left-handed and are made up of right-handed proteins. If I made book, I would take bets on whether they will leave it alone, announce that they had made an error, or change it quickly in the dead of night.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">The DNA in the helix spirals the wrong way. The Institute for Creation Research has just announced a new logo, above. Evidently the helix spirals the wrong way. I wonder if they are all left-handed and are made up of right-handed proteins. If I made book, I would take bets on whether they will leave it alone, announce that they had made an error, or change it quickly in the dead of night.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">David Hillis on the proposal to de-name the Ernst Mayr Award at the Society for Systematic Biology</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/David-Hillis-on-Ernst-Mayr.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="David Hillis on the proposal to de-name the Ernst Mayr Award at the Society for Systematic Biology" /><published>2022-01-06T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-01-06T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/David-Hillis-on-Ernst-Mayr</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/David-Hillis-on-Ernst-Mayr.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.cns.utexas.edu/hillislab/home&quot;&gt;David Hillis&lt;/a&gt; posted the following short essay to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/DoubleHelixRanch/posts/10159648610955170&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; on June 21, 2021. Apparently the leadership of the Society for Systematic Biology (SSB) was discussing a proposal de-name the Ernst Mayr Award.  This proposal &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.systbio.org/award-naming.html&quot;&gt;has now been released&lt;/a&gt;, and, because the Ernst Mayr Award is written into SSB’s constitution (Ernst Mayr and his donations helped found SSB!), a 2/3 vote of the membership is required to change it. Hillis has given me permission to republish his essay here. I have my own comments below the fold. – Nick Matzke&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(210, 210, 210); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Ernst_Mayr_1928.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Mayr in 1928]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;According to the photo description at &lt;a href=&quot;https://achievement.org/achiever/ernst-mayr-ph-d/&quot;&gt;https://achievement.org/achiever/ernst-mayr-ph-d/&lt;/a&gt; : &quot;June 1928: Ernst Mayr with Sario, one of his Malay assistants, in the former Dutch New Guinea. Mayr led ornithological expeditions to Dutch New Guinea and German Mandated New Guinea, an experience that fulfilled 'the greatest ambition of his youth.' Mayr collected ca. 7000 bird skins in two and a half years.&quot; (Caption text added by NM)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.cns.utexas.edu/hillislab/home&quot;&gt;David Hillis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
June 21, 2021&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I find it surprising and sad how quickly the amazing life and accomplishments of Ernst Mayr have faded from the memories of a new generation of biologists. I think Mayr had a bigger and more progressive influence on the development of evolutionary biology in the 20th Century, and the betterment of the world as a whole, than probably any other biologist. 
Mayr emphasized the importance of understanding the natural history of organisms to understand their evolution. He was way ahead of his time in arguing that our emphasis should be on studying whole genomes, rather than individual genes. He spent a lifetime encouraging young people to study biology and the natural world. After immigrating to the US from the horrors of Nazi Germany in the early 1930s, he spoke out against racism and segregation at a time when many of his fellow biologists were doing the opposite. He published over 700 influential articles and 24 books on biological practice and theory, 200 of which he published after he &quot;retired.&quot;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Mayr worked to establish several major evolutionary societies, including the Society for the Study of Evolution and the Society of Systematic Zoologists (now Society of Systematic Biologists). He not only spent his time and efforts to found and support these societies, he also supported them financially. For example, in the 1970s he endowed a student award within SSZ to encourage young systematists to enter the field (now named the Ernst Mayr Award). That award has long been used to encourage young systematic biologists of diverse backgrounds to become engaged in studying biodiversity. He left an additional large gift to SSB in his will, which became the nucleus of SSB's endowment that has enabled the many programs and funding opportunities that society now provides to encourage young systematists.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I greatly admire the life and accomplishments of Mayr, even though he and I frequently disagreed over scientific issues. He was already one of the 20th Century's most famous biologists when I met him, and I was just a lowly graduate student working on bringing molecular techniques into systematics. Mayr was not a big fan of this; he was not anti-molecular systematics, but he argued (quite reasonably) that single gene analyses of systematic questions were problematic, and he thought that many molecular systematists did not pay enough attention to the biology and natural history of their organisms (which was often true). After I co-edited the book Molecular Systematics in 1990, he and I often discussed the development and expansion of molecular techniques in the field. But despite our disagreements over this (as well as various issues of systematic theory), he was always cordial, encouraging, warm, and most of all—knowledgeable. It was always clear to me that he read the literature exhaustively. When he asked me questions about or critiqued my papers, it was clear that he had read and thought about them carefully. He had a command of the literature like no one else that I'd ever encountered, or have encountered since. He taught me that people can disagree about issues, and still be great friends (in fact, it can even help and build a friendship to discuss such disagreements).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Most people today likely picture Mayr as an old man, as he was over 100 when he died in 2005, and most living people would remember him (if at all) as an old man. This photo of him (on the right in the photo) shows him as a 23-year-old field biologist in New Guinea in 1928. He had an enormous, positive influence on the world, and especially on the positive development of evolutionary and systematic biology. We should remember and thank him for that. He worked to make the world, and his discipline, better than they were when he came into them. I think that is the lofty goal that we should all strive to achieve in our lives.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Hillis posted additional comments to his Facebook post on January 6, 2022:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(210, 210, 210); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;David Hillis&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I am deeply saddened to see in today's e-mail a proposal to eliminate Ernst Mayr's name from the Society of Systematic Biology's Ernst Mayr Award. As this post from last year describes, Mayr was champion of inclusion and diversity; he worked to fight discrimination in science; he supported young scientists, and endowed the student award that bares his name. Members of the society will get to vote on this constitutional change, and I hope that they have the wisdom to continue honoring his life and contributions with this named award.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The proposal to change the name claims that some members disagree with some of his writings, even though Mayr &quot;was a prolific and profound scholar of evolutionary biology and a dedicated champion of students.&quot; Really? We are now eliminating mention of people because someone disagrees with some of their academic ideas? That is especially troublesome in this case, as Mayr was an ardent defender of equality and inclusion, and spoke out effectively against racial discrimination (as discussed below).
Please, if you are a member of SSB, vote against this mean-spirited and unfair discrimination against Mayr on the spring 2022 ballot.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;…and then…&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(210, 210, 210); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;David Hillis&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Even given all of Mayr's vast biological accomplishments, I think what most impresses me about him were his efforts to build a better world for all. For example, in 1951, in support of “&lt;a href=&quot;https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000073351&quot;&gt;UNESCO 1951: The race concept: Results of an inquiry&lt;/a&gt;,” Mayr made a public statement opposing the views of R. A. Fisher, and supporting the UNESCO statement:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Mayr stated that he hoped that “the authoritative Statement prepared by UNESCO will help to eliminate the pseudo-scientific race conceptions which have been used as excuses for many injustices and even shocking crimes”… “I applaud and wholeheartedly endorse [it],” Mayr wrote, adding: “It cannot be emphasized too strongly that all so-called races are variable populations, and that there is often more difference between extreme individuals of one race than between certain individuals of different races. All human races are mixtures of populations and the term “pure race” is an absurdity. The second important point which needs stressing is that genetics plays a very minor part in the cultural characteristics of different peoples. . . . The third point is that equality of opportunity and equality in law do not depend on physical, intellectual and genetic identity. There are striking differences in physical, intellectual and other genetically founded qualities among individuals of even the most homogeneous human population, even among brothers and sisters. No acknowledged ethical principle exists which would permit denial of equal opportunity for reason of such differences to any member of the human species.”&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Three years later, US Supreme Court cited this same Mayr-supported UNESCO statement in the landmark desegregation case, Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka. Mayr spoke up and did the right thing at a critical time, when many of his colleagues were doing the opposite.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The rest of this post is by Nick Matzke.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.systbio.org/award-naming.html&quot;&gt;SSB announcement about de-naming the Ernst Mayr Award&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(227, 180, 180); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;SSB Council Review of the Mayr Award and Award Names&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

In the summer of 2020, the SSB Council began a discussion about potentially renaming the Ernst Mayr Award in Systematic Biology at the request of society members. Since then, the SSB leadership have been working in conjunction with the Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion (DEI) Committee to learn more about the origin of named awards and their representation of the diverse membership within the society. Renaming the award is one step toward greater inclusivity within the society, as named awards often lead to feelings of exclusion among those who are members of underrepresented groups whose scientific contributions continue to remain unrecognized. At a council meeting following Virtual Evolution 2021, the Council voted to propose to all members an award name change, in conjunction with other actions intended to better recognize SSB’s history and legacy.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

The SSB Council proposes to rename the Ernst Mayr Award in Systematic Biology to the Outstanding Student Presentation Award in Systematic Biology. Our scientific community is more diverse than the cohort of early scientists with recognized contributions to systematics and science generally. Many current members do not see themselves reflected in awards that bear the names of these early scientists and can feel excluded as potential recipients as a result. In a field whose composition still does not reflect global human diversity, having an award named after a particular individual reinforces that members with other identities are outsiders. By proposing this name change, we hope to address this specific barrier to making our society more inclusive and welcoming. We, the SSB council, are made up of a diverse group of people who don’t all view Mayr in the same light. This proposal is not intended to cast judgement on the legacy of Ernst Mayr, who was a prolific and profound scholar of evolutionary biology and a dedicated champion of students, nor are we intending to defend the contents of his writings which some find problematic. We are grateful for Mayr’s generous gifts to our society, which created the endowment that allows us to support student research today.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

The Council sees preservation of the society’s history and increasing diversity, equity and inclusion as synergistic endeavors toward the improvement of our community. The proposed change continues our history of becoming more inclusive over time: for example, in the 1990s we changed from the Society for Systematic Zoology to the Society of Systematic Biologists (and changed the journal name as well) to welcome members of our community who do not study animals. Thus, SSB President Laura Kubatko has acted on the recommendation of the DEI Committee to form a new committee, the SSB Legacy Committee, that will be tasked with creating accessible content about our society's history (e.g., as a section on our website). The formation of this committee is intended as a way to acknowledge the contributions of past members to the existence of the society and to the field broadly. In this way, the legacy of the society may be understood by our membership more comprehensively than is possible through named awards, and we have the opportunity to celebrate the many people of various backgrounds who have made systematic biology what it is today.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Because the award is named in our Constitution, the name can only be changed by a formal amendment to the Constitution. Following the procedure outlined in our Constitution, the SSB Council thus voted in August 2021 to propose an Amendment to the Constitution to be submitted to the SSB Membership for a vote. The Constitution specifies that the proposed Amendment will pass if at least 2/3 of the members vote in favor. This issue will be presented to the membership on the Spring 2022 ballot. The proposed amendment is shown below.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Proposed amendment&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Original text:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

1) The Ernst Mayr Award in Systematic Biology given for the outstanding paper presented at the Annual Meeting by a student member of the Society or a member who has received the Ph.D. degree within the last 15 months;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

New text:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

1) The Outstanding Student Presentation Award in Systematic Biology given for the outstanding paper presented at the Annual Meeting by a student member of the Society or a member who has received the Ph.D. degree within the last 15 months;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crucial background reading:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barkan, Elazar (1992). &lt;i&gt;The retreat of scientific racism : changing concepts of race in Britain and the United States between the world wars&lt;/i&gt;. Cambridge ; New York : Cambridge University Press, pp. 1-381. https://books.google.co.nz/books/about/The_Retreat_of_Scientific_Racism.html?id=-c8aSO-gnwMC&amp;amp;redir_esc=y&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ernst Mayr: Charles Darwin of the Twentieth Century. Biography — Academy of Achievement. Retrieved January 6, 2022. https://achievement.org/achiever/ernst-mayr-ph-d/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jerry Coyne’s post on the proposed Mayr de-naming:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coyne, Jerry (2022). Famous biologist Ernst Mayr about to be heaved into the dumpster by the Society of Systematic Biologists
January 6, 2022. https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2022/01/06/famous-biologist-ernst-mayr-about-to-be-unjustly-heaved-into-the-dumpster-by-the-society-for-systematic-biology/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main posts on various cannings of evolutionary greats:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On J.B.S. Haldane:
https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/haldane-1938-biology-of-inequality.html&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On T.H. Huxley:
http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statements to the Western Washington University Board on T.H. Huxley
http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments.html&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My attempts to put some context onto Twitter in the midst of the Great R.A. Fisher Panic of June 2020 – almost wholly unsuccessfully, I might add – are here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part 1: https://twitter.com/NickJMatzke/status/1270280876958474240 &lt;br /&gt;
Part 2: https://twitter.com/NickJMatzke/status/1270287477928939521&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently, some of the back-and-forth over Fisher in June 2020 was the origin of the SSB Mayr Award controversy, i.e. these posts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://twitter.com/Lagomarsino_L/status/1270856892630339601 &lt;br /&gt;
https://twitter.com/landismj/status/1270756154940022784&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short version of my argument in June 2020 was that we shouldn’t make hasty judgments about R.A. Fisher, because if you have read much about the history of eugenics or scientific racism, and the history of the opposition to the same, you realise that many of the people who made substantial progress in defeating these repugnant views did not achieve perfection instantaneously.  Views on race and eugenics changed gradually, step-by-step, with some mistakes and prejudices (e.g. polygenism) defeated long before others (e.g. the idea that biological race referred to real, meaningful categories). The people who fought against Nazi eugenics before World War 2 were largely eugenicists themselves (but “reform eugenicists”).  There were anti-racist eugenicists, anti-eugenics racists, etc.  None of this should be surprising to evolutionary biologists, of all people, who generally have an instinct for the importance and complexity of history, and how gradual change in many small steps can add up to big changes where the end result is almost unrecognizable from the beginning point.  The interesting thing about progress in moral views is not when it is done by people who are morally perfect. The interesting thing is when this progress is made by imperfect people, despite received wisdom and their initial prejudices. The process is, I think, not unlike scientific discovery. And in the case of racism &amp;amp; eugenics, scientific discoveries and moral progress were often linked, and many of the people who did the linking were the very evolutionary greats who are now being canned right and left.  For all of these reasons and more, it is more important to acknowledge the important progress people made, rather than the inherited assumptions they failed to overcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this, and more, would have to be taken into consideration in a fair evaluation of R.A. Fisher.  Using the old creationist tactic of quote-mining and putting up something that looks bad on Twitter is not a reliable method for judgment of historical matters. So, in the midst of discussing these issues in a heated Twitter discussion, I said, consider Ernst Mayr: if you google his name plus the word “eugenics”, which anyone can do very easily, you find something. You can play this trick for almost any biologist and/or progressive active between about 1900 and 1970. I never imagined people would take this seriously enough in the case of Ernst Mayr to begin discussing de-naming his award.*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Now, I have to acknowledge that I have been told by Josef Uyeda that (1) those Twitter replies may have kicked off the SSB Board’s discussion of the Mayr Award, but (2) no one made a serious case against Ernst Mayr that he heard about, and the denaming proposal and vote is really, truly, not about Mayr’s views or reputation, but about the abstract issue of whether or not awards should be named after individuals at all.  (I guess everything from the Nobel Prize on down should be denamed according to this logic.) I am happy to acknowledge his representation of his views. However, I think that the SSB proposal text itself, and the overall context of canning famous evolutionists left and right without anything resembling historical due diligence, indicates that much more is involved. We are living through an age of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iconoclasm&quot;&gt;iconoclasm&lt;/a&gt;, and legitimate rage against Trumpism, massive economic inequality, Covid denialism, and the rest, is being redirected to all kinds of weird places due to the difficulty of fixing the core problems.  It is all made worse by everyone being even more online than usual due to the pandemic, physical libraries and old paper books and sources being less accessible than usual, and the lack of face-to-face meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read Uyeda’s views in his own words at his Twitter thread, here: https://twitter.com/pseudacris/status/1479177881360207874&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, if you are in SSB, please vote against this proposal. Spasms of iconoclasm have to burn out somewhere, and it would be a further honor to Ernst Mayr if his award was the firebreak.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Matzke</name></author><summary type="html">David Hillis posted the following short essay to Facebook on June 21, 2021. Apparently the leadership of the Society for Systematic Biology (SSB) was discussing a proposal de-name the Ernst Mayr Award. This proposal has now been released, and, because the Ernst Mayr Award is written into SSB’s constitution (Ernst Mayr and his donations helped found SSB!), a 2/3 vote of the membership is required to change it. Hillis has given me permission to republish his essay here. I have my own comments below the fold. – Nick Matzke According to the photo description at https://achievement.org/achiever/ernst-mayr-ph-d/ : &quot;June 1928: Ernst Mayr with Sario, one of his Malay assistants, in the former Dutch New Guinea. Mayr led ornithological expeditions to Dutch New Guinea and German Mandated New Guinea, an experience that fulfilled 'the greatest ambition of his youth.' Mayr collected ca. 7000 bird skins in two and a half years.&quot; (Caption text added by NM) David Hillis June 21, 2021 I find it surprising and sad how quickly the amazing life and accomplishments of Ernst Mayr have faded from the memories of a new generation of biologists. I think Mayr had a bigger and more progressive influence on the development of evolutionary biology in the 20th Century, and the betterment of the world as a whole, than probably any other biologist. Mayr emphasized the importance of understanding the natural history of organisms to understand their evolution. He was way ahead of his time in arguing that our emphasis should be on studying whole genomes, rather than individual genes. He spent a lifetime encouraging young people to study biology and the natural world. After immigrating to the US from the horrors of Nazi Germany in the early 1930s, he spoke out against racism and segregation at a time when many of his fellow biologists were doing the opposite. He published over 700 influential articles and 24 books on biological practice and theory, 200 of which he published after he &quot;retired.&quot; Mayr worked to establish several major evolutionary societies, including the Society for the Study of Evolution and the Society of Systematic Zoologists (now Society of Systematic Biologists). He not only spent his time and efforts to found and support these societies, he also supported them financially. For example, in the 1970s he endowed a student award within SSZ to encourage young systematists to enter the field (now named the Ernst Mayr Award). That award has long been used to encourage young systematic biologists of diverse backgrounds to become engaged in studying biodiversity. He left an additional large gift to SSB in his will, which became the nucleus of SSB's endowment that has enabled the many programs and funding opportunities that society now provides to encourage young systematists. I greatly admire the life and accomplishments of Mayr, even though he and I frequently disagreed over scientific issues. He was already one of the 20th Century's most famous biologists when I met him, and I was just a lowly graduate student working on bringing molecular techniques into systematics. Mayr was not a big fan of this; he was not anti-molecular systematics, but he argued (quite reasonably) that single gene analyses of systematic questions were problematic, and he thought that many molecular systematists did not pay enough attention to the biology and natural history of their organisms (which was often true). After I co-edited the book Molecular Systematics in 1990, he and I often discussed the development and expansion of molecular techniques in the field. But despite our disagreements over this (as well as various issues of systematic theory), he was always cordial, encouraging, warm, and most of all—knowledgeable. It was always clear to me that he read the literature exhaustively. When he asked me questions about or critiqued my papers, it was clear that he had read and thought about them carefully. He had a command of the literature like no one else that I'd ever encountered, or have encountered since. He taught me that people can disagree about issues, and still be great friends (in fact, it can even help and build a friendship to discuss such disagreements). Most people today likely picture Mayr as an old man, as he was over 100 when he died in 2005, and most living people would remember him (if at all) as an old man. This photo of him (on the right in the photo) shows him as a 23-year-old field biologist in New Guinea in 1928. He had an enormous, positive influence on the world, and especially on the positive development of evolutionary and systematic biology. We should remember and thank him for that. He worked to make the world, and his discipline, better than they were when he came into them. I think that is the lofty goal that we should all strive to achieve in our lives. Hillis posted additional comments to his Facebook post on January 6, 2022:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mimus melanotis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/mimus-melanotis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mimus melanotis" /><published>2022-01-03T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-01-03T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/mimus-melanotis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/mimus-melanotis.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Dave Rintoul&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Rintoul.San_cristobal_mockingbird_0920.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mockingbird&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.darwinfoundation.org/en/datazone/checklist?species=5117&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Mimus melanotis&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; San Cristobal mockingbird (aka Chatham Island mockingbird). Mr. Rintoul writes that the San Cristobal mockingbird &quot;is found only on the island of San Cristobal and nearby Pitt Island in the Galápagos Archipelago. It was one of the first animals encountered by Darwin when he arrived on San Cristobal (which British sailors called Chatham Island) in 1835. Other similar-but-different species of mockingbirds, collected by Darwin on other islands in the archipelago, provided some of the first sparks for his ideas about speciation and common descent. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/science/2008/nov/14/evolution-charles-darwin&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://darwin-online.org.uk/EditorialIntroductions/Chancellor_Keynes_Galapagos.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was drawn to this picture while mining some old contest pictures for this post. When I was in the Galápagos in 2006 (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2021/12/24/readers-wildlife-photos-1500/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2022/01/01/readers-wildlife-photos-1508/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), I did not manage a photograph of a single finch or other small bird, save one or two that are not endemic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Dave Rintoul. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Mimus melanotis &amp;ndash; San Cristobal mockingbird (aka Chatham Island mockingbird). Mr. Rintoul writes that the San Cristobal mockingbird &quot;is found only on the island of San Cristobal and nearby Pitt Island in the Galápagos Archipelago. It was one of the first animals encountered by Darwin when he arrived on San Cristobal (which British sailors called Chatham Island) in 1835. Other similar-but-different species of mockingbirds, collected by Darwin on other islands in the archipelago, provided some of the first sparks for his ideas about speciation and common descent. See here and here.&quot; I was drawn to this picture while mining some old contest pictures for this post. When I was in the Galápagos in 2006 (see here and here), I did not manage a photograph of a single finch or other small bird, save one or two that are not endemic.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The worst ID or creationist argument of 2021? Let us know</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/worst-of-2021.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The worst ID or creationist argument of 2021? Let us know" /><published>2021-12-29T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-12-29T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/worst-of-2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/worst-of-2021.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/400pxRecycleBin.png&quot; alt=&quot;From Wikimedia.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Old arguments never die, they just get recycled.  From Wikimedia.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the end of 2021, which has been a fairly miserable year for most of us.  So it is entirely appropriate for us to consider what is the most ridiculous argument put forward this year for ID or for creationism.  I’m going to give my own choice, which is both highly technical and highly absurd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you get to make a nomination of your own. (There will no winner chosen or prize awarded).  The argument need not be one that was first proposed in 2021, as long as it continued to be put forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own choice is the Algorithmic Specified Complexity argument, which purports to show mathematically that
high levels of adaptation cannot be achieved, because the length of the “program” used is unusually short, and
this is backed up by very impressive, and sometimes quite correct, mathematical proofs.  The effort is usually
to show that the length of the program needed is conserved, so perhaps it cannot be changed by evolution.  Perhaps.    I’ve ranted and
raved in &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/12/Is-Algorithmic-Specified-Complexity-Useless-for-Analyzing-Evolution.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;another
post&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
about the wrongness of this two years ago here.  But the argument has never been disowned by any of its
advocates, including Robert Marks, Winston Ewert, or Eric Holloway.  So it is still out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s why it is silly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There never is any attempt by its advocates to show that an unusually simple program is needed for a highly fit
adaptation, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is never clarified whether the “program” computes the genotype, the phenotype, or something else, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Even the name is ludicrous: “Complexity” is achieved by the program being unusually simple (the reverse of
the way algorithmic complexity theory is used to discuss random numbers),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The distribution of binary bitstrings used is totally arbitrary, and there could be many others as well- (or ill-)
justified.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When one asks about how any of this works, the authors of the theory simply say that they are not biologists,
so they leave the filling in of those details to the biologists, but&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Somehow they still expect people to consider their argument to be meaningful biologically.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument has such a tension between its mathematical pretentiousness and its basic meaninglessness that
for me it achieves worstness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, that’s my candidate for Worst.  What’s yours?  We have quite a few wise heads here who are quite familiar with the
arguments ID advocates and creationists make.  If you aren’t as familiar, just take a look at the Discovery Institute’s “Evolution
News and Science Today” site and start reading stories there.  It will supply
you with lots of candidates. Let’s hear from you, below in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Old arguments never die, they just get recycled. From Wikimedia. It is the end of 2021, which has been a fairly miserable year for most of us. So it is entirely appropriate for us to consider what is the most ridiculous argument put forward this year for ID or for creationism. I’m going to give my own choice, which is both highly technical and highly absurd. But you get to make a nomination of your own. (There will no winner chosen or prize awarded). The argument need not be one that was first proposed in 2021, as long as it continued to be put forward. My own choice is the Algorithmic Specified Complexity argument, which purports to show mathematically that high levels of adaptation cannot be achieved, because the length of the “program” used is unusually short, and this is backed up by very impressive, and sometimes quite correct, mathematical proofs. The effort is usually to show that the length of the program needed is conserved, so perhaps it cannot be changed by evolution. Perhaps. I’ve ranted and raved in another post about the wrongness of this two years ago here. But the argument has never been disowned by any of its advocates, including Robert Marks, Winston Ewert, or Eric Holloway. So it is still out there. Here’s why it is silly: There never is any attempt by its advocates to show that an unusually simple program is needed for a highly fit adaptation, and It is never clarified whether the “program” computes the genotype, the phenotype, or something else, and Even the name is ludicrous: “Complexity” is achieved by the program being unusually simple (the reverse of the way algorithmic complexity theory is used to discuss random numbers), The distribution of binary bitstrings used is totally arbitrary, and there could be many others as well- (or ill-) justified. When one asks about how any of this works, the authors of the theory simply say that they are not biologists, so they leave the filling in of those details to the biologists, but Somehow they still expect people to consider their argument to be meaningful biologically. The argument has such a tension between its mathematical pretentiousness and its basic meaninglessness that for me it achieves worstness. OK, that’s my candidate for Worst. What’s yours? We have quite a few wise heads here who are quite familiar with the arguments ID advocates and creationists make. If you aren’t as familiar, just take a look at the Discovery Institute’s “Evolution News and Science Today” site and start reading stories there. It will supply you with lots of candidates. Let’s hear from you, below in the comments.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Ken Ham thinks about the Webb Space Telescope</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/ham-webb-space-telescope.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Ken Ham thinks about the Webb Space Telescope" /><published>2021-12-27T12:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-12-27T12:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/ham-webb-space-telescope</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/ham-webb-space-telescope.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Ham_Job_Foundation_Earth_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ham tweet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A correspondent sent us this tweet by Ken Ham:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; There's only one way to go back in time &amp;amp; that's to read the true history of the universe God revealed to us in His Word beginning in Genesis. &quot;Where were you when I laid the foundation of the earth?&quot; (Job 38:4)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is Mr. Ham’s take on the recent launch of the James Webb Space Telescope. I find it astonishing, even for something coming from Ken Ham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, it gives quoting out of context a very bad name. The story of Job is a horrible one (I have written a bit more about it &lt;a href=&quot;https://people.mines.edu/mmyoung/wp-content/uploads/sites/99/2019/01/Young_No_Sense_of_Obligation.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, pp. 160-168). In the book, God gives Satan permission to torture Job and kill his family, for no other reason than to win a bet with Satan. Job, in contrast to God, seems to believe in justice or fairness, and calls out to God to show him his guilt. God’s response is to mock Job. Chapter 38, the chapter cited by Mr. Ham, reads (according to the 1985 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sefaria.org/Job.38.4?lang=bi&quot;&gt;JPS Tanakh&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;Where were you when I laid the earth's foundations? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speak if you have understanding. … &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; Onto what were its bases sunk? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who set its cornerstone …? &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;God to goes on to browbeat and belittle Job. Though God never addresses Job’s concern, Job finally gives in, admitting that he is “but dust and ashes.” How such a reprehensible story buttresses the case for creation escapes me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, and perhaps worse, a careful reading of the text shows clearly that its author thought of the earth as a solid object with a physical foundation and a base that was sunk into something (perhaps like a pile driven into the earth?). Unsurprisingly, then, we find that Mr. Ham is quoting as an authority an author who thinks that the earth is a flat slab, possibly sitting on some unknown foundation into which piles have been driven, and probably with a dome over it. (Possibly that foundation is sitting on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Turtles_all_the_way_down&quot;&gt;turtle&lt;/a&gt;.) Hardly a portion of the Bible that I would want to quote if I wanted to cite an authority on the creation of the earth. But with Mr. Ham, we never know. Any out-of-context quotation will suffice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">A correspondent sent us this tweet by Ken Ham: There's only one way to go back in time &amp;amp; that's to read the true history of the universe God revealed to us in His Word beginning in Genesis. &quot;Where were you when I laid the foundation of the earth?&quot; (Job 38:4) It is Mr. Ham’s take on the recent launch of the James Webb Space Telescope. I find it astonishing, even for something coming from Ken Ham. First, it gives quoting out of context a very bad name. The story of Job is a horrible one (I have written a bit more about it here, pp. 160-168). In the book, God gives Satan permission to torture Job and kill his family, for no other reason than to win a bet with Satan. Job, in contrast to God, seems to believe in justice or fairness, and calls out to God to show him his guilt. God’s response is to mock Job. Chapter 38, the chapter cited by Mr. Ham, reads (according to the 1985 JPS Tanakh), 4Where were you when I laid the earth's foundations? Speak if you have understanding. … 6 Onto what were its bases sunk? Who set its cornerstone …? God to goes on to browbeat and belittle Job. Though God never addresses Job’s concern, Job finally gives in, admitting that he is “but dust and ashes.” How such a reprehensible story buttresses the case for creation escapes me. Second, and perhaps worse, a careful reading of the text shows clearly that its author thought of the earth as a solid object with a physical foundation and a base that was sunk into something (perhaps like a pile driven into the earth?). Unsurprisingly, then, we find that Mr. Ham is quoting as an authority an author who thinks that the earth is a flat slab, possibly sitting on some unknown foundation into which piles have been driven, and probably with a dome over it. (Possibly that foundation is sitting on a turtle.) Hardly a portion of the Bible that I would want to quote if I wanted to cite an authority on the creation of the earth. But with Mr. Ham, we never know. Any out-of-context quotation will suffice.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Selasphorus platycercus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/selasphorus_platycercus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Selasphorus platycercus" /><published>2021-12-20T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-12-20T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/selasphorus_platycercus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/selasphorus_platycercus.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Paul Strode&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Strode_Broad_Tailed_Hummingbird_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hummingbird&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broad-tailed_hummingbird&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Selasphorus platycercus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; broad-tailed hummingbird, Skunk Canyon, Boulder, Colorado, May, 2021.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Paul Strode. Selasphorus platycercus &amp;ndash; broad-tailed hummingbird, Skunk Canyon, Boulder, Colorado, May, 2021.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Teaching indigenous “ways of knowing” as science</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/indigenous-ways-of-knowing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Teaching indigenous “ways of knowing” as science" /><published>2021-12-13T11:12:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-12-13T11:12:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/indigenous-ways-of-knowing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/indigenous-ways-of-knowing.html">&lt;p&gt;For readers who have not been following this controversy, I thought I would point out Jerry Coyne’s article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2021/12/13/new-zealand-authorities-stand-firm-in-desire-to-teach-maori-ways-of-knowing-alongside-science-in-high-schools-and-colleges/&quot;&gt; New Zealand’s intention to teach Maori “ways of knowing”&lt;/a&gt; alongside science in schools and universities. Dr. Coyne has been following the situation for some time now, but the article I cite, his latest as of now, provides a good summary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scare quotes (“ways of knowing”) are Dr. Coyne’s, but to my mind they are entirely justified. True, the Maori and other indigenous peoples have learned a great deal about their environments, but much of what they “know” is palpably untrue. Indeed, many indigenous peoples, including the ancient Hebrews, tell what are essentially creationist myths and are therefore demonstrably false. These myths are also generally mutually exclusive. They may be appropriate in anthropology or history classes, but they are not science and do not belong in a science class, except conceivably alongside phlogiston in a unit on the history of science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New Zealand policy, though obviously well-intentioned, is frankly pandering. It leads to the following question: Must we teach Iroquois “ways of knowing” in New York, Navajo “ways of knowing” in &lt;strike&gt;New Mexico&lt;/strike&gt; Arizona, and astrology in Boulder, Colorado – all as if they were science?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">For readers who have not been following this controversy, I thought I would point out Jerry Coyne’s article on New Zealand’s intention to teach Maori “ways of knowing” alongside science in schools and universities. Dr. Coyne has been following the situation for some time now, but the article I cite, his latest as of now, provides a good summary. The scare quotes (“ways of knowing”) are Dr. Coyne’s, but to my mind they are entirely justified. True, the Maori and other indigenous peoples have learned a great deal about their environments, but much of what they “know” is palpably untrue. Indeed, many indigenous peoples, including the ancient Hebrews, tell what are essentially creationist myths and are therefore demonstrably false. These myths are also generally mutually exclusive. They may be appropriate in anthropology or history classes, but they are not science and do not belong in a science class, except conceivably alongside phlogiston in a unit on the history of science. The New Zealand policy, though obviously well-intentioned, is frankly pandering. It leads to the following question: Must we teach Iroquois “ways of knowing” in New York, Navajo “ways of knowing” in New Mexico Arizona, and astrology in Boulder, Colorado – all as if they were science?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">De-naming the Huxley College of the Environment: Comments to the WWU Board</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="De-naming the Huxley College of the Environment: Comments to the WWU Board" /><published>2021-12-09T08:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-12-09T08:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments.html">&lt;p&gt;At 3 pm on Thursday, December 9, 2021, the Western Washington University Board of Directors is having a final hearing on the proposed de-naming of the Huxley College of the Environment. In a late twist, the Board has apparently abandoned its earlier Legacy Review Task Force Report on Huxley, presumably after all of the historical mistake and distortions were pointed out. Instead, it commissioned a last-minute “&lt;a href=&quot;https://trustees.wwu.edu/meeting-materials&quot;&gt;Ad Hoc Committee Report&lt;/a&gt;”, which retreats on most of the anti-Huxley claims, and semi-acknowledges Huxley’s numerous progressive achievements, but in the end still recommends de-naming Huxley because, it judges, student perceptions trump context and truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all matters, because the WWU fight is pretty clearly an initial skirmish in a debate that will continue with the proposed denaming of the Huxley Building at Imperial College London, and other Huxley awards, lectures, and Darwiniana.  Win or lose at WWU, it is important to develop and publicize the evidence and arguments against this kind of thing. What is at stake? Huxley, Darwin, and a great number of other progressive reformers who helped enlighten our society, and, frankly, who helped to develop our modern anti-racist views, will be wiped from the public sphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of us are giving comments today. Mine are posted below. The speakers are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gragg Miller&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/people/s.j.warren&quot;&gt;Stephen Warren, Professor of Astrophysics at Imperial College London&lt;/a&gt; -- &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments.html#Warren&quot;&gt;link to comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meg Town, WWU alum and public school science teacher who has encountered similar disinformation efforts by creationists. Teacher in Washington state in a 1995 fight with creationists in 1995. -- &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments.html#MegTown&quot;&gt;link to comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://unidirectory.auckland.ac.nz/profile/nmat471&quot;&gt;Nick Matzke, Senior Lecturer in Biological Sciences, University of Auckland, New Zealand&lt;/a&gt; -- &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments.html#MatzkeComments&quot;&gt;link to comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mike Town, WWU/Huxley alum, high school science teacher, NSF Einstein Fellow, and member of the Teacher Advisory Council for the National Academies of Science.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://huxley.wwu.edu/people/steve-hollenhorst&quot;&gt;Steve Hollenhorst, Professor and Former Dean, Huxley College of the Environment, Western Washington University&lt;/a&gt; -- &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments.html#Hollenhorst&quot;&gt;link to comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://biology.wwu.edu/people/leaf&quot;&gt;David Leaf, Professor Emeritus, Biology, Western Washington.University&lt;/a&gt;. Coauthor of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://wp.wwu.edu/huxley-legacy/&quot;&gt;Response to the Legacy Review Task Force Report&lt;/a&gt; -- &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments.html#DavidLeaf&quot;&gt;link to comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The live link to listen at 3pm PST will be: &lt;a href=&quot;https://wp.wwu.edu/live/&quot;&gt;https://wp.wwu.edu/live/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My comments below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;These comments represent my personal views, not those of current or previous employers. The documentation for my claims can be found in the links in my essay on this matter:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Updated: Creationists and advocates of social justice unite to take down T.H. Huxley, a leader in educational inclusion
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html&quot;&gt;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html&lt;/a&gt; &amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Text (5 minutes to read):&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for giving me an opportunity to speak. My name is Nick Matzke, I am a Senior Lecturer in Biology at the University of Auckland, but until recently my whole career was in the USA. I am interested in society’s treatment of Thomas Henry Huxley because I have worked in the fields of science education and evolutionary science for almost 20 years. Part of that work involved the 2005 &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover&lt;/i&gt; trial, where I discovered the creationist ancestry of the so-called “intelligent design” movement, promoted by the Discovery Institute of Seattle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huxley is an inspiration for me as the original public advocate for science, science education, and science-informed liberalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;MatzkeComments&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my science-education work, I have seen first-hand the damage that can be done when ideology trumps careful scholarship. Misinformation spreads, trust in science declines, particularly in vulnerable communities - as we have seen with vaccine hesitancy, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Western’s case, we have the bizarre situation where the discussion of Huxley was dominated for over a year by social justice activists relying on anti-Huxley propaganda found on right-wing creationist and conspiracist websites, including a Discovery Institute author. Thankfully, this has finally been tacitly admitted, with the last-minute “Ad Hoc” committee report excising nearly all of the claims now proven false about Huxley being a polygenist, scientific racist, social Darwinist, eugenicist, etc. Nevertheless, this new Report still recommends the de-naming of Huxley, based on nothing but the premise that student perceptions of Huxley trump the actual facts and context of Huxley’s record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is that Huxley was not just a scientist, a progressive, an advocate for diversity and inclusion in science and science education. He was also, in the main, an anti-racist, a radical who said “the North is justified in any expenditure of blood or of money” to eliminate slavery. He was someone who pushed his culture to be better. Due diligence has not been done until the Board accepts a report that includes Huxley’s complete record on race. This absolutely &lt;i&gt;must&lt;/i&gt; include Huxley’s long battle with the scientific racist James Hunt and his Anthropological Society; and Huxley’s membership on the Jamaica Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If “James Hunt” and the “Jamaica Committee” are not familiar to you, that may be because no pro-denaming document issued by Western has yet succeeded in even discussing them! Here is a brief summary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October 1865, just after the end of the US Civil War, hundreds of Black protestors in the British colony of Jamaica marched for justice, land reform, and the vote. The British governor of Jamaica, Edward Eyre, declared martial law and authorized reprisals that killed &lt;a href=&quot;https://victorianweb.org/history/empire/westindies/eyreaffair.html&quot;&gt;439 Black Jamaicans&lt;/a&gt;, including the illegal hanging of former slave George Gordon, a member of the Jamaica House of Assembly (and nowadays a &lt;a href=&quot;https://jis.gov.jm/information/heroes/george-william-gordon/&quot;&gt;National Hero of Jamaica&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A massive multiyear controversy broke out in Britain over the carnage, but the British government refused to even prosecute Governor Eyre. The Jamaica Committee was formed to privately prosecute Eyre for murder. It was soon led by John Stuart Mill, and Huxley signed up, along with other scientists and radicals. When Darwin himself joined, Huxley wrote to thank him for joining, quote, “the right (that is &lt;u&gt;my&lt;/u&gt;) side.” (emphasis original)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ad Hoc Committee Report suggests that, quote, “Huxley’s views were firmly within the mainstream of Victorian thought,” unquote. The massive opposition to the Jamaica Committee gives lie to that claim. The Governor Eyre Defense Fund was supported by John Tyndall, John Ruskin, Thomas Carlyle, Alfred Tennyson, 40 generals, 26 admirals, 400 clergy, 6 bishops, 20 Ministers of Parliament, 71 peers of the House of Lords, and 30,000 others, including Charles Dickens. That’s right: if, during this Christmas season, you see Charles Dickens’ story about Ebenezer Scrooge, A Christmas Carol, you should keep in mind that Dickens was on the wrong side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jamaica Committee had only 800 supporters, so the Victorian elites were 40:1 against Huxley and his colleagues. Huxley took a stand against all of these elites. This is who you are de-naming, if you de-name Huxley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huxley took flack for his stand. James Hunt went after him. Hunt had been fighting with Huxley since 1863 over whether or not Black people were a transitional species between apes and whites – Huxley used words like “nonsense”, “quack”, “thoroughly disgusted”, and “imposter” in response to Hunt. When Huxley joined the Jamaica Committee, Hunt accused him of, quote, “equal-rights mania” and, quote, “Negro-mania”, and joked that Huxley would soon be saying that gorilla-hunters should be prosecuted for murder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hunt and his friends wanted to “cancel” Huxley and devote anthropology to studying the hierarchical “laws of race.” If you de-name Huxley, you are accomplishing something that Hunt never could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for the history of science and of Britain, it was Huxley that crushed Hunt. Virulent racism dominated Darwinism in countries like Germany, but its influence was weaker in the U.K., in part because of Huxley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, as we all know, the effort to dename Huxley College took off in the wake of the murder of George Floyd and the Black Lives Matter protests. And it is understandable, in the heat of legitimate rage against racial injustice and the rabid bigotry of the Trump era, that getting rid of Huxley, because his antiracism was imperfect, can seem like a way to “do something”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But consider this: what was the Jamaica Committee, if not an early expression of the principle that Black Lives Matter – that law enforcement is subject to the same laws as everyone else, that racists who murder Black people should be held accountable under the law, and that Black people deserve the same rights as everyone else? Huxley was already there in 1865, and defended that position against massive opposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does it serve justice to treat T.H. Huxley as if he were James Hunt or Governor Eyre, when he actually was their vehement opponent?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you de-name Huxley, you are de-naming an anti-racist ally, perceived as such at the time by both sides, who defended the principle that Black Lives Matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;(Other testimony)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Warren&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Comments from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/people/s.j.warren&quot;&gt;Stephen Warren, Professor of Astrophysics at Imperial College London&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello I am Stephen Warren&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am Professor of Astrophysics at Imperial College&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for letting me speak to you today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is night time at Imperial, but when I am sitting in my office I am 10 yds from the bust of Huxley, and 100yds from archeopteryx, the fossil Huxley used to show that birds evolved from small dinosaurs. At Imperial, Thomas Huxley is the scientist of whom we are most proud, more than our  Nobel Prize winners. As you know he was a great scientist, a great social reformer, and an unsurpassed educator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like you we have been examining our history and we have inherited directly from you the criticism of Huxley’s 1865 essay Emancipation: Black and White. Because of his alleged belief, in this essay, in a hierarchy of races, our History Group has recommended that the Huxley Building be renamed, and that his bust be hidden away in an archive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you might think I would be pretty annoyed with WWU for starting this problem off, but in a minute I am going to thank you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First let me tell you a little bit about what is happening here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been an very strong negative reaction to the suggestion of renaming:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;major articles have appeared in our national newspapers: &lt;i&gt;The Times&lt;/i&gt;,&lt;i&gt;The Guardian&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;The Telegraph&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;many leading scientists, including Nobel Prize winner Sir Paul Nurse, another 4 knights of the realm, and some 20 Fellows of the Royal Society have denounced the recommendations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a greatgrandson of Thomas Huxley has added his voice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and leading historians have criticised our History Group for poor scholarship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really, most people cannot understand why Imperial wants to cancel their greatest scientist, and given this reaction at the moment I am rather confident that the name will stay on the building, but one can’t be certain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now despite this rather taking over my life the reason I want to thank you is that I have learned such an enormous amount from this process, and it is this educational process that I want to focus on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe all of us have probably gone through similar steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started out being shocked in reading the first three paragraphs of Emancipation Black and White; and then I started to understand better the society Huxley lived in; and then I steadily developed a growing admiration for Huxley’s contributions to many social causes, including of course:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the abolition of slavery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;justice for Gordon in the Jamaica revolt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fighting the scientific racism of the polygenists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;university education for women&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;free education for the working classes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proper historians already knew this, but finally I reached the point, 180 degrees from where I started, where I appreciated that in reality Huxley is truly the greatest Victorian champion of inclusion: inclusion in race, inclusion in gender, and inclusion in class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If today we understand and appreciate better the importance of inclusion, let us thank Huxley for getting us half way there, rather than censor him for not getting all the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read carefully the report of the ad hoc legacy review committee. This is a clear, fair, and measured synthesis of a mass of material. And it seems clear to me that the Board have also gone through this process of understanding Huxley’s greatness as a champion of inclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in reading your report, where you seem to show all this, I was surprised and disappointed to read on the penultimate page `The Ad Hoc Committee recommends removal of the Huxley name.’ Because in doing this you are denying the opportunity for your students to receive the benefits of going through the same educational process that you have enjoyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice is set out starkly in your report starting at the bottom of p4. You can take the safe route: safe for the students and safe for the university, and cancel Huxley. The students lose because they don’t learn about Huxley, they don’t learn from Huxley, they don’t learn the lessons of history, and they don’t overcome this challenge. Or you can take the more difficult route: keep Huxley and teach all about him. The students win for all the reasons given, and the university wins because it faces up to its educational duty. I believe your students are strong enough for the challenge, and all will be grateful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fifty years is actually a long time, so Huxley is part of your history. The name was a wise choice, because he was a great scientist, and also because he was the greatest Victorian pioneer of inclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;MegTown&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Comments from Meg Town, a teacher who was involved in a 1995 battle with the Discovery Institute in Sultan School District, Washington state&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;WWU Board of Trustees Statement&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My name is Meg Town.  Thank you for the opportunity to speak.
I am against the de-naming of Huxley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a BA in environmental biology from the University of Colorado; and a master’s in education UW&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My teaching credentials are from Western&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am endorsed in biology, the physical sciences and mathematics and taught for 30 years in Washington state public school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 3 years I was privileged to work with Upward Bound under the direction of Bernie Thomas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am married to Mike Town a distinguished Huxley College alumnus, and half of my estate is currently endowed to Huxley College, in part to provide scholarships to underrepresented students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Why I’m here.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not the first time the wedge strategy has been used in Washington state to divide the public and undermine science education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my very first course at Western, Dr. Perak gave me a deep understanding of the nature of science and paradigm shifts. Science builds and refines models based on new evidence. The evidence requires rigor, repeated tests and peer review before it becomes accepted. All data is reviewed.  It cannot be cherry picked. This process is conducted in public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My intersection with attacks on science from the same people amplifying the false claim of racism against TH Huxley came about in the fall of 1995, shortly after the release of the Washington State Science Standards AKA the Science EALRs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was appointed head of the science adoption committee for the Sultan School District.  The committee consisted of teachers, an administrator, a school board member, and members of the community. I was teaching middle school science; the high school biology teacher declined the invite as she did not want to tangle with the expected attacks on her teaching of evolution.
Indeed, the school board member along with some members of the community attempted to insert the teaching of Intelligent Design (Creationism) into the science curriculum and curricular materials.  They received help and materials from the Discovery Institute of Seattle and other national creationism organizations to promote creation science and the textbook &lt;i&gt;Of Pandas and People&lt;/i&gt;. The leaders are familiar to you-Morris, Gisch, Glumaz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same folks amplifying the false claims against TH Huxley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tactics:  at a school board meeting, the husband of the school board member on my committee used a copied speech that linked the teaching of evolution with the reason for rapists.  Then he pointed at me and declared, “and there she is!” Coincidentally, The John Birch Society held a meeting in Everett.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This soon became a bigger than just about preserving science.  It was about civil rights. Indigenous members of the community enlightened me to the fact that they didn’t support science because they assimilated evolution as their way of knowing. They did not want the teaching of the Judeo-Christian creation myth in their children’s public-school classrooms.  The preservation of the Judeo-Christian Culture is the stated goal of the Discovery Institute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To counter the creationist movement and the incorrect portrayal of science to the school board and the adoption committee, I engaged with the ACLU and the National Center for Science Education to gain legal, cultural, and content understandings.  Local churches, doctors and science supporters wrote letters in support of science standards and materials without the insertion of Intelligent Design/Creationist ideas and materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a community forum on the issue, attended by 500 people, the school board fortunately unanimously adopted science only standards and materials. Dover Schools in Pennsylvania were not so lucky.  They were involved in a lawsuit stemming from the same time that was decided in 2005.  The court case decided the use of Of Pandas and People which promotes Intelligent Design, Creationism renamed, was not science and violated the establishment clause of the constitution. Disclaimers of evolution were also disallowed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sultan School District experienced a painful and unnecessary chapter in the battle against pseudoscience.  Creationists did succeed in dividing the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next fall there was a turnover of three school board members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next spring, I was involuntarily transferred to teaching math. I left to teach in the Northshore School District.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biology teacher retrained as a firefighter where she could be received as a hero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to today, the same folks are successfully inserting themselves in current challenges facing our public academic institutions.  States are adopting anti-science education legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very true that many students do not have equitable access to university programs.  There are real barriers that need to be identified and removed to correct this disparity.  Changing the name of Huxley, by adopting the false narrative that he was racist is not going to correct the equity issues.
As a teacher from era of the internet, I learned over time that it was far too easy for my students to base their conclusions on a few clicks. My refrain: “Where did you hear it and why do you believe it?” I ask that you please backcheck the sources you are using to make your decision for this public institution. A lack of due diligence can come back to harm Western and the students.  No one has this intent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Student voices do need to be heard and elevated. You have an opportunity to identify and alter policies, practices and behaviors that underly the issues of inequity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow the lead of TH Huxley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He served on the London school board and promoted &lt;b&gt;policies&lt;/b&gt; to expand public access to education and to train science teachers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;In practice&lt;/b&gt;, he taught at a working-class institution akin to Western rather than the elite Cambridge or Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;In behavior&lt;/b&gt;, he consistently wrote and spoke publicly, to the commons, in favor of abolition; the inclusion of women in education; the protection of due process for all; and in support of science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please do not diminish the integrity of Western by de-naming Huxley based on an inaccurate and incomplete portrayal of the man.  Rather, examine the &lt;b&gt;barriers&lt;/b&gt; for students. Work through a public process with students, staff and community to improve access and safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;If in the journey&lt;/b&gt; toward a more equitable institution, the renaming of Huxley will promote a new and improved mission/vision. Do so.  But follow a process with merit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not without notice that a school board in a small rural community was able to see through the rhetoric of the Discovery Institute and others to preserve the integrity of their science program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank again you for your time and considerations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Hollenhorst&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Comments from &lt;a href=&quot;https://huxley.wwu.edu/people/steve-hollenhorst&quot;&gt;Steve Hollenhorst, Professor and Former Dean, Huxley College of the Environment, Western Washington University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you, trustee Meyer. The Ad Hoc Committee states that it grounded its conclusions on the Yale Principles on Renaming, which place the principal legacy of the individual as a primary criterion. Let’s look at that legacy for Thomas H. Huxley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huxley’s legacy, simply, is that evolutionary science is true, and all the immeasurable good that followed from that transformation in the way we see the world, from medical science that combats disease with high tech vaccines and treatment, to life sciences that enable us to feed the world, saving and improving the lives of billions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Western’s legacy, sadly, will be as the public higher education institution to elevate creationist disinformation from the darkest fringe corners of American thought, giving it the legitimacy they’ve long sought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huxley’s legacy is that common descent applies to humans, and scientific justification for the oneness - and equality - of all humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our legacy will be advancing the creationist wedge strategy to undermine science, and how we fell into that trap. We commend the Committee for removing – if not actually acknowledging – the most scurrilous accusations in the Task Force Report. Yet it still includes fringe claims that Huxley held hierarchal views of race, derived from a Lyndon LaRouche operative, Discovery Institute author, and creationist historian. This despite abundant evidence of Huxley’s moral journey from typical Victorian to radical anti-racist, where he rejected such physical hierarchies, arguing instead that they were culturally imposed and enforced–often violently–by an oppressive society. Is that not an early description of what we now call systemic racism?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huxley’s legacy is democratizing an inclusive approach to science education, regardless of race, gender, or class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our legacy, is this exclusionary and divisive decision process, denying a voice for science on the task force, and all requests to meet with the task force, while affording both to Huxley critics. For me, this is the saddest moment in this story, because it set us on a censure path, where biases went unchecked, and distortions and lies internalized to confirm those biases. It’s where we failed our students by underestimating their ability to engage in a journey of learning and discover on this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, our legacy will be this denaming resolution itself, which once passed, will be proclaimed by every creationist group to advance their wedge strategy. Whatever you do, I implore you to not do it with a resolution that affirms their talking points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process has horribly divided the Huxley College community. A just-completed survey of the faculty and staff, conducted by the college leadership, is far from a ringing endorsement of either denaming or this process. My sense is that before all of this, most folks were open to a name change that could bring us into the next 50 years. After this process,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only 44% think the name of the college should be changed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In fact, a solid majority 55% feel Huxley’s views on race were progressive for the time,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And only 40% think it appropriate to use 21st century standards to judge him&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where there is strong agreement, with nearly two thirds or more agreeing, is that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Huxley should be admired for his contributions to both science and social causes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that sources in the task report were inappropriate because of their anti-science agenda&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that the creationist narrative should be denounced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that what is lost in denaming is as important as what is gained.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could have, and still can, follow a more constructive and unifying path. As Dr. Matzke urges, study this further, let’s learn from and incorporate the work going on at Imperial College. They’ve learned a lot from us, and now we can learn from them. At the same time, constitute a study group, inclusive of both social justice and science voices, tasked with mapping a forward-looking and aspirational future for the college. Re-engage our students on this. Through mutual learning, we can develop a collective set of actions to realize our DEI goals, of which a new name could be a part. I for one would support it, and it would bring the college together again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the path we’re on, I fear we will fracture further, our alumni and students will be driven away, and the college will not survive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;DavidLeaf&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Comments from &lt;a href=&quot;https://biology.wwu.edu/people/leaf&quot;&gt;David Leaf, Professor Emeritus, Biology, Western Washington.University&lt;/a&gt;. Coauthor of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://wp.wwu.edu/huxley-legacy/&quot;&gt;Response to the Legacy Review Task Force Report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;David Leaf’s Comments&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the Board of Trustees for the opportunity to comment about denaming Huxley College of the Environment. Also thanks to the Ad Hoc Committee of the Board for their work in producing a memorandum that clearly and carefully illustrates the challenges of balancing the contemporary norms of inclusion and equity with fairly evaluating historical figures. I am a retired professor of Biology at Western. I have taught courses comparing Intelligent Design Creationism with Evolution, so I am well-acquainted with creationist arguments, including arguments linking supporters of Darwinian evolution with racism. And of course, Huxley was the prominent supporter of Darwin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also worked to increase inclusion on campus. I was one of the co-authors of a successful grant proposal to the Howard Hughes Medical Institute to increase inclusion in STEM. And I had the privilege of serving on the University Strategic Plan Committee which placed inclusion as a core element of the Strategic plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am encouraged by the emphasis in memorandum about the importance of mitigating harm after a final decision about denaming. One potential harm with denaming is that it may be used by creationists to claim that Darwin’s theory of evolution is itself racist and to challenge the teaching of Darwinian evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, it is important that instructors in Biology and ESCI can clearly articulate the reasoning used to Board of Trustees to justify the denaming. This need may have been anticipated by Ad Hoc Committee with the suggestion that the Board of Trustees can mitigate the harm of denaming by clearly communicating the competing interests they needed to balance and the complexities of evaluating the issue of whether Huxley was racist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The breadth of opinion offered by the expert scholars solicited by the Legacy Review Task Force clearly indicate these complexities. While the memorandum from the Ad Hoc Committee avoids getting into weeds about the disagreements between the expert scholars, this disagreement is itself the best indication of how complex it is evaluate Huxley. Inclusion of the opinions of all the expert scholars on one or two key questions, such as whether Huxley contributed to Scientific Racism can serve as strong examples of the complexity in evaluating Huxley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the expert scholars opinions, Nicholas Rupke’s evaluation of Huxley was notable as both an outlier in many respects as well as receiving apparently greater emphasis in the memorandum footnotes. Including opinions from all of other expert scholars could help to insulate the Board from criticism of cherry picking the expert opinions, a charge that could jeopardize the perception of the Board’s fairness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would recommend not referring to Rupke’s version of Huxley’s Rule. There is no mention of Huxley’s Rule in the History of Science literature, except in Rupke’s own publications. The Huxley’s Rule known in biology refers to a rule about genetic recombination devised by Julian Huxley, TH Huxley’s grandson. Also, other expert scholars disagree with the Rupke’s premise - that Huxley’s comparative anatomical work on humans and apes led to Scientific Racism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks again for considering these remarks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Matzke</name></author><summary type="html">At 3 pm on Thursday, December 9, 2021, the Western Washington University Board of Directors is having a final hearing on the proposed de-naming of the Huxley College of the Environment. In a late twist, the Board has apparently abandoned its earlier Legacy Review Task Force Report on Huxley, presumably after all of the historical mistake and distortions were pointed out. Instead, it commissioned a last-minute “Ad Hoc Committee Report”, which retreats on most of the anti-Huxley claims, and semi-acknowledges Huxley’s numerous progressive achievements, but in the end still recommends de-naming Huxley because, it judges, student perceptions trump context and truth. This all matters, because the WWU fight is pretty clearly an initial skirmish in a debate that will continue with the proposed denaming of the Huxley Building at Imperial College London, and other Huxley awards, lectures, and Darwiniana. Win or lose at WWU, it is important to develop and publicize the evidence and arguments against this kind of thing. What is at stake? Huxley, Darwin, and a great number of other progressive reformers who helped enlighten our society, and, frankly, who helped to develop our modern anti-racist views, will be wiped from the public sphere. A number of us are giving comments today. Mine are posted below. The speakers are: Gragg Miller Stephen Warren, Professor of Astrophysics at Imperial College London -- link to comments Meg Town, WWU alum and public school science teacher who has encountered similar disinformation efforts by creationists. Teacher in Washington state in a 1995 fight with creationists in 1995. -- link to comments Nick Matzke, Senior Lecturer in Biological Sciences, University of Auckland, New Zealand -- link to comments Mike Town, WWU/Huxley alum, high school science teacher, NSF Einstein Fellow, and member of the Teacher Advisory Council for the National Academies of Science. Steve Hollenhorst, Professor and Former Dean, Huxley College of the Environment, Western Washington University -- link to comments David Leaf, Professor Emeritus, Biology, Western Washington.University. Coauthor of the Response to the Legacy Review Task Force Report -- link to comments The live link to listen at 3pm PST will be: https://wp.wwu.edu/live/ My comments below: These comments represent my personal views, not those of current or previous employers. The documentation for my claims can be found in the links in my essay on this matter: Updated: Creationists and advocates of social justice unite to take down T.H. Huxley, a leader in educational inclusion http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html &amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; Text (5 minutes to read): Thank you for giving me an opportunity to speak. My name is Nick Matzke, I am a Senior Lecturer in Biology at the University of Auckland, but until recently my whole career was in the USA. I am interested in society’s treatment of Thomas Henry Huxley because I have worked in the fields of science education and evolutionary science for almost 20 years. Part of that work involved the 2005 Kitzmiller v. Dover trial, where I discovered the creationist ancestry of the so-called “intelligent design” movement, promoted by the Discovery Institute of Seattle. Huxley is an inspiration for me as the original public advocate for science, science education, and science-informed liberalism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Acronicta americana</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/acronicta_americana.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Acronicta americana" /><published>2021-12-06T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-12-06T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/acronicta_americana</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/acronicta_americana.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Rachel Shannon&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Rachel_Dagger_Moth_Larva_PXL_20210814_161718313_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dagger moth larva&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acronicta_americana&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Acronicta americana&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; American dagger moth larva, Boulder, Colorado, August, 2021.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Rachel Shannon. Acronicta americana &amp;ndash; American dagger moth larva, Boulder, Colorado, August, 2021.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Genetic Lottery: book review</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/genetic-lottery.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Genetic Lottery: book review" /><published>2021-12-03T08:55:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-12-03T08:55:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/genetic-lottery</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/genetic-lottery.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Harden_Genetics_Cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is perhaps a caricature to claim that conservatives think all inequality is genetic, so there is nothing we can do about it. It is probably less of a caricature to claim that liberals think no inequality is genetic, so all we have to worry about is environmental. At least one purpose of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Genetic-Lottery-Matters-Social-Equality/dp/0691190801&quot;&gt;The Genetic Lottery&lt;/a&gt; by Kathryn Paige Harden, Professor of Psychology at the University of Texas at Austin, is apparently to convince liberals that people’s differing genetic inheritances may contribute to inequality (see also a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2021/09/13/can-progressives-be-convinced-that-genetics-matters/&quot;&gt;profile of the author&lt;/a&gt; by Gideon Lewis-Krauss in &lt;i&gt;The New Yorker&lt;/i&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not know why liberals and minority groups (they are overlapping sets) are afraid of research linking, for example, genes and intelligence, but I can guess along with Dr. Harden that it is related to their justifiable fear of eugenics. Comparing Dr. Harden’s work to eugenics is a bit like conflating nuclear power with nuclear bombs; it is right to be afraid of one, but not necessarily the other, and certainly not to be afraid of one because of the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Harden’s book is in two parts: “Taking Genetics Seriously” and “Taking Equality Seriously.” The first is a mostly scientific discussion of the relation between genes and various traits such as intelligence, which she claims partly determine your income and status. I found it a useful primer. The second part is more political and cries for mostly unspecified actions designed to increase the status of those who may be tacitly discriminated against because of a poor genetic inheritance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After dispensing with the candidate-gene hypothesis (a single gene for a complex trait), Dr. Harden moves on to the &lt;i&gt;genome-wide association study&lt;/i&gt;, or GWAS (pronounced gee-wass). The GWAS at first may sound like data dredging, but I think it is not. Rather, the GWAS samples the genomes of countless individuals and deduces which genes, and there are many, correlate with the trait in question. (They are actually single-nucleotide polymorphisms, or SNP’s, but never mind.) Researchers can then calculate a &lt;i&gt;polygenic index&lt;/i&gt; for that trait in a given individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A person with a high polygenic index for height is apt to be tall, though not necessarily tall. Likewise, a person with low polygenic index for height is apt to be short, though not necessarily short. Dr. Harden claims that liberals have no trouble accepting these two statements, but will balk if we replace &lt;i&gt;height&lt;/i&gt; with, for example, &lt;i&gt;intelligence&lt;/i&gt;. She discusses intelligence (IQ) tests and acknowledges that early on they were instruments of eugenics but observes that IQ correlates, for example, with success in school, job performance, and even life span. She insists that we can reject eugenics without rejecting intelligence tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, she is at pains to point out that the vast majority of GWAS research has been carried out on people of White [her capitalization], European descent and cannot be used to demonstrate that one ethnic group may be higher in one trait than another, because different circumstances may cause different genes to correlate with a given trait, such as education. She is pretty convincing claiming that race, at least in the United States, is socially constructed, but frankly, as a Jewish male with a Jewish wife, I might under some conditions want to be screened for Tay-Sachs disease or cystic fibrosis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found the second part of the book interesting, but perhaps a little frustrating. Dr. Harden establishes that a high polygenic index for, say, education correlates with an advanced degree but that a low polygenic index does not preclude an advanced degree. Those who inherit a high polygenic index nevertheless are lucky and have won the “lottery” in the title of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Harden argues, correctly in my judgment, that tracking in U.S. high schools may be part of what she calls a &lt;i&gt;causal chain&lt;/i&gt; that mediates between genes and educational success. Students who get into the wrong track, perhaps in part because of their genes, may find certain options closed to them. The solution to this problem is difficult and cannot be found in genetics. Consequently, at one point she flirts with a kind of utilitarian solution whereby students are chosen by lottery; a lottery, even if carried out among students who are prescreened, runs the danger of punishing the most qualified. It is, nevertheless, not inconsistent with her claim that what genes you get are entirely a matter of luck, and I suppose that sometimes your luck might be bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will not go into detail, but the author takes on Richard Herrnstein and Charles Murray, the authors of &lt;i&gt;The Bell Curve&lt;/i&gt;, which she considers inegalitarian because they consider some traits to be better than others and people who hold those traits to be superior. On the flip side, she takes issue with Robert Plomin of King’s College London, who thinks that your genetic makeup is more decisive than she does. She also cites a number of philosophers, in particular John Rawls, and argues, with him, that the truly egalitarian society would look out for the least advantaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, like the biologist and blogger &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2021/11/19/my-review-of-a-genetics-and-social-policy-book-in-the-washington-post/&quot;&gt;Jerry Coyne&lt;/a&gt;, I was mildly bemused by her ducking the question of whether the universe is deterministic. Like Dr. Coyne, I think it is. That does not stop us from applying statistical methods to the study of gases or even the roll of the dice, both of which are deterministic. In the same way, I see no reason it should stop us from applying statistical methods to genetics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I want to note that the book is well written and clear. The author draws effective analogies to illuminate her discussions, as when she compares calculating a polygenic index with rating restaurants in different cities. If all you look at is one spice (analogous to a single candidate gene), you will get a biased or wrong answer; you have to look at a variety of factors and quantify them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read the book on a Kindle, which was satisfactory except for some of the figures, for which I had to turn to my computer. When I put my editor’s hat on, I found little else to complain about. All in all, with my physicist’s hat and my editor’s hat stacked firmly one on top of the other, I can recommend the book wholeheartedly, though frankly the first part more so than the second.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">It is perhaps a caricature to claim that conservatives think all inequality is genetic, so there is nothing we can do about it. It is probably less of a caricature to claim that liberals think no inequality is genetic, so all we have to worry about is environmental. At least one purpose of The Genetic Lottery by Kathryn Paige Harden, Professor of Psychology at the University of Texas at Austin, is apparently to convince liberals that people’s differing genetic inheritances may contribute to inequality (see also a profile of the author by Gideon Lewis-Krauss in The New Yorker). I do not know why liberals and minority groups (they are overlapping sets) are afraid of research linking, for example, genes and intelligence, but I can guess along with Dr. Harden that it is related to their justifiable fear of eugenics. Comparing Dr. Harden’s work to eugenics is a bit like conflating nuclear power with nuclear bombs; it is right to be afraid of one, but not necessarily the other, and certainly not to be afraid of one because of the other. Dr. Harden’s book is in two parts: “Taking Genetics Seriously” and “Taking Equality Seriously.” The first is a mostly scientific discussion of the relation between genes and various traits such as intelligence, which she claims partly determine your income and status. I found it a useful primer. The second part is more political and cries for mostly unspecified actions designed to increase the status of those who may be tacitly discriminated against because of a poor genetic inheritance.</summary></entry></feed>