<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-09-01T12:26:30-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Dan Phelps lecture on Kentucky Fossils</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/dan-phelps-lecture.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dan Phelps lecture on Kentucky Fossils" /><published>2024-09-01T12:25:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-01T12:25:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/dan-phelps-lecture</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/dan-phelps-lecture.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Phelps_Edrioasteroid.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dan Phelps showing a slide&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Slightly underexposed Dan Phelps showing a slide of his &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edrioasteroidea&quot;&gt;favorite fossil&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fans of Dan Phelps may be interested in his lecture on Kentucky Fossils as part of the Frankfort (Kentucky) Heritage Lecture Series. You may see the lecture, which was delivered on August 27 and is about 90 min long, &amp;lt;a href=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=x2sfqhPodQQ&amp;gt;here&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Lecture Series notes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This presentation [was] an overview of the various types of fossils found in Kentucky, discussing specimens from the Late Ordovician (450 million years ago) to the Pleistocene (ending about 12,000 years ago). There will be numerous fossil specimens on display before and after the talk. The public is encouraged to bring in local fossils for identification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniel J. Phelps is a native of Lexington and a retired environmental geologist with degrees from the University of Kentucky. Besides his environmental work, he has been employed as a petroleum and coal geologist. Additionally, Dan has taught part-time in Kentucky’s Community College system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Slightly underexposed Dan Phelps showing a slide of his favorite fossil. Fans of Dan Phelps may be interested in his lecture on Kentucky Fossils as part of the Frankfort (Kentucky) Heritage Lecture Series. You may see the lecture, which was delivered on August 27 and is about 90 min long, &amp;lt;a href=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=x2sfqhPodQQ&amp;gt;here&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;. According to the Lecture Series notes, This presentation [was] an overview of the various types of fossils found in Kentucky, discussing specimens from the Late Ordovician (450 million years ago) to the Pleistocene (ending about 12,000 years ago). There will be numerous fossil specimens on display before and after the talk. The public is encouraged to bring in local fossils for identification. Daniel J. Phelps is a native of Lexington and a retired environmental geologist with degrees from the University of Kentucky. Besides his environmental work, he has been employed as a petroleum and coal geologist. Additionally, Dan has taught part-time in Kentucky’s Community College system. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creationist astronomer calculates age of the Flood from Utah arch collapse</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/creationist-astronomer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creationist astronomer calculates age of the Flood from Utah arch collapse" /><published>2024-08-24T08:50:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-08-24T08:50:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/creationist-astronomer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/creationist-astronomer.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Van_Den_Bos_Arch_Detail_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Delicate Arch&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;An arch that has not collapsed: Delicate Arch in Utah. &lt;small&gt;Detail of photograph by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/person-in-black-jacket-and-blue-denim-jeans-sitting-on-brown-rock-formation-during-daytime-uDKqTcWDc6U&quot;&gt;Mike van den Bos&lt;/a&gt; on Unsplash.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/geology/how-long-have-arches-been-around/&quot;&gt;How Long Have Arches Been Around?&lt;/a&gt;, by &lt;i&gt;Dr&lt;/i&gt;. Danny Faulkner, describes creationist “research” into geomorphology. It is laughably bad, even for creationists. Natural arches and bridges are aesthetically interesting, but are only a tiny part of some geomorphology studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this piece, Dr. Faulkner* extrapolates backward to “show” that arches in Arches National Park, Utah, have formed since Noah’s Flood, about 4,500 years ago. He claims this timeframe because of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Biblical literalism. Employees of Answers in Genesis must sign a &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/about/faith/&quot;&gt;Statement of Faith&lt;/a&gt; that posits that the earth and universe are 6,000 years old, and that most geology is a result of Noah’s Flood, approximately 4,500 years ago. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;An exponential rate of arch collapse.  Faulkner states he doesn’t use a linear decline in numbers of arches because no arches would remain after 4,500 years. No consideration is given to the possibility of much longer time scales, or changes in climate and erosion rates. Change in regional climates over time is ignored, possibly because the young earth creationists at AIG cram the nearly 2 million years of Pleistocene glacial maxima into a single ice age of only 200 years after the Flood. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conveniently, AiG uses this denial of the Pleistocene to also ignore evidence for past climate changes and the evidence scientists use to support anthropogenic climate change in the present. Faulkner has invented his model by assuming that an exponential model is the best for arch collapse, and then he fits things assuming the rate is 43 arches in 29 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, his scholarship is abysmally shoddy. Conceivably, it would be possible to make a plot of cumulative arches lost vs. time. This would be a more accurate method for modeling. However, Faulkner just assumes the loss rate was constant (a cumulative arches-vs.-time chart would show the accuracy of that assumption).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also seems to assume that the collapse of arches in Utah is related solely to the minerals cementing the sandstone that the arches are formed from. He doesn’t document any effort to examine records to see if any collapses were associated with long term climate changes, intense storms, seismic events, vandalism, and innumerable other possible causes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faulkner also assumes a uniform rate of arch formation. He then uses his model and that assumption to show that, in his view, there would have been an implausible number of arches if the Earth were as old as earth scientists claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All his equations are a smoke screen, an appeal to look like scientific research when religious apologetics is what is actually being presented. In short, this is a parody of how science is actually done. The 4,500 year time frame and the Flood are required by AIG’s  peculiar version of a “Biblical Worldview,” which is more than a bit of a science stopper and a weird excuse to start with creationist conclusions and work backwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Faulkner oddly discusses Kentucky arches in Red River Gorge in addition to Arches National Park, but cannot do a similar calculation for the Kentucky arches, as arch collapse here in Kentucky has not been documented. The reported observations in Kentucky are another smoke screen in the article, basically a non sequitur. The discovery/documentation rate of arches in Kentucky has no bearing on their rate of formation or collapse (and the same holds for Utah).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Faulkner’s apparent assumption of the evolution of arches from formation to collapse is naive. Surely, the height, span, and dimensions of the suspended material are factors to consider. Not all arches are formed in the same fashion: some are formed by wind or water erosion; some by collapse. Not all arches are in the same topographic position: some are isolated and exposed on points; some are parallel to cliff faces. The relationship to and importance of natural fracturing differs among arches. If Dr. Faulkner considered these factors, he didn’t document his efforts. Our assumption is that he was unaware of these complications or deliberately chose to ignore them (and didn’t document why he did so).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nonscientific method used by Answers in Genesis “researchers” results in the publication of materials that don’t reflect reality very well; yet AiG’s conclusions are held by millions of our fellow citizens. Faulkner’s piece is a &lt;i&gt;dazzle-them-with-sciency-sounding-stuff faux research that confirms AIG and their audience’s preexisting biases&lt;/i&gt;. The public deserves better. It should be part of our job as earth scientists to do a better job of explaining science to the public&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Faulkner’s Ph.D. is in astronomy; he works as a researcher for Answers in Genesis. He has some family ties to the region and occasionally has led paid AIG creationist hiking tours of Red River Gorge and its arches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix&lt;/strong&gt;. If you are interested in Kentucky geology, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uky.edu/KGS/geoky/fieldtrip/2005%20NaturalBridge%20red%20river%20gorge%20guide.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uky.edu/KGS/geoky/fieldtrip/2010%20Guidebook%20natural%20bridge%20guidebook.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; are field guides to the Red River Gorge area written by geologists (and you can use these guidebooks to visit the public sites for free!). The Kentucky Geological Survey has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://kgs.uky.edu/arches/&quot;&gt;project and map service&lt;/a&gt; dedicated to Kentucky arches for the hiking public. (Arches on private land are generally excluded from this database.)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps and Brandon Nuttall</name></author><summary type="html">An arch that has not collapsed: Delicate Arch in Utah. Detail of photograph by Mike van den Bos on Unsplash. This article, How Long Have Arches Been Around?, by Dr. Danny Faulkner, describes creationist “research” into geomorphology. It is laughably bad, even for creationists. Natural arches and bridges are aesthetically interesting, but are only a tiny part of some geomorphology studies. In this piece, Dr. Faulkner* extrapolates backward to “show” that arches in Arches National Park, Utah, have formed since Noah’s Flood, about 4,500 years ago. He claims this timeframe because of Biblical literalism. Employees of Answers in Genesis must sign a Statement of Faith that posits that the earth and universe are 6,000 years old, and that most geology is a result of Noah’s Flood, approximately 4,500 years ago. An exponential rate of arch collapse. Faulkner states he doesn’t use a linear decline in numbers of arches because no arches would remain after 4,500 years. No consideration is given to the possibility of much longer time scales, or changes in climate and erosion rates. Change in regional climates over time is ignored, possibly because the young earth creationists at AIG cram the nearly 2 million years of Pleistocene glacial maxima into a single ice age of only 200 years after the Flood.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Buteo lineatus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/buteo-lineatus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buteo lineatus" /><published>2024-08-19T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-08-19T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/buteo-lineatus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/buteo-lineatus.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Ole Lundin&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Lundin_Buteo_lineatus.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Red-shouldered hawk&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.audubon.org/field-guide/bird/red-shouldered-hawk&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Buteo lineatus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; red-shouldered hawk, observed in back yard, Durham, NC, December, 2014. Mr. Lundin writes, &quot;I like this one for the angle of view (slightly downward), and the background coloration that matches the hawk's coloration. This hawk was undoubtedly preying on the colony of rabbits inhabiting the brush in my back yard.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Ole Lundin. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Buteo lineatus &amp;ndash; red-shouldered hawk, observed in back yard, Durham, NC, December, 2014. Mr. Lundin writes, &quot;I like this one for the angle of view (slightly downward), and the background coloration that matches the hawk's coloration. This hawk was undoubtedly preying on the colony of rabbits inhabiting the brush in my back yard.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tax-exempt AIG attacks Presidential candidate, may be reported to IRS</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/heres-what-people-need.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tax-exempt AIG attacks Presidential candidate, may be reported to IRS" /><published>2024-08-14T18:07:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-08-14T18:07:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/heres-what-people-need</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/heres-what-people-need.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Ham_Video_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ken Ham on his video&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Ken Ham on YouTube assuring us that a fertilized egg is a human being.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The original title of this article, borrowed (as you may infer) from Ken Ham, was &quot;Here's What People NEED To Know about Ken Ham.&quot; That title now seems too cute and did not seem to give the article much traction, so we have taken the unusual step of changing it to the present, more descriptive title. The URL remains the same. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ken Ham, on a YouTube video entitled “&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/1aGZoJCdCpo?si=8iLpBwawPiOYOYbE&quot;&gt;Here’s What People NEED to Realize about Kamala Harris&lt;/a&gt;” and specifically credited to Answers in Genesis, explicitly attacks Vice President and presidential candidate Kamala Harris for her views on abortion and other matters. The video received around 150,000 views in a day or so. AIG writes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;In this short video, Ken Ham speaks on the recent political ideologies of Kamala, sharing his perspective on them as a Bible-believing Christian.&quot; [Note how he infantilizes her by using her first name only.]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our colleague Dan Phelps, who sent us this link, asks, “How is AIG, a ministry, still tax exempt?” He notes that AIG’s shell company, Ark Encounter, gets $1.825 million per year in sales tax rebates from Kentucky Tourism and is advertised for free by the taxpayer-supported “Kentucky Faith Trail.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Phelps suggests that you can complain to the IRS using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/f13909.pdf&quot;&gt;Form 13909, Tax-Exempt Organization Complaint (Referral)&lt;/a&gt;. It is not clear whether the IRS will take any action, but a few complaints cannot hurt. AIG’s street address is Answers in Genesis, 2800 Bullittsburg Church Rd., Petersburg, KY 41080, and their EIN, or Employer Identification Number, is 33-0596423.  You need to send a cover letter along with the form, but both may be e-mailed to the address at the bottom of page 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IRS form asks you for “Who/What/Where/When/How you learned about and obtained the information in this report.” I do not know precisely what approach to take, beyond that Mr. Ham runs a tax-exempt religious organization, which he considers a ministry, and in this video he is implicitly campaigning against Kamala Harris. Perhaps this line of reasoning can be fleshed out in the comments to this post. The URL of the video is https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1aGZoJCdCpo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you have the illusion that Mr. Ham is not electioneering, I can assure you that his minions think otherwise. Consider, for example, these (admittedly cherry-picked) comments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;We have had four years of warning. It’s time to vote her OUT!&quot; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Thanks Ken for being bold enough to say the truth about this election. Glory be to God in the Highest!&quot; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;I can barely stand to listen to her. God help us all if she gets to be president.&quot; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &quot;It’s time the we Christians vote politicians like this out of office and keep them out of our political arena..&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;I pray EVERY Christian goes out and votes this November. Pray and Vote. We cannot tolerate this evil any longer. Thank you AIG for making things so clear.&quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A majority of the comments merely pray for our lost souls and whatnot, but comments such as these clearly show that many, if not most, listeners recognize Mr. Ham’s true intention.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Ken Ham on YouTube assuring us that a fertilized egg is a human being. The original title of this article, borrowed (as you may infer) from Ken Ham, was &quot;Here's What People NEED To Know about Ken Ham.&quot; That title now seems too cute and did not seem to give the article much traction, so we have taken the unusual step of changing it to the present, more descriptive title. The URL remains the same. Ken Ham, on a YouTube video entitled “Here’s What People NEED to Realize about Kamala Harris” and specifically credited to Answers in Genesis, explicitly attacks Vice President and presidential candidate Kamala Harris for her views on abortion and other matters. The video received around 150,000 views in a day or so. AIG writes, &quot;In this short video, Ken Ham speaks on the recent political ideologies of Kamala, sharing his perspective on them as a Bible-believing Christian.&quot; [Note how he infantilizes her by using her first name only.] Our colleague Dan Phelps, who sent us this link, asks, “How is AIG, a ministry, still tax exempt?” He notes that AIG’s shell company, Ark Encounter, gets $1.825 million per year in sales tax rebates from Kentucky Tourism and is advertised for free by the taxpayer-supported “Kentucky Faith Trail.” Mr. Phelps suggests that you can complain to the IRS using Form 13909, Tax-Exempt Organization Complaint (Referral). It is not clear whether the IRS will take any action, but a few complaints cannot hurt. AIG’s street address is Answers in Genesis, 2800 Bullittsburg Church Rd., Petersburg, KY 41080, and their EIN, or Employer Identification Number, is 33-0596423. You need to send a cover letter along with the form, but both may be e-mailed to the address at the bottom of page 1. The IRS form asks you for “Who/What/Where/When/How you learned about and obtained the information in this report.” I do not know precisely what approach to take, beyond that Mr. Ham runs a tax-exempt religious organization, which he considers a ministry, and in this video he is implicitly campaigning against Kamala Harris. Perhaps this line of reasoning can be fleshed out in the comments to this post. The URL of the video is https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1aGZoJCdCpo. In case you have the illusion that Mr. Ham is not electioneering, I can assure you that his minions think otherwise. Consider, for example, these (admittedly cherry-picked) comments:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fluorescing minerals</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/fluorescing-minerals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fluorescing minerals" /><published>2024-08-05T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-08-05T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/fluorescing-minerals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/fluorescing-minerals.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Alan Rice&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Fourth Place&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Rice-Alan_Ultraviolet minerals.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cave illuminated by fluorescent light&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Minerals seen in fluorescent light.  Mr. Rice writes, &quot;This photo was taken during field work in a cave in Nevada, USA. One of the best things about being an amateur scientist is getting invited to participate in field work with professional scientists. My brother and I participated in a week of speleological surveys in and around Great Basin National Park, Nevada. In this photo, geologists are examining fluorescent &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calcite&quot;&gt;calcite&lt;/a&gt; and other minerals using an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ultraviolet&quot;&gt;ultraviolet&lt;/a&gt; &quot;black-light.&quot;  This particular light is optimized for mineral identification by selectively emitting two different wavelengths of light (UV-A, 365&amp;nbsp;nm, and UV-C, 245&amp;nbsp;nm), while filtering out all of the visible light. Everything  in this photo is either fluorescing or illuminated from the emitted light of the fluorescent minerals. Recent studies suggest that this cave passage has remained little changed for the past 12 million years.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Alan Rice. Photography Contest, Fourth Place. Minerals seen in fluorescent light. Mr. Rice writes, &quot;This photo was taken during field work in a cave in Nevada, USA. One of the best things about being an amateur scientist is getting invited to participate in field work with professional scientists. My brother and I participated in a week of speleological surveys in and around Great Basin National Park, Nevada. In this photo, geologists are examining fluorescent calcite and other minerals using an ultraviolet &quot;black-light.&quot; This particular light is optimized for mineral identification by selectively emitting two different wavelengths of light (UV-A, 365&amp;nbsp;nm, and UV-C, 245&amp;nbsp;nm), while filtering out all of the visible light. Everything in this photo is either fluorescing or illuminated from the emitted light of the fluorescent minerals. Recent studies suggest that this cave passage has remained little changed for the past 12 million years.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Aphantasia and me</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/aphantasia-and-me.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aphantasia and me" /><published>2024-08-03T08:50:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-08-03T08:50:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/aphantasia-and-me</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/aphantasia-and-me.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Dingfelder_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who knew? I have &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aphantasia&quot;&gt;aphantasia&lt;/a&gt;, the inability to visualize things. Well, probably not fully fledged aphantasia, but certainly &lt;i&gt;dys&lt;/i&gt;phantasia. Aphantasia is a word I first learned on listening to an NPR program with a somewhat lengthy title, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2024/06/26/1198910315/face-blindness-prosopagnosia-memory-aphantasia-sight-imagination&quot;&gt;The human brain is hardwired to recognize faces. But what if you can’t?&lt;/a&gt; It turns out that Sadie  Dingfelder, the author of the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/0316545147/&quot;&gt;Do I Know You? A Faceblind Reporter’s Journey into the Science of Sight, Memory, and Imagination&lt;/a&gt;, can’t. Recognize faces, that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms. Dingfelder is not only face blind; she is also &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stereoblindness&quot;&gt;stereo blind&lt;/a&gt; and aphantasic. Now, I understand that freshman psychology students think they suffer from every affliction they study, but I was surprised to find that I have some degree of all of those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was stereo blind until a dozen or two years ago. Indeed, I remember commenting to the eminent lens designer Rudolf Kingslake that I saw no difference between one eye and two. He was astonished and told me everything popped into life with two eyes open. I in turn was baffled. (I must have had some stereopsis, because I found that, when I looked at a painting or photograph with one eye, I saw more depth than with two eyes, presumably because the clue that the painting was flat was missing without the stereopsis afforded by two eyes. This technique, which was taught to me by a photogrammetrist at the University of Guelph, is very useful when walking around art galleries.) Many years later, while engaging in eye exercises for something else, I suddenly developed what I think may be fairly good stereo vision, and it has never gone away, even after I quit the exercises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that I first learned of face blindness, or &lt;i&gt;prosopagnosia&lt;/i&gt;, from Oliver Sacks’s book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/man-who-mistook-his-wife-hat&quot;&gt;The Man Who Mistook His Wife for a Hat&lt;/a&gt;. According to the NPR report, Ms. Dingfelder is almost completely face blind, more so than almost anyone else. After reading Sacks’s book, I realized that I too have a degree of face blindness – I suppose I could say prosop&lt;i&gt;dys&lt;/i&gt;gnosia, but that would be a dreadful word. At any rate, although I have never accused anyone else’s spouse of buying junk food, as did Ms. Dingfelder, I have a lot of trouble recognizing people I have just met or know only slightly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for aphantasia, I can visualize things but not well. Possibly that is one reason I do not like fiction that is heavy with description. The apple I am visualizing right now is merely a hollow, transparent shell. I can see the stem, the black sepals at the blossom end, and the core, but the skin has no color, and the flesh has no texture, if it exists at all. I think probably this inability to visualize is why I cannot draw objects with curves very well, and faces are out of the question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kirkusreviews.com/book-reviews/sadie-dingfelder/do-i-know-you/&quot;&gt;Kirkus Reviews&lt;/a&gt;, Ms. Dingfelder has amblyopia, or lazy eye, which I presume is the origin of her stereo blindness (unless, of course, it is the other way around). Kirkus says that as a result of her stereo blindness she cannot get around easily, walk on uneven surfaces, or drive a car. Either Ms. Dingfelder or Kirkus partly misunderstands depth perception. We have depth perception even with one eye; it is just not as good as stereo vision. In Colorado, for example, you may drive as long as your vision in one eye is 20/40 or better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sounds as if the book is part memoir and part science, rather like this essay. I have not yet read it, but I intend to do so as soon as I can manage it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 1.&lt;/strong&gt; An appendix is a vestigial part of a document and has no known function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix 2.&lt;/strong&gt; While writing this essay, I was reminded of an anecdote told to our class by my philosophy professor, Murray Turbayne. Professor Turbayne relates asking his mother-in-law to visualize an apple. I forget the exact order, but, roughly, he asks her to imagine that it has no color. OK, no color. No smell or taste. OK. No weight. OK. No texture. A little harder, but OK. What is left? The apple! We then had a discussion, which I only dimly remember, about whether the apple was more than the sum of its attributes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Who knew? I have aphantasia, the inability to visualize things. Well, probably not fully fledged aphantasia, but certainly dysphantasia. Aphantasia is a word I first learned on listening to an NPR program with a somewhat lengthy title, The human brain is hardwired to recognize faces. But what if you can’t? It turns out that Sadie Dingfelder, the author of the book Do I Know You? A Faceblind Reporter’s Journey into the Science of Sight, Memory, and Imagination, can’t. Recognize faces, that is. Ms. Dingfelder is not only face blind; she is also stereo blind and aphantasic. Now, I understand that freshman psychology students think they suffer from every affliction they study, but I was surprised to find that I have some degree of all of those.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy 280th birthday to Jean-Baptiste Lamarck</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/happy-280th-birthday-lamarck.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy 280th birthday to Jean-Baptiste Lamarck" /><published>2024-08-02T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-08-02T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/happy-280th-birthday-lamarck</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/happy-280th-birthday-lamarck.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/2022-04-12-Metro_Lamarck_-_Caulaincourt-8402.jpg&quot; width=&quot;640px&quot; alt=&quot;[Lamarck-Coulaincourt metro station]&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Entrance to the Lamarck-Coulaincourt metro station, Paris.© Superbass / CC-BY-SA-4.0 (via Wikimedia Commons)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, the 1st of August, was the 280th anniversary of the birth of Jean-Baptiste Pierre Antoine 
de Monet, who was the Chevalier de Lamarck.  As I have noted each year here, he was, 
as far as I am concerned, the first evolutionary biologist.  He had a (wrong) mechanism 
that would explain adaptation, and was the major pioneer in drawing evolutionary 
trees.  He was also a pioneer of invertebrate biology.  (Although he made use of 
inheritance of acquired characters in his mechanisms, he did not invent that idea, 
as most folks already believed that).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I want to note the way Lamarck is commemorated in the name of a street 
in Paris, the Rue de Lamarck.  His name is also on streets in some other French cities. 
The explanation that I have heard of why that particular street was named after him 
is that it was being built about the time that Darwin was becoming famous, and the 
French found a then-almost-forgotten French biologist to commemorate, to compete with 
Darwin.  So they named a street for him in an area where new streets were being built and named.  I don’t know whether this is really an accurate explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rue de Lamarck is famous in Paris today as it gives its name to a major Metro 
stop, Lamarck-Coulaincourt.  Above you will see the very dramatic entrance to 
that Metro station, photographed from the Rue de Lamarck.  The entrance is between 
two stairways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy 280th, Jean-Baptiste!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;to-read-or-post-comments-first-click-on-the-title-of-this-post&quot;&gt;To read or post comments, first click on the title of this post.&lt;/h5&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Entrance to the Lamarck-Coulaincourt metro station, Paris.© Superbass / CC-BY-SA-4.0 (via Wikimedia Commons) &amp;nbsp; Yesterday, the 1st of August, was the 280th anniversary of the birth of Jean-Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet, who was the Chevalier de Lamarck. As I have noted each year here, he was, as far as I am concerned, the first evolutionary biologist. He had a (wrong) mechanism that would explain adaptation, and was the major pioneer in drawing evolutionary trees. He was also a pioneer of invertebrate biology. (Although he made use of inheritance of acquired characters in his mechanisms, he did not invent that idea, as most folks already believed that). This time I want to note the way Lamarck is commemorated in the name of a street in Paris, the Rue de Lamarck. His name is also on streets in some other French cities. The explanation that I have heard of why that particular street was named after him is that it was being built about the time that Darwin was becoming famous, and the French found a then-almost-forgotten French biologist to commemorate, to compete with Darwin. So they named a street for him in an area where new streets were being built and named. I don’t know whether this is really an accurate explanation. The Rue de Lamarck is famous in Paris today as it gives its name to a major Metro stop, Lamarck-Coulaincourt. Above you will see the very dramatic entrance to that Metro station, photographed from the Rue de Lamarck. The entrance is between two stairways. Happy 280th, Jean-Baptiste! To read or post comments, first click on the title of this post.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Institutional (and departmental) neutrality</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/institutional-and-departmental.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Institutional (and departmental) neutrality" /><published>2024-07-27T12:58:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-07-27T12:58:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/institutional-and-departmental</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/institutional-and-departmental.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Science_Cover_7_27_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Science magazine cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Cover of this week's issue of &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; magazine. &lt;small&gt;The photo is by David Dee Delgado/Getty Images.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;H. Holden Thorpe, the editor of &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; magazine, ran an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.adr8867&quot;&gt;editorial&lt;/a&gt; this week on institutional neutrality, the idea, as he put it, “that universities in the United States—and especially their presidents—should be politically neutral….” I would add to that the idea that departments and especially their heads should be politically neutral. The editorial is short  and open access, so I think you can read it for yourselves, but he invokes the &lt;a href=&quot;https://provost.uchicago.edu/sites/default/files/documents/reports/KalvenRprt_0.pdf&quot;&gt; Kalven Report&lt;/a&gt;, a mercifully equally short document from the University of Chicago, which declared a “heavy presumption” against universities expressing opinions on political issues or modifying their investments in order to “foster social or political values, however compelling and appealing they may be.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hardly any universities have adopted the Kalven Report as policy, though I gather that a few have adopted the less-stringent &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chicago_principles&quot;&gt;Chicago principles&lt;/a&gt;. Since the war in Gaza, there has been pressure to adopt the Kalven principles, according to Thorpe. For a crash course in the latest activity regarding Kalven or the Chicago principles, see Jerry Coyne’s blog, Why Evolution Is True, &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/category/kalven-report/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thorpe is less of an absolutist regarding Kalven than is Coyne, though he agrees that universities need to be neutral regarding matters of opinion. He draws a distinction, however, between matters of opinion and matters of fact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; But what about matters of science, especially when a finding has powerful political implications such as studies on climate or vaccines? Where should universities draw the line?&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or evolution. Several people told Thorpe that universities must keep strictly away from commenting on any research whatsoever, except to support the right of the researcher to publish that research. Another, Eric Topol, told him that such a stance is “spineless” and appears to dissociate the university from its faculty and their published science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thorpe himself seems somewhat conflicted, and I can understand why, but he expresses concern that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; Stanford University just shut down its disinformation research program after it was hit by lawsuits from conservative groups.… [T]here is a danger that universities will shirk their responsibility to stand up not for any particular finding but for a more overriding principle—the importance of independent scholarship. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Cover of this week's issue of Science magazine. The photo is by David Dee Delgado/Getty Images. H. Holden Thorpe, the editor of Science magazine, ran an editorial this week on institutional neutrality, the idea, as he put it, “that universities in the United States—and especially their presidents—should be politically neutral….” I would add to that the idea that departments and especially their heads should be politically neutral. The editorial is short and open access, so I think you can read it for yourselves, but he invokes the Kalven Report, a mercifully equally short document from the University of Chicago, which declared a “heavy presumption” against universities expressing opinions on political issues or modifying their investments in order to “foster social or political values, however compelling and appealing they may be.” Hardly any universities have adopted the Kalven Report as policy, though I gather that a few have adopted the less-stringent Chicago principles. Since the war in Gaza, there has been pressure to adopt the Kalven principles, according to Thorpe. For a crash course in the latest activity regarding Kalven or the Chicago principles, see Jerry Coyne’s blog, Why Evolution Is True, here. Thorpe is less of an absolutist regarding Kalven than is Coyne, though he agrees that universities need to be neutral regarding matters of opinion. He draws a distinction, however, between matters of opinion and matters of fact: But what about matters of science, especially when a finding has powerful political implications such as studies on climate or vaccines? Where should universities draw the line? Or evolution. Several people told Thorpe that universities must keep strictly away from commenting on any research whatsoever, except to support the right of the researcher to publish that research. Another, Eric Topol, told him that such a stance is “spineless” and appears to dissociate the university from its faculty and their published science. Thorpe himself seems somewhat conflicted, and I can understand why, but he expresses concern that Stanford University just shut down its disinformation research program after it was hit by lawsuits from conservative groups.… [T]here is a danger that universities will shirk their responsibility to stand up not for any particular finding but for a more overriding principle—the importance of independent scholarship. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cheap fossils for only $55!</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/cheap-fossils.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cheap fossils for only $55!" /><published>2024-07-24T11:58:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-07-24T11:58:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/cheap-fossils</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/cheap-fossils.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Duff_Fossils_Under_Ark_Title_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Title slide showing fossils under Ark&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our colleague Dan Phelps, vigilant as usual, has just sent us&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;[a] nice video by Dr. &lt;a href=&quot;https://joelduff.org/&quot;&gt;Joel Duff&lt;/a&gt; about collecting fossils at outcrops adjacent to the Ark Park. I was at these outcrops several years ago and found mostly &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryozoa&quot;&gt;bryozoa&lt;/a&gt; from the Upper Ordovician Kope Formation. The creationist “scientists” at the Ark seem oblivious to the existence of these fossils that don’t jibe with creationist Flood geology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Duff also discusses the grift AiG does of selling bags of fossils in dirt for exorbitant prices (up to $55 a bag for kids to wash out in a fake mining sluice!). This method is obviously not how fossils are typically unearthed, but the kids and parents buying this product wouldn’t be likely to know better. The Ark apparently purchases their fossils from other parts of the world, while not taking advantage of their local abundant fossils.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Duff_Mining_Sluice_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mining sluice&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Sluice for sorting fossils. The prices for these cheap fossils encased in mud range from $8 to $55.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Phelps expresses the hope that Dr. Duff does not give the Ark Park any ideas. Well, he does:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Duff estimates that there may be 1 trillion (yes, not a typo) fossils buried within the Ark’s property. They are encased in layers of limestone and shale, not buried in dirt. Dr. Duff, therefore, recommends that the Ark Park employ a backhoe and dig a trench a few meters deep, so that children can walk into it and see for themselves how real fossils are discovered. He further recommends that children be allowed to sort through the tailings and perhaps take home a small bag full of fossils in return for a modest payment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing they will find is that their small bag of fossils contains a very limited variety, no diatoms, no fish, no reptiles. How come, if the fossils were deposited by a worldwide flood, do we see so little variety over a very large area? Because there was no worldwide flood, and that is why the Ark Park cannot dig the trench and cannot allow the children to pick at the tailings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joel Duff is a professor of biology at the University of Akron. He describes himself &lt;a href=&quot;https://joelduff.org/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; as a Christian who believes, as I understand it, that science is one way of learning about God’s natural world. He blogs as &lt;a href=&quot;https://thenaturalhistorian.com/author/naturalhistorian/&quot;&gt;Naturalis Historia&lt;/a&gt; and is listed as an &lt;a href=&quot;https://biologos.org/people/joel-duff&quot;&gt;author&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://biologos.org/&quot;&gt;BioLogos&lt;/a&gt;. It is regrettable that the Ark Park and other creationists will not listen to him.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Our colleague Dan Phelps, vigilant as usual, has just sent us [a] nice video by Dr. Joel Duff about collecting fossils at outcrops adjacent to the Ark Park. I was at these outcrops several years ago and found mostly bryozoa from the Upper Ordovician Kope Formation. The creationist “scientists” at the Ark seem oblivious to the existence of these fossils that don’t jibe with creationist Flood geology. Dr. Duff also discusses the grift AiG does of selling bags of fossils in dirt for exorbitant prices (up to $55 a bag for kids to wash out in a fake mining sluice!). This method is obviously not how fossils are typically unearthed, but the kids and parents buying this product wouldn’t be likely to know better. The Ark apparently purchases their fossils from other parts of the world, while not taking advantage of their local abundant fossils. Sluice for sorting fossils. The prices for these cheap fossils encased in mud range from $8 to $55. Mr. Phelps expresses the hope that Dr. Duff does not give the Ark Park any ideas. Well, he does:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Holbrookia approximans</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/holbrookia-approximans.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Holbrookia approximans" /><published>2024-07-22T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-07-22T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/holbrookia-approximans</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/07/holbrookia-approximans.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Joseph Long&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Third Place&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Long_Holbrookia_approximans.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Western earless lizard&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holbrookia_approximans&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Holbrookia approximans&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – Western (or speckled) earless lizard, Pawnee National Grassland, Weld County, Colorado, June 1, 2024. Mr. Long writes, &quot;Note that the subject has apparently escaped an attempt by something else to eat it.  Technical: Olympus OM-D EM-1 Mark III, Olympus 300 mm f/4.0 lens on 2.0x teleconverter, 1/1250 s, f/16, ISO 1000, handheld.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Joseph Long. Photography Contest, Third Place. Holbrookia approximans – Western (or speckled) earless lizard, Pawnee National Grassland, Weld County, Colorado, June 1, 2024. Mr. Long writes, &quot;Note that the subject has apparently escaped an attempt by something else to eat it. Technical: Olympus OM-D EM-1 Mark III, Olympus 300 mm f/4.0 lens on 2.0x teleconverter, 1/1250 s, f/16, ISO 1000, handheld.&quot;</summary></entry></feed>