<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-27T07:46:32-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">The Big Chill: How Yosemite Valley and Other Glacial Examples Disprove the Way-Too-Short Biblical Creationist Ice Age</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/the-big-chill.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Big Chill: How Yosemite Valley and Other Glacial Examples Disprove the Way-Too-Short Biblical Creationist Ice Age" /><published>2025-01-23T09:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-01-23T09:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/the-big-chill</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/the-big-chill.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Paul_Yosemite.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Author at Yosemite&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The author at Yosemite.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Gregory Paul is an independent polymath researcher including in paleozoology and geology. His technical studies and popular articles have appeared in Scientific American, BioScience, The Anatomical Record, Annals of the Carnegie Museum, Evolutionary Theory, Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology, Journal of Paleontology, Modern Geology, Historical Biology, Paleobiology, Evolutionary Biology, Cretaceous Research, Science, Nature. His work has been covered by the New York Times, Washington Post, Science Friday, Science News, New Scientist, Discover, Reuters. He designed the Tyrannosaurus in Jurassic Park.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article focuses on a subject that has received not much in the way of consideration, the young earth creationist (YEC) view of the Ice Age that they propose followed the super flood. In this examination I am going to put some emphasis on one of the biggest canyons in these United States. Not the often discussed Grand Canyon – the reasons why that colossal ditch was formed as a classic riverine V-shaped valley over millions of years in rocks up to 1.25 billion years old, rather than suddenly cut by a super flood in short order in post-flood deposits, has been well detailed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The valley focused on here is Yosemite. Yosemite has received notably little attention in either the anti- or pro- creationist literature. That is both despite, and precisely because, the California canyon poses overwhelming problems that YEC theory lacks practical means of explaining. This article also focuses on the apologetics of the top two creationist organizations, the Institute for Creation Research and, especially, Answers in Genesis headed by the most popular living YEC, Ken Ham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Creationist Conspiracy Theory versus the Natural Truth&lt;/strong&gt;
That the role played by the 2.5 year old Quaternary Ice Age is on the side burner of the creation debate is ironic in that it played a critical role in beginning the scientific undermining of scriptural creationism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creationists of various flavors believe those who claim that creation could not have occurred without the existence of a transcendent intelligent designer are engaged in a vast conspiracy of spiritual denial. According the YEC’s, the willful rejection of divine creation includes pretending the planet is more than a few thousand years old. The notion is that stubborn resisters to Biblical creation started to concoct a false geological narrative in the late 1700’s going into the 1800’s in which our planet is supposed to be many millions of years old, disproving the inerrancy of the Word of God. This notion then expanded into a vast conspiracy ofcreator deniers that have been pretending the universe is billions of years old and that organisms evolved over much of that time via natural selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The historical truth is that the great glaciation was a key to the accidental overturning of Biblical time scales. Largely Christian early geologists who presumed they were going to confirm the work of God began to come across extensive evidence for extreme past glaciations in the form of many valleys that had clearly been formed by big ice flows, but did not have ice flowing in them. And evidence for tremendous continent-spanning ice sheets was showing up. Knowing that ice flows carve and move rock and earth downslope at a literally glacial pace, they began to realize that actual earth history time must have been far longer than undocumented Biblical time, to the extent that the latter was refuted – scientists have not been conspiring to refute scripture, instead nature has naturally refuted the Biblical creation story via objective scientific investigation that the researchers are merely reporting on. That the planet was not meeting YEC-compatible criteria in all aspects, including granitic glacial valleys that obviously took tens to hundreds of thousands of years to be cut, helped force the budding scientific community to abandon Bible-based creation timelines. They had no logical alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Great American Freeze&lt;/strong&gt;
That incredible amounts of ice recently covered enormous tracts of the northern hemisphere is so well documented that even YEC makes no attempt to deny the reality of an ice age, even though it is not mentioned in scriptures. And this leads to a tremendous problem for YEC: a lack of sufficient time for vast quantities of frozen water to do very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In science-based geological reality, the Pleistocene ice age began about 2.5 million years ago, with dozens of repeating cycles (Kohler and Wal, 2020) of glacial periods each lasting tens of thousands of years, each interrupted by markedly shorter, warmer interglacials that last about ten thousand years, we being in the Holocene expression of the latest interglacial. With glaciers forming enormous, kilometers-thick ice shields over much of Eurasia and especially North America, and gargantuan ice fields topping many mountain ranges, for a combined total of some 1.5 to 2 million years, there was plenty of time for those super glaciers to form, erode, move, and gouge out and deposit lots of rock and dirt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the height of the glacial maximums, ice sheets and fields covered about a third of the continents (https://www.climate.gov/media/11951). The ice contained so much water transferred from the oceans that the level of the oceans dropped 130 m, over 400 ft. The biggest single ice sheet was northern North America’s Laurentide – for the purposes of this discussion the name is applied to each re-creation of the shield over the ice age – that smothered almost all of Canada and a fair portion of the USA, down to Long Island and over to and across Indiana and Illinois and the upper plains states (https://www.kgs.ku.edu/Publications/PIC/pic28.html). Of course glaciers flow, because thick ice at earthly temperatures is plastic and becomes mobile under the pressure of its own mass. With little or nothing in the way of down-slope force, the flow of continent sized ice sheets is driven largely by the center of the shield being so thick that it pushes out laterally over hundreds to thousands of miles. In the case of the Laurentide its thickness was over 3 km (2 mi) thick in the region of its center, thinning out to 400-650 m (1300-2000 ft) at its edges (USGS; Broad 2018). Because continent spanning ice shields are not flowing down a strongly inclined valley, they move very slowly, about half a meter a year. But because they run for thousands of millennia, any given spot under the shield can experience hundreds of kilometers worth of ice and debris grinding over it during most of the Pleistocene, while any given unit of ice can flow for many hundreds of miles during that time, making long running ice sheets colossal earth movers. To the degree that the multiple Laurentide sheets scoured much of Canada of its soft earth covering, leaving behind the gouged, rocky surface of the Canadian Shield. Much of that dirt and ground up rock ended up in the northern USA where it helped form future farmlands and prominent geographical features such as Long Island, Staten Island, and Cape Cod, which are terminal glacial moraines on a stupendous scale. Those substantial lands would simply not exist but for the fact that the Laurentide shields spent well over a million years moving and dumping vast amounts of stuff, while in the process digging out the basins for the Great Lakes, polishing hard bedrocks, and scattering about big boulders of Canadian rock south of the border called erratics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The closest thing these days to the Laurentide sheet in size and depth is the Antarctic ice cap. Over the main body of the latter, annual snow fall is about half a foot per year, which qualifies as desert conditions (Casey et al. 2014). Rates of snowfall on such continent-scale, miles-thick ice sheets are inherently low – the air above them is automatically thin and very cold due to high altitude; cold air, especially when thin, cannot hold much water vapor, most of the ice caps are far from marine water sources, and there are no sudden high mountain ranges to wring precipitation on steep upwind slopes. The ratio of snow deposition relative to resulting solid ice thickness ranges from over 10 to 2.5 depending on how fluffy to icy is the snow (Casey et al., 2014; Graham 2018). So if we assume that it took 50,000 years for each iteration of the Laurentide ice shield to reach maximum thickness, then it would have required about half a foot to 2.5 ft (20-80 cm) of snow in a given year, equaling about 2 to 3 in of rain. Not a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The many problems with YEC theory and all that ice start with the events that occurred before their version of the Pleistocene. YEC tries to wave away the great geological ages indicated by radiometric dating by arbitrarily believing that radioactive decay used to occur at rates far higher than they currently are (Vardiman et al. 2005). If so, then the heat released by so much radioactivity cooking along within just a couple thousand years would have melted the surface of the planet, precluding any super flood, ice age, or for that matter our currently pleasantly cool planetary surface, while in the process irradiating all life with lethal doses of radiation (Morton and Murphy 2004; Isaac 2007) – YEC’s dismiss these incompatibilities with the truth of the perfect word of God by promising that they are “confident” these gross violations of the physics of the universe will be solved (Vardiman et al. 2005). Also, modern YEC actually postulates that the continents moved the thousands of miles from their preflood supercontinent positions into their current locations while the flood was occurring! Even the YEC who proposed this impossible geoevent has admitted that the amount of heat released by opening a magmatic Atlantic basin in a fraction of a year while dragging the leading edges of tectonics plates into the mantle at the rate of dozens of miles a day and so forth would unleash enough heat to melt most of the crust and/or “boil away a layer of water 25 km deep over the entire earth” (Morton and Murphy 2004).  Aside from steam broiling the life floating in and on top of the floodwaters, the Ark residents included – while making the atmosphere and waters lethally toxic with nasty volcanic gases – this too would prevent a subsequent ice age, and the planet would these days still be too hot to support anything except perhaps some microbial thermophiles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even if the planet were not super heated at the end of the flood, there is the problem of too little time for an ice age. According to the often calculated generational genealogy detailed in the Bible, the earth is ~6000 years old. And the flood, according to the leading YEC organization Answers in Genesis, occurred circa 4500 years before present. Using their entirely faith-based Biblical calculation – there being no actual geological scientific data backing it up – in some posts (Snelling and Matthews 2013, AIG 2018) AIG calculates that the ice age got going circa 4250 years ago, and ended around 4000 years. Just after the Babel affair and before the first cities appeared according to their radical, nonhistorical Bible based estimates (cities actually first appeared circa 9500 BP, Mesopotamia arose 5100 BP, and the Pyramids of Giza went up ~4500 BP). But AIG is very inconsistent. According to another calculation driven by the absurdities of a big freeze lasting a quarter millennium, the ice age lasted 700 years, apparently starting in the immediate aftermath of the flood, which would put its end at just 3750 years ago (Oard 2004; 2007a,b); that, of course, increases the serious problems that stem from trying to squeeze in the beginning of post-flood urban civilizations – which AIG acknowledges did not appear until after the ice sheets were gone – into even less than four millennia. 
So instead of Pleistocene ice for over 2 million years, YEC proposes it was really in existence for just 250 years – about the same age as the USA – to maybe 700.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting with the 250-year YEC ice age, allowing for 100 years of melting, to pile up a couple miles worth of ice in 150 years would require 50 to 200 meters (175 to 700) feet of snow – depending on how icy or fluffy the falling snow was – per year over the majority of the Laurentide sheet, an area covering a third to half of Canada. There simply is no location on the planet that can conceivably receive anywhere close to so much snow so fast.  It is not possible for cold air to contain and dump that much solidified water at a usually or always freezing location in so little time, least of all when not on the narrow zone mountain upslopes chronically downwind of cold coastal air currents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The absurdity of postulating that a glacial shield grew to cover about half a continent with thousands of feet of ice and then all melted away in just a few human lifespans is so reckless, that it helps explain why other AIG posts propose a 700 year long ice age, with ice accumulation covering 500 years. In an additional effort to lessen the growth-time problem, the 700 year scenario proposes that the north continental sheets averaged just 700 m (2300 ft) in depth (Oard 2007a,b), a value too low to drop sea level by the well documented 130 m. Aside from being too shallow a value, the key issue is how to pile all the ice at the deepest region which would be about twice as high as the average. Piling up 1000 m (3500 ft) in 500 years would require some 6 to 25 m (20 to 80 ft) of snow from icy to fluffy respectively a year, over millions of square kilometers. Such snowfall rates are seen in the modern world, but only in locations of limited area, where coastal mountains are capturing steady, wet winter winds, such as northern Japan. Presuming that the ice sheet’s core region got to the more geologically correct two miles demands an even more implausible 18 to 75 m (60 to 250 ft) each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;YEC theory tries to explain this all away with an extremely speculative hypothesis. Oard (2004, 2007) proposes that the post-flood oceans that were still warm from the heating events associated with the flood were evaporating so much water vapor into the atmosphere, while sun blocking volcanic dusts and aerosols from extensive post flood volcanism were making the continents so cold, that incredible rates of ice accumulation occurred on the continents. But to transfer such enormous volumes of water from oceans to continents so fast would have required the northern lands and the air above them staying freezing cold continuously for almost the entire year, while the oceans and air above them remained so steamy warm that the air topping the oceans could absorb and carry all that water vapor, for centuries. But according to Oard, the oceans were merely warm enough for a “pleasant swim” – that’s necessary to avoid killing off most or all marine life, but such is insufficient to pump the needed amounts of water into the atmosphere. Nor were the continent versus marine temperature differentials sustainable. Obviously, the freezing cold and therefore dense continental air would flow via tremendous surface winds in vast quantities out over the balmy oceans, rapidly cooling their surfaces down in alliance with all the suspended volcanics that kept the sun from warming the seas. That would severely suppress water uptake into the air. Meanwhile, all the relatively warm oceanic air back flowing over the continents would partly displace and mix with the cold land air, probably keeping lands at high latitudes too warm for glacier formation at low altitudes, while quickly eliminating the strong temperature ocean-continent differential the YEC hypothesis cannot work without. After all, the surface temperatures of land and sea broadly equalize in just a few months with each change of seasons. For the apparently deeply impractical Oard scenario in which some 45 million cubic kilometers of ocean water (the over 360 million square kilometers of the surface of all oceans times 0.13 kilometers depth) is evaporated from the ocean surfaces and plopped onto the continents as snow in just a few centuries, a rate up to 100,000 cubic kilometers per year, to be taken seriously, its feasibility would need to be supported by sophisticated computer simulations conducted by an objective team of analysts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time problem is not only one of accumulation, it is one of movement. If the Laurentide and other northern hemisphere flatland shields lasted just a few hundred years, creeping along at half a meter or so a year they would have flowed a mere few hundred meters! There would have been no scouring of the Canadian Great Shield, no deposition of the super moraines that make up Long Island et al., no glacial polishing of hard rocks, no deposition of glacial erratics hundreds and thousands of miles from their origin, no digging of the basins of the Great Lakes. In order to accomplish those Sisyphean tasks within the YEC timeframe would require that the shield ice magically zip along at a rate of a couple of hundred meters per day, which violates the physics of the universe including gravity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Big Valley&lt;/strong&gt;
Praised as an exemplar of western America’s God’s Country by devout, mainstream Christian John Muir, with its U-shaped cross section, hanging valleys, and ice-scoured rock surfaces, Yosemite is the paragon par excellence of a glacial valley. YEC and ICR admit such, and they do not offer alternative scenarios, none being viable. Including a sudden super flood, or earthquakes, the necessary faulting not being on hand. A feature of Yosemite is its exceptionally tough graniteThe rock is both very hard and in the main unfractured, which is why it retains such unparalleled tall, sheer vertical cliffs – in some places such as half dome rearing over 4000 ft above the current valley floor, which itself is fill-in that lies 2000 ft above the glacially carved bottom (Huber 1987; Duhnforth et al. 2010; Anderson 2018). The walls of less resilient glacially cut valleys are prone to more collapsing when the lateral support of the ice melts away. The foundations of the valley began in the late Mesozoic with the formation of deep underground plutons associated with plate tectonics. Being well insulated by overlying terrain, very slow cooling of the pluton allowed the development of the large interlocking hard crystals that form the granites most resistant to fracturing and abrasion. During the late Cenozoic, uplift exposed the Sierra Nevada batholith to erosion. Initially the Merced River cut a V-shaped valley perhaps a couple thousand feet deep. Then the repeat formation of the Sierra Nevada ice field sent glaciers up to 4000 ft deep down the canyon, carving the U-shaped main valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rate at which glaciers cut very hard rock such as granite is known from direct observation of current examples. Glacial erosion occurs because of plucking and/or abrasion. The former, in which the flowing ice breaks off substantial chunks of rock by fracturing of pieces, is the faster means, but regularly occurs only when the rock is not especially hard and/or is heavily fractured. And even such quarrying excavates semi-hard rock at a rate of at most 100 mm/year (Hallett et al. 1996; p. 190 in Benn and Evans 2010). If the rock is very hard and has few or no fractures, then abrasion is predominant or exclusive. When abrasion is the primary means of glacial erosion, the rock exhibits glacial polishing, a distinctive surface texture in which the surface is both grooved in a consistent direction that follows the flow of the ice, and is smoothed to a reflective semi-gloss texture. Because plastic mountain glacial ice (Mohs value 2-4) is far softer than granite (Mohs value 6-7), the ice has has any direct effect on the granite. It is rocks carried along the periphery of the ice that do the majority of the cutting. But even those boulders are not harder than those they are eroding, make up only a small percentage of the glacier edges. And liquid water and micro air pockets lubricate the contact between the glaciers and valley rock, so the erosion rate is very slow, on the order of less than a millimeter to a few millimeters per year (Hallett et al. 1996; Benn and Evans 2010; Wirsig et al. 2016). The short term erosive power of glaciers in hard rock valleys is illusive, not amounting to much on a yearly or even century basis. That is why when matters are going on the slow side they are often referred to being glacial in their pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of Yosemite granite is unfractured and about as hard as igneous rock gets. The sheer walls of Yosemite exhibit the glacial polishing that confirms it was cut ever so slowly by abrasion (Duhnforth et al. 2010). Thus, it took hundreds of thousands of years’ worth of river cutting and glacial grinding at a rate of a few millimeters per year to gouge out the 8 square miles worth of granite that forms the 8 mile long, 1 mile wide and deep Yosemite Valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In pseudoscientific YEC mythology the Sierra Nevada Batholith formed as a result of the galloping continental drift during the flood. While being uplifted above sea level and/or shortly afterwards, it was fast cooled by underground water conversion into steam – the kind of process that would have helped boil the global flood sea – while the hardening magma that somehow remains solid rather than infiltrated with water-steam channel cavities. In this time pressed scheme the fantastically swift cooling to below 0°C is needed to allow ice to shortly come along and quickly cut the fresh granite. But such rapid cooling would not have allowed the formation of that existing tough, big crystal, fracture free solid rock it is. Instead the batholith would have consisted of finer grained, softer volcanics like those that form when surface lavas rapidly cool (Huber 1987), which is why lavas never form granites. In the YEC scenario there would have been no time for water erosion of the erosion resistant Yosemite material. Instead rock-laced ice would have had to cut through the hard granites by dozens of feet each year to push out the eight square miles down and across in mere centuries, a rate thousands of times faster than observed with contemporary granite valley glaciers, and that like just about everything else concerning YEC violates the physics of the universe we dwell in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While YEC’s have written at length about their ideas on how the Grand Canyon was recently rapidly formed, as far as I know when it comes to Yosemite the only detailed attempt to deal with the big granite gulley is to explain how the Sierra Nevada glacial field could form in just a hundred years or so (Brewer and Vardiman 2010). Although rapid ice buildup in the coastal high Sierras directly downwind of the Pacific is not as outlandishly impossible as such is in continental interiors, the calculations are a stretch and suffer from the same formation problems noted above. Note that the YEC’s do not try to pass off the formation of the valley to some form of rapid faulting driven by superquakes, there being no evidence for such.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What the YEC’s are abjectly failing to address is how Yosemite granite could have been cut about a mile deep and across in a few hundred years or less when water, solid or liquid, cuts granite extremely slowly. This failure is almost certainly because they cannot devise anything close to an explanation for such a fantastical event that wouldn’t be eye rolling even for YEC’s. In a cynical effort to brush aside the Yosemite difficulty, an AIG PR tract merely alludes to how the “weathering and erosive power of this glacier was immense” (Snelling 2015). The hard fact is that the erosive power of glaciers in tough granite valleys is immense only over immense geological (and non-Biblical) stretches of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Science Based Reality Check of Faith Based Genesis&lt;/strong&gt;
Let’s turn the situation around and consider what our planet would be like if it were formed a half-dozen millennia ago, and a planetary flood occurred about 1500 years after that, followed by a quick ice age. This hypothesis would be verified if radiometrics did not  produce dates much over 6000 years, or if there were not evidence of significant continental drift, nor of granitic plutons that take long spans to cool. Sediments deposited during the super flood would exhibit a chaotic mix of creatures rather than the layered, increasingly complex pattern predicted by evolution. The Canadian shield would be covered by thick soils, there would not be glacial erratics in northern Ohio, and there would not be super moraines such as Long Island. Water erosion of highlands, whether glacial or liquid, would have had too little time to do much to hard rock. Yosemite and other granitic valleys would not exist, and nothing more than superficial polish veneers would record the short term ice age in and on the tough surfaced highlands. And the universe would be only a few thousand light years across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Creationist Credibility Problem&lt;/strong&gt;
That YEC adherents are evading the obvious impossibility of forming famed Yosemite and other resilient rock valleys around the globe in a few hundred years helps expose the pseudoscientific depth of their methods. Their hypocritical tactics of not telling their followers of the many major logic gaps inherent to their unscientific beliefs – including the field trips they hold at Yosemite – are similar to those who promote the new belief in ancient aliens founding human civilization. The latter creation myth according to surveys, may have become more popular than the declining belief in YEC, as have the existence of bigfoot, psychic powers, astrology, the Loch Ness monster, and Elvis being alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some YEC’s, seeing the super inanity of trying to compress all of universal planetary and human history into six millennia, allow that earth might be tens of millennia old. Although this alleviates the time compression problems a little, it still does not allow enough time to allow glaciers to sculpt Yosemite Valley, much less large portions of continents. At the same time, breaking the 6000-year Biblical temporal barrier denies the perfection of scripture’s divine author, rendering the fundamentalist YEC program moot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;YEC’s must convincingly directly explain every critical point raised herein – piling up vast ice sheets in mere centuries including sustaining for that time the dramatic continent/marine temperature differential, having the Laurentide shield move much of Canada into the USA in that time piling up Long Island et al., cooling the Yosemite pluton into very hard granite in decades and cutting it a mile deep in mere centuries, and so forth. This includes producing advanced computer simulations verifying the YEC speculations. Otherwise it is religion-based pseudoscience mixed with conspiracy theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Using Yosemite for Science Promotion&lt;/strong&gt;
While Yosemite in a never ending migraine headache for creationism so toxic to the cause that they ignore it as much as they can, it is a whopping yet oddly underutilized tool for science education that goes untapped. The Grand Canyon has been the premiere super sized chasm for presenting deep geotime to the public, but YEC’s think they can explain it away. In public educational terms, beloved Yosemite is the most readily understandable example (and least subject to seeming refutation) of how a giant canyon could not have been formed in the few hundreds or even thousands of years that the faith-based YEC movement demands that all must believe. It should be at the leading edge of rational outreach as a go-to, user-friendly example of how it took soft ice hundreds of millennia to dig out tough granite a mile deep and wide, firmly disproving the Genesis timeline. This may help accelerate the decline in creationist opinion and Biblical literalism already underway in the USA (Newport 2022; Brenan 2024).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AIG. 2018. Bible Timeline. https://answersingenesis.org/bible-timeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anderson, D. 2018. Formation of Yosemite Valley. https://www.yosemite.ca.us/formation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brenan, M. 2014. Majority still credits God for humankind, but not creationism. Gallup. https://news.gallup.com/poll/647594/majority-credits-god-humankind-not-creationism.aspx.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brewer, W. and L. Vardiman. 2010. Numerical simulation of precipitation in Yosemite National Park with a warm ocean: A pineapple express case study. Answers Research Journal. https://answersingenesis.org/environmental-science/ice-age/simulation-of-precipitation-in-yosemite-with-warm-ocean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Broad, W. 2018. How the ice age shaped New York. The New York Times 6/5.  https://www.nytimes.com/2018/06/05/science/how-the-ice-age-shaped-new-york.html.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burgess, E. et al. 2010. A spatially calibrated model of annual accumulation rate on the Greenland ice sheet (1958-2007). Journal of Geophysical Research 115:1-14.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Casey, K. et al. 2014. The 1500 m South Pole ice core: recovering a 40 ka environmental record. Annals of Glaciology 55:137-146.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Duhnforth, M. et al. 2010. Bedrock fracture control of glacial erosion processes and rates. Geology 38:423-426.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graham, R. 2018. How to calculate rain to snow. Sciencing.  https://sciencing.com/calculate-rain-snow-8344589.html.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hallet, B., L. Hunter and J. Bogen. 1996. Rates of erosion and sediment evacuation by glaciers: A review of field data and their implications. Global and Planetary Change 12: 213-235.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huber, N. 1987. The geologic story of Yosemite Park. USGS Bulletin 1595. https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1595.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isaac, R. 2007. Assessing the RATE project. Perspectives on Science &amp;amp; Christian Faith June: 143-146. eleted them all by hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kohler, P. and Wal, R. S. W. 2020. Interglacial of the Quaternary defined by northern hemispheric land ice distribuation outside of Greenland. Nature Communications 11:5124.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morton, G. and G. Murphy. 2004. Flaws in a young—earth cooling mechanism. Reports of the National Center for Science Education 24(1): 31-32. https://ncse.com/library-resource/flaws-young-earth-cooling-mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newport, F. 2022. Fewer in U.S. now see Bible as literal word of God. Gallup. https://news.gallup.com/poll/394262/fewer-bible-literal-word-god.aspx.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oard, M. 2004. The Genesis flood caused the ice age. https://answersingenesis.org/environmental-science/ice-age/genesis-flood-caused-the-ice-age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oard, M. 2007a. Where does the ice age fit? The New Answers Book 1. https://answersingenesis.org/environmental-science/ice-age/where-does-the-ice-age-fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oard, M. 2007b. Setting the stage for an ice age. Answers Magazine. https://answersingenesis.org/environmental-science/ice-age/setting-the-stage-for-an-ice-age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snelling, A. 2015. Yosemite Valley – colossal ice carving. Answers Magazine. https://answersingenesis.org/geology/catastrophism/yosemite-valley-colossal-ice-carving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snelling, A. and M. Matthews. 2013. When was the ice age in biblical history? Answers Magazine. https://answersingenesis.org/environmental-science/ice-age/when-was-the-ice-age-in-biblical-history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;USGS. The Laurentide Ice Sheet. https://notendur.hi.is/thorstur/teaching/glac/2012_group4_LaurentideIceSheet_notes.pdf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vardiman, L, A. Snelling and E, Chaffin. 2005. Radioisotopes and the Age of the Earth. Waco: Institute for Creation Research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wirsig, C. et al. 2016. Subglacial abrasion rates at Goldbergkees, Hohe Tauern, Austria, determined from cosmogenic 10Be and 36CI concentrations. Earth Surface Processes and Landforms. https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/esp.4093.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gregory Paul</name></author><summary type="html">The author at Yosemite. Gregory Paul is an independent polymath researcher including in paleozoology and geology. His technical studies and popular articles have appeared in Scientific American, BioScience, The Anatomical Record, Annals of the Carnegie Museum, Evolutionary Theory, Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology, Journal of Paleontology, Modern Geology, Historical Biology, Paleobiology, Evolutionary Biology, Cretaceous Research, Science, Nature. His work has been covered by the New York Times, Washington Post, Science Friday, Science News, New Scientist, Discover, Reuters. He designed the Tyrannosaurus in Jurassic Park. This article focuses on a subject that has received not much in the way of consideration, the young earth creationist (YEC) view of the Ice Age that they propose followed the super flood. In this examination I am going to put some emphasis on one of the biggest canyons in these United States. Not the often discussed Grand Canyon – the reasons why that colossal ditch was formed as a classic riverine V-shaped valley over millions of years in rocks up to 1.25 billion years old, rather than suddenly cut by a super flood in short order in post-flood deposits, has been well detailed. The valley focused on here is Yosemite. Yosemite has received notably little attention in either the anti- or pro- creationist literature. That is both despite, and precisely because, the California canyon poses overwhelming problems that YEC theory lacks practical means of explaining. This article also focuses on the apologetics of the top two creationist organizations, the Institute for Creation Research and, especially, Answers in Genesis headed by the most popular living YEC, Ken Ham. The Creationist Conspiracy Theory versus the Natural Truth That the role played by the 2.5 year old Quaternary Ice Age is on the side burner of the creation debate is ironic in that it played a critical role in beginning the scientific undermining of scriptural creationism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Darwin Day 2025</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/darwin-day-2025.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Darwin Day 2025" /><published>2025-01-22T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-01-22T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/darwin-day-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/darwin-day-2025.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Escultura_de_Charles_Darwin.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sculpture of Darwin.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Credit: Luisalvaz, &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Escultura_de_Charles_Darwin_en_la_Facultad_de_Ciencias_de_la_UNAM_02.jpg&quot;&gt;Escultura de Charles Darwin, con la barba y las cejas rosas, en la Facultad de Ciencias de la UNAM&lt;/a&gt;, 20 January 2024, CC BY-SA 4.0.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darwin_Day&quot;&gt;Darwin Day&lt;/a&gt;, variously known, I think, as Evolution Day and later Evolution Weekend and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theclergyletterproject.org/rasweekend2025.html&quot;&gt;Religion and Science Weekend&lt;/a&gt;, commemorates Darwin’s birthday on February 12, 1809 (yes, the same day as Abraham Lincoln).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Center for Science Education warns us that &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/darwin-day-2025-approaches&quot;&gt;Darwin Day approaches&lt;/a&gt; and announces:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt; For its part, NCSE, with the National Association of Biology Teachers and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8qNWW6NRfjE&quot;&gt;Katie Hinde&lt;/a&gt;, will be reprising the popular evolution symposium &quot;A Lioness Walks Into an Orca: How Stories Enhance Science Education&quot; and sharing exciting information about the 2025 March Mammal Madness tournament online at 7:00 p.m. Eastern on February 12, 2025 (details to be announced). And of course, NCSE will be active on social media in support of evolution education — look for (and use) the hashtag #whyteachevolution on Darwin Day, and check out our #whyteachevolution &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/why-teach-evolution-2020&quot;&gt;essays&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to search a little harder to find other events.  Here they come:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.evolutionmeetings.org&quot;&gt;Evolution 2025&lt;/a&gt; is the joint meeting of the American Society of Naturalists, the Society of Systematic Biologists, and the Society for the Study of Evolution.  The meeting is one of the premiere international opportunities for sharing research on evolutionary biology. “The conference will be held in 2 parts:  A 2 day virtual conference with live online workshops, talks, symposia, and networking events May 29-30, followed a few weeks later by a 5 day in-person conference in Athens, GA, USA at the Classic Center, June 20-24, 2025.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://darwinday.org/events/list/?tribe-bar-date=2025-02-01&quot;&gt;International Darwin Day&lt;/a&gt; listed four events:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;February 12, 7:00-8:30 pm, Darwin Day Lecture: &quot;Twists and Turns in Teaching Evolution over the Years, Calkins Science Center - Grand Rapids Community College , 226 Bostwick Ave. NE, Grand Rapids, MI, United States. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 12, 7:00-9:00 pm, Darwin Day, &quot;Evolution und Medizin,&quot; Siegmund Freud Universität, Freudplatz 3, Wien, Austria. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 13, 6:00-7:30 pm, &quot;The Past is the Key to the Future: Oregon’s Fossil Rodents and the Impacts of Environmental Change,&quot; The Museum of Natural and Cultural History, 1680 E. 15th Ave., Eugene, OR, United States. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;April 4-5, Iowa City Darwin Day: Science Fest, three speakers for talks on Friday, April 4 and Saturday, April 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may find URL's and further information on the Darwin Day website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to search for others and found the following after a relatively few minutes of searching for Darwin Day and Evolution Weekend:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;14-15 February 2025, 12:00-5:00pm (1 hour tours),  &lt;a href=&quot;https://essig.berkeley.edu/events/darwin-day/&quot;&gt;Essig Museum of Entomology&lt;/a&gt;, University of California, Berkeley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunday, February 23, 12-4 pm EST &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/darwin-day-2025-celebration-at-the-mcclung-tickets-1154833872199&quot;&gt;McClung Museum of Natural History &amp;amp; Culture&lt;/a&gt;, Knoxville, TN 37916&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 14-16, 2025, Religion and Science Weekend (formerly Evolution Weekend), noted above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 28, 5-8 pm, &lt;a href=&quot;https://eeb.tamu.edu/darwin-day/darwin-day-2025/&quot;&gt;An Annual Celebration of All Things Biology!&lt;/a&gt;, Ecology &amp;amp; Evolutionary Biology Program at Texas A&amp;amp;M University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Date and time not given. &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution.wisc.edu/darwin-day/&quot;&gt;The Gene’s Eye View of Evolution&lt;/a&gt;, J. Arvid Ågren, evolutionary biologist and author of The Gene’s-Eye View of Evolution, J.F. Crow Institute for the Study of Evolution. Also art contest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 17, 7-9 pm UTC, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/northern-ireland-humanists/events/303805213/&quot;&gt;Annual Darwin Day Lecture: How evolution gave us Free Will&lt;/a&gt;, Kevin Mitchell, Associate Professor, Genetics and Neuroscience, Trinity College Dublin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 10, Darwin Day Speaker, Timothy Mousseau, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stonybrook.edu/commcms/ecoevo/_events/darwinday.php&quot;&gt;Evolution across Mutagenic Landscapes: Adventures at Chernobyl, Fukushima, and Other Hot Places&lt;/a&gt;, Department of Ecology and Evolution, Stony Brook University&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 15, 10 am-3 pm local time, &lt;a href=&quot;https://uwm.edu/geosciences/event/darwin-day-at-the-thomas-a-greene-geological-museum/&quot;&gt;Darwin Day at the Thomas A. Greene Geological Museum&lt;/a&gt;, University of Wisconsin Milwaukee, Geosciences. Looks like an open house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please use the comments to add any further events as you discover them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Credit: Luisalvaz, Escultura de Charles Darwin, con la barba y las cejas rosas, en la Facultad de Ciencias de la UNAM, 20 January 2024, CC BY-SA 4.0. Darwin Day, variously known, I think, as Evolution Day and later Evolution Weekend and Religion and Science Weekend, commemorates Darwin’s birthday on February 12, 1809 (yes, the same day as Abraham Lincoln). The National Center for Science Education warns us that Darwin Day approaches and announces: For its part, NCSE, with the National Association of Biology Teachers and Katie Hinde, will be reprising the popular evolution symposium &quot;A Lioness Walks Into an Orca: How Stories Enhance Science Education&quot; and sharing exciting information about the 2025 March Mammal Madness tournament online at 7:00 p.m. Eastern on February 12, 2025 (details to be announced). And of course, NCSE will be active on social media in support of evolution education — look for (and use) the hashtag #whyteachevolution on Darwin Day, and check out our #whyteachevolution essays. I had to search a little harder to find other events. Here they come:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hoarfrost</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/hoarfrost.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hoarfrost" /><published>2025-01-20T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-01-20T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/hoarfrost</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/hoarfrost.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Rusty Mattinson&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/IMG_6612_Rusty_Hoarfrost_600_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hoarfrost&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frost#Hoar_frost&quot;&gt;Hoarfrost&lt;/a&gt;, Platteville, Colorado, January, 2025.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Rusty Mattinson. Hoarfrost, Platteville, Colorado, January, 2025.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Young-earth creationist takes on flat-earthers</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/young-earth-creationist-takes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Young-earth creationist takes on flat-earthers" /><published>2025-01-19T16:53:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-01-19T16:53:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/young-earth-creationist-takes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/young-earth-creationist-takes.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Duffy_Flat_Earth.jpg&quot; alt=&quot; Depiction of flat earth&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Ruch_S%C5%82o%C5%84ca_i_Ksi%C4%99%C5%BCyca.jpg&quot;&gt;Depiction of flat earth&lt;/a&gt;, showing sun and moon. &lt;small&gt; Credit: &quot;Towarzysz Przewodniczący,&quot; CC BY-SA 4.0.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to an article by Noelle Phillips in today’s Boulder Daily Camera, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dailycamera.com/2025/01/17/flat-earth-final-experiment-antarctica-will-duffy/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Colorado pastor thought he could make flat-Earthers see the light in Antarctica. It didn’t work.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Will Duffy traveled to bottom of the world last month to stage ‘The Final Experiment’ under 24 hours of sunlight[.]”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That about says it all: The flat-earthers could not believe the result and spent their time developing conspiracy theories to maintain their belief in the flat earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got curious about Will Duffy. He is pastor of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.akf.church/&quot;&gt;Agape Kingdom Fellowship&lt;/a&gt; of Wheatridge, Colorado. Their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.akf.church/faith&quot;&gt;Statement of Faith&lt;/a&gt; assures us, “[God] made the heavens and the earth and everything in them in six literal days[.]” Are we surprised? Mr. Duffy is a young-earth creationist. The flat-earthers, however, are too goofy even for him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incontrovertible evidence will not convince flat-earthers that the earth is round. What will it take to convince Mr. Duffy that the earth is very, very old?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Depiction of flat earth, showing sun and moon. Credit: &quot;Towarzysz Przewodniczący,&quot; CC BY-SA 4.0. According to an article by Noelle Phillips in today’s Boulder Daily Camera, “A Colorado pastor thought he could make flat-Earthers see the light in Antarctica. It didn’t work. Will Duffy traveled to bottom of the world last month to stage ‘The Final Experiment’ under 24 hours of sunlight[.]” That about says it all: The flat-earthers could not believe the result and spent their time developing conspiracy theories to maintain their belief in the flat earth. I got curious about Will Duffy. He is pastor of Agape Kingdom Fellowship of Wheatridge, Colorado. Their Statement of Faith assures us, “[God] made the heavens and the earth and everything in them in six literal days[.]” Are we surprised? Mr. Duffy is a young-earth creationist. The flat-earthers, however, are too goofy even for him. Incontrovertible evidence will not convince flat-earthers that the earth is round. What will it take to convince Mr. Duffy that the earth is very, very old?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Vaccine denialist as Secretary of HHS?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/vaccine-denialist.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vaccine denialist as Secretary of HHS?" /><published>2025-01-18T10:50:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-01-18T10:50:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/vaccine-denialist</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/vaccine-denialist.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Death_Rate_Covid_US.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Death rate in US due to Covid 19, October 19, 2021 through April 1, 2023.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/covid-deaths-by-vaccination&quot;&gt;Weekly US death rate per 100,000.&lt;/a&gt; Red, unvaccinated; green, vaccinated without bivalent booster; blue, with bivalent booster. &lt;small&gt;Edouard Mathieu and Max Roser (2021) - “How do death rates from COVID-19 differ between people who are vaccinated and those who are not?” Published online at OurWorldinData.org. Retrieved from: 'https://ourworldindata.org/covid-deaths-by-vaccination' [Online Resource]. CC BY.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;i&gt;New York Times&lt;/i&gt; article yesterday reported that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2025/01/17/health/rfk-jr-covid-vaccines.html&quot;&gt;Kennedy Sought to Stop Covid Vaccinations 6 Months After Rollout&lt;/a&gt;. The Kennedy in question is Robert F. Kennedy Jr., Donald J. Trump's nominee for Secretary of Health and Human Services, and the &lt;i&gt;Times&lt;/i&gt; reports that in May, 2021, Mr. Kennedy petitioned the Food and Drug Administration, &quot;demanding that officials rescind authorization for the shots and refrain from approving any Covid vaccine in the future.&quot; Mr. Kennedy's petition &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;claimed that the risks of the vaccines outweighed the benefits and that the vaccines weren’t necessary because good treatments were available, including ivermectin and hydroxychloroquine, which had already been deemed ineffective against the virus. &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hardly anyone noticed at the time, and the petition was promptly denied. Now, however, Mr. Kennedy has been nominated to head HHS, a move that the epidemiologist Gregg Gonsalves compared to &quot;putting a flat earther in charge of NASA,&quot; which as far as I am concerned may be too kind to Mr. Kennedy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little bird, who chirped anonymity, led us to an article by the National Institutes of Health, &lt;a href=&quot;https://newsinhealth.nih.gov/2021/10/covid-19-vaccines-prevented-nearly-140000-us-deaths&quot;&gt;COVID-19 Vaccines Prevented Nearly 140,000 U.S. Deaths&lt;/a&gt; through May, 2021, the very date when Mr. Kennedy submitted his petition. NIH claims, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;About 570,000 people died of COVID-19 in the U.S. through that time. The [statistical] model [used in the study] estimated that there would have been about 709,000 deaths without the vaccines.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A later study, titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.commonwealthfund.org/blog/2022/two-years-covid-vaccines-prevented-millions-deaths-hospitalizations&quot;&gt;Two Years of U.S. COVID-19 Vaccines Have Prevented Millions of Hospitalizations and Deaths&lt;/a&gt;, found, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;From December 2020 through November 2022, we estimate that the COVID-19 vaccination program in the U.S. prevented more than 18.5 million additional hospitalizations and 3.2 million additional deaths. Without vaccination, there would have been nearly 120 million more COVID-19 infections. The vaccination program also saved the U.S. $1.15 trillion (Credible Interval: $1.10 trillion–$1.19 trillion) (data not shown) in medical costs that would otherwise have been incurred. [Parentheses in original.]&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Possibly 3 million additional deaths if Mr. Kennedy's petition had been granted. That is approximately the population of Kansas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The frontispiece to this article, incidentally, shows weekly Covid death rates by vaccination status from October 9, 2021 through April 1, 2023. (The article includes a nice discussion explaining why rates, not absolute numbers, are critical.) The result is striking: At the peak in January, 2022, the death rate among unvaccinated people was approximately 10 times that among vaccinated people. Let us hope that Mr. Kennedy has learned something since 2021.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Weekly US death rate per 100,000. Red, unvaccinated; green, vaccinated without bivalent booster; blue, with bivalent booster. Edouard Mathieu and Max Roser (2021) - “How do death rates from COVID-19 differ between people who are vaccinated and those who are not?” Published online at OurWorldinData.org. Retrieved from: 'https://ourworldindata.org/covid-deaths-by-vaccination' [Online Resource]. CC BY. A New York Times article yesterday reported that Kennedy Sought to Stop Covid Vaccinations 6 Months After Rollout. The Kennedy in question is Robert F. Kennedy Jr., Donald J. Trump's nominee for Secretary of Health and Human Services, and the Times reports that in May, 2021, Mr. Kennedy petitioned the Food and Drug Administration, &quot;demanding that officials rescind authorization for the shots and refrain from approving any Covid vaccine in the future.&quot; Mr. Kennedy's petition claimed that the risks of the vaccines outweighed the benefits and that the vaccines weren’t necessary because good treatments were available, including ivermectin and hydroxychloroquine, which had already been deemed ineffective against the virus. Hardly anyone noticed at the time, and the petition was promptly denied. Now, however, Mr. Kennedy has been nominated to head HHS, a move that the epidemiologist Gregg Gonsalves compared to &quot;putting a flat earther in charge of NASA,&quot; which as far as I am concerned may be too kind to Mr. Kennedy. A little bird, who chirped anonymity, led us to an article by the National Institutes of Health, COVID-19 Vaccines Prevented Nearly 140,000 U.S. Deaths through May, 2021, the very date when Mr. Kennedy submitted his petition. NIH claims,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Caligo teucer</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/caligo-teucer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Caligo teucer" /><published>2025-01-06T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-01-06T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/caligo-teucer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/caligo-teucer.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;James Kocher&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Kocher_Owl_Butterfly.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Owl butterfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caligo_teucer&quot;&gt;Caligo teucer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; owl butterfly, &lt;a href=&quot;https://stlzoo.org/zones/discovery-corner/insectarium&quot;&gt;Bayer Insectarium&lt;/a&gt;, St. Louis Zoo, January, 2023. Mr. Kocher writes, &quot;An example of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mimicry&quot;&gt;mimicry&lt;/a&gt; coloration. Butterfly has recently emerged from a chrysalis partially composed of enrolled leaf (to right of the body).&quot; See also: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mimicry&quot;&gt;eyespot&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by James Kocher. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Caligo teucer &amp;ndash; owl butterfly, Bayer Insectarium, St. Louis Zoo, January, 2023. Mr. Kocher writes, &quot;An example of mimicry coloration. Butterfly has recently emerged from a chrysalis partially composed of enrolled leaf (to right of the body).&quot; See also: eyespot.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Editorial board of human evolution journal resigns en masse</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/editorial-board-journal-resigns.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Editorial board of human evolution journal resigns en masse" /><published>2024-12-27T14:10:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-12-27T14:10:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/editorial-board-journal-resigns</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/editorial-board-journal-resigns.html">&lt;p&gt;I once published an article in a proprietary journal. It was new, it had no page charges, and I had no funding. Little did I know that it was the bare tip of an iceberg of proprietary journals that would, among other faults, strain university libraries to the breaking point. I have been apologizing ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It gets worse. A day or so ago, a colleague sent us a post that included a press release to the effect that the editorial board of the &lt;i&gt;Journal of Human Evolution&lt;/i&gt;, a proprietary Elsevier journal, &lt;a href=&quot;https://bsky.app/profile/markgrabowski.bsky.social/post/3le7wqrryhc2y&quot;&gt;had resigned en masse&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elsevier&quot;&gt;Elsevier&lt;/a&gt; is an academic publishing firm that, according to Wikipedia, enjoyed a profit of £2.3 billion and a profit margin of 33 % in 2023.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the press release, which was posted by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/journal/journal-of-human-evolution &quot;&gt;Mark Grabowski, a co-editor with Andrea B. Taylor&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;i&gt;Journal of Human Evolution&lt;/i&gt; is the “flagship journal in paleoanthropological and human evolution research,” but “Elsevier has steadily eroded the infrastructure essential to the success of the journal while simultaneously undermining [its] core principles and practices….” The editors note, among other complaints, that Elsevier has eliminated the position of copy editor on the grounds that “the editors should not be paying attention to language, grammar, readability, consistency, or accuracy of proper nomenclature or formatting.” The result is that errors that were not found in the original manuscript are introduced during the production of the paper. The editors further complain about the cost of page charges and open access charges to institutions, and the relative paucity of institutions with whom Elsevier has negotiated open access agreements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two editors-in-chief, the emeritus editors, and all associate editors but one, “with heartfelt sadness and great regret,” therefore have resigned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is an elephant in the room, and he is hiding in plain sight in footnote 2: artificial intelligence. The press release notes that, without telling anyone, Elsevier introduced artificial intelligence during some phase of production and generated articles in which proper nouns (including epochs, site names, countries, cities, and genera) were not capitalized, and genera and species were not italicized. Thus, papers that had been properly formatted became embarrassingly wrong, and it took the persistent efforts of the editors over six months to resolve the problem. The footnote concludes, “AI processing … regularly reformats submitted manuscripts to change meaning and formatting and require extensive author and editor oversight during proof stage.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://retractionwatch.com/2024/12/27/evolution-journal-editors-resign-en-masse-to-protest-elsevier-changes/&quot;&gt;Evolution journal editors resign en masse to protest Elsevier’s changes&lt;/a&gt; in Retraction Watch. You may find Elsevier’s open access agreements &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.elsevier.com/open-access/agreements&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;; there are only a couple of dozen or so in the United States. My thanks to several Panda’s Thumbelinos for providing the press release and making perceptive suggestions ahead of my drafting the present post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I once published an article in a proprietary journal. It was new, it had no page charges, and I had no funding. Little did I know that it was the bare tip of an iceberg of proprietary journals that would, among other faults, strain university libraries to the breaking point. I have been apologizing ever since. It gets worse. A day or so ago, a colleague sent us a post that included a press release to the effect that the editorial board of the Journal of Human Evolution, a proprietary Elsevier journal, had resigned en masse. Elsevier is an academic publishing firm that, according to Wikipedia, enjoyed a profit of £2.3 billion and a profit margin of 33 % in 2023. According to the press release, which was posted by Mark Grabowski, a co-editor with Andrea B. Taylor, the Journal of Human Evolution is the “flagship journal in paleoanthropological and human evolution research,” but “Elsevier has steadily eroded the infrastructure essential to the success of the journal while simultaneously undermining [its] core principles and practices….” The editors note, among other complaints, that Elsevier has eliminated the position of copy editor on the grounds that “the editors should not be paying attention to language, grammar, readability, consistency, or accuracy of proper nomenclature or formatting.” The result is that errors that were not found in the original manuscript are introduced during the production of the paper. The editors further complain about the cost of page charges and open access charges to institutions, and the relative paucity of institutions with whom Elsevier has negotiated open access agreements. The two editors-in-chief, the emeritus editors, and all associate editors but one, “with heartfelt sadness and great regret,” therefore have resigned. Finally, there is an elephant in the room, and he is hiding in plain sight in footnote 2: artificial intelligence. The press release notes that, without telling anyone, Elsevier introduced artificial intelligence during some phase of production and generated articles in which proper nouns (including epochs, site names, countries, cities, and genera) were not capitalized, and genera and species were not italicized. Thus, papers that had been properly formatted became embarrassingly wrong, and it took the persistent efforts of the editors over six months to resolve the problem. The footnote concludes, “AI processing … regularly reformats submitted manuscripts to change meaning and formatting and require extensive author and editor oversight during proof stage.” For more, see Evolution journal editors resign en masse to protest Elsevier’s changes in Retraction Watch. You may find Elsevier’s open access agreements here; there are only a couple of dozen or so in the United States. My thanks to several Panda’s Thumbelinos for providing the press release and making perceptive suggestions ahead of my drafting the present post.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Polygonia c-album</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/polygonia-c-album.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Polygonia c-album" /><published>2024-12-23T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-12-23T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/polygonia-c-album</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/polygonia-c-album.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Marilyn Susek&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Susek_Comma_Butterfly_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Comma butterfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polygonia_c-album&quot;&gt;Polygonia c-album&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; comma butterfly, September, 2020. The photographer writes, &quot;I was in the garden when this butterfly startled me, as it was so close and came in to land and rest under the log. Very well camouflaged. I didn't see its open wing. It didn't mind me being there. I've never seen one before.&quot; Additionally, BugGuide discusses why &quot;c&quot; and why &quot;album&quot; &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugguide.net/node/view/722347&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Album means white, but the creature looks anything but white to me.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Marilyn Susek. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Polygonia c-album &amp;ndash; comma butterfly, September, 2020. The photographer writes, &quot;I was in the garden when this butterfly startled me, as it was so close and came in to land and rest under the log. Very well camouflaged. I didn't see its open wing. It didn't mind me being there. I've never seen one before.&quot; Additionally, BugGuide discusses why &quot;c&quot; and why &quot;album&quot; here. Album means white, but the creature looks anything but white to me.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Merry Kitzmas! 2025 is the 20th anniversary of Kitzmiller v. Dover and the 100th of the Scopes Trial</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/KvDv19.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Merry Kitzmas! 2025 is the 20th anniversary of Kitzmiller v. Dover and the 100th of the Scopes Trial" /><published>2024-12-20T12:01:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-12-20T12:01:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/KvDv19</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/KvDv19.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Matzke_Scopes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Nick Matzke at the Dayton County Courthouse, site of the 1925 Scopes Monkey Trial]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Nick Matzke at the Dayton County Courthouse where the Scopes Trial was held in 1925. (photo from ~2014)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;UPDATE, Dec. 22: I have now listed 52 separate events I found, including links and quotes of the summaries where available. Please contribute more in the comments!&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merry Kitzmas to all!  Today is the 19th anniversary of the &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover Area School District&lt;/i&gt; trial, aka the Dover Panda Trial, held from September-November 2005, and decided on December 20, 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year, 2025, will be the 20th anniversary of Kitzmiller, as well as the 100th anniversary of &lt;i&gt;Tennessee v. Scopes&lt;/i&gt;, aka the Scopes Monkey Trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stuck as I am, in Australia/New Zealand with 3 little kids, I expect I will have to follow events from afar.  But I will use this thread to accumulate links &amp;amp; dates for relevant events as they come up. And please contribute ones you come across!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect that many are glum about current politics and science, but I recall a similar feeling in 2004, and that &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover&lt;/i&gt; was one of the early signs that committed citizens could move events in a pro-science direction. May 2025 be another such time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summaries of events are posted below, with abstracts where available:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vanderbilt-university-scopes-trial-symposium-july-12-13-2025&quot;&gt;Vanderbilt University, Scopes Trial Symposium, July 12-13, 2025&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/2025-07-12_Scopes_Trial_Symposium_at_Vanderbilt.png&quot; alt=&quot;[Vanderbilt Scopes Trial Symposium schedule, July 12-13, 2025]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Vanderbilt Scopes Trial Symposium schedule, July 12-13, 2025&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vanderbilt.edu/evolution/scopes-symposium/&quot;&gt;Scopes &quot;Monkey&quot; Trial Centennial Symposium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Vanderbilt University, July 12-13, 2025&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vanderbilt.edu/evolution/scopes-symposium/&quot;&gt;https://www.vanderbilt.edu/evolution/scopes-symposium/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
...following on from...&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;ISEMPH 2025 Meeting&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
International Society for Evolution, Medicine, and Public Health&lt;br /&gt;
Vanderbilt University, July 8-10, 2025&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The weekend following the ISEMPH conference (7/12/25 – 7/13/25), we will host an academic symposium featuring dozens of wonderful guest speakers from around the world. This event is sponsored in part by the National Center for Science Education. Leading experts (Ed Larson, Randy Moore, and Adam Laats) on all things Scopes will speak about the history of the trial. Next, we’ll hear about issues facing teachers today as they try to navigate teaching evolution (Barbara Forrest, Kenneth Miller, Amanda Townley). Then, we will hear from folks at the forefront of their evolution-focused fields about their research (Sean Carroll, Jonathan Losos, Marlene Zuk, Stephen Brusatte, and Briana Pobiner). We’ll finish off Day 1 with a roundtable discussion on evolutionary science in the 21st century.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Day 2 will kick off with evolutionary research in fields other than biology, such as medicine (Paul Turner), agriculture (Sophien Kamoun), and the law (Owen Jones). After that, we’ll have another section on teaching evolution in a broader sense (Gale Sinatra, Patricia Hawley, Corrie Moreau, Riley Black, and Joseph Graves, Jr.). Our last proper session will be on the relationship of evolution and religion (Jamie Jensen, Katy Hinman, Liz Barnes and Lee Meadows). We’ll end with a second roundtable discussion on the future of evolution education.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-scopes-trial-centennial-at-the-university-of-tennessee-knoxville&quot;&gt;The Scopes Trial Centennial at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Scopes Trial Centennial Celebration&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://artsci.utk.edu/scopes-trial-centennial-celebration/&quot;&gt;https://artsci.utk.edu/scopes-trial-centennial-celebration/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Scopes Trial Centennial at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville, is a year-long program that marks the 100th anniversary of the July 1925 trial of John Thomas Scopes. As a high-school teacher in Dayton, Tennessee, Scopes was accused of violating the state’s Butler Act, which made it illegal to teach human evolution in any public school or university.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The trial generated intense national publicity, as reporters flocked to Dayton to cover the high-profile lawyers facing each other in court. William Jennings Bryan, a three-time presidential candidate and former secretary of state, argued for the prosecution against ACLU lawyer Clarence Darrow, who served as the defense attorney for Scopes. The trial reflected a tension between religious fundamentalists and modern science that persists in America today.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Scopes Trial Centennial program will include Clarence Brown Theatre’s production of Inherit the Wind (February 14–March 2, 2025), which portrays a fictionalized version of the trial.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The program will also showcase the university’s annual Darwin Day, hosted by the McClung Museum on a Sunday afternoon the week of Darwin’s birthday in early February.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Throughout the year, a rich variety of speakers and exhibitions are being planned to address issues related to religion and science, American history, evolution, eugenics, journalism, law, and related topics. Additional programming is being developed that will be included as it is finalized.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Scopes Trial Centennial is organized by the UT College of Arts and Sciences (involving all three divisions) in collaboration with the College of Law, UT Libraries, the Institute for American Civics, Phi Beta Kappa Epsilon of Tennessee, and the Knoxville History Project.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Historical images are from the public domain, originally taken by the Associated Press in 1925.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A variety of talks on Scopes history and evolutionary science...I will quote the abstracts of the Scopes ones below.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Events&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Religion vs. Science? The Scopes Trial and Beyond&lt;br /&gt;
November 12, 2024, 4:30 – 5:30 P.M., John C. Hodges Library, Room 100&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Simone des Roches: Conserving Intraspecific Variation for Ecosystems and People&lt;br /&gt;
November 13, 2024, 12:40 – 1:30 P.M., Science and Engineering Building&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Evolution, Intelligent Design, and a Pennsylvania School Board – a discussion with Gordy Slack&lt;br /&gt;
November 14, 2024, 4:00 P.M., Student Union Executive Dining Room 377A&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
An evening with Gordon Burghardt on the Scopes Trial and Evolution in East Tennessee&lt;br /&gt;
November 19, 2024, 7:00 – 9:00 P.M., Student Union 262 A/B&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Naturalist Club Photo Gallery&lt;br /&gt;
January &amp;amp; February 2025, Hodges Library Starbucks&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Naturalist Club Photo Gallery – Reception&lt;br /&gt;
January 27, 2025, 1:00 – 3:00 P.M., Mary Greer room in Hodges Library&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Catherine Schuman: Evolution and Computing&lt;br /&gt;
January 29, 2025, 12:40 – 1:30 P.M., Science and Engineering Building 307&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Pamela Soltis: Polyploid Evolution: Integration across scales and biological systems&lt;br /&gt;
February 12, 2025, 12:40 – 1:30 P.M., Science and Engineering Building 307&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Inherit the Wind&lt;br /&gt;
February 14-March 2, 2025, Times Vary, Clarence Brown Theatre&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Ed Larson: The Scopes Trial in History and Folklore&lt;br /&gt;
February 13, 2025, 5:30 – 6:30 P.M., Student Union 262&lt;br /&gt;

Darwin Day at the McClung Museum&lt;br /&gt;
February 23, 2025, Frank H. McClung Museum of Natural History and Culture&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Sara Lipshutz: Fighting for fitness: Integrating behavioral, hormonal and neurogenomic perspectives on the evolution of female competition&lt;br /&gt;
February 24, 2025, 12:40 – 1:30 P.M., Science and Engineering Building&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Charles Israel: Before Scopes: Evangelicals, Education and Evolution in Tennessee, 1870-1925&lt;br /&gt;
March 25, 2025, 12:00 – 1:00 P.M., College of Law&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Matthew Sutton: The Scopes Trial and the Rise of Evangelical Politics&lt;br /&gt;
March 27, 2025, 5:00 – 6:00 P.M., Mossman 102&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Paul A. Lombardo: “Apes, Men &amp;amp; Morons”: Evolution, Eugenics, and the Scopes Trial&lt;br /&gt;
March 31, 2025, 7:30 – 9:30 P.M., Strong Hall B1&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Menno Schilthuizen: “Darwin Comes to Town: How the Urban Jungle Drives Evolution”&lt;br /&gt;
April 7, 2025, 3:30 – 5:00 P.M., Student Union 169&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Jessica Ware: Dragonflies and damselflies: genomics, systematics and evolution
May 5, 2025, 12:40 – 1:30 P.M., Science and Engineering Building
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/religion-vs-science-the-scopes-trial-and-beyond&quot;&gt;Religion vs. Science? The Scopes Trial and Beyond&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/religion-vs-science-the-scopes-trial-and-beyond&quot;&gt;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/religion-vs-science-the-scopes-trial-and-beyond&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Religion vs. Science? The Scopes Trial and Beyond&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Tuesday, November 12, 2024 4:30pm to 6pm&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
About this Event&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
John C Hodges Library, 100&lt;br /&gt;
1015 Volunteer Blvd, Knoxville TN&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The 1925 Scopes “Monkey” Trial often stands as a classic case demonstrating a fundamental conflict between religious and scientific worldviews. However, such characterizations mask the deeper complexities involved both in the trial and other historical engagements between religious and scientific perspectives. This panel brings together four scholars of religious studies to discuss how academic approaches to religion, culture, science, and media help move beyond the conflict thesis, demonstrating avenues for collaboration and understanding between diverse stakeholders as the 21st century progresses.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Panel Participants: &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Dr. Joseph Witt: Associate Professor of Religious Studies, focusing on Religion, the Natural World, and Appalachia&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Dr. David Kline: Senior Lecturer of Religious Studies, focusing on Religion, Media, and Political and Contextual Christian Thought&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Dr. Megan Bryson: Associate Professor of Religious Studies, focusing on Asian Religions and Scientific Discourse&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Dr. Erin Darby: Associate Professor of Religious Studies, focusing on Judaism and the interpretation of Hebrew Bible/Old Testament&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
If you are unable to attend inperson, we welcome you to join my registering with the link below.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/evolution-intelligent-design-and-a-pennsylvania-school-board-gordy-slack&quot;&gt;Evolution, Intelligent Design and a Pennsylvania School Board - Gordy Slack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/evolution-intelligent-design-and-a-pennsylvania-school-board-gordy-slack&quot;&gt;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/evolution-intelligent-design-and-a-pennsylvania-school-board-gordy-slack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
Thursday, November 14, 2024 4pm to 5:30pm&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Evolution, Intelligent Design and a Pennsylvania School Board - Gordy Slack&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Flyer for talk&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
About this Event&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Student Union, 377A&lt;br /&gt;
1502 Cumberland Ave. Knoxville, TN 37996&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A first-hand account by an author who witnessed the 2005 trial challenging the  teaching of intelligent design alongside evolution, in the school district of Dover PA. 
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/an-evenng-with-gordon-burghardt-on-the-scopes-trial-and-evolution-in-east-tennessee
&quot;&gt;An evening with Gordon Burghardt on the Scopes Trial and Evolution in East Tennessee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/an-evenng-with-gordon-burghardt-on-the-scopes-trial-and-evolution-in-east-tennessee
&quot;&gt;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/an-evenng-with-gordon-burghardt-on-the-scopes-trial-and-evolution-in-east-tennessee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Tuesday, November 19, 2024 7pm to 9pm&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
An evening with Gordon Burghardt on the Scopes Trial and Evolution in East Tennessee&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
About this Event&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Student Union, Su262 A/B&lt;br /&gt;
1502 Cumberland Ave. Knoxville, TN 37996&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Part of a seminar series on Innovations In Evolution  on the 100th anniversary of the Scopes Trial
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/the-scopes-trial-in-history-and-folklore&quot;&gt;The Scopes Trial in History and Folklore&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/the-scopes-trial-in-history-and-folklore&quot;&gt;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/the-scopes-trial-in-history-and-folklore&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Thursday, February 13, 2025 5:30pm to 6:30pm&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Scopes Trial in History and Folklore&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Edward Larson&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Event description&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A century ago in Dayton, Tennessee, sensation-loving journalists of the 1920s transformed a small-town misdemeanor trial, brought under a new state law against teaching the theory of evolution in public schools, into a legendary clash of worldviews pitting populist orator, politician William Jennings Bryan and libertarian secularist, attorney Clarence Darrow. Over the ensuing years, fact and fiction blurred into the mythical version of the Tennessee Monkey Trial celebrated in bestselling books, Broadway plays, and Hollywood movies. In his lecture, Pulitzer Prize winning historian Edward Larson separates history from folklore in relating the story of the Scopes trial then and thereafter.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Ed Larson holds the Darling Chair in Law and is a University Professor of History at Pepperdine University. Recipient of the 1998 Pulitzer Prize in History, Larson served as Associate Counsel for the U.S. House of Representatives and taught for twenty years at the University of Georgia, where he chaired the history department. The author of fifteen books and over eighty published articles, his books include A Magnificent Catastrophe: The Tumultuous Election of 1800; Evolution: The Remarkable History of a Scientific Theory; the Pulitzer Prize winning Summer for the Gods: The Scopes Trial and America's Continuing Debate Over Science and Religion, and the New York Times bestsellers, The Return of George Washington, 1783-1789 and Franklin &amp;amp; Washington: The Founding Partnership. Larson recently published, American Inheritance: Liberty and Slavery in the Birth of a Nation, 1765-1795. Larson has served as a visiting professor at Yale Law School, Stanford Law School, the University of Melbourne, Leiden University, and the University of Richmond.

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Darwin Day at the McClung Museum&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
February 23, 2025, Frank H. McClung Museum of Natural History and Culture&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[Details TBA it looks like]
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/before-scopes-evangelicals-education-and-evolution-in-tennessee-1870-1925-3274&quot;&gt;Before Scopes: Evangelicals, Education and Evolution in Tennessee, 1870-1925&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/before-scopes-evangelicals-education-and-evolution-in-tennessee-1870-1925-3274&quot;&gt;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/before-scopes-evangelicals-education-and-evolution-in-tennessee-1870-1925-3274&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Tuesday, March 25, 2025 12pm to 1pm&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Before Scopes: Evangelicals, Education and Evolution in Tennessee, 1870-1925&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Dr. Charles Israel, Auburn University, will discuss his award winning book as part of the Scopes series of events. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Event dates&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Tuesday, March 25, 2025 12pm to 1pm&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/the-scopes-trial-and-the-rise-of-evangelical-politics&quot;&gt;The Scopes Trial and the Rise of Evangelical Politics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/the-scopes-trial-and-the-rise-of-evangelical-politics&quot;&gt;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/the-scopes-trial-and-the-rise-of-evangelical-politics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Event description&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Part of &quot;Scopes Trial Centennial&quot; series of events&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
2025 Milton Klein Lecture Series&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
with speaker Matt Sutton, Edward R. Meyer Distinguished Professor of History at Washington State University&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In recent years, evangelicals have become the largest and most powerful multi-issue interest group in the Republican Party. Historians have long focused on the Scopes Trial as the start of evangelical political engagement, setting the trajectory that runs through the 2024 presidential campaign. Sutton will argue that Scopes marked an important turning point, but not necessarily for the reasons we usually think.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Matthew Avery Sutton is the Berry Family Distinguished Professor in the Liberal Arts and the chair of the Department of History at Washington State University. His most recent book is Double Crossed: The Missionaries Who Spied for the United States During the Second World War (Basic Books, 2019). He is also the author of American Apocalypse: A History of Modern Evangelicalism (Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 2014), and Aimee Semple McPherson and the Resurrection of Christian America (Harvard University Press, 2007). He has written for the New York Times, Washington Post, and New Republic. In 2016 he was appointed a Guggenheim Foundation Fellow.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Event dates&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Thursday, March 27, 2025 5pm
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/apes-men-and-morons-evolution-eugenics-and-the-scopes-trial&quot;&gt;Apes, Men, and Morons: Evolution, Eugenics, and the Scopes Trial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/apes-men-and-morons-evolution-eugenics-and-the-scopes-trial&quot;&gt;https://calendar.utk.edu/event/apes-men-and-morons-evolution-eugenics-and-the-scopes-trial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Event description&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Dr. Paul Lombardo, Regents’ Professor and Bobby Lee Cook Professor of Law at Georgia State University, is a noted historian of eugenics and compulsory sterilization laws in the United States. He will be speaking on the role that eugenics played in the Scopes &quot;Monkey&quot; Trial. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The “Monkey Trial” Centennial provides an opportunity to examine the widespread misunderstanding about how ideas of evolution and eugenics were implicated in the famous Scopes controversy.  George William Hunter’s textbook Civic Biology was the focus of the case. It endorsed evolution, a theory “that denies the story of the Divine Creation of man as taught in the Bible” -- content prohibited by a 1925 Tennessee law. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Hunter text also contained a chapter on eugenics. In recent years an elaborate mythology has arisen suggesting that the case, and William Jennings Bryan’s advocacy at trial, represented a challenge to eugenics. That claim is demonstrably false. The teaching of eugenics in its many forms was supported not only by educators, but also by members of the clergy and politicians all across the United States. That support was evident before the Scopes case and continued for decades afterwards, persisting even in full awareness of the Nazi government program that sterilized almost 1/2 million Germans.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
This talk will explain that while William Jennings Bryan rejected the monkey- to-man account of evolution and the cruelties he associated with Darwinian “natural selection,” he made no blanket condemnation of eugenics. To the contrary, Bryan and his wife readily allied themselves with several famous eugenists and supported eugenic ideology when it coincided with the social policies they favored.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Event dates&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Monday, March 31, 2025 7:30pm to 9:30pm&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Event Location&lt;br /&gt;
Strong Hall , B1 &lt;br /&gt;
1621 West Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scopes-trial-centennial&quot;&gt;Scopes Trial Centennial&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;March-July 2025, Dayton, Tennessee&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dayton, Tennessee, back to and including 1925, has promoted the town and the region as the site of the famous Scopes Monkey Trial, the (first) “Trial of the Century”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the 100th, they do not disappoint, with a variety of events ranging from scholarly to artistic and stage, and including even a Strawberry Festival.  Naturally, some of this involves fundamentalist Bryan College in Dayton, which itself traces right back to the Scopes Trial and William Jennings Bryan, so your mileage may vary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, having attended some similar events in 2014-2015, I expect many of these are worth going to.  In 2014 or 2015 I went to a stage production called something like “Our Story”, which was in a sense about the Scopes Trial, but more about the perspective of the locals, which they felt had been left out with the usual discussion of the huge science/religion issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
Dayton, Tennessee&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/&quot;&gt;Scopes Trial Centennial 2025&lt;/a&gt;
March-July 2025, Dayton, Tennessee&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
For more information about the celebration of the Scopes Trial Centennial visit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/&lt;/a&gt;


&lt;b&gt;Events&lt;/b&gt;
Throughout the balance of 2024 and through 2025, we will be celebrating the Scopes Trial Centennial in a variety of ways. We invite you to participate in as many of these events as possible. Check the website and our social media links (Facebook and Instagram) regularly for updates.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Centennial Exhibit at Rhea County Heritage and Scopes Trial Museum&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The museum will display a special collection of historic items during the Scopes100 Centennial.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Student Visits to Courthouse &amp;amp; Museum&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Rhea County’s historic courthouse offers a unique and convenient educational experience for students.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
March 18-20: How It Started (and Why?)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Junior high and high school students can enjoy a one-hour play, followed by a lecture &amp;amp; tour.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/centennial-exhibit&quot;&gt;Centennial Exhibit at Rhea County Heritage and Scopes Trial Museum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/centennial-exhibit&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/centennial-exhibit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Oct 11&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Centennial Exhibit&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Museum open 8:00 a.m. – 4:30 p.m. daily. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Rhea County Heritage and Scopes Trial Museum&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In conjunction with Scopes100 Centennial activities and events, the Scopes Trial Museum, located in the basement of the historic Rhea County courthouse. The museum will display a special collection of historic items during the Scopes100 Centennial.  Details regarding these items will be provided on this page as we move closer to 1925.  The museum is designed for free, self-guided touring, but a representative of the historical Society will be available to assist and answer questions.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/ongoing-student-tours-of-courthouse-museum&quot;&gt;Student Visits to Courthouse &amp;amp; Museum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/ongoing-student-tours-of-courthouse-museum&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/ongoing-student-tours-of-courthouse-museum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Courthouse &amp;amp; Museum Visits&lt;br /&gt;
Museum open 8:00 a.m. – 4:30 p.m. daily. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Historic Rhea County Courthouse&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Call (423) 775-7801 to schedule a visit for your class.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Rhea County’s historic courthouse  offers a unique and convenient educational experience for to students. A national historic landmark which served as the setting for the nation’s most famous courtroom trial, the courthouse, its courtroom and its museum enable students to travel back in time and learn about the debate between “creationist” and “evolutionist.”  They will also come to understand the current issue of who decides a public school’s curriculum -- the parents or the teachers – is one which is long-standing.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/how-it-started-and-why&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/how-it-started-and-why&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/how-it-started-and-why&quot;&gt;March 18-20: How It Started (and Why?)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;How It Started&quot; Play &amp;amp; Discussion&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
March 18, 19, 20, 2025&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Historic Rhea County Courthouse
&lt;br /&gt;
FREE - Email admin@rheaheritage.com for reservations&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Junior high and high school students are invited to learn about the Scopes Trial through a one-hour fact-based play, followed by a lecture/discussion and a tour of the Rhea Heritage &amp;amp; Scopes Trial Museum. A study guide will be given to teachers and students. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Space is limited, so reservations are necessary for this free event.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/march-21-22-centennial-kickoff-event&quot;&gt;March 21-22: Centennial Kickoff Event
Scopes Trial Centennial Kick-Off Dinner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/march-21-22-centennial-kickoff-event&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/march-21-22-centennial-kickoff-event&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Friday, March 21, 2025, &lt;br /&gt;
Bryan College&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
TICKETS SALES (coming soon)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Join us for an evening of commemoration at the Scopes Trial Centennial Kick-Off Dinner, honoring the legacy of the Butler Act with distinguished speaker Ed Larson, Pulitzer Prize-winning author of Summer for the Gods: The Scopes Trial and America's Continuing Debate Over Science and Religion. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The evening will begin with a dinner featuring a prominent Tennessean, who will be announced closer to the event. Following the dinner, Ed Larson will unveil newly acquired and previously unseen photographs of the Scopes Trial, donated by a private party. These significant images will be presented to Bryan College and the Rhea County Historical Genealogical Society. Attendees will have the opportunity to view enlarged displays of the newly revealed photos, offering a unique glimpse into the historical significance of the Scopes Trial.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Tickets for this event are available for purchase, but seating is limited, so be sure to secure your spot for this important occasion!&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Breakfast and Lecture Discussion&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Saturday, March 22, 2025&lt;br /&gt;
Breakfast, (this event for educators only) 8:00 a.m.-9:00 a.m., Bryan College
Lecture-Discussion, 9:30 a.m.-12:00 p.m., Rhea County Courthouse&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Reservations are FREE, but are required&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Join us for a stimulating morning of conversation and insights with Dr. Edward J. Larson,&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Pulitzer Prize-wining author of Summer for the Gods. Dr. Larson will meet with teachers forbreakfast at Bryan College, then move to the Rhea County Courthouse where he will deliver the keynote address, “Why we Celebrate the Scopes Trial,” offering a profound exploration of this pivotal moment in American history. Following his lecture he will take questions from the audience, including selected students.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The lecture will be presented in the Scopes Trial Courtroom of the Rhea County Courthouse.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Ticket reservations will be available soon, so stay tuned for your opportunity to participate in this engaging discussion! Don’t miss out on this chance to deepen your understanding of the Scopes Trial and its lasting implications and to introduce students to an eminent historian.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/college-debate-at-the-courthouse&quot;&gt;April 17: College Debate at the Courthouse: A Debate on School Choice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/college-debate-at-the-courthouse&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/college-debate-at-the-courthouse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Thursday, April 17, 2025, &lt;br /&gt;
Rhea County Courthouse&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Reservations are FREE, but are required&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Join us for an engaging debate featuring two talented students from the Bryan College Debate Team on Thursday, April 17th at 6:30 PM, held at the historic Rhea County Courthouse. The topic of discussion will be &quot;School Choice,&quot; a crucial issue affecting education today. This event is free to attend, but registration is required due to limited seating. It promises to be an excellent educational opportunity for students and the Rhea County community alike. Don’t miss your chance to participate in the Scopes100 Centennial Celebration and witness a thought-provoking exchange of ideas!
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/78th-annual-tennessee-strawberry-festival&quot;&gt;May 5-10: 78th Annual Tennessee Strawberry Festival&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/78th-annual-tennessee-strawberry-festival&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/78th-annual-tennessee-strawberry-festival&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Dec 13&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Theme: The Great Berry Debate&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Join us for the 78th Annual Tennessee Strawberry Festival from May 5-10, 2025, with the exciting theme &quot;The Great Berry Debate!&quot; This year, we are not only celebrating the beloved strawberry but also commemorating 100 years since the Scopes Trials. Our unique theme will feature a strawberry debate that promises to engage and entertain participants of all ages.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The festival is packed with fun activities for everyone, from delicious strawberry treats to engaging events. Be sure to check the schedule for details on your favorite parts of the festival.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Don’t miss out on this delightful celebration! For more information, visit our website at &lt;a href=&quot;https://tnstrawberryfestival.com/&quot;&gt;https://tnstrawberryfestival.com/&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-11-heritage-days-expo&quot;&gt;July 11-12: Heritage Days&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-11-heritage-days-expo&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-11-heritage-days-expo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Dec 13&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Heritage Days Celebration&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Friday, July 11 - Saturday, July 12, 2025&lt;br /&gt;
Lawn of Historic Rhea County Courthouse&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Booths and displays on the grounds of the historic Rhea County Courthouse will offer educational and entertaining information about Rhea County and its heritage. Games, displays – some hands-on – and food will make for a fun outing for the whole family. Most activities will be free. If you are interested in exhibiting, email admin@rheaheritage.com for information.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-11-12-heritage-days-expo&quot;&gt;July 11-12: Destiny in Dayton Drama&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-11-12-heritage-days-expo&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-11-12-heritage-days-expo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Oct 12&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Scopes Trial Dramatization&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Fri., July 11, 2025, 7:00 PM / Sat., July 12, 2025, 2:00 PM&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Scopes Trial Courtroom, Historic Rhea County Courthouse&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
BUY TICKETS&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
See a dramatization of the Scopes Trial in the courtroom where the trial was held in 1925. Destiny in Dayton adapts the trial transcript to an engrossing account of the trial, giving viewers an accurate picture of this duel of great men and great ideas.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-11-12-buttram-cemetery-tour&quot;&gt;July 11-12: Visit Historic Buttram Cemetery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-11-12-buttram-cemetery-tour&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-11-12-buttram-cemetery-tour&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Nov 4&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Burial Site of Notable Scopes Trial Participants &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
July 11 &amp;amp; 12, 2025&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Historic Rhea County Courthouse&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Free transportation provided on demand.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Buttram Cemetery, situated north of Dayton, Tennessee, and east of U.S. Highway 27, serves as the final resting place for numerous individuals having historical significance to Rhea County. Dating back to 1811, it is the burial location for no less than thirteen local citizens who played a notable role in trial of John Scopes.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
To those wishing to visit the cemetery, transportation to and from Dayton’s historic courthouse will be provided upon demand at no charge. A representative of the Rhea County Historical Society will be available at the cemetery to answer questions. For those wishing to visit the cemetery on their own, a brochure will be available at the courthouse which allows for a self-guided tour.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-13-return-to-1925&quot;&gt;July 13: Return to 1925&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-13-return-to-1925&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-13-return-to-1925&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Oct 11&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
What Life Was Like During the Scopes Trial
Sunday, July 13, 1:00 PM – 7:30 PM&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Historic Rhea County Courthouse Courtroom and Courthouse Lawn&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Silent films free to public on  a first-come/first serve basis.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Spend the day traveling back to the year 1925 and walk into the world of those local residents who attended the trial of John Scopes. See a collection of circa 1915-1925 vintage automobiles at the historic courthouse which were likely parked around its grounds. Attend one or more showings of silent films of the day in the courtroom where John Scopes was brought to trial. View the advertising art of the most popular commercial products available to consumers at the time of the trial.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-17-scopes-trial-symposium-in-the-historic-courtroom&quot;&gt;July 16-17: Evolving Conflict: Scopes at 100&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-17-scopes-trial-symposium-in-the-historic-courtroom&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-17-scopes-trial-symposium-in-the-historic-courtroom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Oct 12&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;A Symposium on the Scopes Trial&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Wednesday, July 16, 2025; 9:00 a.m.–10:00 a.m./10:30 a.m.–11:30 a.m./ 1:00p.m–2:00 p.m.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Thursday, July 17, 2025, 9:00 a.m. – 10:00 a.m. / 10:30 a.m. – 11:30 a.m. /
1:00 p.m. – 2:00 p.m. / 2:30 p.m. – 3:30 p.m.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Scopes Trial Courtroom&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
BUY TICKETS&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In 1925, the legal question debated during the Scopes Trial was whether John Scopes broke the law by teaching the Darwinian theory of human origins. But lawyers also debated questions which still are at the center of public discussion today: Parental rights in public education, can the majority impose its will on the minority, academic freedom (of teachers and students), the role of religion in public life. Hotly debated then, still capable of raising temperatures today, these questions were not settled in 1925 – and probably won’t be settled during this discussion.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In 1925, both sides had their say; in this symposium you will hear more than one viewpoint presented by experts in their disciplines, and you will have an opportunity to interact with the presenters.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The program begins promptly at 9 a.m. Wednesday and Thursday, July 16 and 17, in the Scopes Trial courtroom of the historic Rhea County Courthouse.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Dr. Nick Spencer will lead off with a presentation on “Science, Religion and How We Got Here;” followed by Attorney Jerry Summers, speaking on “The Trial and Its People.” After a break for lunch, Dr. Edward Larson, recipient of the Pulitzer Prize in History for his book “Summer for the Gods,” will speak on the legacy of the trial in American life. Following Dr. Larson’s program, the afternoon will be open for tours of historic sites in and near Dayton.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
On Thursday, Dr. Neal Doran will discuss ”Science at the Scopes Trial and Since;” and Dr. John Hawks will present his findings on “Human Origins: What Paleontology Tells Us.” After lunch, Dr. Joel Duff will speak on “Christians and Evolution after the Trial,” and Dr. Todd Wood and Mr. Paul Garner will discuss “A History of Creationism and the Future of the Creation/Evolution Debate.” Free time will be available for tours Thursday afternoon.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There will be breaks between sessions and for lunch both days. A study guide will be provided for your further reflection on the presentations.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Scopes Trial Symposium Dinner&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Wednesday, July 17, 2025, 6:30 – 9:00 PM&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Trinity Chapel&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
BUY TICKETS&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Join us for a festive 1920s-themed dinner in historic Trinity Chapel on Wednesday, July 16. Trinity Chapel, today an event venue but Dayton’s Northern Methodist Church in 1925, has its own unique place in the Scopes Trial story. The congregation and the minister disagreed about hearing a sermon on evolution – and we’ll tell the rest of the story when you get here!&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
After a hearty meal, serenaded by music from the era, Dr. Randy Moore, author of the recently published John Thomas Scopes: A Biography, will speak on “John Scopes: The Rest of the Story.” After you hear his talk, you definitely will want to read the book.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Space is limited, so order your tickets soon.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-18-19-local-history-expo&quot;&gt;July 18-19: Local History Expo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-18-19-local-history-expo&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-18-19-local-history-expo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Dec 13&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Learn More About the Educational and Commercial History of Rhea County&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Friday, July 18  - Saturday, July 19, 2025&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Historic Courthouse and Lawn&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
FREE to the General Public&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Booths and displays located on the grounds of the historic Rhea County courthouse will provide educational information regarding the history of Rhea County and surrounding southeastern Tennessee counties. Historical societies and site-specific historic groups will display historic items associated with their activities. Major employers will present their origin stories and highlight their historic contributions to the local economy. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
If you are an organization in the East Tennessee area whose mission is history-related and you would like be a part of the Expo, please contact the Rhea County Historical Society at 916-710-1747.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-18-19-buttram-cemetery-tour&quot;&gt;July 18-19: Visit Historic Buttram Cemetery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-18-19-buttram-cemetery-tour&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-18-19-buttram-cemetery-tour&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Nov 4&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Burial Site of Notable Scopes Trial Participants&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
July 11 &amp;amp; 12, 2025&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Historic Rhea County Courthouse&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Free transportation provided on demand.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Buttram Cemetery, situated north of Dayton, Tennessee, and east of U.S. Highway 27, serves as the final resting place for numerous individuals having historical significance to Rhea County. Dating back to 1811, it is the burial location for no less than thirteen local citizens who played a notable role in trial of John Scopes.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
To those wishing to visit the cemetery, transportation to and from Dayton’s historic courthouse will be provided upon demand at no charge. A representative of the Rhea County Historical Society will be available at the cemetery to answer questions. For those wishing to visit the cemetery on their own, a brochure will be available at the courthouse which allows for a self-guided tour.

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-18-19-destiny-in-dayton-drama&quot;&gt;July 18-19: Destiny in Dayton Drama&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-18-19-destiny-in-dayton-drama&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-18-19-destiny-in-dayton-drama&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Oct 12&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Scopes Trial Dramatization &lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Fri., July 18, 2025, 7:00 PM / Sat., July 19, 2025, 2:00 PM (Dinner with Cast included)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Scopes Trial Courtroom, Rhea County Courthouse&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
BUY TICKETS&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
See a dramatization of the Scopes Trial in the courtroom where the trial was held in 1925. Destiny in Dayton adapts the trial transcript to an engrossing account of the trial, giving viewers an accurate picture of this duel of great men and great ideas. Following Saturday’s show, enjoy a 1920s-themed Dinner with the Cast of Destiny in Dayton under tents on the courthouse lawn, in the shade of trees – some of which were there for the trial!
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-19-destiny-in-dayton-dinner&quot;&gt;July 19: Play and Dinner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-19-destiny-in-dayton-dinner&quot;&gt;https://www.scopes100.com/post/july-19-destiny-in-dayton-dinner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Updated: Dec 9&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Dinner with the Cast and Crew &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Saturday. July 19. 2025, Immediately following the play &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Rhea County Courthouse lawn&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
BUY TICKETS&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
See a dramatization of the Scopes Trial in the courtroom where the trial was held in 1925. Destiny in Dayton adapts the trial transcript to an engrossing account of the trial, giving viewers an accurate picture of this duel of great men and great ideas. Following the show, enjoy a 1920s-themed Dinner with the Cast of Destiny in Dayton under tents on the courthouse lawn, in the shade of trees – some of which were there for the trial!
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Matzke</name></author><summary type="html">Nick Matzke at the Dayton County Courthouse where the Scopes Trial was held in 1925. (photo from ~2014) UPDATE, Dec. 22: I have now listed 52 separate events I found, including links and quotes of the summaries where available. Please contribute more in the comments! Merry Kitzmas to all! Today is the 19th anniversary of the Kitzmiller v. Dover Area School District trial, aka the Dover Panda Trial, held from September-November 2005, and decided on December 20, 2005. Next year, 2025, will be the 20th anniversary of Kitzmiller, as well as the 100th anniversary of Tennessee v. Scopes, aka the Scopes Monkey Trial. Stuck as I am, in Australia/New Zealand with 3 little kids, I expect I will have to follow events from afar. But I will use this thread to accumulate links &amp;amp; dates for relevant events as they come up. And please contribute ones you come across! I expect that many are glum about current politics and science, but I recall a similar feeling in 2004, and that Kitzmiller v. Dover was one of the early signs that committed citizens could move events in a pro-science direction. May 2025 be another such time! Summaries of events are posted below, with abstracts where available:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Eric Hedin, meet Granville Sewell</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/eric-hedin-meet-granville-sewell.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Eric Hedin, meet Granville Sewell" /><published>2024-12-11T22:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2024-12-11T22:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/eric-hedin-meet-granville-sewell</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/eric-hedin-meet-granville-sewell.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Nuucichthys.png&quot; alt=&quot;[An intermediate step]&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;One of the intermediate steps that Granville Sewell does not 
mention, and which Eric Hedin sort-of-knows occur.  (a), Reconstruction 
of a very early vertebrate, the fossil &lt;em&gt;Nuucichthys&lt;/em&gt;, which lived 
518 million years ago, with (b) its inferred position shown on the vertebrate phylogeny.  From &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; class=&quot;external free&quot; href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1098/rsos.240350&quot;&gt;a paper by Rudy Lerosey-Aubril &amp;amp; Javier Ortega-Hernández&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0&quot; title=&quot;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0&quot;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt; From Wikimedia.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Physicist Eric Hedin has posted to the Discovery Institute site 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2024/11/theres-a-limit-to-what-nature-can-do&quot;&gt;Evolution News on 27 November 2024&lt;/a&gt;
an argument that the processes of physics cannot 
account for intelligent life.  As he is a well-trained physicist (whose Ph.D. 
degree was from my university), and who has done experimental 
work on plasma physics, we can expect a mathematically sophisticated 
argument which would give us all pause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, here’s the guts of his argument, from the Evolution News post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In fact, for making anything other than large-scale conglomerations of matter (such as stars and planets), nature has only one tool in its bag — the electromagnetic force. This tool primarily manifests as the electric force, causing opposite charges (such as electrons and protons) to attract, and like charges to repel. It is completely indiscriminate, and cannot select between multiple options, preferring one charge over another, except for the rule that the bigger the charges and the closer the distance between them the stronger the resulting force. Can you imagine such blind, brute forces pulling together countless atoms of specific elements into the necessary configurations to result in a functioning laptop computer?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The “boundaries of science” refers to the common-sense conclusion that nature is limited in what it can produce to outcomes consistent with the laws and forces of nature. Natural processes are sought and found to be sufficient for natural phenomena, such as star formation or precipitation.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;However, attempting to naturally explain the origin of some things found within our universe comes into conflict with the boundaries of science. Positing a natural explanation for the origin of the universe itself, the origin of the specific suite of physical parameters finely tuned to allow life, the origin of life itself, and the origin of conscious, intelligent minds, all defy what we have discovered about the limits of natural processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And basically, that’s the argument.  Evolutionary biology does not pretend to address the origin of the universe, or the issue of fine-tuning in physics, and even the origin of life is outside its scope, though adjacent.  But somehow Hedin knows that physical forces cannot explain “the origin of conscious, 
intelligent minds”.   I wonder how he knows that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;meet-granville-sewell&quot;&gt;Meet Granville Sewell&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hedin’s argument is quite similar to Granville Sewell’s. Sewell asks (rhetorically) whether it is not implausible that advanced technology such as iPhones could have resulted from natural forces, which involve only random collisions of particles.   An example of his argument will be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2021/04/some-problems-can-be-proved-unsolvable/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, where he asks whether it is possible to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Explain how life could have originated and evolved into intelligent humans, through entirely natural (unintelligent) processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granville Sewell is a mathematician, who is Professor Emeritus in the Departrment of Mathematical Sciences at the University of Texas at El Paso.  He is a specialist in numerical solution of differential equations. Here is how he invokes physics to solve this problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Well, I have a very simple proof that the biological problem #3  [the one mentioned above] posed above is also impossible to solve, that does fit in the margin of this document. All one needs to do is realize that if a solution were found, we would have proved something obviously false, that a few (four, apparently) fundamental, unintelligent forces of physics alone could have rearranged the fundamental particles of physics into libraries full of science texts and encyclopedias, computers connected to monitors, keyboards, laser printers and the Internet, cars, trucks, airplanes, nuclear power plants and Apple iPhones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are from a 2021 post at Evolution News (which I linked to above). It should be obvious that Hedin’s and Sewell’s  arguments are similar, since they invoke physics.  They are also similar in lacking mathematical details, although elsewhere Sewell does present a partial differential equation for the simple diffusion of a chemical element outwards from an area of concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-sewell-has-left-out&quot;&gt;What Sewell has left out&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granville Sewell’s argument has been repeatedly promoted by him, in various versions.  In addition to the link in the previous section, examples of his advocacy will be found in blogs such as Evolution News and Uncommon Descent and in papers, book chapters and videos (here I take a deep breath)
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.utep.edu/faculty/sewell/articles/mathint.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.utep.edu/faculty/sewell/articles/open.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://spectator.org/47666_evolutions-thermodynamic-failure/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.utep.edu/faculty/sewell/AML_3497.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2012/02/looking_for_the/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/new-video-evolution-is-a-natural-process-running-backward-2/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://bio-complexity.org/ojs/index.php/main/article/view/BIO-C.2013.2/BIO-C.2013.2&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://dx.doi.org/10.1142/9789814508728_0007&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Beginning-Other-Essays-Intelligent-Design/dp/1936599279/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.utep.edu/faculty/sewell/articles/pe_sewell.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2018/05/i-believe-in-the-evolution-of-life-and-the-evolution-of-automobiles/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2018/08/who-is-doing-pseudoscience/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2018/11/why-evolution-and-reproduction-are-unnatural/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2019/05/two-schemes-to-defeat-the-second-law/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2020/01/how-science-lost-its-mind/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2020/06/new-video-why-evolution-is-different/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2020/10/my-failed-computer-simulation/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2022/01/the-underlying-principle-behind-the-second-law/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2022/06/three-realities-chance-cant-explain-that-intelligent-design-can/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2023/03/yes-extraordinary-claims-require-extraordinary-evidence-lets-hear-some-for-darwinian-evolution/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2023/07/in-summary-presenting-the-evidence-for-intelligent-design/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2023/08/how-the-supernatural-entered-science/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2024/03/life-and-the-underlying-principle-behind-the-second-law-of-thermodynamics/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2024/07/introduction-to-the-scientific-theory-of-intelligent-design/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I may have missed a few, but you get the idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granville Sewell’s argument has been commented on many times over the years. The late physicist Mark Perakh 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.talkreason.org/articles/sewell.cfm&quot;&gt;(here)&lt;/a&gt;, 
the mathematician Jason Rosenhouse &lt;a href=&quot;https://skepticalinquirer.org/exclusive/does-evolution-have-a-thermodynamics-problem/&quot;&gt;(here)&lt;/a&gt;, and physicist Dan Styer 
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.oberlin.edu/physics/dstyer/SandE/StyerRemarksOnSewellPE.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.oberlin.edu/physics/dstyer/SandE/ObviousImplausibility.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)
sternly criticized his assertions that evolution contradicts the Second Law of Thermodynamics.  Sewell has since 
quietly backed away from his original assertions about the Second Law of Thermodynamics, instead coming up 
with an ill-defined concept of “X-entropy”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His arguments have been 
commented on many times here.  I have posted a number of times at Panda’s Thumb and at The Skeptical Zone 
(&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2010/02/evidence-that-t.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2011/02/granville-sewel.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2011/11/granville-sewel-1.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/Granville-Sewell-thinks-its-obvious.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
and &lt;a href=&quot;http://theskepticalzone.com/wp/what-is-obvious-to-granville-sewell/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my 2021 post (the fourth one above), I noted that the processes 
that Sewell thinks that the “rearrangement” of fundamental particles includes quite 
a few steps that we generally don’t attribute to Design Intervention, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Elementary particles aggregating to form larger particles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Those particles forming atoms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Atoms becoming connected by bonds to form chemicals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Chemicals interacting to form cosmic dust&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Cosmic dust forming clouds by the attraction of gravity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Gravity in dust clouds leading to clumps that become a solar system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; ... including the formation of a star and planets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Lots of geology (steps omitted)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; An early Earth with interesting organic chemicals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Origin of life&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Evolution of protists and single-celled eukaryotes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Evolution of multicellular life&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Evolution of people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; People producing tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; People producing agriculture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; and civilization,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; and technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include processes of physics, astronomy, geology, and chemistry.  Those are fields that get 
along fine without any Design Intervention.  Likewise we know people can produce agriculture, 
civilization, and technology.  That’s already an awful lot of Granville Sewell’s process of “particles 
rearranging themselves”.  There are numerous parts of the evolution of life (and the origin of life) 
that ID advocates dispute, but much of their concentration is on two of the list items, the 
origin of life and the evolution of humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hedin-compared-to-sewell&quot;&gt;Hedin compared to Sewell&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Hedin faces similar issues, but is more cautious in his assertions.    He focuses on fine-tuning arguments, which are outside of the domain of evolutionary biology, but also on the origin of life and on the origin of conscious, 
intelligent minds.   Hedin has written many posts on Evolution News (for a list of them see &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/author/ehedin/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).  In &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2023/05/is-life-an-information-ratchet/&quot;&gt;one of the earlier ones&lt;/a&gt; last year, he argued that a conservation-of-information argument showed that an evolving species could not gain specified information.  I disputed this 
in &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/08/Hedin-information-principle.html&quot;&gt;a post here at Panda’s Thumb&lt;/a&gt;.  Reading Hedin’s post closely, it could be seen that while he didn’t think it was possible for evolving organisms to 
produce “novel complex functionality”, he did acknowledge that natural selection can accumulate information:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But what can this “ratchet” do? No more than it was designed to do — namely to reproduce daughter organisms according to its inherent mechanism of reproduction. Variations in the organism’s genome, by any unguided process, may lead to an increase in fitness and therefore survivability. But natural processes cannot produce unnatural results. Selection based on the ratchet mechanism of increased fitness cannot of itself produce novel complex functionality if each successive small change does not give some increased advantage towards survival and reproduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while Granville Sewell implies, without proof, that accumulation of favorable mutants by natural selection is a thermodynamic impossibility, Eric Hedin acknowledges that it is a possibility.  He confines his objections to “novel, complex functionality”.  The chief example he gives of this is the origin of a conscious, intelligent “mind”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;intelligent-brains--or-minds&quot;&gt;Intelligent brains?  Or “minds”?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to be careful here.  It is tempting to think that Hedin is describing conscious, intelligent &lt;em&gt;brains&lt;/em&gt;.  After all, our mind is just stuff that happens in our brains, isn’t it?  In Hedin’s terminology, “mind” is quite distinct from the mere activity of the brain.  Hedin is a dualist, in that he thinks that our brain exists in the real world, while our “mind” exists in a spiritual world (see an article of his &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2024/04/mind-matter-and-intelligent-design/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no understanding of how minds might evolve in a spiritual world, so I am going to discuss only brains, under the assumption – or perhaps the delusion – that we should think about the evolution of brains, and leave the issue of “mind” to those who understand things spiritual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;can-brains-evolve-to-get-smarter-more-conscious&quot;&gt;Can brains evolve to get smarter? More conscious?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can brains get better at thinking?  They certainly vary from species to species in the ability to think.  In their simplest forms they can’t do very much thinking.   That’s where the image at the start of this article becomes relevant.  It shows &lt;em&gt;Nuucichthys&lt;/em&gt;, a recently-discovered early vertebrate, from the early Cambrian.  It has eyes near its front, and it is quite a good assumption that they connect to a primitive brain.  Given that bigger brains are needed to have more intelligent behavior, there is really no reason to imagine a barrier to the evolution of more intelligence by ordinary evolutionary processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what about consciousness?  We usually think about consciousness in terms of conscious behavior of humans, contemplating beauty, morality, and mortality.  All very lofty and difficult.  But if we take an evolutionary view of it, 
we can ask whether much earlier species could show the basics of consciousness.  If a mouse is looking at its surroundings and is able to have some representation of them, a representation that includes itself, then if it can 
choose a route for itself to its burrow, that seems to me to be an early form of consciousness.  “Let’s see, 
if I am &lt;em&gt;there&lt;/em&gt; and the bush is &lt;em&gt;there&lt;/em&gt; and the log is &lt;em&gt;there&lt;/em&gt;, and my burrow is behind the tree, then I should go 
to the left of the bush, over the log, and to the right of the tree, and there will be the burrow.”  The mouse is making a representation of its environment which includes a representation of itself, viewed from outside.  From there, more elaborate forms of consciousness could, I think, evolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there is, in fact, evidence of such a map of the surroundings in the brains of rats.   See, for example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hhmi.org/news/uncovering-the-neural-basis-for-hypothetical-thinking-in-rats&quot;&gt;this report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If any of this makes sense then there is no reason to suppose that there is some barrier to the evolution of conscious, intelligent brains.  In which case Eric Hedin’s argument boils down to simple incredulity, without any logical proof of a barrier to evolution by ordinary evolutionary processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is where Granville Sewell’s argument ended up, too.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">One of the intermediate steps that Granville Sewell does not mention, and which Eric Hedin sort-of-knows occur. (a), Reconstruction of a very early vertebrate, the fossil Nuucichthys, which lived 518 million years ago, with (b) its inferred position shown on the vertebrate phylogeny. From a paper by Rudy Lerosey-Aubril &amp;amp; Javier Ortega-Hernández, CC BY 4.0 From Wikimedia. &amp;nbsp; Physicist Eric Hedin has posted to the Discovery Institute site Evolution News on 27 November 2024 an argument that the processes of physics cannot account for intelligent life. As he is a well-trained physicist (whose Ph.D. degree was from my university), and who has done experimental work on plasma physics, we can expect a mathematically sophisticated argument which would give us all pause. Well, here’s the guts of his argument, from the Evolution News post: In fact, for making anything other than large-scale conglomerations of matter (such as stars and planets), nature has only one tool in its bag — the electromagnetic force. This tool primarily manifests as the electric force, causing opposite charges (such as electrons and protons) to attract, and like charges to repel. It is completely indiscriminate, and cannot select between multiple options, preferring one charge over another, except for the rule that the bigger the charges and the closer the distance between them the stronger the resulting force. Can you imagine such blind, brute forces pulling together countless atoms of specific elements into the necessary configurations to result in a functioning laptop computer? and The “boundaries of science” refers to the common-sense conclusion that nature is limited in what it can produce to outcomes consistent with the laws and forces of nature. Natural processes are sought and found to be sufficient for natural phenomena, such as star formation or precipitation. However, attempting to naturally explain the origin of some things found within our universe comes into conflict with the boundaries of science. Positing a natural explanation for the origin of the universe itself, the origin of the specific suite of physical parameters finely tuned to allow life, the origin of life itself, and the origin of conscious, intelligent minds, all defy what we have discovered about the limits of natural processes. And basically, that’s the argument. Evolutionary biology does not pretend to address the origin of the universe, or the issue of fine-tuning in physics, and even the origin of life is outside its scope, though adjacent. But somehow Hedin knows that physical forces cannot explain “the origin of conscious, intelligent minds”. I wonder how he knows that.</summary></entry></feed>