<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-01-29T02:21:50-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Are cephalopods better designed than humans?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/cephalopods-better-designed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are cephalopods better designed than humans?" /><published>2023-01-23T08:42:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-01-23T08:42:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/cephalopods-better-designed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/cephalopods-better-designed.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Leopard_Tapetum_Keven_Law_Wikimedia_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reflections in eyes of leopard&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Amur leopard (not a cephalopod), showing retroreflection from tapetum. &lt;small&gt;Colchester Zoo, Monday, November 19, 2007. &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Amur_leopard_by_Keven_Law.jpg&quot;&gt;Photograph&lt;/a&gt; by Keven Law. Wikimedia Commons, CC BY-SA 2.0.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to the titular question depends on what you think they are designed for; hence, it seems to be a silly question. When it comes to the eyes, however, there is little doubt: human (and other vertebrate) retinas are in backward in that nerves, blood vessels, and other structures are piled on top of the photoreceptors and thus reduce sensitivity, if not resolution. Additionally, the nerves go out through a hole in the retina, which makes us susceptible to glaucoma. Cephalopod retinas, by contrast, face forward, with nothing covering the photoreceptors, and the nerves do not have to pass through a hole in the retina. Cephalopod eyes are thus clearly better designed than human eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I raise this question by way of introducing an article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://skepticalinquirer.org/2022/12/the-night-begins-to-shine-the-tapetum-lucidum-and-our-backward-retinas/&quot;&gt;The night begins to shine: The tapetum lucidum and our backward retinas&lt;/a&gt;, by Nathan H. Lents, in the January-February issue of &lt;i&gt;Skeptical Inquirer&lt;/i&gt;. The tapetum lucidum, or just tapetum, is a reflective membrane in the retinas of many nocturnal vertebrates and is located just behind the photoreceptors. Its purpose is presumedly to direct the light that the photoreceptors miss back into them and thereby increase the sensitivity. Interestingly, tapetums composed of many different materials appear to have evolved many different times in different creatures. Cephalopods have no tapetum, presumably because their retinas face forward, with the photoreceptors directly facing the light. Prof. Lents explains all this and more in great but easily understandable detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please forgive a physicist’s digression. I once lost a debate as to whether the retina is in backward or not. It is in backward. (In most anatomical drawings, however, the cones appear at least vaguely conical, with the open end facing the incoming light. Thus, the cones themselves are not exactly in backward.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At night, we are presumably dealing with rod (scotopic) vision, and the rods supposedly trap light due to total internal reflection. If that is so, then the law of refraction prohibits light traveling in the opposite direction (toward the light source) from getting into the rod. How then is the tapetum helpful?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot immediately find an answer to this question, so I will stick my neck out and suggest that the evanescent wave penetrates the rod and is absorbed by the dyes in the rod, similarly to frustrated total internal reflection. If that is so, then it is hard to see how the tapetum can be very effective, but I guess every little bit counts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/strong&gt;. Thanks to Nathan Lents for discovering what I can only call a silly mistake and to Steven Fliesler of the school of medicine of the University of Buffalo for interesting comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Amur leopard (not a cephalopod), showing retroreflection from tapetum. Colchester Zoo, Monday, November 19, 2007. Photograph by Keven Law. Wikimedia Commons, CC BY-SA 2.0. The answer to the titular question depends on what you think they are designed for; hence, it seems to be a silly question. When it comes to the eyes, however, there is little doubt: human (and other vertebrate) retinas are in backward in that nerves, blood vessels, and other structures are piled on top of the photoreceptors and thus reduce sensitivity, if not resolution. Additionally, the nerves go out through a hole in the retina, which makes us susceptible to glaucoma. Cephalopod retinas, by contrast, face forward, with nothing covering the photoreceptors, and the nerves do not have to pass through a hole in the retina. Cephalopod eyes are thus clearly better designed than human eyes. I raise this question by way of introducing an article, The night begins to shine: The tapetum lucidum and our backward retinas, by Nathan H. Lents, in the January-February issue of Skeptical Inquirer. The tapetum lucidum, or just tapetum, is a reflective membrane in the retinas of many nocturnal vertebrates and is located just behind the photoreceptors. Its purpose is presumedly to direct the light that the photoreceptors miss back into them and thereby increase the sensitivity. Interestingly, tapetums composed of many different materials appear to have evolved many different times in different creatures. Cephalopods have no tapetum, presumably because their retinas face forward, with the photoreceptors directly facing the light. Prof. Lents explains all this and more in great but easily understandable detail.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ken Ham Using Creation Museum for Kentucky Politics</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/ken-ham-using.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ken Ham Using Creation Museum for Kentucky Politics" /><published>2023-01-20T09:45:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-01-20T09:45:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/ken-ham-using</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/ken-ham-using.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Phelps_501c3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;IRS brochure&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;, January 28, 2023, 3:30 p.m., MST. A version of this post appeared in the Lexington (Kentucky) Herald-Leader under the head &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kentucky.com/opinion/op-ed/article271570602.html&quot;&gt;Creation Museum to host anti-abortion event with extremist pastor, Ky legislators | Opinion&lt;/a&gt;. Mark Looy replied under the head &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kentucky.com/opinion/letters-to-the-editor/article271724962.html &quot;&gt;Abortion clarification&lt;/a&gt;. You may see the text of his letter in &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/ken-ham-using.html#comment-6101095162&quot;&gt;Comment 6101095162&lt;/a&gt;. Mr. Phelps replies there that Mr. Looy’s reply “seems to concede what I said, but tries to obfuscate. He admits that the legislation would cause women that have abortions be charged with murder and that Pastor Jeff Durbin advocates the death penalty.”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ken Ham and Answers in Genesis (AiG), along with &lt;a href=&quot;https://metro.co.uk/2017/02/27/hipster-says-he-wants-to-execute-women-who-have-abortions-6475717/&quot;&gt;the extremist Jeff Durbin&lt;/a&gt; of Arizona’s Apologia Church, are hosting a political event for pastors at the Creation Museum to support &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5lyiv2zQr6k&quot;&gt;pending Kentucky anti-abortion legislation&lt;/a&gt;.  To my knowledge &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.legislature.ky.gov/record/23rs/index_headings.html&quot;&gt;this legislation has not yet been introduced&lt;/a&gt; as of January 18. The rally is also advertised on January 18, AiG’s weekly “Answers News”, near the end of the show (&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/AUkCdwY6LVs&quot;&gt;about 34 minutes in&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in March 2007, when the Creation Museum was about to open, AiG’s Mark Looy and Ken Ham penned a post to their website titled “&lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/world-religions/humanism/goose-stepping-to-zion/&quot;&gt;Goose-stepping to Zion&lt;/a&gt;.”    This essay claims AiG is “apolitical” and states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although Hedges insinuates that the creation movement (especially AiG, for he spends most of his chapter on us) is a major part of America’s religious right and its fascist tendencies, AiG is apolitical. It avoids the political arena. It’s not our job to change the culture—it’s our job to disseminate information, proclaim the gospel, and stand on the authority of God’s Word … and THEN see hearts changed for the Lord.&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;p&gt;Now, if these changed lives impact the culture, and if God blesses that, then we’re happy to see it. But we’re not going to be an activist ministry in the sense of legislating, litigating or lobbying key leaders to mandate change in society.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, policy on politicking has changed for AiG since 2007. Last October AiG had an “Answers for Pastors” meeting at the Ark Encounter featuring White Christian Nationalist Tony Perkins of the Family Research Council. I reported on this on the Panda’s Thumb &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/09/extreme-right-wing-Christian-nationalist.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this upcoming political rally for pastors supporting specific legislation is particularly disturbing, and not because it is about abortion. This event indicates Ham/AiG are becoming more overtly involved in Kentucky politics. Will Kentuckians see AiG become more involved in a multitude of political issues? Will AiG begin to endorse political candidates? AiG’s 501(c)(3) religious non-profit status may preclude such activities, but the IRS has generally been lax in its enforcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be interesting to see which state legislators, candidates for governor, and other politicians attend the Creation Museum rally. The separation of church and state in Kentucky looks weak at this writing. Meanwhile, AiG’s influence in Kentucky, political and otherwise, continues to grow.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Update, January 28, 2023, 3:30 p.m., MST. A version of this post appeared in the Lexington (Kentucky) Herald-Leader under the head Creation Museum to host anti-abortion event with extremist pastor, Ky legislators | Opinion. Mark Looy replied under the head Abortion clarification. You may see the text of his letter in Comment 6101095162. Mr. Phelps replies there that Mr. Looy’s reply “seems to concede what I said, but tries to obfuscate. He admits that the legislation would cause women that have abortions be charged with murder and that Pastor Jeff Durbin advocates the death penalty.” Ken Ham and Answers in Genesis (AiG), along with the extremist Jeff Durbin of Arizona’s Apologia Church, are hosting a political event for pastors at the Creation Museum to support pending Kentucky anti-abortion legislation. To my knowledge this legislation has not yet been introduced as of January 18. The rally is also advertised on January 18, AiG’s weekly “Answers News”, near the end of the show (about 34 minutes in). Back in March 2007, when the Creation Museum was about to open, AiG’s Mark Looy and Ken Ham penned a post to their website titled “Goose-stepping to Zion.” This essay claims AiG is “apolitical” and states:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Trioceros jacksonii</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/Trioceros-jacksonii.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trioceros jacksonii" /><published>2023-01-16T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-01-16T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/Trioceros%20jacksonii</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/Trioceros-jacksonii.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Mark Sturtevant&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photogrphy Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Sturtevant.Jacksons_Chameleon.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Chameleon&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Trioceros jacksonii&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; Jackson’s chameleon. Dr. Sturtevant writes, &quot;The Hawaiian islands harbor many unique species of plants and animals that have evolved there while in isolation. But of course humans have introduced many non-native species to the islands, and these foreigners come from around the world. This large chameleon was found along a forested path on Maui, and is one of many species of chameleons that thrive on the islands after having been introduced there through the pet trade and general human stupidity. This large chameleon is quite capable of swallowing baby birds that are in the nest, and so it is a threat to the native birds.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Mark Sturtevant. Photogrphy Contest, Honorable Mention. Trioceros jacksonii &amp;ndash; Jackson’s chameleon. Dr. Sturtevant writes, &quot;The Hawaiian islands harbor many unique species of plants and animals that have evolved there while in isolation. But of course humans have introduced many non-native species to the islands, and these foreigners come from around the world. This large chameleon was found along a forested path on Maui, and is one of many species of chameleons that thrive on the islands after having been introduced there through the pet trade and general human stupidity. This large chameleon is quite capable of swallowing baby birds that are in the nest, and so it is a threat to the native birds.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Another Impressive Year for Creationist Journal BIO-Complexity [sic]</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/impressive-year-creationist-journal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Another Impressive Year for Creationist Journal BIO-Complexity [sic]" /><published>2023-01-05T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-01-05T10:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/impressive-year-creationist-journal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/impressive-year-creationist-journal.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Lents_Evolution_Foot.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lateral view of ankle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;The foot and ankle of the chimpanzee (A) and human (B). T: axis of transverse tarsal joint; U: axis of upper ankle joint; L: axis of lower ankle joint.  Note: All bones are conserved and homologous. &lt;small&gt;Credit: Elftman, H., &amp;amp; Manter, J. (1935). The evolution of the human foot, with especial reference to the joints. Journal of anatomy, 70(Pt 1), 56.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new article has been published in the illustrious journal &lt;i&gt;BIO-Complexity&lt;/i&gt; [sic]:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Burgess, S. (2022). &lt;a href=&quot;https://bio-complexity.org/ojs/index.php/main/article/view/BIO-C.2022.3&quot;&gt;Why the Ankle-Foot Complex Is a Masterpiece of Engineering and a Rebuttal of “Bad Design” Arguments&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;i&gt;BIO-Complexity&lt;/i&gt;, 2022.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those not familiar with it, &lt;i&gt;BIO-Complexity&lt;/i&gt; [sic] is a journal dedicated to publishing work from the Intelligent Design creationist community. Frustrated by their almost completely futile efforts to get their work or ideas published in peer-reviewed scientific journals, intelligent design proponents took to creating their own journal in 2010 with Douglas Axe as the founding editor-in-chief. Axe was also head of the Biologic Institute, the only research institute dedicated to intelligent design creationism, and the publisher of &lt;i&gt;BIO-Complexity&lt;/i&gt; [sic]. The institute &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/biologic-institute-closes.html&quot;&gt;has now closed&lt;/a&gt;. No word yet on what will happen with the journal, but I imagine &lt;a href=&quot;https://arstechnica.com/science/2012/12/inteliigent-design-think-tanks-institute-is-a-shutterstock-image/&quot;&gt;the green screen&lt;/a&gt; has been repurposed. You can read more about the history of the journal &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/latest-intelligent-design-journal&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;BIO-Complexity&lt;/i&gt; [sic] and The Biologic Institute (and Axe himself to a certain extent), are all funded by the Discovery Institute, the organizing body of the intelligent design creationist movement, which probably needs no introduction to the readers of Panda’s Thumb. But in case you’ve just crawled out of the Olduvai Gorge, you can read about it &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Discovery_Institute&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new article on the human ankle by Stuart Burgess perfectly aligns with the grand traditions of &lt;i&gt;BIO-Complexity&lt;/i&gt; [sic]:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;This is just the third and final article published in in the journal &lt;a href=&quot;https://bio-complexity.org/ojs/index.php/main/issue/view/36&quot;&gt;in all of 2022&lt;/a&gt;. Their original ambitious goal was one article per month (lol), but they have yet to exceed four articles in any calendar year. In 2017, they published just one manuscript in the &quot;research article&quot; category and one &quot;critical review.&quot; This year, the three published articles are in the &quot;critical focus&quot; category, meaning they did not publish a single “research article” in 2022.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;li&gt;The article above was written by someone who is also on &lt;a href=&quot;https://bio-complexity.org/ojs/index.php/main/about/editorialTeam&quot;&gt;the editorial board&lt;/a&gt; of the journal. In fact, nearly all of the contributing authors in the history of the journal are also editors and most are also Discovery Institute fellows or contributors. In 2010-2011, the journal published a total of seven articles across all article types, four of them co-authored by editor-in-chief Douglas Axe. Of course, it is not unheard of that a journal &lt;i&gt;occasionally&lt;/i&gt; publishes original work by someone on the editorial board, but this practice is usually kept to a minimum for obvious reasons.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;li&gt;2022 was exceptional, however, because the three articles published in &lt;i&gt;BIO-Complexity&lt;/i&gt; [sic] are all by different authors! In most years, to reach the impressive feat of 3 or 4 articles, they publish multiple articles from the same author or team of authors, essentially by cutting articles into pieces. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://bio-complexity.org/ojs/index.php/main/issue/view/35&quot;&gt;the entire published work of the journal in 2021&lt;/a&gt; is three articles, all by the same author, with titles ending in &quot;part 1,&quot; &quot;part 2,&quot; and &quot;part 3.&quot; In the year before that, two of the four published articles were by the same trio of authors and cover the same topic. The exact same was true for 2016.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;li&gt;The reason the article above caught my attention is that it is written as a rebuttal to a few paragraphs in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehumanevolutionblog.com/book-human-errors/&quot;&gt;2018 popular science book &lt;i&gt;Human Errors&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I am mentioned by name 19 times (20 if you count the reference list), including in the abstract and in one of the section headings. I am most flattered by this continued attention, but it is not exactly in keeping with the standards and customs of academic science. Scientific data and ideas generally stand on their own and are offered on their own terms. While debates and rebuttals are also part of science, and I have been involved in some of those as well, they are never structured as a debate between persons, especially in the published literature. This article reads more like a blog post.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://bio-complexity.org/ojs/index.php/main/article/view/BIO-C.2022.3&quot;&gt;article itself&lt;/a&gt; is simply a summary of the structure and function of the human ankle, which can be summed up by saying the ankle is incredibly complex and good at what it does (notwithstanding the strains and sprains we all get). Somehow, this is offered as evidence against evolution and for intelligent design. Please feel free to read the article itself and comment below if you find any evidence against the notion that the human ankle is the product of standard evolutionary forces. I didn't.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the contrary, in the words of fellow Panda’s Thumb contributor Anj Petto, an expert in functional morphology, “There is not a single aspect of the ankle that I can think of that exists in anticipation of the needs for the particular combination of stability, strength, and flexibility that bipedal striding requires. All of the pieces exist in the generalized primate foot, and there is a series of changes in the foot among the hominins (certainly from &lt;i&gt;Ardipithecus&lt;/i&gt; forward) that show transitional features that reduce the muscle activity required to walking on 2 legs so that in the modern human ankle (foot, knee, hips, and lower back, as well) the skeletal system (bones, joints, cartilage, and ligaments) are supporting the upright posture so that the muscles are mostly used for propulsion rather than for supporting the upright posture.” This latter item is among the points I was making in &lt;i&gt;Human Errors&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;Burgess does a fine job explaining the structure and function of the human ankle, but for some reason takes its functioning as evidence that it was intentionally designed and not evolved. The human body is truly impressive, a point I repeatedly made in &lt;i&gt;Human Errors&lt;/i&gt;, but it also harbors abundant evidence of its long evolutionary past including, in my opinion, some examples of suboptimal functional design that are only comprehensible in the light of the limitations of evolutionary processes and our shared ancestry with other animals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I have no idea why they chose to hyphenate (and weirdly capitalize) &lt;i&gt;BIO-Complexity&lt;/i&gt; [sic] when the perfectly serviceable word &lt;i&gt;Biocomplexity&lt;/i&gt; already exists, sans hyphen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Nathan Lents is Professor of Biology at the John Jay College of Criminal Justice and author, most recently, of the book &lt;/i&gt;Human Errors: A Panorama of Our Defects, from Broken Genes to Pointless Bones&lt;i&gt;, and many technical articles.  He blogs at The Human Evolution Blog and Psychology Today.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Lents</name></author><summary type="html">The foot and ankle of the chimpanzee (A) and human (B). T: axis of transverse tarsal joint; U: axis of upper ankle joint; L: axis of lower ankle joint. Note: All bones are conserved and homologous. Credit: Elftman, H., &amp;amp; Manter, J. (1935). The evolution of the human foot, with especial reference to the joints. Journal of anatomy, 70(Pt 1), 56. A new article has been published in the illustrious journal BIO-Complexity [sic]: Burgess, S. (2022). Why the Ankle-Foot Complex Is a Masterpiece of Engineering and a Rebuttal of “Bad Design” Arguments. BIO-Complexity, 2022. For those not familiar with it, BIO-Complexity [sic] is a journal dedicated to publishing work from the Intelligent Design creationist community. Frustrated by their almost completely futile efforts to get their work or ideas published in peer-reviewed scientific journals, intelligent design proponents took to creating their own journal in 2010 with Douglas Axe as the founding editor-in-chief. Axe was also head of the Biologic Institute, the only research institute dedicated to intelligent design creationism, and the publisher of BIO-Complexity [sic]. The institute has now closed. No word yet on what will happen with the journal, but I imagine the green screen has been repurposed. You can read more about the history of the journal here. BIO-Complexity [sic] and The Biologic Institute (and Axe himself to a certain extent), are all funded by the Discovery Institute, the organizing body of the intelligent design creationist movement, which probably needs no introduction to the readers of Panda’s Thumb. But in case you’ve just crawled out of the Olduvai Gorge, you can read about it here. The new article on the human ankle by Stuart Burgess perfectly aligns with the grand traditions of BIO-Complexity [sic]:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pandas, Kitzmiller, and the frozen frog fallacy</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/Pandas-and-Frogs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pandas, Kitzmiller, and the frozen frog fallacy" /><published>2023-01-04T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-01-04T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/Pandas-and-Frogs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/Pandas-and-Frogs.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Paul Braterman is Professor Emeritus at the University of North Texas and Honorary Senior Research Fellow in Chemistry at the University of Glasgow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/PandasCover001.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cover of &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Of Pandas and People&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Cover of &lt;em&gt;Of Pandas and People&lt;/em&gt;, Second edition. Fair use claimed.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Kitzmas was different. For the first time, the Discovery Institute allowed the anniversary of 
Kitzmiller v. Dover Area School District to pass without complaining about the verdict. Perhaps 
they are hoping that we will forget about the incredible badness of the text that they were 
trying to foist on the District’s students. &lt;em&gt;Of Pandas and People&lt;/em&gt; is carefully constructed to 
be as misleading as possible, and we shouldn’t let them forget this, as long as contributors 
and advisers responsible for it remain in position within the Discovery Institute&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;, while 
the Institute continues to promote  works such as Denton’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discovery.org/v/legacy-of-evolution/?hilite=theory+crisis&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evolution – A Theory in Crisis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 
that perpetuate the same elementary errors of logic.  But first, an apparent digression.  When 
students first come across the use of molecular or DNA sequencing in constructing phylogenetic 
trees, they are sometimes puzzled. They have been told that mammals are descended from fish by 
way of amphibians. Therefore, as a matter of common sense, they might expect that frogs should 
be closer to fish in evolutionary terms than we are. This is another example of the Evolution 
as Progress error. While amniotes have progressed through synapsid to mammal to humans, the 
pinnacle of creation, the frog has remained a lowly frog and should, therefore, be closer to 
the common ancestor, as if the ineluctable processes of molecular mutation had somehow been 
suspended.  We might call this the “frozen frog fallacy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, a Table like the one shown below might help:
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/PandasTable1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Table of cytochrome c differences&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Table of cytochrome c differences, from &lt;em&gt;Of Pandas and People&lt;/em&gt;, Second edition. Fair use claimed.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the multicellular organisms shown are, apart from small random fluctuations, at the same distance from the bacterium, as expected if they share a common ancestor distinct from bacteria, which have of course, independently, been accumulating their own set of changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the animals shown are, apart from small random fluctuations, at the same distance from wheat, as expected if they share a common ancestor distinct from plants. And the relative number of mutations shows that the split between plants and animals is more recent than the split between multicellular organisms and bacteria. More recent yet is the split between fish and tetrapods, leaving all tetrapods (including you and me, and of course present-day frogs) at the same distance from the fish. And so on. Most tellingly, humans share a common ancestor with monkeys, more recent than their common ancestor with non-simian mammals. There is a lot more detail in the Table, for example about how to birds relate to reptiles, and how the different orders of mammal relate to each other. And of course the construction of a phylogenetic tree is based on the specific differences found, rather than the overall number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are now numerous published studies of the phylogenetic relationships revealed by Cytochrome C, to say nothing of the vast recent literature using numerous molecular and morphological traits to develop detailed high-resolution phylogenies, and to explore the limitations of the concept of a unique phylogeny. What is interesting about the particular Table I have quoted is its origin, and the uses that its authors make of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us back to our original theme. The Table actually comes from Of Pandas and People, 2nd edition, 1993, which by the time of the trial had gone through five printings. The book does not give a reference to the source of the data, but much (not all) of the information can be found in a classic 1967 paper [2], which also explains the reasoning behind the method, and critically examines the assumptions made. So there is no excuse for what the book does next, which is to repeatedly assert that the data refute claims of common ancestry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;one might expect analysis to reveal that the cytochromes in fish are most similar to the cytochromes in amphibians. But this is not the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To use the classic Darwinian scenario, amphibians are intermediate between fish and the other band-dwelling invertebrates. Analysis of their amino acids should place amphibians in an approximately intermediate position, but it does not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note the use of Darwin’s name to denote the whole of evolution. In fact, the book is obsessed with Darwin, mentioning him on almost every page, and on some pages up to 10 times. In fact, by my count, and I may have missed a few, Darwin’s name or some variant of it occurs 262 times within the 144 pages of text. This emphasis on Darwin is of course found throughout the whole of the creationist literature, although by now evolutionary theory is almost as different from what Darwin proposed as atomic theory is from that proposed by Democritus.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just two of five separate reiterations of the fallacy, leading up to the extraordinary statement that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Based upon the evolutionary series, we should expect some amphibians to be closer to fish (“primitive” species) and others to be closer to reptiles (“advanced” species).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to make sure that the message sticks, we have this Figure, with the plain implication that the data point, not to evolution, but to separate creation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/PandasFig9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 9 from &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Of Pandas and People&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Figure 9 from &lt;em&gt;Of Pandas and People&lt;/em&gt;, Second Edition. Fair use claimed.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fallacy is not merely being stated; it is being repeated, rationalised, and reinforced. The kindest explanation is that the authors simply do not understand the science that they are presenting, seeing a hierarchical structure where none exists, and imposing on their biology a perspective in terms of “higher” and “lower” which do not belong in modern science, but have been carried over, such as the power of human vanity, from a worldview more akin to Aristotle and the mediaeval Great Chain of Being. The same fallacy also occurs in Michael Denton’s 1985 Evolution - A Theory in Crisis, and while he had by 1998 [3] quietly walked away from this, his 2016 sequel, Evolution – Still a Theory in Crisis, retains his preference for Aristotelian over phylogenetic classification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And why should this matter? Because it reminds us, and we should not forget, that the Discovery Institute does not only deal in dis-information, but in dis-education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thank Maarten Boudry, Glenn Branch, Joe Felsenstein, John Harshman, Kim Johnson, Larry Moran, and Massimo Pigliucci for helpful comments and links to the literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;footnotes-and-citations&quot;&gt;Footnotes and citations:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(1) Dean Kenyon (co-author), Charles Thaxton (Academic Editor), and Stephen Meyer, Michael Behe, and Nancy Pearcey (contributors) all hold positions at the Discovery Institute, as do Raymond Bohlin, Walter Bradley, Robert Kaita, J.P. Moreland, and Paul Nelson, who are on the list of those thanked for being “critical reviewers”, as, also, are Meyer and Behe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(2) Walter M Fitch and Emanuel Margoliash, &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; 155(3760), 279, 1967; DOI: 10.1126/science.155.3760.279&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(3) For a discussion of Denton’s revised position, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandwalk.blogspot.com/2006/12/michael-denton-and-molecular-clocks.html&quot;&gt;this 2006 post at Larry Moran’s &lt;em&gt;Sandwalk&lt;/em&gt; blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman</name></author><summary type="html">Paul Braterman is Professor Emeritus at the University of North Texas and Honorary Senior Research Fellow in Chemistry at the University of Glasgow Cover of Of Pandas and People, Second edition. Fair use claimed. &amp;nbsp; This Kitzmas was different. For the first time, the Discovery Institute allowed the anniversary of Kitzmiller v. Dover Area School District to pass without complaining about the verdict. Perhaps they are hoping that we will forget about the incredible badness of the text that they were trying to foist on the District’s students. Of Pandas and People is carefully constructed to be as misleading as possible, and we shouldn’t let them forget this, as long as contributors and advisers responsible for it remain in position within the Discovery Institute1, while the Institute continues to promote works such as Denton’s Evolution – A Theory in Crisis, that perpetuate the same elementary errors of logic. But first, an apparent digression. When students first come across the use of molecular or DNA sequencing in constructing phylogenetic trees, they are sometimes puzzled. They have been told that mammals are descended from fish by way of amphibians. Therefore, as a matter of common sense, they might expect that frogs should be closer to fish in evolutionary terms than we are. This is another example of the Evolution as Progress error. While amniotes have progressed through synapsid to mammal to humans, the pinnacle of creation, the frog has remained a lowly frog and should, therefore, be closer to the common ancestor, as if the ineluctable processes of molecular mutation had somehow been suspended. We might call this the “frozen frog fallacy.” At this point, a Table like the one shown below might help:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breakthroughs of 2022</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/breakthroughs-of-2022.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breakthroughs of 2022" /><published>2023-01-02T15:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-01-02T15:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/breakthroughs-of-2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/breakthroughs-of-2022.html">&lt;p&gt;I consider a miracle to be something that I understand in some detail and know it is impossible, yet there it is in my hand for $200 – a digital camera, for example. I do not understand the James Webb Space Telescope in nearly as much detail, but I still consider it a miracle. &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; may not agree with my definition of a miracle, but they consider the telescope the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/breakthrough-2022&quot;&gt;Breakthrough of the Year&lt;/a&gt;. Hard to argue with: the telescope itself is absolutely remarkable, as are some of the images it has returned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;’s runners-up include perennial rice, the new-found creativity of artificial intelligence, deflection of an asteroid, two advances in virology – a nascent RSV vaccine and the discovery that multiple sclerosis is caused by a virus – and several others. What they call “Breakdowns” are fewer: the fact that zero Covid no longer works (if it ever did), the fact that science ties between nations are “fraying,” and the increase in CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; emissions owing to the war in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers in Genesis posted a &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/science/year-review-top-science-news-2022/&quot;&gt;Year in Review&lt;/a&gt;, by Troy Lacey, which they arranged chronologically by month, rather than in order of importance. A few comments below the fold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their subhead reads, “From Giant Millipedes to Giant Pterosaurs, Looking Back at 2022 Science Stories.” Odd choices to highlight, I thought, and not a single mention of the James Webb Space Telescope. Perhaps they are afraid that it will demonstrate once and for all that the firmament is not a hammered-metal dome covering the earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They cite an article by Rob Webb, which discusses “rocket science through a biblical worldview” and include the following quotation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;… Rocket Rob points out that precision, predictability, and order are all necessary for rocket science to work, and yet these things are unexplainable in a purely materialistic atheistic worldview. As Rob explained, “We expect the universe to be organized and to consistently obey the natural laws that make rocket science possible.” &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not the foggiest idea why an atheist [read: anyone who is not a biblical literalist à la Ken Ham] would not expect the universe to obey natural laws; indeed, it seems to me that biblical literalists who invoke miracles are the ones who do not expect the universe to necessarily obey natural laws.  Another odd comment discusses the not particularly new observation that Venus is not hospitable to life and notes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; Scripture doesn’t indicate that God assigned life forms on any planet or moon in the universe other than Earth. Venus would naturally be very different from Earth because it was prepared for a different purpose.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That settles it then!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AIG is also impressed with the facts that a 35-million-year-old mayfly fossil looks very much like extant mayflies and that a clam long thought to be extinct is actually in existence today. They claim that “no ‘evolution’ [sic] had taken place in the supposed ~30 thousand years since the fossil clam had allegedly last lived.” Are the clams, for example, immune to the same viruses as they were 30,000 years ago? Or have they evolved immunity to newer pathogens? I doubt that anyone at AIG knows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review seems strikingly devoid of anything you might call a breakthrough. But at least they got off a good pun: “In April, we disarmed the evolutionary story of how snakes may have lost their limbs.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comments? On the &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; article or the AIG article? Other candidates for runner-up?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I consider a miracle to be something that I understand in some detail and know it is impossible, yet there it is in my hand for $200 – a digital camera, for example. I do not understand the James Webb Space Telescope in nearly as much detail, but I still consider it a miracle. Science may not agree with my definition of a miracle, but they consider the telescope the Breakthrough of the Year. Hard to argue with: the telescope itself is absolutely remarkable, as are some of the images it has returned. Science’s runners-up include perennial rice, the new-found creativity of artificial intelligence, deflection of an asteroid, two advances in virology – a nascent RSV vaccine and the discovery that multiple sclerosis is caused by a virus – and several others. What they call “Breakdowns” are fewer: the fact that zero Covid no longer works (if it ever did), the fact that science ties between nations are “fraying,” and the increase in CO2 emissions owing to the war in Ukraine. Answers in Genesis posted a Year in Review, by Troy Lacey, which they arranged chronologically by month, rather than in order of importance. A few comments below the fold.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ice crystals</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/ice-crystals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ice crystals" /><published>2023-01-02T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-01-02T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/ice-crystals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/ice-crystals.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/DSC05398_Ice_Crystals_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ice crystals&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Ice crystals on a window during the recent cold snap, December 23, 2022, at around 7:40 a.m. The window is nearly 2&amp;nbsp;m tall and double-paned. It sits behind an insulated Roman shade known as a Warm Window, so it gets very cold near the bottom. The hills are a few millimeters across and melt very quickly once the shade is pulled up. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Ice crystals on a window during the recent cold snap, December 23, 2022, at around 7:40 a.m. The window is nearly 2&amp;nbsp;m tall and double-paned. It sits behind an insulated Roman shade known as a Warm Window, so it gets very cold near the bottom. The hills are a few millimeters across and melt very quickly once the shade is pulled up.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What didn’t happen in 2022?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/what-didnt-happen-in-2022.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What didn’t happen in 2022?" /><published>2022-12-31T19:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-31T19:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/what-didnt-happen-in-2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/what-didnt-happen-in-2022.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/GlassHalfFull.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; of=&quot;&quot; glass-half-full=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Did or didn't happen in 2022?&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we are at the last day of 2022, the newspapers are full of accounts of what happened in 2022.  Even the Discovery Institute has bragged, at its site &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2022/12/the-year-in-review-intelligent-design-grows-in-influence-and-depth/&quot;&gt;Evolution News &amp;amp; Science Today&lt;/a&gt;
how much the cause of Intelligent Design advanced in the last year.  This account, by Brian Miller, was mocked by critics of ID (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/12/30/the-enduring-futility-of-intelligent-design-creationism/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://discourse.peacefulscience.org/t/id-achievements-of-the-year/15635&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/01/01/follow-up-on-id-at-conferences/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to come up with lists of things that happened in 2022.  But much easier to make lists of things that didn’t happen.  I wondered: what are the major things 
that &lt;em&gt;didn’t&lt;/em&gt; happen in 2022?  Particularly with regard to arguments for Intelligent Design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll provide my suggested non-event.   It is the clarification of how the Algorithmic Complexity argument for Intelligent Design works.  It remains, as it has been 
for some years, basically unexplained.  A reading of the whole course of argument using Specified Complexity, from William Dembski’s book &lt;em&gt;The Design Inference&lt;/em&gt; on, 
shows that the algorithmic complexity calculation started out as a peripheral suggestion and gradually changed until it is now said to be central to that 
argument.  But in the course of these changes, the logic of the criterion became no clearer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I puzzled over this &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/12/Is-Algorithmic-Specified-Complexity-Useless-for-Analyzing-Evolution.html&quot;&gt;perhaps at too great a length&lt;/a&gt; in a post here at Panda’s Thumb.  Was the algorithm supposed to compute the genotype?  the phenotype? 
Why was observation that it was nonrandomly un-complex supposed to favor ID?  How did the probability distribution of algorithms that was used make biological sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another year has passed, and none of these questions have been answered.  So I nominate this non-event as the greatest non-achievement of Intelligent Design proponents 
in 2022.  I congratulate them.  But our readers may have other non-achievements to suggest.  Let’s hear from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To read the comments on this post in context, click on the title of this post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Did or didn't happen in 2022? &amp;nbsp; Now that we are at the last day of 2022, the newspapers are full of accounts of what happened in 2022. Even the Discovery Institute has bragged, at its site Evolution News &amp;amp; Science Today how much the cause of Intelligent Design advanced in the last year. This account, by Brian Miller, was mocked by critics of ID (e.g. here, here, and here). It is hard to come up with lists of things that happened in 2022. But much easier to make lists of things that didn’t happen. I wondered: what are the major things that didn’t happen in 2022? Particularly with regard to arguments for Intelligent Design. I’ll provide my suggested non-event. It is the clarification of how the Algorithmic Complexity argument for Intelligent Design works. It remains, as it has been for some years, basically unexplained. A reading of the whole course of argument using Specified Complexity, from William Dembski’s book The Design Inference on, shows that the algorithmic complexity calculation started out as a peripheral suggestion and gradually changed until it is now said to be central to that argument. But in the course of these changes, the logic of the criterion became no clearer. Some time ago I puzzled over this perhaps at too great a length in a post here at Panda’s Thumb. Was the algorithm supposed to compute the genotype? the phenotype? Why was observation that it was nonrandomly un-complex supposed to favor ID? How did the probability distribution of algorithms that was used make biological sense? Another year has passed, and none of these questions have been answered. So I nominate this non-event as the greatest non-achievement of Intelligent Design proponents in 2022. I congratulate them. But our readers may have other non-achievements to suggest. Let’s hear from them. To read the comments on this post in context, click on the title of this post.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Take the science and religion quiz</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/science-and-religion-quiz.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Take the science and religion quiz" /><published>2022-12-29T11:55:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-29T11:55:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/science-and-religion-quiz</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/science-and-religion-quiz.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Faraday_Institute_Results_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Survey results&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jerry Coyne on his blog today advises us to &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2022/12/29/take-the-faraday-institutes-science-vs-religion-quiz/&quot;&gt;Take the Faraday Institute’s Science vs. Religion quiz!&lt;/a&gt; So I did! &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencereligioncompass.org/&quot;&gt;(Here.)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may see my result to the left. I ended up in the fourth quadrant, relatively close to the y-axis. The axis labels are to some extent jargon: Functional means that religion is best at social activities, what Dr. Coyne and I would call “tikkun olam,” or “repairing the world.” Substantive, by contrast, means that religion has meaning or content. The terms on the x-axis are reasonably clear, but I consider scientism to be pejorative and wish they had found a better term. (I have more than once been accused of scientism and am somewhat gratified that I did not land farther to the right.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is what the quiz makers said about me, and it is fairly accurate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Science is true, but religion has some value”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For you, science is the only (or main) way to the truth and religion is only really a cultural phenomenon, so the two can get on just fine. But you’re likely to add an important caveat to this: the two can get on just as long as religion doesn’t try and make any truth claims and sticks to what it does best – building community and helping others. When it comes to the job of understanding reality, it has nothing important to contribute. If you’re here, your temperature is probably a bit cool.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s pretty good, and they are certainly correct that I think religion gets into hot water when it makes truth claims. I have no objection to religious beliefs that do not tread on scientific fact, though I do not hold such religious beliefs myself. I came out a little lower on the thermometer than I expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Faraday Institute also provided an estimate of where the great scientists of history may end up on their graph, shown below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Faraday_Institute_Great_Scientists_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Graph&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suppose you could quibble with some of the placements, but it was interesting that I find myself below Darwin, Heisenberg, and Huxley. Dr. Coyne is a more militant atheist than I am, and he ended up in the first quadrant, about where Bohr appears, and farther than I would have expected from the “New Atheists.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you decide to take the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencereligioncompass.org/&quot;&gt; quiz&lt;/a&gt;, feel free to discuss your results in the Comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Jerry Coyne on his blog today advises us to Take the Faraday Institute’s Science vs. Religion quiz! So I did! (Here.) You may see my result to the left. I ended up in the fourth quadrant, relatively close to the y-axis. The axis labels are to some extent jargon: Functional means that religion is best at social activities, what Dr. Coyne and I would call “tikkun olam,” or “repairing the world.” Substantive, by contrast, means that religion has meaning or content. The terms on the x-axis are reasonably clear, but I consider scientism to be pejorative and wish they had found a better term. (I have more than once been accused of scientism and am somewhat gratified that I did not land farther to the right.) Here is what the quiz makers said about me, and it is fairly accurate:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Miracles: William Dembski gets it (mostly) right; NY Times does not</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/miracles-william-dembski.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Miracles: William Dembski gets it (mostly) right; NY Times does not" /><published>2022-12-27T09:06:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-12-27T09:06:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/miracles-william-dembski</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/miracles-william-dembski.html">&lt;p&gt;The New York Times on Sunday ran what I consider a very credulous article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2022/12/24/opinion/miracles-neuroscience-proof.html&quot;&gt;How Would You Prove That God Performed a Miracle?&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/column/molly-worthen&quot;&gt;Molly Worthen&lt;/a&gt;, an historian who, I thought, had not the foggiest idea how you would do so. You may read Jerry Coyne’s takedown of her article &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2022/12/26/nyt-touts-religious-miracles-as-proof-of-god/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Worthen lets William Dembski get the last word. We have criticized Dr. Dembski seemingly endlessly on this blog, but here I think he’s got it essentially right:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I believe in miracles, but I think they require scrutiny,” Dr. Dembski told me [Dr. Worthen]. “I don’t tend to see things as flamboyant as in the New Testament.” He published a moving &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.baptistpress.com/resource-library/news/first-person-faith-healing-wheres-the-evidence/&quot;&gt;account&lt;/a&gt; of his family’s disappointment at a healing revival, where he sought prayer for his autistic son. “There can be quite a bit of self-delusion on the part of people looking for miracles, and it troubles me,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Dembski’s family has learned to look for the miraculous in everyday loving encounters, like when a teacher’s aide made it her mission to help his son learn to use the bathroom on his own. “His life is so much better because of this person who wouldn’t give up on him,” he said. “It was no miracle, in terms of a magic wand that touched him and everything was fine. It was people who were willing to love him and do the hard work.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Dembski says he believes in miracles. Or perhaps gives lip service to a belief in miracles. What happened when it got down to brass tacks, as when he took his autistic child to the so-called faith healer? The supposed healer refused to see the child because he did not “look the part”; Dr. Dembski saw right through faith healing and indeed recognized it as “self-delusion.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consider a miracle to be a figure of speech for when, say, that teacher takes his son under her wing, does the very best she can with him, and, against the odds, succeeds. Dr. Dembski professes a belief in literal miracles, but seems more impressed with practical, figure-of-speech–type miracles. On that, we can agree.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">The New York Times on Sunday ran what I consider a very credulous article, How Would You Prove That God Performed a Miracle? by Molly Worthen, an historian who, I thought, had not the foggiest idea how you would do so. You may read Jerry Coyne’s takedown of her article here. Dr. Worthen lets William Dembski get the last word. We have criticized Dr. Dembski seemingly endlessly on this blog, but here I think he’s got it essentially right: “I believe in miracles, but I think they require scrutiny,” Dr. Dembski told me [Dr. Worthen]. “I don’t tend to see things as flamboyant as in the New Testament.” He published a moving account of his family’s disappointment at a healing revival, where he sought prayer for his autistic son. “There can be quite a bit of self-delusion on the part of people looking for miracles, and it troubles me,” he said. Dr. Dembski’s family has learned to look for the miraculous in everyday loving encounters, like when a teacher’s aide made it her mission to help his son learn to use the bathroom on his own. “His life is so much better because of this person who wouldn’t give up on him,” he said. “It was no miracle, in terms of a magic wand that touched him and everything was fine. It was people who were willing to love him and do the hard work.” Dr. Dembski says he believes in miracles. Or perhaps gives lip service to a belief in miracles. What happened when it got down to brass tacks, as when he took his autistic child to the so-called faith healer? The supposed healer refused to see the child because he did not “look the part”; Dr. Dembski saw right through faith healing and indeed recognized it as “self-delusion.” I consider a miracle to be a figure of speech for when, say, that teacher takes his son under her wing, does the very best she can with him, and, against the odds, succeeds. Dr. Dembski professes a belief in literal miracles, but seems more impressed with practical, figure-of-speech–type miracles. On that, we can agree.</summary></entry></feed>