<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-03-18T13:38:09-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Pantherophis alleghaniensis-quadrivittatus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/pantherophis-alleghaniensis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pantherophis alleghaniensis-quadrivittatus" /><published>2025-03-17T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-17T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/pantherophis-alleghaniensis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/pantherophis-alleghaniensis.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Denelsbeck_Pantherophis_alleghaniensis_quadrivittata.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Eastern ratsnake&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern_rat_snake&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Pantherophis alleghaniensis-quadrivittatus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; eastern rat snake. You may find a discussion of the scientific name &lt;a href=&quot;https://auth1.dpr.ncparks.gov/reptiles/view.php?checklist_number=103.0&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Al Denelsbeck. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Pantherophis alleghaniensis-quadrivittatus &amp;ndash; eastern rat snake. You may find a discussion of the scientific name here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The President and the Paleontologist: Jimmy Carter’s Dalliance with Creationism and Stephen Jay Gould’s Stumble in Rebutting It</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/president-paleontologist.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The President and the Paleontologist: Jimmy Carter’s Dalliance with Creationism and Stephen Jay Gould’s Stumble in Rebutting It" /><published>2025-03-05T10:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-05T10:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/president-paleontologist</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/president-paleontologist.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Branch_Carter_Gould.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Left, Jimmy Carter. Right, Stephen Jay Gould.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Left, &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Jimmy_Carter_1971_a.jpg&quot;&gt;Jimmy Carter&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;small&gt;Wikimedia. Public domain. Not subject to copyright in the United States.&lt;/small&gt; Right, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Stephen_Jay_Gould_2015,_portrait_(unknown_date).jpg&quot;&gt;Stephen Jay Gould&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;small&gt;Wikimedia. Photograph posted by Wally McNamee. Fair use: copyright owner unknown.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Glenn Branch is deputy director of the National Center for Science Education, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as &lt;/i&gt;Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher, &lt;i&gt;and the &lt;/i&gt;Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics, &lt;i&gt;and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of &lt;/i&gt;Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools (2006). &lt;i&gt; He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Jimmy Carter &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2024/12/29/us/politics/jimmy-carter-dead.html&quot;&gt;died&lt;/a&gt; on December 29, 2024, the nation lost not only its 39th president but also a prominent born-again Christian who accepted evolution. In chapter 5 of his 2005 book &lt;i&gt;Our Endangered Values &lt;/i&gt;, entitled “No Conflict Between Science and Religion,” Carter insisted, “The existence of millions of distant galaxies, the evolution of species, and the big bang theory cannot be rejected because they are not described in the Bible, and neither does confidence in them cast doubt on the Creator of it all.” Yet in the late 1980s, he proposed a creationist argument to no less a figure than the Harvard paleontologist Stephen Jay Gould — whose rebuttal, surprisingly, was inadequate.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Gould related in a postscript to his 1988 essay “In a Jumbled Drawer” (reprinted in his 1991 book &lt;i&gt;Bully for Brontosaurus&lt;/i&gt;), Carter called him out of the blue one day in the late 1980s, “simply to express his good wishes and his hopes for my continued good health” (Gould was in remission from cancer). In gratitude, he then sent Carter a copy of &lt;i&gt;Wonderful Life&lt;/i&gt; (1989), his new book about the Cambrian fauna of the Burgess Shale. As was typical with Gould, the paleontology served as a springboard to explore a larger theme: “the ‘pageant’ of evolution as a staggeringly improbable series of events, sensible enough in retrospect and subject to rigorous explanation, but utterly unpredictable and quite unrepeatable.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having read &lt;i&gt;Wonderful Life&lt;/i&gt; with pleasure while attempting to defuse armed conflicts in the Horn of Africa, Carter nevertheless offered a counterargument:

&lt;blockquote&gt;You seem to be straining mightily to prove that everything that has happened prior to an evolutionary screening period was just an accident, and that if the tape of life was replayed in countless different ways it is unlikely that cognitive creatures [such as humans] would have been created or evolved. It may be that when you raise “one chance in a million” to the 4th or 5th power there comes a time when pure “chance” can be questioned. I presume that you feel more at ease with the luck of 1 out of 10 to the 30th power than with the concept of a creator who/that has done some orchestrating.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gould described Carter’s argument, a bit fulsomely, as “a brilliant riposte ... a brilliant twentieth-century version of natural theology ... fascinating.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he insisted that Carter’s argument was nevertheless wrong, and wrong for the same reason that a similar argument he discussed in “In a Jumbled Drawer,” due to the 19th-century Harvard paleontologist Nathaniel Shaler, was wrong: “because a probability cannot even be calculated for a singular occurrence known only after the fact.” (It’s because of the similarity of Shaler’s and Carter’s arguments that Gould added the postscript to “In a Jumbled Drawer.”) Gould approvingly quoted the 19th-century Harvard philosopher and psychologist William James, as writing, in a letter to Shaler, “Where only one fact is in question, there is no relation of ‘probability’ at all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gould’s answer to Carter thus presupposed that attributions to probability to individual events are not legitimate: it’s wrong to say that the chance that the next toss of a coin will be heads is 1 in 2, or that there’s a 30 percent chance of rain in Chicago tomorrow, or that the probability that a given atom of cobalt-60 will decay in about 5.27 years is 0.5. Such a view is indeed accepted by a few (such as the mathematician Richard von Mises, who famously declared, “The phrase ‘probability of death,’ when it refers to a single person, has no meaning at all for us”), but it is hard to square with the abundance in ordinary life and scientific practice of attributions to probability to individual events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;i&gt;Wonderful Life&lt;/i&gt; itself abounds in such attributions. Early in the book, Gould explained, “This book is about the nature of history and the overwhelming improbability of human evolution under themes of contingency and the metaphor of replaying life’s tape”; toward the end, he mused, with reference to &lt;i&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/i&gt;, “we are an improbable and fragile entity,” and interpolated a new adjective in a familiar Shakespearean line: “O brave — and improbable — new world, that has such people in it!” In light of these and similar passages, it is hardly fair for Gould to have faulted Carter for wanting to discuss the improbability of human existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What should Gould have said to Carter instead? Carter in effect was arguing that because the probability of human existence is very low on the hypothesis of evolution without divine guidance, and humans yet exist, the hypothesis of evolution without divine guidance is therefore false. But the form of inference is incorrect, as the philosopher Elliott Sober (among others) &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1023/A:1019579220694&quot;&gt;observes&lt;/a&gt;. To see why, take a homely example exactly parallel to Carter’s. Suppose that you buy a single Powerball ticket. If the drawing is conducted properly, it is very improbable (about 1 in 300 million) that you hold a jackpot ticket. But if you turn out to hold a jackpot ticket, are you entitled to infer that the drawing was rigged in your favor? Surely not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Endorsement of the incorrect form of inference is not limited to creationists. The biologist Richard Dawkins, who is about as far from creationism as anyone could be, fell into the trap in his discussion of the origin of life in &lt;i&gt;The Blind Watchmaker&lt;/i&gt; (1986), for example. But it is common among creationists, and Carter’s argument was creationist, at least in a broad sense, for he thought that it showed that it was scientifically necessary to appeal to divine guidance in explaining the facts of life. That was apparently a deviation from his settled views on science and religion, however: in &lt;i&gt;Our Endangered Values&lt;/i&gt;, he relates, “I had always understood that we didn’t need scientific proof of the existence or character of God.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It actually isn’t clear what Carter himself thought of Gould’s rebuttal. In &lt;i&gt;Living Faith&lt;/i&gt; (1996), he wrote that Gould “later contradicted my argument — with good humor.” But in his later book &lt;i&gt;Our Endangered Values&lt;/i&gt;, he seemed a little miffed, writing, “He didn’t respond directly, but subsequently quoted and slyly ridiculed my opinion.” Any rancor evidently subsided by the time of &lt;i&gt;Faith: A Journey for All&lt;/i&gt; (2018), in which Carter listed the influences on his thinking about theology and philosophy, ending with Gould. Although he alluded to their arguments “about facts or principles,” he stressed their agreement about science and described Gould’s &lt;i&gt;Rocks of Ages&lt;/i&gt; (1999) as one of his favorite books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, despite his dalliance with the creationist argument he proposed to Gould, Carter was a stalwart defender of the teaching of evolution. In 1980, as the presidential contest was peaking, his challenger Ronald Reagan declared that evolution “is a scientific theory only” and that “the biblical theory of creation” deserved a place in public schools. Carter &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.210.4465.35&quot;&gt;replied&lt;/a&gt;, through his science adviser, that the scientific evidence for evolution was convincing and that schools ought to respect the constitutional separation of church and state. Since creationism was &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.gallup.com/poll/21814/evolution-creationism-intelligent-design.aspx&quot;&gt;favored&lt;/a&gt; by about 44 percent of the American public at the time, Carter’s reply was — typically for him — both principled and courageous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;i&gt;Reprinted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/the-president-and-the-paleontologist-jimmy-carters-dalliance-with-creationism-and-stephen-jay-goulds-stumble-in-rebutting-it/&quot;&gt; Righting America&lt;/a&gt; with the permission of Glenn Branch and William Trollinger.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Glenn Branch</name></author><summary type="html">Left, Jimmy Carter. Wikimedia. Public domain. Not subject to copyright in the United States. Right, Stephen Jay Gould. Wikimedia. Photograph posted by Wally McNamee. Fair use: copyright owner unknown. Glenn Branch is deputy director of the National Center for Science Education, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher, and the Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics, and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools (2006). He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers. When Jimmy Carter died on December 29, 2024, the nation lost not only its 39th president but also a prominent born-again Christian who accepted evolution. In chapter 5 of his 2005 book Our Endangered Values , entitled “No Conflict Between Science and Religion,” Carter insisted, “The existence of millions of distant galaxies, the evolution of species, and the big bang theory cannot be rejected because they are not described in the Bible, and neither does confidence in them cast doubt on the Creator of it all.” Yet in the late 1980s, he proposed a creationist argument to no less a figure than the Harvard paleontologist Stephen Jay Gould — whose rebuttal, surprisingly, was inadequate.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Spatula clypeata</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/spatula-clypeata.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spatula clypeata" /><published>2025-03-03T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-03T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/spatula-clypeata</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/spatula-clypeata.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/P1031480_Northern_Shoveler_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Northern shoveler&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Northern_Shoveler/overview&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Spatula clypeata&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; northern shoveler, East Boulder (Colorado) Community Center, February, 2025. It was hard to get a halfway decent picture of this pair, because they kept swimming around in circles with their bills in the water, almost as if they were filter feeding. According to the link, in fact they &lt;i&gt;were&lt;/i&gt; filter feeding: &quot;Shovelers eat tiny crustaceans, other aquatic invertebrates, and seeds which they filter out of the water with comblike projections (called lamellae) along the edge of the bill.&quot; You may see a nice picture of the lamellae &lt;a href=&quot;https://roadsendnaturalist.com/2016/02/24/meandering-at-mattamuskeet/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Spatula clypeata &amp;ndash; northern shoveler, East Boulder (Colorado) Community Center, February, 2025. It was hard to get a halfway decent picture of this pair, because they kept swimming around in circles with their bills in the water, almost as if they were filter feeding. According to the link, in fact they were filter feeding: &quot;Shovelers eat tiny crustaceans, other aquatic invertebrates, and seeds which they filter out of the water with comblike projections (called lamellae) along the edge of the bill.&quot; You may see a nice picture of the lamellae here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">State Police Proselytized during K9 Training at Ark Park; No Word on How Dogs Reacted</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/state-police-proselytized.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="State Police Proselytized during K9 Training at Ark Park; No Word on How Dogs Reacted" /><published>2025-03-01T14:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-01T14:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/state-police-proselytized</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/state-police-proselytized.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_KSP_Ark_Fig_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kentucky trooper with dog&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2020, the Kentucky State Police (KSP) were embroiled in a controversy after it was discovered that a &lt;a href=&quot;https://manualredeye.com/90096/news/local/police-training-hitler-presentation/&quot;&gt;training PowerPoint presentation&lt;/a&gt; quoted Adolf Hitler and advocated ruthless violence.  In spite of this horrendous exception, the Kentucky State Police is well-respected and noted for their professionalism and devotion to duty. Imagine my surprise when I learned that the KSP paid Answers in Genesis (AIG) to send an officer on a K9 training class on February 1 to 4, 2025, at the Ark Encounter. Besides K9 training, the class included Fundamentalist Christian and Christian Nationalist propaganda. With the government agencies and politicians increasingly becoming entangled Christian Nationalism, this incident is particularly disturbing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On February 7, 2025, Ken Ham &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2025/02/07/aig-impacts-law-enforcement-k-9-conference/&quot;&gt;bragged&lt;/a&gt; in his daily blog that the AIG Department of Public Safety had hosted numerous law enforcement organizations in K9 training at the Ark. Photos indicated a Kentucky State Police officer was there with his vehicle, as were several other regional law enforcement agencies. Moreover, an organization known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://tacticaministries.org/&quot;&gt;TACTICA Ministries&lt;/a&gt; (Teaching Authorities Christian Truth in Central America) was also present. My curiosity was immediately piqued by the presence of the KSP trooper. The questions I immediately had were, “Why is a major law enforcement organization being trained by AIG?” and “Why isn’t AIG going to a major organization like the KSP for training instead?” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then wrote a Kentucky Open Records Act (KORA) request. Surprisingly, perhaps as a delaying tactic, my initial request was rejected. The rejection claimed I was not a Kentucky resident, even though I specifically said I was a resident in the KORA request. (I was born here and have owned a house which I have lived in in Lexington for more than 20 years. Many of my ancestors came to the state with Daniel Boone in the late 18th Century.) I resubmitted the request and received a small number of documents. Some of the requested information was not available; no mileage records were kept, and the KSP trooper did not save all of his training materials. Additional withheld information included the redaction of the identities of all third-party instructors “…due to sensitivity of their respective jobs and the need for anonymity.” Were these third-party instructors members of government law enforcement? We may never know. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The open records information showed that Kentucky taxpayers paid approximately $225 for the training of one officer. This doesn’t include money spent by other Kentucky law enforcement agencies. Kentucky law enforcement from Villa Hills Police Department and the Boone County Sheriff’s Office participated. Some out-of-state regional law enforcement that participated included the Genesee County Ohio, Twinsburg (Ohio) Police Department, and the Collier County (Florida) Sheriff’s Department. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event included several breakfasts and lunches, as well as one diner that was sponsored by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nutramaxlabs.com/our-passion&quot;&gt; Nutramax Laboratories&lt;/a&gt; (a company that produces supplements for pets and does a lot of evangelism on the side). Interestingly, the event Welcome Package showed that each lunch included “testimony.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_KSP_Ark_Attachment.pdf&quot;&gt;Welcome Package&lt;/a&gt; for the event also included a message from AIG’s Department of Public Safety’s Sgt. Adam Witherspoon: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also, AIG Dept of Public Safety makes no effort to hide who we are. We care deeply about your working relationship with your dog and want to do everything we can to help you improve as a K9 team. More importantly though we care about you as an individual. God created all of us in His image. Due to our sin, and we are all sinners, Romans 3:23-24. 23. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;...for all have sinned and fall short of the glory of God, 24. being justified as a gift by His grace through the redemption which is in Christ Jesus; we are condemned to spend eternity
separated from God. Jesus Christ however took our punishment on the Cross. Our most sincere prayer is that if you don’t know Jesus Christ as your savior, come and talk to us. We
would love to share with you the Good News of the Gospel, which grants us eternity with God in heaven. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let’s get to some great training, enjoy some great food, fellowship, and learning, and I look forward to meeting and getting to know each one of you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In His Service,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; Sgt Adam Witherspoon &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_KSP_Ark_Fig_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tactica ministries hat&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_KSP_Ark_Fig_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Memorization Card&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt; A presentation at the K9 training (and a major vendor/sponsor) was by a Michigan-based TACTICA Ministries. This ministry apparently gives police/paramilitary training plus substantial religious instruction to police forces in Central and South American countries. Disturbingly, there are numerous YouTube videos available of TACTICA paramilitary training set to high energy Christian music (see: https://youtu.be/x7PKZ7_KA3w?feature=shared, https://youtu.be/SAwjK4QzLUM?si=xvhnvOajsXJ4X53I, and https://youtu.be/ZoHRcZ4SmP0?si=cowgfvsRRT4D-yqi). Figure 2 is a hat that TACTICA Ministries sells. Apparently, part of the TACTICA “training” at the event included memorization of Bible verses on a “Memorization Card.” What do any of these verses have to do with K9 training? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TACTICA Ministries is run by Ryan Rought. At least one presentation was done by Mr. Rought. The training documents give this biography and description of Rought’s work: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ryan is a man fervently committed to his Christian faith, his family, and serving others. His energy is contagious as he is unashamedly committed to investing in the public safety community through high quality training, relationship building, and Gospel centered teaching. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several other participants' biographies mention going on mission trips and long term training in with TACTICA Ministries, including Marty Buffenbarger (2.5 years with TACTICA in Costa Rica), Chris Carpenter of Livingston Security Solutions (several training mission trips), and Bill and Cindy Gruppen (also of Association of Baptists for World Evangelism). The Gruppens' bios indicate that their “mission is to share God's good news through creative and impactful avenues.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the itinerary, a good deal of the first day of training (14:00 to 19:00) involved signing in and “roaming” the Ark. This visitation combined with the speakers' bios and other activities, such as lunchtime “testimonials” show that religious instruction and evangelism of law enforcement officers was a substantial portion of the K9 training. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_KSP_Ark_Fig_4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot; Officer Charity, a K9 dog&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is some evidence that the KSP and other Kentucky law enforcement has participated in similar past events. On July 9, 2024, conservative Republican Kentucky Attorney General Russell Coleman posted pictures of “K9 Officer Charity” in front of the Ark Encounter. Officer Charity is a K9 with the Attorney General’s Office’s Department of Criminal Investigations. This sweet doggie has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/officercharity_k9/&quot;&gt; her own Instagram page&lt;/a&gt;. (The Attorney General’s post mentions that the KSP and the Boone County Sheriff’s Office participated in K9 training at the Ark in early July 2024. The instruction in February 2025 is probably one of several similar events that have used taxpayer money for an odd combination of training and evangelism.) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More disturbing than the use of taxpayer funding to evangelize law enforcement is the likelihood of the officers being indoctrinated in Christian Nationalism. Answers in Genesis is becoming more and more an advocate for far-right politics. On February 25, 2025, Founder CEO of Answers in Genesis, Ken Ham, posted an essay on his blog titled “&lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2025/02/25/what-happens-when-your-god-dies/&quot;&gt;What Happens When Your God Dies&lt;/a&gt;.” In this political essay he attacks “wokeness,” “racist” DEI hiring, pronoun use, and transgender ideology while praising the new administration and attacking Democrats. This theme is common throughout AIG’s online publications. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_KSP_Ark_Fig_5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;God's religion, according to AIG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On July 15, 2023, Bodie Hodge (Ken Ham’s son-in-law) had an essay on AIG’s page called “The Religion of Sexual Humanism” (you may now find it on the Wayback Machine &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20250114135356/https://answersingenesis.org/culture/religion-sexual-humanism/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). In this post, Hodge claims what he and AIG represent is “God’s Religion” while most other people belong to “Not God’s Religion.” Note that “Not God’s Religion” has a sub-section “Counterfeits of Biblical Christianity” that includes Roman Catholics, Seventh Day Adventists, Mormons, Jehovah’s Witnesses, Unitarians, “Moonies,” and even more bizarrely (if possible) Jews, Muslims, Freemasons, and Satanists (isn’t that special?) among many others. Eastern religions and secularism are given separate categories in this incredible (in the literal sense of the word) chart. I almost find this chart comical, but considering the very real possibility of Christian Nationalism becoming an arm of the government, the graphic is simply horrifying. AIG is very well-connected in state politics and apparently is looking to expand their reach. At one point Ken Ham was scheduled to speak at an event on April 24 along with Secretary of Defense Pete Hegseth and Franklin Graham. Recently, Hegseth backed out, presumably because of other duties, but a list of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20250117152827/https://www.dayspringchristian.com/remember-america/speaker-series/&quot;&gt;originally scheduled speakers is available on the Internet Wayback Machine&lt;/a&gt; as recently as January 17, 2025. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every July the Tri-State Freethinkers have a protest near the entrance to Ark Encounter to protest the fake science plus the sales-tax rebate incentives and other handouts that the Ark has received from state, county, and Williamstown governments. I have avoided participating in this event in the past because of concerns about the event’s effectiveness and the possibility of a creationist provocateur causing a disruption. I was recently asked to speak at this event. I am frankly very hesitant. I have to wonder whether law enforcement will look the other way if the protest is attacked, actively disrupt the protest, or find another way of punishing or harassing the participants. In any case the government should not be paying to give their employees religious instruction especially when the employees are in a position where fairness and equanimity should be standard. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Back in 2020, the Kentucky State Police (KSP) were embroiled in a controversy after it was discovered that a training PowerPoint presentation quoted Adolf Hitler and advocated ruthless violence. In spite of this horrendous exception, the Kentucky State Police is well-respected and noted for their professionalism and devotion to duty. Imagine my surprise when I learned that the KSP paid Answers in Genesis (AIG) to send an officer on a K9 training class on February 1 to 4, 2025, at the Ark Encounter. Besides K9 training, the class included Fundamentalist Christian and Christian Nationalist propaganda. With the government agencies and politicians increasingly becoming entangled Christian Nationalism, this incident is particularly disturbing. On February 7, 2025, Ken Ham bragged in his daily blog that the AIG Department of Public Safety had hosted numerous law enforcement organizations in K9 training at the Ark. Photos indicated a Kentucky State Police officer was there with his vehicle, as were several other regional law enforcement agencies. Moreover, an organization known as TACTICA Ministries (Teaching Authorities Christian Truth in Central America) was also present. My curiosity was immediately piqued by the presence of the KSP trooper. The questions I immediately had were, “Why is a major law enforcement organization being trained by AIG?” and “Why isn’t AIG going to a major organization like the KSP for training instead?”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fratercula arctica</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/fratercula-arctica.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fratercula arctica" /><published>2025-02-17T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-02-17T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/fratercula-arctica</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/fratercula-arctica.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/IMG_0662_Puffin_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Puffin&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlantic_puffin&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;Fratercula arctica&lt;/i&gt;   &amp;ndash; Atlantic puffin, Iceland, August, 2010.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The eminent physicist R.W. Wood is well remembered for his work &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/physicaloptic00wood/&quot;&gt;Physical Optics&lt;/a&gt;, published in 1911. I always had a paperback handy and used it well into the 1990’s. In 1907, Wood published &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/1593&quot;&gt;How to Tell the Birds from the Flowers&lt;/a&gt;, A Manual of Flornithology for Beginners&lt;/i&gt;, illustrated by the author. His discussion of the puffin follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Upon this cake of ice is perched,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paddle-footed Puffin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find his double we have searched,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But have discovered—Nuffin!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The puffin is the only creature in the book that has no double.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Fratercula arctica &amp;ndash; Atlantic puffin, Iceland, August, 2010. The eminent physicist R.W. Wood is well remembered for his work Physical Optics, published in 1911. I always had a paperback handy and used it well into the 1990’s. In 1907, Wood published How to Tell the Birds from the Flowers, A Manual of Flornithology for Beginners, illustrated by the author. His discussion of the puffin follows: Upon this cake of ice is perched, The paddle-footed Puffin To find his double we have searched, But have discovered—Nuffin! The puffin is the only creature in the book that has no double.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Conservation of arguments</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/Conservation-of-arguments.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Conservation of arguments" /><published>2025-02-06T21:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2025-02-06T21:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/Conservation-of-arguments</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/Conservation-of-arguments.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Peas.png&quot; alt=&quot;[not-too-hard Shell game]&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A shell game in which 
the odds are not too bad,&lt;br /&gt; especially as we can see what's going on.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Dembski has recently made two posts (&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2025/01/the-displacement-fallacy-evolutions-shell-game/&quot;&gt;on January 10&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2025/01/conservation-of-information-the-history-of-an-idea/&quot;&gt;on January 20&lt;/a&gt;) at
&lt;em&gt;Evolution News&lt;/em&gt;, the advocacy site of the Discovery Institute’s Center for 
Science and Culture.  He describes them as sections of a paper he 
submitted to the DI’s house journal BIO-Complexity.  The paper was not 
immediately accepted, he said, and in the meantime he wanted to post the
sections at EN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Dembski declares in the preface to the first of these posts, their argument in these posts is, in effect, that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Conservation of information is a big result of the intelligent design literature, even if to date it hasn’t gotten the attention it deserves. It quantifies the amount of information needed to increase the probability of finding a needle in a haystack so that the needle can actually be found. The upshot of conservation of information is that the information needed to find a needle in a haystack in turn requires finding another needle in a haystack, implying there is no free lunch in search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Dembski’s account, when evolutionary biologists argue that processes such as natural selection can put 
adaptive information into the genome, they are failing to explain where the information comes from.  They are 
building it into their evolutionary algorithms as a detailed goal, and not informing the reader that they have done that.  The biologists’ argument has thus simply displaced the question, not answered it.  Dembski’s first post is illustrated by an illustration of the Shell Game, to label the argument of evolutionary biologists as a dishonest trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, the two posts leave Dembski’s argument no further than it was 
some years ago.  We can deal with it without going into great detail, 
because we have seen these arguments before.  Let’s ask, and answer, some brief questions as to what 
was accomplished:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;do-these-posts-clarify-how-his-algorithmically-specified-complexity-argument-deals-with-natural-selection&quot;&gt;Do these posts clarify how his Algorithmically Specified Complexity argument deals with natural selection?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, not at all.  That argument, which was the centerpiece of Dembski and Ewert’s recent book: &lt;em&gt;The Design Inference: Eliminating Chance through Small Probabilities, 2nd edition&lt;/em&gt;, which I discussed &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/dembskiewert2.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; recently, was left hanging by them, with 
the essential questions unanswered.  And Dembski’s recent two EN posts do not discuss ASC at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;have-we-seen-the-arguments-of-the-recent-en-posts-before&quot;&gt;Have we seen the arguments of the recent EN posts before?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes.  Applied to evolution, the conservation of information argument is 
the Active Information argument of Dembski and Marks, which has been 
discussed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.evoinfo.org/papers/2009_ConservationOfInformationInSearch.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://bio-complexity.org/ojs/index.php/main/article/download/BIO-C.2013.4/BIO-C.2013.4&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  It basically says that 
if natural selection can find genotypes of better fitness by climbing 
uphill on a fitness surface, that this &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; an increase of 
information in the genome.  But, they argued, it is not creating new information, 
because the information was already there in the structure of 
the fitness surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;does-the-active-information-argument-rule-out-any-role-for-natural-selection&quot;&gt;Does the Active Information argument rule out any role for natural selection?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not at all, as you can see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-dembski-and-ewert-and-marks-accept-that-natural-selection-explains-adaptations&quot;&gt;So Dembski (and Ewert and Marks) accept that natural selection explains adaptations?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, they are arguing that &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; natural selection can increase 
specfied information in the genome, this is not new 
information.  But they have always been very resistant to 
acknowledging that natural selection does much in 
evolution. In the first of the two EN posts that we 
are discussing, Dembski grapples with Richard Dawkins’s 
book &lt;em&gt;Climbing Mount Improbable&lt;/em&gt;.  Dawkins gives examples of 
natural selection achieving major adaptations by gradual 
small changes.  Dembski calls Dawkins’s argument “displacement”, 
arguing this way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It could be that Mount Improbable is sheer on all sides and getting to the top via baby-steps is effectively impossible. Consequently, it is not enough to presuppose that a fitness-increasing sequence of baby steps always connects biological systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Dembski argues that Dawkins’s examples are a misleading reflection of how 
well (or badly) natural selection will typically be able to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;connection-to-possible-and-likely-fitness-surfaces&quot;&gt;Connection to possible, and likely, fitness surfaces&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dembski argues that fitness surfaces that allow natural selection to work are unlikely, and their existence needs explanation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mountains, after all, do not magically materialize — they have to be formed by some process of mountain formation. Of all the different ways Mount Improbable might have emerged, how many are sheer so that no gradual path to the summit exists? And how many do allow a gradual path to the summit? A Mount Improbable with gradual paths to the top may itself be improbable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improbable in what sense?  We’ll see that only a tiny fraction of all possible fitness surfaces 
will be smooth – but this is true only if all possible fitness surfaces are equally probable.  Which they definitely are not.  Smooth ones are vastly more probable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;connection-to-the-no-free-lunch-argument&quot;&gt;Connection to the No Free Lunch argument&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue has come up before, in Dembski’s 2001 book “No Free Lunch: Why Specified Complexity Cannot Be Purchased without Intelligence”.  There he invokes a mathematical theorem about the success of search algorithms on all possible problems.  This is the No Free Lunch theorem of Wolpert and Macready, which shows that &lt;em&gt;averaged over all possible problems&lt;/em&gt; all search algorithms do equally well, and are no more successful than examining a random set of points and choosing the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolpert and Macready did not prove that all search algorithms will do that badly in finding large values of, say, fitness on all fitness surfaces.  As Dembski’s title says, he cites Wolpert and Macready’s theorem as showing that we need to invoke intelligence, as we cannot expect that natural selection on fitness surfaces to find genomes of better fitness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;was-dembskis-2001-no-free-lunch-argument-refuted&quot;&gt;Was Dembski’s 2001 No Free Lunch argument refuted?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, almost immediately, by many authors, including &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.talkorigins.org/design/faqs/nfl/&quot;&gt;Richard Wein&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://educ.jmu.edu/~rosenhjd/dembski.pdf&quot;&gt;Jason Rosenhouse&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/7429/ef6c62a9cd544df79f0b21985c42dddf138f.pdf?_ga=2.130757519.169921541.1540934691-51823296.1540934691&quot;&gt;the late Mark Perakh&lt;/a&gt;, by Wesley Elsberry and Jeffrey Shallit (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.talkreason.org/articles/eandsdembski.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007%2Fs11229-009-9542-8.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), by &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20071011030112mp_/http://www.talkreason.org/articles/nfl_gavrilets6.pdf&quot;&gt;Erik Tellgren&lt;/a&gt; and by &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007%2Fs10539-006-9040-z.pdf&quot;&gt;Ole Häggström&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nfl-and-smoothness-of-fitness-surface&quot;&gt;NFL and smoothness of fitness surface&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the original Wolpert-MacReady No Free Lunch theorem considers all possible 
problems, it has a space, such as all possible genomes.  Each is assigned a 
value (such as a fitness), and &lt;em&gt;all possible assignments are considered&lt;/em&gt;.  In effect, 
the fitnesses are scrambled among the genotypes in all possible ways, all equally 
probable.  So when we see a fitness of a genotype, what can we say about the 
fitness of a nearby genotype, say one which differs by a single change of a 
single base?  &lt;em&gt;Nothing&lt;/em&gt;.  Every possible DNA sequence has its fitness assigned 
at random, including the nearest neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads to vast numbers of infinitely rough fitness surfaces, of “white noise” 
fitness surfaces. They have no 
smoothness whatsoever.  Dembski’s original NFL argument is that these do not allow for 
much evolution.  If they were typical of fitness surfaces in nature, this would be 
a big obstacle to the effectiveness of natural selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;empirical-evidence-on-mutational-effects&quot;&gt;Empirical evidence on mutational effects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such fitness surfaces are very, very atypical in real biology.  Look at it 
this way: the effect of a single base mutation on such a surface is 
to carry us to a genotype whose fitness is just like that of a 
totally random sequence, one which differs by being mutated at 75 percent 
of the sites!   If this were a human genome, it would be mutated at about 
2,250,000,000 sites simultaneously.  The idea that the effect of one mutation 
is the same as the effect of billions of mutations is bizarre and unreal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when Dembski considers “all the different ways” that a fitness 
surface could have emerged, overwhelmingly those are unreal 
fitness surfaces that would never emerge in real biological cases.
Real ones are much smoother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tight-interaction&quot;&gt;Tight Interaction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only does the equidistribution of all possible fitness 
surfaces imply unreal effects of mutations, it also implies 
incredibly tight interactions between all mutations.  Consider 
the effect of a mutation at one site, and the effect of a 
mutation at another site, millions of sites away.  We’ve 
seen that in the NFL distribution of fitnesses, these two 
mutations are each probably disastrous.  But what about the 
interaction between them?  What if we make both of these 
changes?  Even if each of the two mutations happened to have 
a mild effect on fitness, what would be the effect if both 
mutations occurred?   We cannot predict that the effect would 
also be mild.  Because the fitness would, once again, be drawn 
totally at random, with no predictability from the effects of 
single mutations.  The result is an incredibly strong, and 
unpredictable, interaction between mutations at these two 
sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not just these two sites – at all pairs of sites, and at 
all combinations of sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No biological system works like this.  Mutational changes 
in the genes affecting the production of earwax generally 
have little effect on the development of our kidneys.  And 
for a very simple reason – these are processes separated 
in time and space, and in the real world it is hard for them 
to interact strongly.  In the NFL world, every gene, by default, 
interacts incredibly strongly with everything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-anthropogenetic-principle&quot;&gt;The Anthrop(ogenet)ic Principle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Natural selection could achieve very little if fitness 
surfaces were rough, white-noise surfaces.  We can 
conclude that they aren’t those, because we have in 
fact evolved.  This is, in a sense, like the 
Anthropic Principle in cosmology.  We’re here, so 
we must have been able to evolve.  Perhaps it should 
be called the Anthrop(ogenet)ic Principle.  Of course 
this argument would not convince an “ID theorist” who 
does not believe that natural selection played a 
major role in our evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;choice-of-region-of-the-fitness-surface&quot;&gt;Choice of region of the fitness surface&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When different parts of a fitnes surface have different 
properties, the Anthropogenetic Principle argues that 
life evolved into a region that had sufficient smoothness. 
That is, it sought out evolvability.  Computer simulations 
by Lee Altenberg and Kenneth Kinnear and Günter Wagner 
have shown evolution doing this,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;and-what-about-physics-itself&quot;&gt;And what about physics itself?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if the properties of the fitness surface have 
not evolved, it seems reasonable that physics itself 
predisposes fitness surfaces to be smooth.  After all, 
the forces of physics tend to be local in time and space 
and to lose influence with greater distance.  If I 
gesture with my fingers, there is hardly any effect 
on objects at a distance.  The floor of our room 
does not collapse, nor does the ceiling cave in. Different 
objects are scarcely affected by each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may summarize briefly that William Dembski’s conservation- 
of-information argument is not new, and has been convincingly 
dismissed in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Altenberg L 1994. Kinnear, Kenneth (ed.). “The evolution of evolvability in genetic programming”. &lt;em&gt;Advances in Genetic Programming&lt;/em&gt;, pp. 47–74.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Altenberg L. 1995. “Genome growth and the evolution of the genotype–phenotype map”. &lt;em&gt;Evolution and Biocomputation.&lt;/em&gt; Lecture Notes in Computer Science. Vol. 899. pp. 205–259.  doi:10.1007/3-540-59046-3_11.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wagner G.P., and Altenberg L. 1996. “Perspective: Complex adaptations and the evolution of evolvability”. &lt;em&gt;Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 50 (3): 967–976.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">A shell game in which the odds are not too bad, especially as we can see what's going on. &amp;nbsp; William Dembski has recently made two posts (on January 10 and on January 20) at Evolution News, the advocacy site of the Discovery Institute’s Center for Science and Culture. He describes them as sections of a paper he submitted to the DI’s house journal BIO-Complexity. The paper was not immediately accepted, he said, and in the meantime he wanted to post the sections at EN. As Dembski declares in the preface to the first of these posts, their argument in these posts is, in effect, that Conservation of information is a big result of the intelligent design literature, even if to date it hasn’t gotten the attention it deserves. It quantifies the amount of information needed to increase the probability of finding a needle in a haystack so that the needle can actually be found. The upshot of conservation of information is that the information needed to find a needle in a haystack in turn requires finding another needle in a haystack, implying there is no free lunch in search. In Dembski’s account, when evolutionary biologists argue that processes such as natural selection can put adaptive information into the genome, they are failing to explain where the information comes from. They are building it into their evolutionary algorithms as a detailed goal, and not informing the reader that they have done that. The biologists’ argument has thus simply displaced the question, not answered it. Dembski’s first post is illustrated by an illustration of the Shell Game, to label the argument of evolutionary biologists as a dishonest trick. Actually, the two posts leave Dembski’s argument no further than it was some years ago. We can deal with it without going into great detail, because we have seen these arguments before. Let’s ask, and answer, some brief questions as to what was accomplished:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A plug for The Elements of Marie Curie, by Dava Sobel</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/plug-elements-marie-curie.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A plug for The Elements of Marie Curie, by Dava Sobel" /><published>2025-02-04T13:31:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-02-04T13:31:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/plug-elements-marie-curie</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/plug-elements-marie-curie.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Sobel_Marie_Curie_Cover_600.jpg &quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a plug, not a review. The full title is &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Elements-Marie-Curie-Radium-Science/dp/0802163823/&quot;&gt;The Elements of Marie Curie&lt;/a&gt;: How the Glow of Radium Lit a Path for Women in Science&lt;/i&gt;, by Dava Sobel. The use of “elements” in the title is a pun in more ways than one: besides Mme. Curie’s discovery of radium and polonium, each chapter is related, sometimes very tenuously, to a chemical element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is a scientific biography of Marie Curie and her myriad of protégées. Interestingly, though Madame Curie was sometimes perceived early on as Pierre Curie’s assistant, and as a woman she was not voted into the &lt;i&gt;Académie des sciences&lt;/i&gt;, Ms. Sobel gives no indication of any deliberate prejudice. In North America, by contrast, at least one of her protégées was threatened with losing her job if she married, and another simply gave up science upon her marriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dava_Sobel&quot;&gt;Dava Sobel&lt;/a&gt; is a distinguished science writer with several science biographies to her name. It has been my pleasure to read &lt;i&gt;Longitude&lt;/i&gt;, the story of John Harrison, who invented the naval chronometer and should be a household name; &lt;i&gt;Galileo’s Daughter&lt;/i&gt;; and &lt;i&gt;The Glass Universe&lt;/i&gt;, about how a number of women at Harvard College Observatory revolutionized astronomy, while working essentially for peanuts. In addition, Ms. Sobel has written a play, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davasobel.com/books-by-dava-sobel/and-the-sun-stood-still-book&quot;&gt;And the Sun Stood Still&lt;/a&gt;, about Copernicus; I was indeed privileged to see the premiere of the play by the Boulder Ensemble Theatre Company, as well as an earlier staged reading while the play was being workshopped. All told, depending how you count, Ms. Sobel has written a half-dozen scientific biographies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">This is a plug, not a review. The full title is The Elements of Marie Curie: How the Glow of Radium Lit a Path for Women in Science, by Dava Sobel. The use of “elements” in the title is a pun in more ways than one: besides Mme. Curie’s discovery of radium and polonium, each chapter is related, sometimes very tenuously, to a chemical element. The book is a scientific biography of Marie Curie and her myriad of protégées. Interestingly, though Madame Curie was sometimes perceived early on as Pierre Curie’s assistant, and as a woman she was not voted into the Académie des sciences, Ms. Sobel gives no indication of any deliberate prejudice. In North America, by contrast, at least one of her protégées was threatened with losing her job if she married, and another simply gave up science upon her marriage.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Uria sp.</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/uria-sp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Uria sp." /><published>2025-02-03T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-02-03T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/uria-sp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/uria-sp.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/IMG_0750_Common_Murre_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Murre&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/animal/murre&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;Uria&lt;/i&gt; sp., probably &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Common_Murre/id&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;U. aalge&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; common murre, or guillemot (but what do I know?), Iceland, August, 2010.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Uria sp., probably U. aalge &amp;ndash; common murre, or guillemot (but what do I know?), Iceland, August, 2010.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Big Chill: How Yosemite Valley and Other Glacial Examples Disprove the Way-Too-Short Biblical Creationist Ice Age</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/the-big-chill.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Big Chill: How Yosemite Valley and Other Glacial Examples Disprove the Way-Too-Short Biblical Creationist Ice Age" /><published>2025-01-23T09:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-01-23T09:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/the-big-chill</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/the-big-chill.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Paul_Yosemite.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Author at Yosemite&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The author at Yosemite.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Gregory Paul is an independent polymath researcher including in paleozoology and geology. His technical studies and popular articles have appeared in Scientific American, BioScience, The Anatomical Record, Annals of the Carnegie Museum, Evolutionary Theory, Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology, Journal of Paleontology, Modern Geology, Historical Biology, Paleobiology, Evolutionary Biology, Cretaceous Research, Science, Nature. His work has been covered by the New York Times, Washington Post, Science Friday, Science News, New Scientist, Discover, Reuters. He designed the Tyrannosaurus in Jurassic Park.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article focuses on a subject that has received not much in the way of consideration, the young earth creationist (YEC) view of the Ice Age that they propose followed the super flood. In this examination I am going to put some emphasis on one of the biggest canyons in these United States. Not the often discussed Grand Canyon – the reasons why that colossal ditch was formed as a classic riverine V-shaped valley over millions of years in rocks up to 1.25 billion years old, rather than suddenly cut by a super flood in short order in post-flood deposits, has been well detailed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The valley focused on here is Yosemite. Yosemite has received notably little attention in either the anti- or pro- creationist literature. That is both despite, and precisely because, the California canyon poses overwhelming problems that YEC theory lacks practical means of explaining. This article also focuses on the apologetics of the top two creationist organizations, the Institute for Creation Research and, especially, Answers in Genesis headed by the most popular living YEC, Ken Ham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Creationist Conspiracy Theory versus the Natural Truth&lt;/strong&gt;
That the role played by the 2.5 year old Quaternary Ice Age is on the side burner of the creation debate is ironic in that it played a critical role in beginning the scientific undermining of scriptural creationism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creationists of various flavors believe those who claim that creation could not have occurred without the existence of a transcendent intelligent designer are engaged in a vast conspiracy of spiritual denial. According the YEC’s, the willful rejection of divine creation includes pretending the planet is more than a few thousand years old. The notion is that stubborn resisters to Biblical creation started to concoct a false geological narrative in the late 1700’s going into the 1800’s in which our planet is supposed to be many millions of years old, disproving the inerrancy of the Word of God. This notion then expanded into a vast conspiracy ofcreator deniers that have been pretending the universe is billions of years old and that organisms evolved over much of that time via natural selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The historical truth is that the great glaciation was a key to the accidental overturning of Biblical time scales. Largely Christian early geologists who presumed they were going to confirm the work of God began to come across extensive evidence for extreme past glaciations in the form of many valleys that had clearly been formed by big ice flows, but did not have ice flowing in them. And evidence for tremendous continent-spanning ice sheets was showing up. Knowing that ice flows carve and move rock and earth downslope at a literally glacial pace, they began to realize that actual earth history time must have been far longer than undocumented Biblical time, to the extent that the latter was refuted – scientists have not been conspiring to refute scripture, instead nature has naturally refuted the Biblical creation story via objective scientific investigation that the researchers are merely reporting on. That the planet was not meeting YEC-compatible criteria in all aspects, including granitic glacial valleys that obviously took tens to hundreds of thousands of years to be cut, helped force the budding scientific community to abandon Bible-based creation timelines. They had no logical alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Great American Freeze&lt;/strong&gt;
That incredible amounts of ice recently covered enormous tracts of the northern hemisphere is so well documented that even YEC makes no attempt to deny the reality of an ice age, even though it is not mentioned in scriptures. And this leads to a tremendous problem for YEC: a lack of sufficient time for vast quantities of frozen water to do very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In science-based geological reality, the Pleistocene ice age began about 2.5 million years ago, with dozens of repeating cycles (Kohler and Wal, 2020) of glacial periods each lasting tens of thousands of years, each interrupted by markedly shorter, warmer interglacials that last about ten thousand years, we being in the Holocene expression of the latest interglacial. With glaciers forming enormous, kilometers-thick ice shields over much of Eurasia and especially North America, and gargantuan ice fields topping many mountain ranges, for a combined total of some 1.5 to 2 million years, there was plenty of time for those super glaciers to form, erode, move, and gouge out and deposit lots of rock and dirt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the height of the glacial maximums, ice sheets and fields covered about a third of the continents (https://www.climate.gov/media/11951). The ice contained so much water transferred from the oceans that the level of the oceans dropped 130 m, over 400 ft. The biggest single ice sheet was northern North America’s Laurentide – for the purposes of this discussion the name is applied to each re-creation of the shield over the ice age – that smothered almost all of Canada and a fair portion of the USA, down to Long Island and over to and across Indiana and Illinois and the upper plains states (https://www.kgs.ku.edu/Publications/PIC/pic28.html). Of course glaciers flow, because thick ice at earthly temperatures is plastic and becomes mobile under the pressure of its own mass. With little or nothing in the way of down-slope force, the flow of continent sized ice sheets is driven largely by the center of the shield being so thick that it pushes out laterally over hundreds to thousands of miles. In the case of the Laurentide its thickness was over 3 km (2 mi) thick in the region of its center, thinning out to 400-650 m (1300-2000 ft) at its edges (USGS; Broad 2018). Because continent spanning ice shields are not flowing down a strongly inclined valley, they move very slowly, about half a meter a year. But because they run for thousands of millennia, any given spot under the shield can experience hundreds of kilometers worth of ice and debris grinding over it during most of the Pleistocene, while any given unit of ice can flow for many hundreds of miles during that time, making long running ice sheets colossal earth movers. To the degree that the multiple Laurentide sheets scoured much of Canada of its soft earth covering, leaving behind the gouged, rocky surface of the Canadian Shield. Much of that dirt and ground up rock ended up in the northern USA where it helped form future farmlands and prominent geographical features such as Long Island, Staten Island, and Cape Cod, which are terminal glacial moraines on a stupendous scale. Those substantial lands would simply not exist but for the fact that the Laurentide shields spent well over a million years moving and dumping vast amounts of stuff, while in the process digging out the basins for the Great Lakes, polishing hard bedrocks, and scattering about big boulders of Canadian rock south of the border called erratics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The closest thing these days to the Laurentide sheet in size and depth is the Antarctic ice cap. Over the main body of the latter, annual snow fall is about half a foot per year, which qualifies as desert conditions (Casey et al. 2014). Rates of snowfall on such continent-scale, miles-thick ice sheets are inherently low – the air above them is automatically thin and very cold due to high altitude; cold air, especially when thin, cannot hold much water vapor, most of the ice caps are far from marine water sources, and there are no sudden high mountain ranges to wring precipitation on steep upwind slopes. The ratio of snow deposition relative to resulting solid ice thickness ranges from over 10 to 2.5 depending on how fluffy to icy is the snow (Casey et al., 2014; Graham 2018). So if we assume that it took 50,000 years for each iteration of the Laurentide ice shield to reach maximum thickness, then it would have required about half a foot to 2.5 ft (20-80 cm) of snow in a given year, equaling about 2 to 3 in of rain. Not a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The many problems with YEC theory and all that ice start with the events that occurred before their version of the Pleistocene. YEC tries to wave away the great geological ages indicated by radiometric dating by arbitrarily believing that radioactive decay used to occur at rates far higher than they currently are (Vardiman et al. 2005). If so, then the heat released by so much radioactivity cooking along within just a couple thousand years would have melted the surface of the planet, precluding any super flood, ice age, or for that matter our currently pleasantly cool planetary surface, while in the process irradiating all life with lethal doses of radiation (Morton and Murphy 2004; Isaac 2007) – YEC’s dismiss these incompatibilities with the truth of the perfect word of God by promising that they are “confident” these gross violations of the physics of the universe will be solved (Vardiman et al. 2005). Also, modern YEC actually postulates that the continents moved the thousands of miles from their preflood supercontinent positions into their current locations while the flood was occurring! Even the YEC who proposed this impossible geoevent has admitted that the amount of heat released by opening a magmatic Atlantic basin in a fraction of a year while dragging the leading edges of tectonics plates into the mantle at the rate of dozens of miles a day and so forth would unleash enough heat to melt most of the crust and/or “boil away a layer of water 25 km deep over the entire earth” (Morton and Murphy 2004).  Aside from steam broiling the life floating in and on top of the floodwaters, the Ark residents included – while making the atmosphere and waters lethally toxic with nasty volcanic gases – this too would prevent a subsequent ice age, and the planet would these days still be too hot to support anything except perhaps some microbial thermophiles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even if the planet were not super heated at the end of the flood, there is the problem of too little time for an ice age. According to the often calculated generational genealogy detailed in the Bible, the earth is ~6000 years old. And the flood, according to the leading YEC organization Answers in Genesis, occurred circa 4500 years before present. Using their entirely faith-based Biblical calculation – there being no actual geological scientific data backing it up – in some posts (Snelling and Matthews 2013, AIG 2018) AIG calculates that the ice age got going circa 4250 years ago, and ended around 4000 years. Just after the Babel affair and before the first cities appeared according to their radical, nonhistorical Bible based estimates (cities actually first appeared circa 9500 BP, Mesopotamia arose 5100 BP, and the Pyramids of Giza went up ~4500 BP). But AIG is very inconsistent. According to another calculation driven by the absurdities of a big freeze lasting a quarter millennium, the ice age lasted 700 years, apparently starting in the immediate aftermath of the flood, which would put its end at just 3750 years ago (Oard 2004; 2007a,b); that, of course, increases the serious problems that stem from trying to squeeze in the beginning of post-flood urban civilizations – which AIG acknowledges did not appear until after the ice sheets were gone – into even less than four millennia. 
So instead of Pleistocene ice for over 2 million years, YEC proposes it was really in existence for just 250 years – about the same age as the USA – to maybe 700.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting with the 250-year YEC ice age, allowing for 100 years of melting, to pile up a couple miles worth of ice in 150 years would require 50 to 200 meters (175 to 700) feet of snow – depending on how icy or fluffy the falling snow was – per year over the majority of the Laurentide sheet, an area covering a third to half of Canada. There simply is no location on the planet that can conceivably receive anywhere close to so much snow so fast.  It is not possible for cold air to contain and dump that much solidified water at a usually or always freezing location in so little time, least of all when not on the narrow zone mountain upslopes chronically downwind of cold coastal air currents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The absurdity of postulating that a glacial shield grew to cover about half a continent with thousands of feet of ice and then all melted away in just a few human lifespans is so reckless, that it helps explain why other AIG posts propose a 700 year long ice age, with ice accumulation covering 500 years. In an additional effort to lessen the growth-time problem, the 700 year scenario proposes that the north continental sheets averaged just 700 m (2300 ft) in depth (Oard 2007a,b), a value too low to drop sea level by the well documented 130 m. Aside from being too shallow a value, the key issue is how to pile all the ice at the deepest region which would be about twice as high as the average. Piling up 1000 m (3500 ft) in 500 years would require some 6 to 25 m (20 to 80 ft) of snow from icy to fluffy respectively a year, over millions of square kilometers. Such snowfall rates are seen in the modern world, but only in locations of limited area, where coastal mountains are capturing steady, wet winter winds, such as northern Japan. Presuming that the ice sheet’s core region got to the more geologically correct two miles demands an even more implausible 18 to 75 m (60 to 250 ft) each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;YEC theory tries to explain this all away with an extremely speculative hypothesis. Oard (2004, 2007) proposes that the post-flood oceans that were still warm from the heating events associated with the flood were evaporating so much water vapor into the atmosphere, while sun blocking volcanic dusts and aerosols from extensive post flood volcanism were making the continents so cold, that incredible rates of ice accumulation occurred on the continents. But to transfer such enormous volumes of water from oceans to continents so fast would have required the northern lands and the air above them staying freezing cold continuously for almost the entire year, while the oceans and air above them remained so steamy warm that the air topping the oceans could absorb and carry all that water vapor, for centuries. But according to Oard, the oceans were merely warm enough for a “pleasant swim” – that’s necessary to avoid killing off most or all marine life, but such is insufficient to pump the needed amounts of water into the atmosphere. Nor were the continent versus marine temperature differentials sustainable. Obviously, the freezing cold and therefore dense continental air would flow via tremendous surface winds in vast quantities out over the balmy oceans, rapidly cooling their surfaces down in alliance with all the suspended volcanics that kept the sun from warming the seas. That would severely suppress water uptake into the air. Meanwhile, all the relatively warm oceanic air back flowing over the continents would partly displace and mix with the cold land air, probably keeping lands at high latitudes too warm for glacier formation at low altitudes, while quickly eliminating the strong temperature ocean-continent differential the YEC hypothesis cannot work without. After all, the surface temperatures of land and sea broadly equalize in just a few months with each change of seasons. For the apparently deeply impractical Oard scenario in which some 45 million cubic kilometers of ocean water (the over 360 million square kilometers of the surface of all oceans times 0.13 kilometers depth) is evaporated from the ocean surfaces and plopped onto the continents as snow in just a few centuries, a rate up to 100,000 cubic kilometers per year, to be taken seriously, its feasibility would need to be supported by sophisticated computer simulations conducted by an objective team of analysts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time problem is not only one of accumulation, it is one of movement. If the Laurentide and other northern hemisphere flatland shields lasted just a few hundred years, creeping along at half a meter or so a year they would have flowed a mere few hundred meters! There would have been no scouring of the Canadian Great Shield, no deposition of the super moraines that make up Long Island et al., no glacial polishing of hard rocks, no deposition of glacial erratics hundreds and thousands of miles from their origin, no digging of the basins of the Great Lakes. In order to accomplish those Sisyphean tasks within the YEC timeframe would require that the shield ice magically zip along at a rate of a couple of hundred meters per day, which violates the physics of the universe including gravity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Big Valley&lt;/strong&gt;
Praised as an exemplar of western America’s God’s Country by devout, mainstream Christian John Muir, with its U-shaped cross section, hanging valleys, and ice-scoured rock surfaces, Yosemite is the paragon par excellence of a glacial valley. YEC and ICR admit such, and they do not offer alternative scenarios, none being viable. Including a sudden super flood, or earthquakes, the necessary faulting not being on hand. A feature of Yosemite is its exceptionally tough graniteThe rock is both very hard and in the main unfractured, which is why it retains such unparalleled tall, sheer vertical cliffs – in some places such as half dome rearing over 4000 ft above the current valley floor, which itself is fill-in that lies 2000 ft above the glacially carved bottom (Huber 1987; Duhnforth et al. 2010; Anderson 2018). The walls of less resilient glacially cut valleys are prone to more collapsing when the lateral support of the ice melts away. The foundations of the valley began in the late Mesozoic with the formation of deep underground plutons associated with plate tectonics. Being well insulated by overlying terrain, very slow cooling of the pluton allowed the development of the large interlocking hard crystals that form the granites most resistant to fracturing and abrasion. During the late Cenozoic, uplift exposed the Sierra Nevada batholith to erosion. Initially the Merced River cut a V-shaped valley perhaps a couple thousand feet deep. Then the repeat formation of the Sierra Nevada ice field sent glaciers up to 4000 ft deep down the canyon, carving the U-shaped main valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rate at which glaciers cut very hard rock such as granite is known from direct observation of current examples. Glacial erosion occurs because of plucking and/or abrasion. The former, in which the flowing ice breaks off substantial chunks of rock by fracturing of pieces, is the faster means, but regularly occurs only when the rock is not especially hard and/or is heavily fractured. And even such quarrying excavates semi-hard rock at a rate of at most 100 mm/year (Hallett et al. 1996; p. 190 in Benn and Evans 2010). If the rock is very hard and has few or no fractures, then abrasion is predominant or exclusive. When abrasion is the primary means of glacial erosion, the rock exhibits glacial polishing, a distinctive surface texture in which the surface is both grooved in a consistent direction that follows the flow of the ice, and is smoothed to a reflective semi-gloss texture. Because plastic mountain glacial ice (Mohs value 2-4) is far softer than granite (Mohs value 6-7), the ice has has any direct effect on the granite. It is rocks carried along the periphery of the ice that do the majority of the cutting. But even those boulders are not harder than those they are eroding, make up only a small percentage of the glacier edges. And liquid water and micro air pockets lubricate the contact between the glaciers and valley rock, so the erosion rate is very slow, on the order of less than a millimeter to a few millimeters per year (Hallett et al. 1996; Benn and Evans 2010; Wirsig et al. 2016). The short term erosive power of glaciers in hard rock valleys is illusive, not amounting to much on a yearly or even century basis. That is why when matters are going on the slow side they are often referred to being glacial in their pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of Yosemite granite is unfractured and about as hard as igneous rock gets. The sheer walls of Yosemite exhibit the glacial polishing that confirms it was cut ever so slowly by abrasion (Duhnforth et al. 2010). Thus, it took hundreds of thousands of years’ worth of river cutting and glacial grinding at a rate of a few millimeters per year to gouge out the 8 square miles worth of granite that forms the 8 mile long, 1 mile wide and deep Yosemite Valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In pseudoscientific YEC mythology the Sierra Nevada Batholith formed as a result of the galloping continental drift during the flood. While being uplifted above sea level and/or shortly afterwards, it was fast cooled by underground water conversion into steam – the kind of process that would have helped boil the global flood sea – while the hardening magma that somehow remains solid rather than infiltrated with water-steam channel cavities. In this time pressed scheme the fantastically swift cooling to below 0°C is needed to allow ice to shortly come along and quickly cut the fresh granite. But such rapid cooling would not have allowed the formation of that existing tough, big crystal, fracture free solid rock it is. Instead the batholith would have consisted of finer grained, softer volcanics like those that form when surface lavas rapidly cool (Huber 1987), which is why lavas never form granites. In the YEC scenario there would have been no time for water erosion of the erosion resistant Yosemite material. Instead rock-laced ice would have had to cut through the hard granites by dozens of feet each year to push out the eight square miles down and across in mere centuries, a rate thousands of times faster than observed with contemporary granite valley glaciers, and that like just about everything else concerning YEC violates the physics of the universe we dwell in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While YEC’s have written at length about their ideas on how the Grand Canyon was recently rapidly formed, as far as I know when it comes to Yosemite the only detailed attempt to deal with the big granite gulley is to explain how the Sierra Nevada glacial field could form in just a hundred years or so (Brewer and Vardiman 2010). Although rapid ice buildup in the coastal high Sierras directly downwind of the Pacific is not as outlandishly impossible as such is in continental interiors, the calculations are a stretch and suffer from the same formation problems noted above. Note that the YEC’s do not try to pass off the formation of the valley to some form of rapid faulting driven by superquakes, there being no evidence for such.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What the YEC’s are abjectly failing to address is how Yosemite granite could have been cut about a mile deep and across in a few hundred years or less when water, solid or liquid, cuts granite extremely slowly. This failure is almost certainly because they cannot devise anything close to an explanation for such a fantastical event that wouldn’t be eye rolling even for YEC’s. In a cynical effort to brush aside the Yosemite difficulty, an AIG PR tract merely alludes to how the “weathering and erosive power of this glacier was immense” (Snelling 2015). The hard fact is that the erosive power of glaciers in tough granite valleys is immense only over immense geological (and non-Biblical) stretches of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Science Based Reality Check of Faith Based Genesis&lt;/strong&gt;
Let’s turn the situation around and consider what our planet would be like if it were formed a half-dozen millennia ago, and a planetary flood occurred about 1500 years after that, followed by a quick ice age. This hypothesis would be verified if radiometrics did not  produce dates much over 6000 years, or if there were not evidence of significant continental drift, nor of granitic plutons that take long spans to cool. Sediments deposited during the super flood would exhibit a chaotic mix of creatures rather than the layered, increasingly complex pattern predicted by evolution. The Canadian shield would be covered by thick soils, there would not be glacial erratics in northern Ohio, and there would not be super moraines such as Long Island. Water erosion of highlands, whether glacial or liquid, would have had too little time to do much to hard rock. Yosemite and other granitic valleys would not exist, and nothing more than superficial polish veneers would record the short term ice age in and on the tough surfaced highlands. And the universe would be only a few thousand light years across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Creationist Credibility Problem&lt;/strong&gt;
That YEC adherents are evading the obvious impossibility of forming famed Yosemite and other resilient rock valleys around the globe in a few hundred years helps expose the pseudoscientific depth of their methods. Their hypocritical tactics of not telling their followers of the many major logic gaps inherent to their unscientific beliefs – including the field trips they hold at Yosemite – are similar to those who promote the new belief in ancient aliens founding human civilization. The latter creation myth according to surveys, may have become more popular than the declining belief in YEC, as have the existence of bigfoot, psychic powers, astrology, the Loch Ness monster, and Elvis being alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some YEC’s, seeing the super inanity of trying to compress all of universal planetary and human history into six millennia, allow that earth might be tens of millennia old. Although this alleviates the time compression problems a little, it still does not allow enough time to allow glaciers to sculpt Yosemite Valley, much less large portions of continents. At the same time, breaking the 6000-year Biblical temporal barrier denies the perfection of scripture’s divine author, rendering the fundamentalist YEC program moot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;YEC’s must convincingly directly explain every critical point raised herein – piling up vast ice sheets in mere centuries including sustaining for that time the dramatic continent/marine temperature differential, having the Laurentide shield move much of Canada into the USA in that time piling up Long Island et al., cooling the Yosemite pluton into very hard granite in decades and cutting it a mile deep in mere centuries, and so forth. This includes producing advanced computer simulations verifying the YEC speculations. Otherwise it is religion-based pseudoscience mixed with conspiracy theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Using Yosemite for Science Promotion&lt;/strong&gt;
While Yosemite in a never ending migraine headache for creationism so toxic to the cause that they ignore it as much as they can, it is a whopping yet oddly underutilized tool for science education that goes untapped. The Grand Canyon has been the premiere super sized chasm for presenting deep geotime to the public, but YEC’s think they can explain it away. In public educational terms, beloved Yosemite is the most readily understandable example (and least subject to seeming refutation) of how a giant canyon could not have been formed in the few hundreds or even thousands of years that the faith-based YEC movement demands that all must believe. It should be at the leading edge of rational outreach as a go-to, user-friendly example of how it took soft ice hundreds of millennia to dig out tough granite a mile deep and wide, firmly disproving the Genesis timeline. This may help accelerate the decline in creationist opinion and Biblical literalism already underway in the USA (Newport 2022; Brenan 2024).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AIG. 2018. Bible Timeline. https://answersingenesis.org/bible-timeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anderson, D. 2018. Formation of Yosemite Valley. https://www.yosemite.ca.us/formation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brenan, M. 2014. Majority still credits God for humankind, but not creationism. Gallup. https://news.gallup.com/poll/647594/majority-credits-god-humankind-not-creationism.aspx.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brewer, W. and L. Vardiman. 2010. Numerical simulation of precipitation in Yosemite National Park with a warm ocean: A pineapple express case study. Answers Research Journal. https://answersingenesis.org/environmental-science/ice-age/simulation-of-precipitation-in-yosemite-with-warm-ocean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Broad, W. 2018. How the ice age shaped New York. The New York Times 6/5.  https://www.nytimes.com/2018/06/05/science/how-the-ice-age-shaped-new-york.html.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burgess, E. et al. 2010. A spatially calibrated model of annual accumulation rate on the Greenland ice sheet (1958-2007). Journal of Geophysical Research 115:1-14.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Casey, K. et al. 2014. The 1500 m South Pole ice core: recovering a 40 ka environmental record. Annals of Glaciology 55:137-146.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Duhnforth, M. et al. 2010. Bedrock fracture control of glacial erosion processes and rates. Geology 38:423-426.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graham, R. 2018. How to calculate rain to snow. Sciencing.  https://sciencing.com/calculate-rain-snow-8344589.html.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hallet, B., L. Hunter and J. Bogen. 1996. Rates of erosion and sediment evacuation by glaciers: A review of field data and their implications. Global and Planetary Change 12: 213-235.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huber, N. 1987. The geologic story of Yosemite Park. USGS Bulletin 1595. https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/b1595.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isaac, R. 2007. Assessing the RATE project. Perspectives on Science &amp;amp; Christian Faith June: 143-146. eleted them all by hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kohler, P. and Wal, R. S. W. 2020. Interglacial of the Quaternary defined by northern hemispheric land ice distribuation outside of Greenland. Nature Communications 11:5124.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morton, G. and G. Murphy. 2004. Flaws in a young—earth cooling mechanism. Reports of the National Center for Science Education 24(1): 31-32. https://ncse.com/library-resource/flaws-young-earth-cooling-mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newport, F. 2022. Fewer in U.S. now see Bible as literal word of God. Gallup. https://news.gallup.com/poll/394262/fewer-bible-literal-word-god.aspx.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oard, M. 2004. The Genesis flood caused the ice age. https://answersingenesis.org/environmental-science/ice-age/genesis-flood-caused-the-ice-age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oard, M. 2007a. Where does the ice age fit? The New Answers Book 1. https://answersingenesis.org/environmental-science/ice-age/where-does-the-ice-age-fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oard, M. 2007b. Setting the stage for an ice age. Answers Magazine. https://answersingenesis.org/environmental-science/ice-age/setting-the-stage-for-an-ice-age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snelling, A. 2015. Yosemite Valley – colossal ice carving. Answers Magazine. https://answersingenesis.org/geology/catastrophism/yosemite-valley-colossal-ice-carving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snelling, A. and M. Matthews. 2013. When was the ice age in biblical history? Answers Magazine. https://answersingenesis.org/environmental-science/ice-age/when-was-the-ice-age-in-biblical-history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;USGS. The Laurentide Ice Sheet. https://notendur.hi.is/thorstur/teaching/glac/2012_group4_LaurentideIceSheet_notes.pdf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vardiman, L, A. Snelling and E, Chaffin. 2005. Radioisotopes and the Age of the Earth. Waco: Institute for Creation Research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wirsig, C. et al. 2016. Subglacial abrasion rates at Goldbergkees, Hohe Tauern, Austria, determined from cosmogenic 10Be and 36CI concentrations. Earth Surface Processes and Landforms. https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/esp.4093.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gregory Paul</name></author><summary type="html">The author at Yosemite. Gregory Paul is an independent polymath researcher including in paleozoology and geology. His technical studies and popular articles have appeared in Scientific American, BioScience, The Anatomical Record, Annals of the Carnegie Museum, Evolutionary Theory, Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology, Journal of Paleontology, Modern Geology, Historical Biology, Paleobiology, Evolutionary Biology, Cretaceous Research, Science, Nature. His work has been covered by the New York Times, Washington Post, Science Friday, Science News, New Scientist, Discover, Reuters. He designed the Tyrannosaurus in Jurassic Park. This article focuses on a subject that has received not much in the way of consideration, the young earth creationist (YEC) view of the Ice Age that they propose followed the super flood. In this examination I am going to put some emphasis on one of the biggest canyons in these United States. Not the often discussed Grand Canyon – the reasons why that colossal ditch was formed as a classic riverine V-shaped valley over millions of years in rocks up to 1.25 billion years old, rather than suddenly cut by a super flood in short order in post-flood deposits, has been well detailed. The valley focused on here is Yosemite. Yosemite has received notably little attention in either the anti- or pro- creationist literature. That is both despite, and precisely because, the California canyon poses overwhelming problems that YEC theory lacks practical means of explaining. This article also focuses on the apologetics of the top two creationist organizations, the Institute for Creation Research and, especially, Answers in Genesis headed by the most popular living YEC, Ken Ham. The Creationist Conspiracy Theory versus the Natural Truth That the role played by the 2.5 year old Quaternary Ice Age is on the side burner of the creation debate is ironic in that it played a critical role in beginning the scientific undermining of scriptural creationism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Darwin Day 2025</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/darwin-day-2025.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Darwin Day 2025" /><published>2025-01-22T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-01-22T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/darwin-day-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/01/darwin-day-2025.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Escultura_de_Charles_Darwin.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sculpture of Darwin.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Credit: Luisalvaz, &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Escultura_de_Charles_Darwin_en_la_Facultad_de_Ciencias_de_la_UNAM_02.jpg&quot;&gt;Escultura de Charles Darwin, con la barba y las cejas rosas, en la Facultad de Ciencias de la UNAM&lt;/a&gt;, 20 January 2024, CC BY-SA 4.0.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darwin_Day&quot;&gt;Darwin Day&lt;/a&gt;, variously known, I think, as Evolution Day and later Evolution Weekend and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theclergyletterproject.org/rasweekend2025.html&quot;&gt;Religion and Science Weekend&lt;/a&gt;, commemorates Darwin’s birthday on February 12, 1809 (yes, the same day as Abraham Lincoln).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Center for Science Education warns us that &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/darwin-day-2025-approaches&quot;&gt;Darwin Day approaches&lt;/a&gt; and announces:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt; For its part, NCSE, with the National Association of Biology Teachers and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8qNWW6NRfjE&quot;&gt;Katie Hinde&lt;/a&gt;, will be reprising the popular evolution symposium &quot;A Lioness Walks Into an Orca: How Stories Enhance Science Education&quot; and sharing exciting information about the 2025 March Mammal Madness tournament online at 7:00 p.m. Eastern on February 12, 2025 (details to be announced). And of course, NCSE will be active on social media in support of evolution education — look for (and use) the hashtag #whyteachevolution on Darwin Day, and check out our #whyteachevolution &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/why-teach-evolution-2020&quot;&gt;essays&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to search a little harder to find other events.  Here they come:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.evolutionmeetings.org&quot;&gt;Evolution 2025&lt;/a&gt; is the joint meeting of the American Society of Naturalists, the Society of Systematic Biologists, and the Society for the Study of Evolution.  The meeting is one of the premiere international opportunities for sharing research on evolutionary biology. “The conference will be held in 2 parts:  A 2 day virtual conference with live online workshops, talks, symposia, and networking events May 29-30, followed a few weeks later by a 5 day in-person conference in Athens, GA, USA at the Classic Center, June 20-24, 2025.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://darwinday.org/events/list/?tribe-bar-date=2025-02-01&quot;&gt;International Darwin Day&lt;/a&gt; listed four events:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;February 12, 7:00-8:30 pm, Darwin Day Lecture: &quot;Twists and Turns in Teaching Evolution over the Years, Calkins Science Center - Grand Rapids Community College , 226 Bostwick Ave. NE, Grand Rapids, MI, United States. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 12, 7:00-9:00 pm, Darwin Day, &quot;Evolution und Medizin,&quot; Siegmund Freud Universität, Freudplatz 3, Wien, Austria. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 13, 6:00-7:30 pm, &quot;The Past is the Key to the Future: Oregon’s Fossil Rodents and the Impacts of Environmental Change,&quot; The Museum of Natural and Cultural History, 1680 E. 15th Ave., Eugene, OR, United States. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;April 4-5, Iowa City Darwin Day: Science Fest, three speakers for talks on Friday, April 4 and Saturday, April 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may find URL's and further information on the Darwin Day website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to search for others and found the following after a relatively few minutes of searching for Darwin Day and Evolution Weekend:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;14-15 February 2025, 12:00-5:00pm (1 hour tours),  &lt;a href=&quot;https://essig.berkeley.edu/events/darwin-day/&quot;&gt;Essig Museum of Entomology&lt;/a&gt;, University of California, Berkeley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunday, February 23, 12-4 pm EST &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/darwin-day-2025-celebration-at-the-mcclung-tickets-1154833872199&quot;&gt;McClung Museum of Natural History &amp;amp; Culture&lt;/a&gt;, Knoxville, TN 37916&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 14-16, 2025, Religion and Science Weekend (formerly Evolution Weekend), noted above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 28, 5-8 pm, &lt;a href=&quot;https://eeb.tamu.edu/darwin-day/darwin-day-2025/&quot;&gt;An Annual Celebration of All Things Biology!&lt;/a&gt;, Ecology &amp;amp; Evolutionary Biology Program at Texas A&amp;amp;M University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Date and time not given. &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution.wisc.edu/darwin-day/&quot;&gt;The Gene’s Eye View of Evolution&lt;/a&gt;, J. Arvid Ågren, evolutionary biologist and author of The Gene’s-Eye View of Evolution, J.F. Crow Institute for the Study of Evolution. Also art contest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 17, 7-9 pm UTC, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/northern-ireland-humanists/events/303805213/&quot;&gt;Annual Darwin Day Lecture: How evolution gave us Free Will&lt;/a&gt;, Kevin Mitchell, Associate Professor, Genetics and Neuroscience, Trinity College Dublin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 10, Darwin Day Speaker, Timothy Mousseau, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stonybrook.edu/commcms/ecoevo/_events/darwinday.php&quot;&gt;Evolution across Mutagenic Landscapes: Adventures at Chernobyl, Fukushima, and Other Hot Places&lt;/a&gt;, Department of Ecology and Evolution, Stony Brook University&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 15, 10 am-3 pm local time, &lt;a href=&quot;https://uwm.edu/geosciences/event/darwin-day-at-the-thomas-a-greene-geological-museum/&quot;&gt;Darwin Day at the Thomas A. Greene Geological Museum&lt;/a&gt;, University of Wisconsin Milwaukee, Geosciences. Looks like an open house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please use the comments to add any further events as you discover them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Credit: Luisalvaz, Escultura de Charles Darwin, con la barba y las cejas rosas, en la Facultad de Ciencias de la UNAM, 20 January 2024, CC BY-SA 4.0. Darwin Day, variously known, I think, as Evolution Day and later Evolution Weekend and Religion and Science Weekend, commemorates Darwin’s birthday on February 12, 1809 (yes, the same day as Abraham Lincoln). The National Center for Science Education warns us that Darwin Day approaches and announces: For its part, NCSE, with the National Association of Biology Teachers and Katie Hinde, will be reprising the popular evolution symposium &quot;A Lioness Walks Into an Orca: How Stories Enhance Science Education&quot; and sharing exciting information about the 2025 March Mammal Madness tournament online at 7:00 p.m. Eastern on February 12, 2025 (details to be announced). And of course, NCSE will be active on social media in support of evolution education — look for (and use) the hashtag #whyteachevolution on Darwin Day, and check out our #whyteachevolution essays. I had to search a little harder to find other events. Here they come:</summary></entry></feed>