<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-02-24T12:21:10-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Chemistry Professor Paul Kilmartin on “mauri” in the NZ Chemistry/Biology curriculum</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/NZ-mauri-chemistry-kilmartin-seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chemistry Professor Paul Kilmartin on “mauri” in the NZ Chemistry/Biology curriculum" /><published>2022-02-20T17:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-02-20T17:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/NZ-mauri-chemistry-kilmartin-seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/NZ-mauri-chemistry-kilmartin-seminar.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Paul_Kilmartin.png&quot; alt=&quot;[Prof. Paul Kilmartin university webpage]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Prof. Paul Kilmartin's university webpage. &lt;a href=&quot;https://unidirectory.auckland.ac.nz/profile/p-kilmartin&quot;&gt;Source: UoA webpage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday, February 18, I attended (on Zoom) a fascinating seminar given by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unidirectory.auckland.ac.nz/profile/p-kilmartin&quot;&gt;Paul Kilmartin, Professor of Chemistry&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auckland.ac.nz/en/science/about-the-faculty/school-of-chemical-sciences.html&quot;&gt;School of Chemical Sciences&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auckland.ac.nz/en.html&quot;&gt;University of Auckland&lt;/a&gt;, here in Aotearoa/New Zealand. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://unidirectory.auckland.ac.nz/profile/nmat471&quot;&gt;I work&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auckland.ac.nz/en/science/about-the-faculty/school-of-biological-sciences.html&quot;&gt;School of Biological Sciences&lt;/a&gt; at the same institution.) Prof. Kilmartin specialises in wine chemistry, among other things, and in addition to chemistry, has degrees in theology and philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kilmartin’s talk was entitled &lt;b&gt;“Chemistry and Mātauranga Māori: A Conversation.”&lt;/b&gt; Kilmartin has given me permission to quote this part of his talk, below, which covers science education material of international interest. I will also include the talk summary. Other parts of Kilmartin’s seminar focused on his own background coming to this issue (Scottish and Māori ancestry, member of &lt;a href=&quot;https://ngaitahu.iwi.nz/&quot;&gt;Ngāi Tahu&lt;/a&gt;, deep knowledge of Ngāi Tahu history and land claims), and ideas for Auckland’s chemistry program to explore regarding mātauranga Māori.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Panda’s Thumb blog has an international readership interested in science and science education, and I have been involved with science education controversies for 20 years (and with PT for 18!). But I’m sure the NZ situation is new to many readers. Therefore, I will give some background/introduction to the controversy around the science curriculum, after the quote from Kilmartin’s talk.  For more (much more) on current science education controversies in New Zealand, please search &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.google.com/search?q=science%2C%20M%C4%81tauranga%20M%C4%81ori&amp;amp;hl=en-NZ&amp;amp;gl=NZ&amp;amp;ceid=NZ%3Aen&quot;&gt;Google News&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=science%20%20M%C4%81tauranga%20M%C4%81ori&amp;amp;src=typed_query&amp;amp;f=live&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/?s=mauri+zealand&amp;amp;orderby=relevance&amp;amp;order=DESC&amp;amp;post_type=post&quot;&gt;blogs&lt;/a&gt; etc. on the various terms mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;(Please not that all of non-talk material is written by me, and should not necessarily be taken as Kilmartin’s views. And, these are my personal views, not those of current or former employers.)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Quotes from: “Chemistry and Mātauranga Māori: A Conversation”&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Seminar by Professor Paul Kilmartin&lt;br /&gt;
School of Chemical Sciences, University of Auckland&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[Comments/clarifications by Matzke are in square brackets like this.]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[Seminar given on Zoom by Prof. Paul Kilmartin at 2022-02-18 at 11 am.]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[Around 27 minutes in, Kilmartin continues...]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The second Ministry of Education text I would like to comment upon concerns proposals for NCEA science. The courses here involve so-called Big Ideas, and the inclusions of concepts drawn from Mātauranga Māori.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
These were proposed last year for inclusion in the NCEA curriculum, and have been piloted in some schools.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I understand that this year, a further 5 schools will be involved in mini-pilots, with full pilots to take place next year, and full implementation by 2024.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
One of the Big Ideas in the Chemistry area has to do with the properties of matter, as follows:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Kilmartin1.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
But what is mauri? Its definition is important for teachers and students alike. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The following Glossary is provided, where mauri is defined as:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Kilmartin2.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[Then follows several minutes of discussion of various definitions and usages of the mauri concept; Kilmartin states that insofar as mauri is used to refer to a concept like individual or ecosystem health, he can work with it.  Kilmartin also discusses Prof. T.K.K.B. Morgan's &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mauriometer.com/&quot;&gt;mauri-o-meter&lt;/a&gt;, etc.]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[Resume at about minute 33:00]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
But is there more to the concept of mauri than this?  In an earlier publication, within a civil engineers' proceeding, Prof. Morgan provides more background to mauri. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Kilmartin3.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
And there are some new concepts here. Not only do all natural objects possess it, mauri is seen as the binding force between the physical and the spiritual. Indeed, when mauri is impacted and the bond weakened, the physical and the spiritual are separated, leading to death.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
One question is whether using mauri in the sense of life-supporting capacity implies all of this additional meaning.  If it does, then I would want to ask, Who discovered this binding force between the physical and the spiritual?  And what evidence was involved in its discovery? If this binding force is real, then everyone needs to know about it. It needs to be in the chemistry syllabus of every country, not just in New Zealand.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
So how has this new syllabus been received by teachers? We have one publication on this topic from last year [&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.46786/ac21.1591&quot;&gt;Stewart and Tedoldi 2021&lt;/a&gt;], which explains that the inclusion of Māori concepts is an attempt to reflect the principal of equal mana, mana ōrite, for Māori knowledge -- one of the seven principles within the NCEA Change package, announced by the government in May 2019.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Kilmartin4.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
We also learn that these proposals have sparked heated discussions, in which NCEA science teachers have referred to Māori knowledge as &quot;myths and legends,&quot; or &quot;’spiritual concepts’ that do not belong in the science curriculum.&quot; Well, good on the teachers for having their say.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The authors of this article [&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.46786/ac21.1591&quot;&gt;Stewart and Tedoldi 2021&lt;/a&gt;] have other views. The problem with the teachers is seen as a narrow understanding of what is living, as taught under the &quot;MRS GREN&quot; life processes: Movement, Respiration, Sensitivity, Growth, Reproduction, Excretion, and Nutrition, and I remember teaching MRS GREN in my two years as a secondary school teacher in Christchurch in the early 90s.  Instead this should be expanded to consider a river as living. To support this understanding, teachers are recommended to look to the Gaia concept of the Earth as a living thing. I hadn't heard much about Gaia recently, and it was much more popular in the 80s and 90s, and I might be showing my age here.  I had to look up Wikipedia for some recent information. There is every indication that Gaia has little current following in the scientific community, after some years of more active debate.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
One final example of mauri is of interest to myself as an electrochemist, given our use of electricity to interface with chemistry.  And this relates to domestic electrical wiring. In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worksafe.govt.nz/dmsdocument/1580-new-zealand-electrical-code-of-practice-for-homeowneroccupiers-electrical-wiring-work-in-domestic-installations-nzecp-51-2004&quot;&gt;current New Zealand Electrical Code of Practice&lt;/a&gt;, we are encouraged to think of the Green/Yellow=Earth wire as a Papatuanuku or Earth Mother. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Kilmartin5.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I must admit, I do have trouble taking this seriously, and I doubt the use of tapu and noa in this matter matches their meaning within Mātauranga Māori.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
My own view is that the concept of mauri has no place in the Chemistry curriculum. I would suggest to re-write the Big Idea along these lines:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Kilmartin6.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[...]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[References cited above]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Georgina Stewart and Angelo Tedoldi (2021). Bringing Māori concepts into school science: NCEA. Access: Contemporary Issues in Education. 41(1), 77-81. https://pesaagora.com/access-vol-41/bringing-maori-concepts-into-school-science-ncea/ &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Gaia – Wikipedia. Wikimedia Foundation. Accessed 2022-02-18. https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaia &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
T. K. K. B. Morgan (2006). Decision-support tools and the indigenous paradigm. Proceedings of the Institution of Civil Engineers - Engineering Sustainability. 159(4), 169-177. December 2006. https://www.icevirtuallibrary.com/doi/10.1680/ensu.2006.159.4.169 &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
NCEA (2021). Science: Chemistry and Biology. NCEA Level 1 Curriculum.&lt;br /&gt; https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/chemistry-and-biology?view=learning . Accessed 2022-02-18.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
NCEA (2021). Chemistry and Biology Glossary. NCEA Level 1 Curriculum. &lt;br /&gt;
https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/chemistry-and-biology?view=subject-glossary . Accessed 2022-02-18.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;poster&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Poster&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give a fuller summary of the talk, here is the poster advertising and summarising Kilmartin’s seminar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Paul_Kilmartin_talk_poster.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; alt=&quot;[Paul Kilmartin poster for Feb. 18 chemistry seminar on mātauranga Māori]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Poster for Paul Kilmart's Feb. 18 seminar in the School of Chemical Sciences, University of Auckland on mātauranga Māori and the NCEA Chemistry curriculum&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the text for the same:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Poster and summary of Kilmartin Seminar&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
School of Chemical Sciences - Friday Seminar Series&lt;br /&gt;
Friday 18 February 2022&lt;br /&gt;
11 am&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Chemistry and Mātauranga Māori&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;A Conversation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Professor Paul Kilmartin&lt;br /&gt;
School of Chemical Sciences, University of Auckland&lt;br /&gt;
https://unidirectory.auckland.ac.nz/profile/p-kilmartin &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The NCEA Education web-site provides the following material for the “Big Idea” named “Properties of matter are determined by attractive forces between particles”, prepared for teaching Chemistry and Biology as a consolidated subject at Curriculum level 6 (NCEA 1):&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Mauri is present in all matter. All particles have their own mauri and presence as part of a larger whole, for example within a molecule, polymer, salt, or metal. When matter is broken into smaller particles each particle remains as part of the taiao [environment], for example when a substance is burnt or dissolved the particles remain, with their own mauri.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A glossary definition of mauri is also provided:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The vital essence, life force of everything: be it a physical object, living thing or ecosystem. In Chemistry and Biology, mauri refers to the health and life-sustaining capacity of the taiao, on biological, physical, and chemical levels.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/chemistry-and-biology?view=learning &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
This presentation will provide a personal perspective on several issues related to Chemistry and Mātauranga Māori. These will include selected points from Ngāi Tahu/family history, through to a critique of recent Ministry of Education publications where Mātauranga Māori concepts are being brought into the School curriculum.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The presentation will be organised around the following topics:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Moa bones and the Kemp purchase&lt;br /&gt;
Rowallan land blocks&lt;br /&gt;
The Opihi Taniwha&lt;br /&gt;
Ngā Tautake Pūtaiao me ngā Kōrero o Mua&lt;br /&gt;
Chemistry curriculum&lt;br /&gt;
Legitimate voices&lt;br /&gt;
Future opportunities for the School of Chemical Sciences&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A 45 minute presentation will be followed by ample time for discussion.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In addition to his chemistry background, Paul has degrees in philosophy and theology, and is a Trustee on two blocks of forested land provided to the family under 1906 SILNA act. His research into family history has been deposited with the Ngāi Tahu whakapapa unit.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;background&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quick Backgrounder for international readers (by Matzke)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;i&gt;mātauranga Māori&lt;/i&gt; means Māori knowledge.  (It is often just “mātauranga” when the context is obvious; it is often also abbreviated MM.) Often this primarily refers to traditional indigenous knowledge, but it can also include newer knowledge that was developed or incorporated more recently.  Much more detail is available via google, see for example the Māori dictionary and mātauranga Māori and science, from the NZ Science Learning Hub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was hired in NZ in 2018, and I have gradually learned of a widespread movement to promote MM at all levels. For example, it is an aspect of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mbie.govt.nz/science-and-technology/science-and-innovation/agencies-policies-and-budget-initiatives/vision-matauranga-policy/&quot;&gt;Vision Mātauranga&lt;/a&gt;, the governmental strategy for encouraging scientific research that benefits Māori interests. It is promoted in university strategic plans, and in school systems.  All of this is motivated by many honorable values. I cannot list them all, but motivations include everything from (1) making science education and research more interesting and relevant to Māori students, through to (2) encouraging Māori cultural advancement and renewal (much like government promotion of te reo Māori, the Māori language) – especially important to help repair damaged caused by colonisation, through to (3) economic and conservation benefits that could accrue from deploying traditional knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is well and good, and it is hard to see how anyone could reasonably object to these ideas in general. However, specifics and implementation matter a lot, and controversy has recently arisen over a governmental policy to revise the school curriculum with guideline mandating “parity” between “Western science” and mātauranga Māori. In July 2021, seven professors (full or emeritus) from the University of Auckland wrote a letter to a NZ magazine, &lt;i&gt;The Listener&lt;/i&gt;, objecting to this and other Ministry of Education statements. The initial reaction was swift and harshly negative, as some perceived the letter as denigrating mātauranga.  But over time a more normal public discussion ensued in &lt;i&gt;The Listener&lt;/i&gt; and elsewhere (which is ongoing), and now the Vice Chancellor of the University of Auckland, Dawn Freshwater, has stated “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeshighereducation.com/news/auckland-plans-dialogue-maori-knowledge-and-science&quot;&gt;Nobody is wrong here&lt;/a&gt;,” and promised to host an academic symposium to thoroughly discuss the various issues raised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(The symposium was going to be in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeshighereducation.com/news/auckland-plans-dialogue-maori-knowledge-and-science&quot;&gt;first quarter of 2022&lt;/a&gt;, but now the omicron variant of SARS-CoV-2 has slipped through quarantine, and NZ is experiencing it’s first huge wave of SARS-CoV-2. I say SARS-CoV-2, because NZ is highly vaccinated and omicron is milder, so hopefully we will avoid most of the actual Covid disease. In any case, the University of Auckland is online-only (mostly) for at least the first half of Semester 1, so I imagine the symposium will likely be delayed.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was not involved in &lt;i&gt;The Listener&lt;/i&gt; controversy, except to try to defend the principle of academic freedom of everyone involved. To me, the word “parity” could mean a lot of things, NZ generally seems like a place where common sense prevails (rather than everything going to the nuclear option of litigation or political polarisation, as occurs in the USA), and in any case I’m just a recent immigrant, lucky to be here. It seemed to me that the whole debate needed to happen in long-form (rather than letters, petitions, and tweets) where issues can be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rnz.co.nz/news/on-the-inside/448453/let-s-choose-our-words-more-carefully-when-discussing-matauranga-maori-and-science&quot;&gt;discussed thoroughly&lt;/a&gt;, and perhaps now this will happen in the VC’s Symposium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there has been a new development. The NZ Ministry of Education’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/&quot;&gt;NCEA (“National Certificate of Educational Achievement”)&lt;/a&gt; released its curricula for a &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;variety of classes at NCEA Level 1&lt;/a&gt; (translation: students approximately age 15-16). NCEA Levels 2 and 3 are essentially university preparatory material, and include high-stakes exams run by NZQA, relevant for credits for University admissions. Level 1 is more basic material, and some students choose to skip Level 1 to go straight to higher levels, but the “NCEA Change Process” will move to Levels 2 and 3 when NCEA Level 1 changes are completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NCEA Level 1 includes classes on &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/chemistry-and-biology?view=learning&quot;&gt;Chemistry and Biology&lt;/a&gt; (CB), general &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/science?view=learning&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt; (SC), &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/physics-earth-and-space-science?view=learning&quot;&gt;Physics Earth and Space Science&lt;/a&gt; (PESS), and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/mathematics-and-statistics/mathematics-and-statistics?view=learning&quot;&gt;Mathematics and Statistics&lt;/a&gt; (MS). Reviewing the curricula, some of it, including some of the mātauranga Māori content, seems fine, or at least not something to raise a public ruckus about. (E.g., the curriculum is often pretty vague and general, but NZ deliberately decided to not create hyper-detailed curricula like the 1000+ page curricula used in Australia.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But some of it is…very surprising. The example that leapt out to me is also the section that Kilmartin critiqued: the chemistry discussion of atoms, molecules, chemical bonds, and conservation of mass/energy/the First Law of Thermodynamics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is some quick translations for the international reader. Please see the NCEA glossary or other online resources for more:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;ākonga&lt;/b&gt; = students&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;taiao&lt;/b&gt; = the environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;kaitiakitanga&lt;/b&gt; = guardianship and protection, e.g. of the environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;whakapapa&lt;/b&gt; = genealogy framework used to record relationships (genealogical or otherwise), but more generally, it is often used to refer to heritage, inheritance, cultural and familial connections, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;mauri&lt;/b&gt; (quoting from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/chemistry-and-biology?view=subject-glossary&quot;&gt;NCEA Glossary&lt;/a&gt;) = &quot;The vital essence, life force of everything: be it a physical object, living thing or ecosystem. In Chemistry and Biology, mauri refers to the health and life-sustaining capacity of the taiao, on biological, physical, and chemical levels.&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NCEA Chemistry and Biology curriculum says (or said as of November 2021, if they change it, which they eventually will have to):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;b&gt;Big Idea: Properties of matter are determined by attractive forces between particles&lt;/b&gt;

Mauri is present in all matter. All particles have their own mauri and presence as part of a larger whole, for example within a molecule, polymer, salt, or metal. When matter is broken into smaller particles each particle remains as part of the taiao, for example when a substance is burnt or dissolved the particles remain, with their own mauri. They do not just disappear.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is meant by “mauri” here?  We might avoid conflict by imagining that the term is being used here to refer to individual or ecosystem health, as it is some other places in the curriculum. Elsewhere in his talk, Kilmartin notes that concepts of health are something that he can work with as a scientist, and I agree. For example, a toxin might damage an individual organism, chemical pollution might damage an ecosystem, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that interpretation cannot be applied to this Big Idea. For starters, virtually all matter in the Universe has zero to do with health of living things, because it is outside of our solar system. Even if we stretch the health interpretation to some science fiction scenario where humans and other Earth organisms have escaped our solar system, most of the relevance of various “particles” to organismal/ecosystem health is not due just to the particles’ properties; we must also consider their temperature, arrangement, relative amounts, and the needs of the various organisms. Methane in large amounts is toxic to humans, healthy to certain microorganisms, and deadly to all of them on Titan where the temperature is -179.6 degrees Celsius on a hot day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in any event, whatever “life-sustaining” capacity of a particle we might imagine, it decidedly does &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; remain upon being burnt. Oxygen (O2) is necessary for human life, but carbon dioxide (CO2), the product of burning carbon-containing compounds like methane in oxygen, is toxic at sufficient levels.  If by “particles”, the NCEA actually meant “atoms”, (a) they should have just said that, and (b) while the “atom” interpretation does refer to something that doesn’t change upon burning, understanding atomic properties is fairly remote from understanding health impacts, which mostly concern how molecules interact with organismal processes, and (c) the term “particles” explicitly refers to “molecule, polymer, salt, or metal” in the standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The passage does not make sense if interpreted as referring to health impacts. What we are left with is the more fundamental definition of mauri, which is closer to its original usage anyway, which is the “vital essence, life force of everything.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the concept of a life force or vital essence is…vitalism!  And vitalism is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/topic/vitalism&quot;&gt;very old&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6208063/&quot;&gt;very very discredited&lt;/a&gt; idea. Wohler’s 1828 synthesis of urea from inorganic compounds, when it was previously thought to be an organic molecule produced only by life, was later recognized as an early episode in the defeat of vitalism, and is cited in virtually all chemistry textbooks and classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note that, as is always the case when the history of science is explored in depth, the history is more complex than the defeat of vitalism in a single experiment. Vitalism was an amorphous doctrine, not refutable by a single experiment, but it died a gradual death by many cuts, as experiments accumulated that synthesized various organic compounds from inorganic sources. See Ramberg 2000.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern chemistry and biology, especially organic chemistry and biochemistry, essentially arose through the examination and experimental defeat of vitalism, including the defeat of many rear-guard attempts to defend some reduced version of the concept of a life force or life essence – something “extra” beyond material matter and forces which gave living things the breath of life. To have some government bureaucrats try to bring it back into chemistry by administrative declaration is not going to fly.  Seeing vitalism in chemistry standards is as surprising as it would be to see a Geology curriculum endorse Noah’s Flood or the idea that the Earth is 6,000 years old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;other_problems&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Other problems&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These problems should have been obvious, and they certainly were to the many science teachers who objected. Unfortunately, science teachers’ objections seem to be being hand-waved away by the educational establishment, for example by &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.46786/ac21.1591&quot;&gt;Stewart &amp;amp; Tedoldi (2021)&lt;/a&gt;, who seem to be closely involved with the science curricula. They note the strong objections that science teachers voiced to bringing mauri into the Chemistry/Biology curriculum in this way, but they reply by bringing up…Gaia. Even if one ignored Kilmartin’s point, namely that the Gaia Hypothesis is itself controversial, Gaia aims to explain how the Earth is a homeostatic system; it doesn’t solve the problems with trying to bring back vitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are other huge problems with the inclusion of mauri in the discussion of particles, chemical bonds, and conservation of mass.  These include: What will be on the exams? Will one question be a chemical formula, and the next a spiritual concept?  Won’t the inclusion of spiritual concepts in amongst basic chemistry concepts create conflict in the classroom between students (or teachers) with differing spiritual views? Is this even authentic mātauranga, or is it actually something hatched in the bowels of the Ministry of Education in mid-2021 in the service of some goal other than science education? And, especially, how did all of this get pushed through over negative reviews that the Ministry must have gotten from scientists and science teachers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Also, where is the “e-word”, evolution? &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=avoiding+the+e-word%2C+evolution&amp;amp;oq=avoiding+the+e-word%2C+evolution&quot;&gt;Avoiding the e-word in Biology curricula is often a warning sign in itself.&lt;/a&gt; Perhaps the idea is that it can be replaced with the concept of whakapapa, but everything I’ve heard suggests it is wildly oversimplified and basically wrong to equate evolution/phylogeny with whakapapa. But perhaps the Ministry of Education thinks it can just declare they are the same.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is a rather profound meta-issue that keeps arising in these discussions, namely, “Who has the authority to speak?”  Professor Kilmartin (in a part of the talk I did not quote) argues strongly that everyone should be allowed to participate in the discussion – scientists, mātauranga Māori experts, and the general public whose children will be educated under these curricula in the schools. I agree, but there is another point worth making. When the subject is a public school curriculum, we should keep in mind the &lt;i&gt;purpose&lt;/i&gt; of such curricula: to get everyone on the same page, to supply the basic concepts and definitions and will be taught. If an introductory curriculum requires a complex hermeneutic to correctly interpret it, or if advanced knowledge is required to understand it, then the curriculum is failing at its basic purpose. Being simple and clear, providing a common baseline for everyone, is the &lt;i&gt;whole point&lt;/i&gt; of a curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this post is long enough as it is, so these other questions will have to wait for future posts. I do encourage others concerned about the situation with science standards in New Zealand to get in touch (nickmatzke@gmail.com); the way that problems like this can get solved is by activism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;refs&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NCEA/Ministry of Education (2021). SCIENCE: Chemistry and Biology Level 1 Curriculum. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/chemistry-and-biology?view=learning&quot;&gt;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/chemistry-and-biology?view=learning&lt;/a&gt;. Accessed 2022-02-21.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Ross (2021). Does the teaching of indigenous knowledge need to be examined? New Zealand’s embrace of Māori vocabulary goes hand-in-hand with the incorporation of Māori understandings into curricula. But is a debate about the unintended consequences of this move being stifled by fear of speaking out? &lt;i&gt;Times Higher Education&lt;/i&gt;, November 11, 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeshighereducation.com/depth/does-teaching-indigenous-knowledge-need-be-examined&quot;&gt;https://www.timeshighereducation.com/depth/does-teaching-indigenous-knowledge-need-be-examined&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Ross (2021). Auckland plans dialogue on Māori knowledge and science: Vice-chancellor commits to ‘challenging and confronting debate’ on hot-button issue.   &lt;i&gt;Times Higher Education&lt;/i&gt;, December 15, 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeshighereducation.com/news/auckland-plans-dialogue-maori-knowledge-and-science&quot;&gt;https://www.timeshighereducation.com/news/auckland-plans-dialogue-maori-knowledge-and-science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter J. Ramberg (2000) “The Death of Vitalism and The Birth of Organic
Chemistry: Wohler’s Urea Synthesis and the Disciplinary Identity of Organic Chemistry.” &lt;i&gt;Ambix&lt;/i&gt;,
47:3, 170-195, DOI: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1179/amb.2000.47.3.170&quot;&gt;10.1179/amb.2000.47.3.170&lt;/a&gt;
To link to this article: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1179/amb.2000.47.3.170&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1179/amb.2000.47.3.170&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Georgina Tuari Stewart and Angelo Tedoldi (2021). Bringing Māori concepts into school science: NCEA. Access: Contemporary Issues in Education. 41(1), 77-81. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.46786/ac21.1591&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.46786/ac21.1591&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ian Wilkinson (2002). “History of Clinical Chemistry.” &lt;i&gt;The Journal of the International Federation of Clinical Chemistry and Laboratory Medicine&lt;/i&gt; (EJIFCC). 13(4): 114–118. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6208063/&quot;&gt;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6208063/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Note: I am going to be out of town and off the grid on a trek, so I ask other PT moderators to please eliminate spam and trolling in the comments, if any.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Matzke</name></author><summary type="html">Prof. Paul Kilmartin's university webpage. Source: UoA webpage. On Friday, February 18, I attended (on Zoom) a fascinating seminar given by Paul Kilmartin, Professor of Chemistry in the School of Chemical Sciences at the University of Auckland, here in Aotearoa/New Zealand. (I work in the School of Biological Sciences at the same institution.) Prof. Kilmartin specialises in wine chemistry, among other things, and in addition to chemistry, has degrees in theology and philosophy. Kilmartin’s talk was entitled “Chemistry and Mātauranga Māori: A Conversation.” Kilmartin has given me permission to quote this part of his talk, below, which covers science education material of international interest. I will also include the talk summary. Other parts of Kilmartin’s seminar focused on his own background coming to this issue (Scottish and Māori ancestry, member of Ngāi Tahu, deep knowledge of Ngāi Tahu history and land claims), and ideas for Auckland’s chemistry program to explore regarding mātauranga Māori. The Panda’s Thumb blog has an international readership interested in science and science education, and I have been involved with science education controversies for 20 years (and with PT for 18!). But I’m sure the NZ situation is new to many readers. Therefore, I will give some background/introduction to the controversy around the science curriculum, after the quote from Kilmartin’s talk. For more (much more) on current science education controversies in New Zealand, please search Google News, Twitter, blogs etc. on the various terms mentioned. (Please not that all of non-talk material is written by me, and should not necessarily be taken as Kilmartin’s views. And, these are my personal views, not those of current or former employers.) Quotes from: “Chemistry and Mātauranga Māori: A Conversation” Seminar by Professor Paul Kilmartin School of Chemical Sciences, University of Auckland [Comments/clarifications by Matzke are in square brackets like this.] [Seminar given on Zoom by Prof. Paul Kilmartin at 2022-02-18 at 11 am.] [Around 27 minutes in, Kilmartin continues...] The second Ministry of Education text I would like to comment upon concerns proposals for NCEA science. The courses here involve so-called Big Ideas, and the inclusions of concepts drawn from Mātauranga Māori.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Morpho peleides</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/morpho-peleides.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Morpho peleides" /><published>2022-02-14T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-02-14T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/morpho-peleides</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/morpho-peleides.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Mark Sturtevant&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Sturtevant.Morpho.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Morpho butterfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morpho&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Morpho peleides&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; an old morpho butterfly sits out its final days in a local butterfly house. The iridescent blue color is not due to pigment, but is rather a structural color caused by wave interference of light that is reflected from the scales on the upper wing surface. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Mark Sturtevant. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Morpho peleides &amp;ndash; an old morpho butterfly sits out its final days in a local butterfly house. The iridescent blue color is not due to pigment, but is rather a structural color caused by wave interference of light that is reflected from the scales on the upper wing surface.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Neo-Confederate Michael Peroutka to run for Maryland Attorney General</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/neo-confederate-peroutka-to-run.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Neo-Confederate Michael Peroutka to run for Maryland Attorney General" /><published>2022-02-03T16:38:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-02-03T16:38:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/neo-confederate-peroutka-to-run</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/neo-confederate-peroutka-to-run.html">&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps slightly off-topic, but we have not heard from the neo-Confederate and one-time secessionist &lt;a href=&quot;http://americanloons.blogspot.com/2014/05/1022-michael-peroutka.html&quot;&gt;Michael Peroutka&lt;/a&gt; in a long time, not since he &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2014/05/dinosaur-fossil.html&quot;&gt;donated a dinosaur fossil to the Creation &quot;Museum&quot;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2014/11/michael-peroutk.html&quot;&gt;was elected to the Anne Arundel County Council in Maryland&lt;/a&gt;. According to an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.baltimoresun.com/politics/bs-md-pol-peroutka-ag-20220202-x6lcsbwfynaordddshodb7tlt4-story.html&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; by Pamela Wood in yesterday’s  &lt;i&gt;Baltimore Sun&lt;/i&gt;, he now plans a run for Attorney General of Maryland. As we noted in 2014,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;… Michael Peroutka until recently was also a board member of the League of the South, a white supremacist, neo-Confederate and pro-secessionist organization that has been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.splcenter.org/fighting-hate/extremist-files/group/league-south&quot;&gt;named a hate group&lt;/a&gt; by the Southern Poverty Law Center. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us hope that the citizens of Maryland show more discernment than the citizens of Anne Arundel County.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">This is perhaps slightly off-topic, but we have not heard from the neo-Confederate and one-time secessionist Michael Peroutka in a long time, not since he donated a dinosaur fossil to the Creation &quot;Museum&quot; or was elected to the Anne Arundel County Council in Maryland. According to an article by Pamela Wood in yesterday’s Baltimore Sun, he now plans a run for Attorney General of Maryland. As we noted in 2014, … Michael Peroutka until recently was also a board member of the League of the South, a white supremacist, neo-Confederate and pro-secessionist organization that has been named a hate group by the Southern Poverty Law Center. Let us hope that the citizens of Maryland show more discernment than the citizens of Anne Arundel County.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">21st Century Left-Handed DNA</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/21st-century-left-handed-DNA.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="21st Century Left-Handed DNA" /><published>2022-01-31T13:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2022-01-31T13:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/21st-century-left-handed-DNA</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/21st-century-left-handed-DNA.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt; The left-handed DNA helix model that was displayed in the Seattle World's Fair ended up in storage
in a utility tunnel underneath the Pacific Science Center.  (We'll show the image here as soon as we get
permission to show it on this page.)  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/PacSci/photos/pcb.10152437776723855/10152437771508855/&quot;&gt;This link&lt;/a&gt; shows the image on the PSC Facebook page.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On January 11, Matt Young reported that the Institute for Creation Science announced a new logo that depicted left-handed DNA. Although regularly occurring in vivo in the form of Z-DNA left-handed DNA only represent a very tiny proportion of the world’s DNA which consists predominantly of right-handed B-DNA as Watson and Crick described it in their 1954 paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ICR left-handed DNA logo made it on the pages of &lt;a href=&quot;http://users.fred.net/tds/leftdna/&quot;&gt;Tom Schneider’s Left Handed DNA Hall of Fame&lt;/a&gt; immediately and became the sites first entry in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Institute for Creation Research has created a new logo representing their support for left handed DNA research and the ongoing takeover! First reported on 2022 Jan 11, new as of 2022 Jan 112&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases depicting DNA left-handed will be caused by mirroring a correct picture to better suit design purposes or likely more often by copying publicly available pictures. The same may be true for the ICR logo. Still, the incident reminded me of the likely first ever publicly displayed left-handed DNA model that was part of the Science Exhibition at the Seattle World Fair in 1962 which I came across when I studied the history of a right-handed DNA model Max Delbrück purchased for the Institute of Genetics of the University of Cologne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://spl.contentdm.oclc.org/digital/api/singleitem/image/p15015coll3/523/default.jpg&quot;&gt;There were two DNA models on display in the exhibition&lt;/a&gt;, a right-handed ball and stick model and a left-handed abstract model which depicted the four bases of DNA as poker card suits (diamonds, spades, clubs and hearts) adopting a presentation of nucleotides George Gamow used in a 1955 &lt;em&gt;Scientific American&lt;/em&gt; article (1). Both models can be seen in the promotional film &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/iNMpy2dbEgE&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Century 21 Calling&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; starting at 3:33.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Gamow learned about the double helix structure of DNA he suggested a model by which DNA could encode protein sequences. It turned out later that this model was completely wrong (since the intermediate messenger- and transfer-RNA involved in protein synthesis were unknown back then he assumed a direct interaction between DNA and amino acids during the formation of protein chains), but he suggested that a code of triplets of bases of DNA would be sufficient to encode the 20 proteinogenic amino acids. This idea was adopted by Crick who together with Sydney Brenner, Leslie Barnett and R.J. Watts-Tobin proved the three-letter code in 1961. Actually, by the use of T4 one of the phages Delbrück introduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It remains unclear if Delbrück or Gamow, who both studied in Göttingen, Germany, spent some postdoctoral time in Niels Bohr’s lab in Copenhagen, and stayed in contact later in the US, were involved in the planning of the Seattle World Fair Science Exhibition. But Delbrück was corresponding with Hans Neurath who joined the University of Washington School of Medicine
faculty in 1950 to head the new biochemistry department and later would become &lt;a href=&quot;https://magazine.washington.edu/hans-neurath-1909-2002/&quot;&gt;a member of the
national science planning board of the 1962 Seattle World’s Fair&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, its section on molecular biology, a science still in its infancy in 1962, would not have been possible without the scientific work Delbrück had done since the early 1930s. In a 1935 publication also known as the “Green Pamphlet” he, N. Timofeeff-Ressovky and K. G. Zimmer presented evidence that genes are material and not just abstract entities (2). Delbrück envisioned the gene as a collection of atoms that should be accessible for concrete experimental analyses. Since 1938 Delbrück worked in the US where he introduced bacteriophages, viruses that infect bacteria, into the scientific field that would become molecular genetics. Together with Salvador Luria, Delbrück demonstrated that mutations in microorganisms do occur randomly at a certain rate and are not a reaction to selection by a changing environment thereby proving that Darwin’s evolution theory also applies to bacteria (3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 1945 he established a yearly phage course at the Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory that would run until 1970. He also gathered the so-called phage group around him which beside many others consisted of later to become Nobel laureates Salvador Luria, Alfred Hershey, James D. Watson, Frank Stahl, and Renato Dulbecco. Hershey together with Martha Chase showed in 1952 that DNA is the carrier of genetic information. Watson together with Francis Crick unraveled the structure of DNA in 1953. Stahl together with Matthew Meselson later showed that both strands of a given DNA molecule serve as templates for newly synthesized strands thus, resulting in two daughter molecules that consist of one of the strands of the original double helix and a newly formed one (semiconservative mode of replication).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted though, that the Century 21 exhibit didn’t just display DNA as the newest scientific sensation but presented molecular biology in a much broader context that started out from Darwin’s Beagle voyage and presented genetics as the brainchild of evolution theory (4) that via phage genetics represented by a &lt;a href=&quot;https://cdm16118.contentdm.oclc.org/digital/api/singleitem/image/p15015coll3/322/default.jpg&quot;&gt;huge 3D model of the T2 phage&lt;/a&gt;, one of Delbrück’s T phages, led to the elucidation of the double helix structure of DNA as the molecular basis of inheritance. That the final report (5) summarized the exhibition under the title “Evolution and Heredity – From Darwin to DNA” and the visitors path started with the work of Darwin and ended with the DNA models indicates that Evolution Theory and the Modern Synthesis were central to the exhibition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t find contemporary reactions from creationists. However, this may be not surprising because Morris and Whitcomb published The Genesis Flood just the year before and the ICR would only be established a decade later. Thus, creationism in its today’s highly organized form just didn’t exist or any such critique is hidden in archives not accessible today. On the other hand, religion seems to have been a part of the exhibition which offered rooms for prayer and Billy Graham visited the fair. According to James Gilbert who covered the Seattle World’s Fair and especially the astronomy part of the science exhibition in his book “Redeeming Culture: American Religion in an Age of Science” (6) it turned out that “even in an age of science it would be unthinkable to avoid a major gesture towards religion”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was some back and forth regarding the involvement of religion. While there were suggestions for a Shrine for All Faiths, efforts for a Hall of Religions and a World of Religion display even attempts to depict Christianity with all its facets failed and a committee of local protestant churches, the Christian Witness, became the major religious presence with their own building on the fair ground. However, their idea to compete in the marketplace of ideas has not been too successful although reportedly at some point there were more religious than science events. According to Gilbert even Christian Witness admitted they’ve failed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, how effective was the science exhibition? Gilbert argues that it did not effectively teach the lessons it intended. Gilbert concluded:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“1962 no one could reconcile science and religion to the satisfaction of scientists or religious groups, if neither orientation to the world and its problems could prevail in public discussion, if the federal government, scientists, and the business community believed they needed to bring religion inside this grand American commemoration of scientific achievement, the lesson then and now is that science and religion cannot be reconciled nor can either be conquered or contained. The accommodation at Seattle continued the dialectic, extended a running exchange, and signaled the continuing revision of relationships. Extraordinary changes had occurred in American culture since the Scopes trial of 1925 and the foundation of the Conference on Science, Philosophy, and Religion fifteen years later. But nothing had been settled, and that in itself was the only settlement possible.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irrespective of the correctness of the orientation of the displayed DNA models one should be aware that they presented cutting edge science: Watson and Crick would only be awarded the Nobel Prize at the end of the same year, Jacob and Monod’s published their operon theory just the year before, the genetic code was still not fully deciphered, mRNA was more of a concept than an established fact, DNA sequencing was 15 years ahead and things like PCR or Crispr/Cas gene editing were not even imaginable. In addition, it has to be considered that the form and the shape of DNA haven’t been on public display to often before if at all and that the molecule was far from being the icon everybody nowadays recognizes and its name was likely unfamiliar to the majority of the population. Thus, one may conclude that the exhibit’s aim to explain how science works may have been too ambitious and its content may have been too complex for the general public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a European born in the early 60s the US always appeared to be on the cutting edge of science although I must admit that I was more impressed by things like the atomic car and rockets rather than genetics and evolution back then. I guess the same is true for the majority of visitors. On the other hand, the escalation of the conflict and the power creationism would gain was neither foreseeable at the time and it is sad to see how many people in the US still deny evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There actually was a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/PacSci/photos/a.132354883854/10159386557128855/&quot;&gt;third correctly right-handed DNA model&lt;/a&gt; displayed outside of the exhibition hall which today is still in its original place in one of the pools on the fair ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gamow, G. (1955) “Information Transfer in the Living Cell.” &lt;em&gt;Scientific American&lt;/em&gt;. 193,(4), 70–79
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jstor.org/stable/24943758&quot;&gt;http://www.jstor.org/stable/24943758&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Timofeeff-Ressovsky, N.W. and Zimmer, K.G. and Delbrueck, M. (1935) “Über die Natur der Genmutation und der Genstruktur.“ &lt;em&gt;Nachrichten von der Gesellschaft der Wissenschaften zu Göttingen&lt;/em&gt;. 1935, pp. 190-245
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ini.uzh.ch/~tobi/fun/max/timofeeffZimmerDelbruck1935.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.ini.uzh.ch/~tobi/fun/max/timofeeffZimmerDelbruck1935.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Luria SE, Delbrück M. (1943) “Mutations of Bacteria from Virus Sensitivity to Virus Resistance.” &lt;em&gt;Genetics&lt;/em&gt;. 28(6):491-511 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1209226/pdf/491.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1209226/pdf/491.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;US Department of Commerce (1962) &lt;em&gt;United States science exhibit, World’s Fair in Seattle, 1962 Souvenir Guide Book&lt;/em&gt;](
&lt;a href=&quot;https://spl.contentdm.oclc.org/digital/collection/p15015coll3/id/503&quot;&gt;https://spl.contentdm.oclc.org/digital/collection/p15015coll3/id/503&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;US Department of Commerce: &lt;em&gt;United States Scientific Exhibit Seattle World’s Fair Final Report&lt;/em&gt; (1963) Library of Congress Card No. 63-60022
&lt;a href=&quot;https://cdm16118.contentdm.oclc.org/digital/collection/p15015coll3/id/311&quot;&gt;https://cdm16118.contentdm.oclc.org/digital/collection/p15015coll3/id/311&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gilbert, J. (1997) &lt;em&gt;Redeeming culture: American religion in an age of science.&lt;/em&gt; Chicago: Univ. of Chicago Press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Hafner</name></author><summary type="html">The left-handed DNA helix model that was displayed in the Seattle World's Fair ended up in storage in a utility tunnel underneath the Pacific Science Center. (We'll show the image here as soon as we get permission to show it on this page.) This link shows the image on the PSC Facebook page. On January 11, Matt Young reported that the Institute for Creation Science announced a new logo that depicted left-handed DNA. Although regularly occurring in vivo in the form of Z-DNA left-handed DNA only represent a very tiny proportion of the world’s DNA which consists predominantly of right-handed B-DNA as Watson and Crick described it in their 1954 paper. The ICR left-handed DNA logo made it on the pages of Tom Schneider’s Left Handed DNA Hall of Fame immediately and became the sites first entry in 2022. The Institute for Creation Research has created a new logo representing their support for left handed DNA research and the ongoing takeover! First reported on 2022 Jan 11, new as of 2022 Jan 112 In most cases depicting DNA left-handed will be caused by mirroring a correct picture to better suit design purposes or likely more often by copying publicly available pictures. The same may be true for the ICR logo. Still, the incident reminded me of the likely first ever publicly displayed left-handed DNA model that was part of the Science Exhibition at the Seattle World Fair in 1962 which I came across when I studied the history of a right-handed DNA model Max Delbrück purchased for the Institute of Genetics of the University of Cologne.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rock glacier</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/rock-glacier.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rock glacier" /><published>2022-01-31T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-01-31T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/rock-glacier</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/rock-glacier.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;James Kocher&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/JimKocher_SanJuanMountainRockGlacier.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rock glacier&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rock_glacier&quot;&gt;Rock glacier&lt;/a&gt; on unnamed peak (Mountain 12730 on USGS topo maps) in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Juan_Mountains&quot;&gt;San Juan Mountains&lt;/a&gt;. Viewed from Kendall Mountain (13,338&amp;nbsp;ft) south flank, Silverton, San Juan County, Colorado, July, 1997. (Kodachrome 64 and Olympus OM-10 FC with Toshiba 35-105&amp;nbsp;mm, F/2.8 zoom lens.) 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by James Kocher. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Rock glacier on unnamed peak (Mountain 12730 on USGS topo maps) in San Juan Mountains. Viewed from Kendall Mountain (13,338&amp;nbsp;ft) south flank, Silverton, San Juan County, Colorado, July, 1997. (Kodachrome 64 and Olympus OM-10 FC with Toshiba 35-105&amp;nbsp;mm, F/2.8 zoom lens.)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Not really evolution?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/not-really-evolution.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Not really evolution?" /><published>2022-01-29T19:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-01-29T19:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/not-really-evolution</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/not-really-evolution.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/notusker512.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tuskless Asian bull elephant&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Tuskless bull Asian Elephant in Huai Kha Khaeng wildlife sanctuary, Thailand. &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.m.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Tuskless_bull_Asian_Elephant_in_Huai_Kha_Khaeng_wildlife_sanctuary_(15942505646).jpg&quot;&gt;From
Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When is evolution not evolution?  When it's described by creationist/ID sources and is
obviously change effected by selection.  Case in point: any form of selection resulting
from human activity.  On January 27, 2022 the ever-astonishing Denyse O’Leary (“News” at the anti-evolution
website Uncommon Descent) made &lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/are-humans-changing-evolution/#comments&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;a post&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in which she linked to an article
on BBC Future by David Farrier.  He starts out by saying that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Humans have shaped the bodies of other creatures at least since dogs were domesticated around
30,000 years ago. But the combination of industrialised farming, introduced species,
urbanisation, pollution, and climate change are creating unprecedented selective pressures. We
have become the world's greatest evolutionary force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Farrier’s post, which you will find
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20220125-how-humans-are-changing-evolution&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
gives numerous examples of ways humans are accidentally, or deliberately, influencing
evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statement looks straightforward, but News will have none of it.  Her response:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In a human-dominated world, things happen faster, for better or worse. Should we still call
it “evolution” if we did it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, her answer is no, and the UD commenters all applaud this. But they’re all wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;The Origin of Species&lt;/em&gt; Darwin started out, in the first chapter, by reviewing
variation of animals and plants under domestication, and attributes many of the
changes from their wild ancestors to conscious or unconscious artificial selection.
He regarded these processes as a close parallel to natural selection, a good way
to introduce the concept to readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creationists have a way of totally dismissing the analogy.  Why, it's intelligent design
by humans, they cry.  How can anyone think that it in any way the same as natural
selection?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, we can.  When we set out to breed cows for, say, increased butterfat content of
their milk, the one thing that artificial selection does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; do is start with a
detailed scheme of the genes that influence butterfat content, and then engineer each
one to increase that trait.  Instead we breed from the cattle that have highest
milk butterfat content, or their immediate relatives. Farmers and herders have been
doing that for thousands of years.  They don’t know what genes are involved, and how
they influence the trait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The situation is the same for natural selection.  Certain phenotypes have higher
fitness than others, and that itself leads to the alleles they contain being
better represented in the next generation.  Neither wolves preying on deer, nor farmers
trying to get more butterfat from their cows, carry around with them a detailed
genetic plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Darwin's analogy is a powerful and convincing one.  All that creationists can do
is to flatly declare that the analogy is false.   There's more to say, but I'll
leave that to the comment section, and mostly to our commenters.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Tuskless bull Asian Elephant in Huai Kha Khaeng wildlife sanctuary, Thailand. From Wikimedia Commons When is evolution not evolution? When it's described by creationist/ID sources and is obviously change effected by selection. Case in point: any form of selection resulting from human activity. On January 27, 2022 the ever-astonishing Denyse O’Leary (“News” at the anti-evolution website Uncommon Descent) made a post in which she linked to an article on BBC Future by David Farrier. He starts out by saying that Humans have shaped the bodies of other creatures at least since dogs were domesticated around 30,000 years ago. But the combination of industrialised farming, introduced species, urbanisation, pollution, and climate change are creating unprecedented selective pressures. We have become the world's greatest evolutionary force. Farrier’s post, which you will find here gives numerous examples of ways humans are accidentally, or deliberately, influencing evolution. The statement looks straightforward, but News will have none of it. Her response: In a human-dominated world, things happen faster, for better or worse. Should we still call it “evolution” if we did it? Obviously, her answer is no, and the UD commenters all applaud this. But they’re all wrong.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unfounded attack on the late E.O. Wilson</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/unfounded-attack-on-wilson.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unfounded attack on the late E.O. Wilson" /><published>2022-01-29T14:55:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-01-29T14:55:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/unfounded-attack-on-wilson</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/unfounded-attack-on-wilson.html">&lt;p&gt;I will keep this short, but I wanted to call attention to two &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; articles on E.O. Wilson, who died on Dec. 26 and, I think, needs no introduction.  First: an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.abn9848&quot;&gt;obituary&lt;/a&gt; by Stuart Pimm of Duke University and an expert on conservation biology. Second: an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.abo2335&quot;&gt;editorial&lt;/a&gt; by H. Holden Thorp, the editor of &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;. Dr. Pimm in particular notes Wilson’s assertion that natural selection might actually select for human behaviors and observed that he was attacked for this view, sometimes unfairly. Both articles were pleasant and made me wish I had met Wilson, rather than just read a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Naturalist-Edward-Wilson-ebook/dp/B009LO4796&quot;&gt;memoir&lt;/a&gt; of his.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The attacks have not stopped, and on December 29, before Wilson’s body was metaphorically cold, &lt;i&gt;Scientific American&lt;/i&gt; published a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/the-complicated-legacy-of-e-o-wilson/&quot;&gt;hatchet job&lt;/a&gt; by a nursing professor, &lt;a href=&quot;https://profiles.ucsf.edu/monica.mclemore&quot;&gt;Monica McLemore&lt;/a&gt; of the University of California, San Francisco. You may read a detailed critique of Dr. McLemore’s paper, &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2021/12/30/scientific-american-does-an-asinine-hit-job-on-e-o-wilson-calling-him-a-racist/&quot;&gt;Scientific American does an asinine hit job on E. O. Wilson, calling him a racist&lt;/a&gt;, by Jerry Coyne, who does not mince his words, even in a title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Google Scholar, Dr. McLemore is an author or coauthor of a fair number of papers in scientific journals (she says, “81 peer reviewed articles, OpEds and commentaries,” as well as being cited here and there, but only journal articles count). She is thus supposedly a competent researcher. Yet her article said barely a word about Wilson and accused even &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4707027/&quot;&gt;Gregor Mendel&lt;/a&gt; of racism, though how she might know that is beyond me. I should have stopped reading then and there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was in graduate school, during the Vietnam war, we listened as an earnest young medical resident told about his project to find the psychological causes of war. One of my friends told him, “If you set out to find the psychological causes of war, you will surely find them.” The point was not lost on the resident. I think likewise that if you set out to find racism in science, you will surely find it. Even where it does not exist.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I will keep this short, but I wanted to call attention to two Science articles on E.O. Wilson, who died on Dec. 26 and, I think, needs no introduction. First: an obituary by Stuart Pimm of Duke University and an expert on conservation biology. Second: an editorial by H. Holden Thorp, the editor of Science. Dr. Pimm in particular notes Wilson’s assertion that natural selection might actually select for human behaviors and observed that he was attacked for this view, sometimes unfairly. Both articles were pleasant and made me wish I had met Wilson, rather than just read a memoir of his. The attacks have not stopped, and on December 29, before Wilson’s body was metaphorically cold, Scientific American published a hatchet job by a nursing professor, Monica McLemore of the University of California, San Francisco. You may read a detailed critique of Dr. McLemore’s paper, Scientific American does an asinine hit job on E. O. Wilson, calling him a racist, by Jerry Coyne, who does not mince his words, even in a title. According to Google Scholar, Dr. McLemore is an author or coauthor of a fair number of papers in scientific journals (she says, “81 peer reviewed articles, OpEds and commentaries,” as well as being cited here and there, but only journal articles count). She is thus supposedly a competent researcher. Yet her article said barely a word about Wilson and accused even Gregor Mendel of racism, though how she might know that is beyond me. I should have stopped reading then and there. When I was in graduate school, during the Vietnam war, we listened as an earnest young medical resident told about his project to find the psychological causes of war. One of my friends told him, “If you set out to find the psychological causes of war, you will surely find them.” The point was not lost on the resident. I think likewise that if you set out to find racism in science, you will surely find it. Even where it does not exist.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Genealogical Adam and Eve: book review</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/genealogical-adam-eve.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Genealogical Adam and Eve: book review" /><published>2022-01-23T16:03:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-01-23T16:03:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/genealogical-adam-eve</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/genealogical-adam-eve.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Swamidass_Cover_384.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author of this interesting &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ivpress.com/the-genealogical-adam-and-eve&quot;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/S._Joshua_Swamidass&quot;&gt;S. Joshua Swamidass&lt;/a&gt;, posits that the scientific evidence is consistent with the hypothesis that we could all be descended from a single couple who lived in comparatively recent times, say, 10,000 years or so ago. The conventional wisdom is that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitochondrial_Eve&quot;&gt;Mitochondrial Eve&lt;/a&gt;, the most recent matrilineal common ancestor of all people alive today, and Y-Chromosomal Adam, our most recent patrilineal common ancestor, lived at very different times 100,000 or more years ago and so could not have been a couple. Dr. Swamidass, an MD, holds a PhD in information science, and is an associate professor at Washington University in St Louis. He is the real McCoy, not someone who has quit to shill for Answers in Genesis, Reasons to Believe, or Aish HaTorah, and must be taken seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full title of the book is &lt;i&gt;The Genealogical Adam and Eve: The Surprising Science of Universal Ancestry&lt;/i&gt;. In it, the author makes a distinction between your &lt;i&gt;genealogical&lt;/i&gt; ancestry and your &lt;i&gt;genetic&lt;/i&gt; ancestry. He notes that your genes are diluted from one generation to the next, so that eventually people who are in fact your descendants will very probably have none of your genes. I think of it as diluting a solution over and over again: eventually, none of the solute will remain in the solvent, because the solute is not infinitely continuous but rather is made up of atoms or molecules. Once the last solute molecule is gone, the concentration is 0. In the same way, your genes (or your genetic inheritance) are not continuous, and once the last gene is gone, your descendants inherit none of your DNA. (When I read this account, I was reminded of T.H. Huxley’s lament after having read &lt;i&gt;On the Origin of Species&lt;/i&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Thomas_Henry_Huxley&quot;&gt;How extremely stupid of me not to have thought of that&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your descendants, though they are not genetic descendants, are still your descendants; Dr. Swamidass calls them your &lt;i&gt;genealogical descendants&lt;/i&gt;. Unlike your genetic descendants, who dwindle in number, your genealogical descendants are apt to grow in number. Eventually, as they crossbreed with the genealogical descendants of others, one lineage will comprise the entire population of earth (I will not go into detail here, but Dr. Swamidass is at pains to document what you might call sufficient “crosstalk” among nearly all populations on earth, though I think he may have forgotten about New Guinea).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At any rate, one lucky couple eventually becomes the most recent universal genealogical ancestral couple, and Dr. Swamidass dubs them the MRUGA (a designation which, alas, does not have the same ring as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Last_universal_common_ancestor&quot;&gt;LUCA&lt;/a&gt;). I did not understand precisely why he chose the date 1 CE, but Dr. Swamidass estimates that the MRUGA may have lived “a few thousand years ago,” and the entire population of the earth became their genealogical descendants in 1 CE. Could they have been Adam and Eve? Did God create them &lt;i&gt;de novo&lt;/i&gt;? Sure, I suppose they (or a couple ancestral to them) could have and he could have. I began to think of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russell%27s_teapot&quot;&gt;Russell’s teapot&lt;/a&gt;, but Dr. Swamidass presents us with his own version, a unicorn on the far side of the Moon. Dr. Swamidass is somewhat coy, but he remarks on the absence of evidence for or against his hypotheses so frequently, especially in the first half of the book, that I began to think, with Gertrude, the doctor doth protest too much, methinks. Nevertheless, if his purpose is to debunk the conventional wisdom concerning Y-Chromosomal Adam and Mitochondrial Eve, I think he has succeeded admirably. And perhaps he has taught scientists a lesson: Don’t be too sure of yourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Swamidass’s vision seems to be that of a Garden of Eden in which Adam and Eve are created &lt;i&gt;de novo&lt;/i&gt; from dust and a rib, and eventually released into the world of (to borrow a phrase from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/The-Science-of-God/Gerald-L-Schroeder/9781439129586&quot;&gt;Gerald Schroeder&lt;/a&gt;, 1997 ed.) pre-Adamic hominids; at least, he argues that scientific evidence cannot rule out this possibility, and indeed he considers others as well. Even if Adam and Eve have been created miraculously, the pre-Adamic hominids evolved according to normal evolution. Dr. Swamidass calls Adam and Eve and their descendants, &lt;i&gt;textual humans&lt;/i&gt;, because they are mentioned in the Bible. These textual humans and their descendants interbreed with the pre-Adamic hominids, whom Dr. Swamidass calls &lt;i&gt;biological humans&lt;/i&gt;, and &lt;i&gt;their&lt;/i&gt; descendants. Eventually the textual humans and their genealogical descendants predominate. To put it bluntly, I see no reason to think there is a unicorn on the far side of the Moon, and I similarly see no reason to think that Adam and Eve were created &lt;i&gt;de novo&lt;/i&gt; in a sequestered garden just a few thousand years ago, while other humans evolved outside the garden in the normal manner. (Did Adam and Eve have the same genome, incidentally, and if so was their relationship incestuous?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Schroeder declared that Adam and Eve were the first hominids to be given souls. As evidence, he points to the sudden flowering of civilization and technology at about the right time. Dr. Swamidass likewise seems to think that there was something (theologically) special about Adam and Eve, but I think he does not really specify what that means.  He notes, however, that Adam and Eve and their descendants are otherwise indistinguishable from the hominids living around them and indeed interbreed with them. I am frankly disturbed by this concept, because (protestations to the contrary), it implies that biological humans who did not descend from the Garden of Eden were somehow less than fully textual humans, that is, less than genealogical descendants of the pair in the garden. I do not want to inveigh against a proposition because of its possible consequences, but I know all too well what happens when some people are considered to be intrinsically different (a problem which Dr. Swamidass to his credit also acknowledges).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope I am not putting words into his mouth, but Dr. Swamidass must think that something, some essence, call it textuality if you like, somehow propagates to the descendants of Adam and Eve, but exactly how does it do so? Is the textuality encoded genetically?  Epigenetically?  Is it dominant or recessive? Do all the descendants become textual humans, or do some remain merely biological humans? Is textuality badly diluted generation after generation, until it disappears? If not, does it follow Adam and Eve’s genealogical descendants, and if so, how? None of these questions is posed, let alone answered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Swamidass has avowedly written his book in order to attract creationists to evolutionary biology or at least to make them feel less threatened by evolutionary biology, and also to attract atheists and agnostics to religion. I cannot speak for creationists, but I cannot see atheists taking the book very seriously. The last chapter is in part an appeal to anyone who does not take the origin story literally, and Dr. Swamidass rightly corrects those who think that science has definitively ruled out Adam and Eve. He calls for tolerance and suggests that we avoid abusing scientific authority. All very well, and I cannot agree with him more. But does his discovery that Adam and Eve “could have” been an actual couple that existed in the near past influence my belief or nonbelief in God? Not one whit. And the suggestion that they “may have” been created &lt;i&gt;de novo&lt;/i&gt; in a walled garden seems to me like sheer fantasy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am keenly interested in scientific or textual arguments designed to elucidate the origins of the Bible and the existence or nonexistence of the people and events therein. Perhaps that is one reason that I was interested in the concept of a genealogical descendant. The argument that a single couple could have been the ancestors of everyone alive today was interesting and clever, and people will assume that that couple was Adam and Eve. Indeed, the book would not be particularly interesting if we thought the couple might not have been Adam and Eve. Before the couple’s descendants dominated the entire earth, however, each previous generation would have had a different pair of ancestors, as Dr. Swamidass himself makes clear. Why would we not think that one of those many couples may have been Adam and Eve?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A confession: I could barely get through the theological arguments in the latter part of the book. They read to me like the proverbial &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/How_many_angels_can_dance_on_the_head_of_a_pin%3F&quot;&gt;angels dancing on the head of a pin&lt;/a&gt;, which I have always understood to be a metaphor for answering the question whether angels have volume or mass or something, while implicitly presuming the somewhat problematic existence of angels. Dr. Swamidass expends considerable energy trying to deduce whether people existed outside the Garden. All you have to do is take one look at the text and conclude that, of course, it implies existence of other people (see, for example, Nephilim or the myth surrounding the mark of Cain and Cain’s wife in Genesis 6:4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Dr. Swamidass has an ax to grind – he needs to be acceptable to fundamentalist Christians – so he scrutinizes the text in fine detail in order to establish the existence of people outside the Garden &lt;i&gt;Biblically&lt;/i&gt;. The Appendix, which is a reprint of a paper by the author, seemed unnecessary and unrelated to the rest of the book; it must similarly be intended to appeal to a fundamentalist Christian audience. I cannot agree with his conclusion concerning the historicity of either Jesus of Nazareth or his supposed Resurrection. I do not doubt that someone like the Jesus described in the so-called New Testament may have existed, but in fact, there is no contemporaneous evidence in support of that contention; even the earliest Gospel was written 40 years after Jesus died. Likewise, I maintain that “prophecies” in the Hebrew Bible are mere cherry-picked anachronisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not get me wrong. The book is well thought out and mostly clearly written, though frankly it could have used an editor to shorten it by 30 % or so. It has a great many figures, most of which are clear and add to our understanding (I found, among a few others, Figure 1 and one or two of its variants somewhat difficult, however).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of genealogical ancestry is clever, and the estimates as to when they existed are surprisingly recent. Equally surprising, our most recent genealogical ancestors are a couple; this conclusion is contrary to the conventional wisdom, which focuses on genetic ancestry and places Mitochondrial Eve and Y-Chromosomal Adam many thousands of years in the past. Nevertheless, to my mind there is no evidence to suggest that our genealogical ancestors have any Biblical or theological significance whatsoever. Genealogical ancestry is merely an amusing puzzle, and the discovery that our most recent universal genealogical ancestors have been recent seems to me to have no more significance than the discovery that our last universal common (genetic) ancestor was not recent. It does not make me think, “Oh, maybe there is more to this Adam and Eve myth than I had supposed!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/strong&gt;. Deanna Young, who had little choice, and Glenn Branch, who did, read a draft and provided many provocative comments. You may find Mr. Branch’s review of the same book &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1111/rirt.13913&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, alas, behind a paywall. Joshua Swamidass graciously read a subsequent draft and offered specific criticisms, which I have tried to address.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">The author of this interesting book, S. Joshua Swamidass, posits that the scientific evidence is consistent with the hypothesis that we could all be descended from a single couple who lived in comparatively recent times, say, 10,000 years or so ago. The conventional wisdom is that Mitochondrial Eve, the most recent matrilineal common ancestor of all people alive today, and Y-Chromosomal Adam, our most recent patrilineal common ancestor, lived at very different times 100,000 or more years ago and so could not have been a couple. Dr. Swamidass, an MD, holds a PhD in information science, and is an associate professor at Washington University in St Louis. He is the real McCoy, not someone who has quit to shill for Answers in Genesis, Reasons to Believe, or Aish HaTorah, and must be taken seriously. The full title of the book is The Genealogical Adam and Eve: The Surprising Science of Universal Ancestry. In it, the author makes a distinction between your genealogical ancestry and your genetic ancestry. He notes that your genes are diluted from one generation to the next, so that eventually people who are in fact your descendants will very probably have none of your genes. I think of it as diluting a solution over and over again: eventually, none of the solute will remain in the solvent, because the solute is not infinitely continuous but rather is made up of atoms or molecules. Once the last solute molecule is gone, the concentration is 0. In the same way, your genes (or your genetic inheritance) are not continuous, and once the last gene is gone, your descendants inherit none of your DNA. (When I read this account, I was reminded of T.H. Huxley’s lament after having read On the Origin of Species: How extremely stupid of me not to have thought of that.)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ernst Mayr versus racism</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/Ernst-Mayr-versus-racism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ernst Mayr versus racism" /><published>2022-01-20T21:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-01-20T21:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/Ernst-Mayr-versus-racism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/Ernst-Mayr-versus-racism.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Ernst_Mayr_bust_Berlin.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Mayr bust in Berlin museum]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Bust of Ernst Mayr at the Museum für Naturkunde in Berlin. &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Ernst_Mayr_-_B%C3%BCste_-_Museum_f%C3%BCr_Naturkunde_-_Berlin.jpg&quot;&gt;Source and license at Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ongoing &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/David-Hillis-on-Ernst-Mayr.html&quot;&gt;controversy over the proposal to de-name the Ernst Mayr Award at the Society for Systematic Biology&lt;/a&gt; is one of many examples of the ongoing re-examination of the history of evolutionary biology with respect to racism in the 2020s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have developed many worries about the way that the evaluation of major historical figures in evolutionary biology has been occurring. (I know that the SSB proposal formally tries to avoid having this discussion about Mayr, but evaluating the legacy of a historical figure is simply an unavoidable feature of people reaching a decision about naming/de-naming that historical figure.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of my main worries are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Twitter-neutics: The Twitter hermenutic.&lt;/b&gt; I have noticed in recent years that the common hermeneutic for discussing these issues is basically trial-by-Twitter, where sentences from decades and centuries past are ripped from their original context (sometimes originally taken from creationist quote-mines) and read as if they were modern Twitter posts. This boldly assumes that the quote should be read as if the writer had access to all of the modern scientific knowledge and ethical development that occurred in the years since the passage was written.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Paper-denialism.&lt;/b&gt; Another feature of trial-by-Twitter is the principle &quot;If it's not freely online and text-searchable by google, it doesn't exist.&quot; This problem is made worse in the age of the pandemic, where academics are (a) harried and juggling families and work, let alone side-projects, and (b) often locked out of their offices and university libraries.  It is especially problematic when the views of historical figures are being considered, as much of their key work on &quot;public interest&quot; topics like race is in old paper books, old magazines and pamphlets, etc., that are typically not online, and sometimes only available via old-fashioned interlibrary loan.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Historians-schmistorians.&lt;/b&gt; For similar reasons, historians of science are rarely consulted. This is despite the fact that the history of scientific racism (and eugenics, a closely related but non-identical topic) is one of the most prolific cottage industries in history of science. Even getting on top of the secondary historical literature in this area is a massive task. (That said, the best single resource I have found on this topic is: Elazar Barkan (1992). &lt;i&gt;The Retreat of Scientific Racism: Changing Concepts of Race in Britain and the United States between the World Wars&lt;/i&gt;. Cambridge University Press. Here is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511558351&quot;&gt;official link if you have library access&lt;/a&gt;, and googling may turn up other PDFs.)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the main worrying thing I see in online discussions of evolutionary biologists and racism is &lt;b&gt;a major lack of awareness of The Historical Big Picture,&lt;/b&gt; which is that evolutionary biologists, especially and specifically (a) Darwin/T.H. Huxley and (b) the architects of the Modern Synthesis, have been some of the crucial individuals who helped destroy key pillars of scientific racism, and (slowly and painfully) brought academia and society along with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Darwin and Huxley, for instance, basically destroyed polygenism once and for all, and established the overwhelming similarity and close kinship of all modern humans, opposing the view that various extant races were transitional forms. They also vocally opposed slavery, supported the Jamaica Committee, endorsed equal rights and voting rights, etc. (&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html&quot;&gt;I covered this in detail for T.H. Huxley, here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the Modern Synthesis versus racism, writing it all up is more than I have bandwidth for, but read Barkan’s (1992) &lt;i&gt;The Retreat of Scientific Racism&lt;/i&gt;. The short version is that the key individuals in the U.K. were people like Julian Huxley (T.H. Huxley’s grandson; another grandson was Aldous Huxley, author of &lt;i&gt;Brave New World&lt;/i&gt;), who long before he wrote his 1942 &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.280031&quot;&gt;Evolution: The Modern Synthesis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;, lead-authored the 1935 &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wellcomecollection.org/works/rr2c6azf&quot;&gt;We Europeans: a survey of ‘racial’ problems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;.  This was one of the first and most important major debunkings of “race science.” Huxley was encouraged and supported by &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/haldane-1938-biology-of-inequality.html&quot;&gt;J.B.S. Haldane&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lancelot_Hogben&quot;&gt;Lancelot Hobgen&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Singer&quot;&gt;Charles Singer&lt;/a&gt; (the latter is essentially an unacknowledged coauthor of &lt;i&gt;We Europeans&lt;/i&gt;; his name was left off to avoid the charge of the book being Jewish propaganda).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the USA, the key nexus was Columbia University in New York City, where the anthropologist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franz_Boas&quot;&gt;Franz Boas&lt;/a&gt; and his students (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruth_Benedict&quot;&gt;Ruth Benedict&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melville_J._Herskovits&quot;&gt;Melville J. Herskovits&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.berkeley.edu/2020/07/24/alfred-kroeber-and-his-relations-with-california-indians/&quot;&gt;Alfred L. Kroeber&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margaret_Mead&quot;&gt;Margaret Mead&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ashley_Montagu&quot;&gt;Ashley Montagu&lt;/a&gt;) waged a long public campaign against racism, joined most notably by Theodosius Dobzhansky (originally a member of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Hunt_Morgan&quot;&gt;T.H. Morgan&lt;/a&gt;’s “fly-room” at Columbia) and his colleague, Columbia geneticist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L._C._Dunn&quot;&gt;Leslie Clarence Dunn&lt;/a&gt;. Dobzhansky wrote books and articles against racism for decades (see e.g. Dunn &amp;amp; Dobzhansky, 1947, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wellcomecollection.org/works/akf3dnfs&quot;&gt;Heredity, Race, and Society&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;).  Reviewing Dobzhansky’s work in this area will have to wait for when The Great Iconoclasm of the 2020s comes for him (give it a few weeks!).  I do include a few quotes from Dobzhansky below, as clearly Dobzhansky helped inspire Mayr’s anti-racism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning to Ernst Mayr: Mayr and Dobzhansky were probably &lt;b&gt;the two biggest boosters of the idea that population genetic thinking destroyed the typological concept of race, and thus undermined the basic foundation of racism.&lt;/b&gt;  For them, races were pretty arbitrary divisions of a continuously mixing gene pool, the differences between individuals within each “race” were far greater than any between them, and individual variation meant there was no such thing as a “typical” member of a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Mayr is on the radar, I thought it would be worthwhile to quote him through the decades on the issue of race. Although we can see some features indicating that he was clearly a person of his time (for example, the then-conventional use of “Man” for “humankind” throughout), including a few vestiges of older views on race, on the whole I found it surprising just how much of Mayr is now just conventional wisdom, so thoroughly embedded in all of our heads that we moderns don’t even think about how these views were promoted and accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is hazardous for us moderns to judge historical figures if we don’t even realize how much of our modern worldview was built by those same figures. Hopefully, posting these quotes, for reading and google-ability, will help with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Any bolds are added by me. Any italics etc. are original.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theodosius Dobzhansky (1951 [1937]). &lt;i&gt;Genetics and the Origin of Species&lt;/i&gt;. Third edition, revised. Columbia University Press, New York. 1-364.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
Chapter 4: Selection, p. 77:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Concept of Adaptive Value&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
It is well known that Darwin's conception of natural selection was derived from the idea of Malthus, that even the slowest breeding organisms tend to produce more offspring that [sic] can survive without eventually outrunning the food supply. Death and destruction of a part of the progeny undoubtedly take place in all organisms. It was the differential mortality of the carriers of different genotypes composing a population that was supposed to make selection effective. Unfortunately, this process was also described by metaphors which were more picturesque than accurate, such as &quot;struggle for life&quot; and &quot;the survival of the fittest.&quot; Natural selection became associated in too many minds with emotional slogans like &quot;eat or be eaten,&quot; and this led to misuse of Darwinism by propagandists and bigots.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p. 140&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
People with O and with A blood groups are not distinct races, because they do not form different populations, although different populations often differ in the incidence of these blood groups. Similarly, people with long and with short heads, or slender and fat people, are not races. Calling them races leads to the absurd situations when brothers and sisters would differ in race from each other and from their parents.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bergman, R. A. M.; Dahlberg, Gunnar; Dunn, Leslie C.; Haldane, J. B. S.; Montagu, M.F. Ashley; Mourant, A. E.; Nachtscheim, Hans; Schreider, Eugene; Shapiro, Harry L.; Trevor, J. C.; Vallois, Henri V.; Zuckerman, S.; Dobzhansky, Theodosius; Huxley, Julian (1952). &lt;i&gt;The Race concept: results of an inquiry.&lt;/i&gt; Part of the UNESCO series &lt;i&gt;The Race Question in Modern Science&lt;/i&gt;. Statement text drafted at Unesco House, Paris, on 8 June 1951; comments then solicited from numerous authorities. Paris: UNESCO. https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000073351&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;p. 18: &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Mayr also hopes that &quot;the authoritative Statement prepared by Unesco will help to eliminate the pseudoscientific race conceptions which have been used as excuses for many injustices and even shocking crimes&quot;. &quot;I applaud and wholeheartedly endorse [it],&quot; he writes, adding: &lt;b&gt;&quot;It cannot be emphasized too strongly that all so-called races are variable populations, and that there is often more difference between extreme individuals of one race than between certain individuals of different races. All human races are mixtures of populations and the term &quot;pure race&quot; is an absurdity. The second important point which needs stressing is that genetics plays a very minor part in the cultural characteristics of different peoples&lt;/b&gt;....The third point is that equality of opportunity and equality in law do not depend on physical, intellectual and genetic identity. There are striking differences in physical, intellectual and other genetically founded qualities among individuals of even the most homogeneous human population, even among brothers and sisters. No acknowledged ethical principle exists which would permit denial of equal opportunity for reason of such differences to any member of the human species.&quot;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ernst Mayr (1959). Review of: &lt;i&gt;Darwin and the Darwinian Revolution&lt;/i&gt; by Gertrude Himmelfarb. &lt;i&gt;Scientific American&lt;/i&gt; 201(5), 209-216. November 1959. https://www.jstor.org/stable/24941160&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;[Himmelfarb's] discussion of Darwin's relation to teleological thinking fails to penetrate to the core of the issue. Neither she nor the majority of philosophers seem to realize that the &quot;Why?&quot; that Darwin asks so often is not the teleological &quot;What for?&quot; but the scientific &quot;How come?&quot; The investigator who asks, &quot;Why are there tides in the ocean?,&quot; is inquiring into their causation . The anti-teleological impact of this kind of &quot;Why?,&quot; correctly emphasized by John Dewey, is missed by Dr. Himmelfarb entirely when she calls Darwin's questioning a &quot;preeminently teleological inquiry.&quot; No wonder she is puzzled &quot;that Darwin, the least philosophical of men, should have fastened upon that most philosophical and metaphysical of all questions [and yet that] his questions, while fundamental, were never abstract.&quot; The reason is that Darwin was intensely interested in ultimate causes, but never in &quot;final&quot; causes.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
One might claim that these errors are irrelevant in a book primarily concerned with the Darwinian revolution, the impact of Darwin on the contemporary scene. But even here I feel that Dr. Himmelfarb has not done Darwin justice. She describes quite correctly how bewildered Darwin was about the social and ethical applications of Darwinism.&lt;b&gt; He certainly would not have excused war, class struggle, robber baronism and racism as logical consequences of Darwinism. Yet she nowhere points out that it is totally unjustifiable to interpret such things in terms of Darwinism.&lt;/b&gt; It does not matter which of Darwin's basic principles one takes: the population principle or the principle of the biological contribution to the next generation (the true touchstone of natural selection); applying either of these principles to &quot;social Darwinism&quot; shows that they are in complete opposition to it. The adoption of pseudo-Darwinism by all-or-nothing philosophers, by typologists and by others unable to think statistically has led to all sorts of monstrous ideologies that no true Darwinian could ever have conceived. It is the term &quot;struggle,&quot; which Darwin so unfortunately took over from Thomas Malthus and Lyell, that seems to have given misinformed laymen the idea that physical struggle was the basic principle of Darwinism.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mayr, Ernst (1963). &lt;i&gt;Animal Species and Evolution&lt;/i&gt;. The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press. Cambridge, Mass. 1-797.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
358&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[summarizing &lt;b&gt;Chapter 12: The Polytypic Species of the Taxonomist&lt;/b&gt;]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The term &quot;species&quot; is as useful in purely taxonomic as in evolutionary studies of animals. On the infraspecific level a slight dualism is unavoidable, without calling, however, for an elaborate new terminology. The application of the word &quot;subspecies&quot; is best restricted to taxonomy, while terms like &quot;deme,&quot; &quot;race,&quot; &quot;geographic isolate,&quot; and &quot;cline&quot; belong to the field of evolutionary biology. Finally, terms like &quot;variety&quot; and &quot;biological race&quot; have been such catchalls for heterogenous phenomena that they would better be discarded altogether.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

[Chapter 20: Man as a Biological Species]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
643&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;The Polytypic Species &lt;i&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
All the different kinds of living man on the face of the earth belong to a single species. They form a single set of intercommunicating gene pools. As a matter of fact, the various races of man are less different from each other than are the subspecies of many polytypic species of animals. Yet a few misguided individuals have applied a type of typological species definition to man and have divided him into five or six separate species by using such artificial criteria as white, yellow, red, or black skin color. Such a division not only leaves a considerable portion of mankind unclassified as intermediates or relic primitives, but also is completely contrary to the biological species concept (Chapters 2 and 12). There are no genetic isolating mechanisms separating any of the races of mankind, and even the social barriers function inefficiently where different races come into contact.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
It is often asked whether man is in the process of speciating and whether the races of man should be considered incipient species. In attempting to answer this question one must recall that the hominids occupy one of the most spectacularly distinctive adaptive zones on earth. In the animal kingdom the invasion of a new adaptive zone usually results in a burst of adaptive radiation into various subniches. This has not happened in the history of the family Hominidae. Mayr (1950a) has pointed out that this failure of man to species is due to two causes: &quot;It seems to me that [one] reason is man's great ecological diversity. Man has, so to speak, specialized in despecialization. Man occupies more different ecological niches than any known animal. If the single species man occupies&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
644&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
successfully all the niches that are open for &lt;i&gt;Homo&lt;/i&gt;-like creatures, it is obvious that he cannot speciate.&quot; The second reason is that isolating mechanism in hominids apparently develop only slowly. There have been many isolates in the polytypic species &lt;i&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/i&gt; and in the species ancestral to it, but isolation never lasted sufficiently long for isolating mechanisms to become perfected. Man's great mobility and independence of the environment have made perfect geographic isolation impossible. As a consequence all parts of the globe, including all climatic zones, are now occupied by a single species. What other species of animal includes populations adapted to the Arctic as well as to the tropics, and ranging from almost pure vegetarians to almost pure carnivores? The probability of man's breaking up into several species has become smaller and smaller with the steady improvement of communication and means of transport. The internal cohesion of the genetic system of man is being strengthened constantly.&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;The Races of Man&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There is no agreement yet on the formal classification of the subdivisions of &lt;i&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/i&gt;. Of two highly competent treatises on the races of man, both published in 1950, one (Boyd 1950) recognizes 6 races, the other (Coon &lt;i&gt;et al.&lt;/i&gt; 1950) recognizes 30. Both classifications are equally legitimate. Yet even the division into 30 races is by no means exhaustive. Race number 9 (&quot;Negrito&quot;), of Coon &lt;i&gt;et al.&lt;/i&gt; lumps together numerous relict populations from the Congo in Africa and from southeast Asia, the Phillipines, and New Guinea, populations that (if they are related at all) are less closely related than are the four European races recognized by these authors. The same is true, to a lesser extent, of nearly all the other races. All are collective groupings of more or less differentiated local populations. Even Lundman's recognition (1952) of 37 races and some 30 additional subraces contains several heterogenous groupings. And yet this is only one of the difficulties. All these are contemporary races of Recent Man. If we go back in history we find chronological subdivisions of Homo sapiens such as, let us say, Cro-Magnon Man or more differentiated Neanderthal and finally the Steinheim-Swanscombe Man, the earliest &lt;i&gt;Homo&lt;/i&gt; that cannot clearly be separated from the polytypic species &lt;i&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/i&gt;. Biologically, it is immaterial how many subspecies and races of man one wants to recognize. The essential point is to recognize the genetic and biological continuity of all these gene pools, localized in space and time, and to recognize the biological meaning of their adaptations and specializations. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[...]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[646]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;The Amount of Difference Among Human Races&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
It is relatively easy to describe the differences among human races in terms of dimensions, proportions, pigmentation, hair shape, and other morphological characters. Yet the question is raised again and again: just how meaningful are such morphological data? First of all, they have only a partial genetic basis since, as is well known, pigmentation may depend on exposure to sun and size on nutrition. More serious is the objection that neither size nor pigmentation is a critical human characteristic. The critical characteristics are intelligence, inventiveness, imagination, compassion, and other traits that are difficult to measure and to compare. As stated above, the extreme viewpoint has been to deny that such differences among humans exist. A more conservative view would be to assume that as a consequence of manifold genetic differences among human populations there will be average differences for any kind of trait that has at least in part a genetic basis. All attempts to separate genetic and nongenetic characters (or contributions to the characters) have until now been quite unsuccessful. So far as I know, there is not one single mental trait for which a clear-cut racial different has been established, in spite of high probability that such differences exist. Twin studies are so far the only reliable proof of the partial genetic determination of mental traits. This much is certain, however, that the differences between individuals of a single population or race are usually larger than those between populations or races.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;The Population Concept in Man&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
As in biology, the outstanding conceptual revolution that has occurred in physical anthropology is the replacement of typological thinking by population thinking. This shift has affected every concept in anthropology, although none as strongly as the race concept. &lt;b&gt;The typological race concept of the racists is something thoroughly odious;&lt;/b&gt; the statistically defined race of the botanist and zoologist is a fact of nature. The basis for race formation is the same for all sexually reproducing organisms and consists in the fact that no two individuals are identical nor are any two local populations. No individual can therefore be &quot;typical&quot; of a race. Indeed, in polymorphic races different individuals may be strikingly different. [647] To look for and speak of &quot;pure races&quot; is sheer nonsense. Variability is inherent in any natural population and is favored by natural selection on account of the frequent superiority of heterozygotes and the diversity of the environment (Chapters 9 and 10). What differs from race to race is the degree of variability and this depends on the size of the populations, the variability of the habitat, and other factors discussed in previous chapters. Much of the phenotypic variability of mankind is presumably due to the occasional production of homozygotes by heterozygous parents. This is particularly true of constitutional extremes, individuals that are exceptionally large, small, obese, or thin.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There are other reasons for man's phenotypic variability. Man is a restless creature and since prehistoric times he has made large-scale migrations. The numerous colonizations of America by Asiatic tribes, the conquest of the South Seas by the Polynesians, the great Bantu migrations, and the massive movements of Slavic and Germanic tribes in the dying days of the Roman Empire are only a few spectacular examples. Conquerors almost invariably absorb part of the defeated tribe or nation or are absorbed by it. On this basis one might expect man to have exceptionally high individual variability, but this is not the case. Schultz (1944, 1947) has shown that some of the anthropoids far exceed man in this respect, as do many other animals. Some human populations that are clearly the product of hybridization do not seem to have signficantly higher variability than have unmixed races (Trevor 1953).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[...]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
649&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Claims of human identity [Mayr means the concept that all humans are identical, which he contrasts with the concept of moral/legal equality] are the outcome of typological thinking, of a belief that within the human type there is &quot;no essential variation.&quot; &lt;b&gt;Political theorizers have invariably applied such typological formulas when trying to resolve the difficulties posed by man's variability. The racism of the Nazis, for instance, was an outcome of such thinking. They rigidly defined each race by absolute characteristics: the &lt;i&gt;X&lt;/i&gt; race &quot;is lazy,&quot; the &lt;i&gt;Y&lt;/i&gt; race is &quot;of great intelligence,&quot; and &lt;i&gt;Z&lt;/i&gt; race is &quot;musical,&quot; and, worst of all, the &lt;i&gt;A&lt;/i&gt; race is &quot;superior.&quot; This allowed neither for the fact that many of the characteristics mentioned have only a partial (often a very small) genetic component, nor for the fact that many members of the various races do not have these characteristics at all.&lt;/b&gt; Another fallacy of typological racism is that it claims perfect correlation between the various characteristics ascribed to each race. Accordingly it claims an association between a particular color of the eyes or the hair and certain traits of the [650] mind or the character. Actually, all available evidence negates the existence of such absolute correlations.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Every politician, clergyman, educator, or physician, in short, anyone dealing with human individuals, is bound to make grave mistakes if he ignores these two great truths of population zoology: (1) no two individuals are alike, and (2) both environment and genetic endowment make a contribution to nearly every trait. 
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mayr, Ernst (1963). The Biology, Genetics, and Evolution of Man. Review of &lt;i&gt;Mankind Evolving: The Evolution of the Human Species&lt;/i&gt; by Theodosius Dobzhansky. &lt;i&gt;Quarterly Review of Biology&lt;/i&gt;, 38(3), 221-288. September 1963. https://www.jstor.org/stable/2820130&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
Nothing has delayed a modern approach to the study of man more than antiquated ideologies and meaningless controversies. Nature versus nurture, instinct versus learning, race versus biological identity, equality versus biological identity all such antitheses have provoked arguments that have long been shown by biologists to be meaningless, yet much political argument and indecision in public policy is due to the painful lag between scientific recognition and public understanding. This is why a scientifically sound volume on man such as Dobzhansky's is of such extraordinary importance. It admirably fulfills two functions: it presents that which we know, and, perhaps more importantly, it demolishes a considerable number of harmful misconceptions.&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Appreciating the grave danger of various misconceptions such as that of the master race, the nongenetic aspects of nonphysical characteristics, the concept of the tabula rasa of some psychologists, etc., Dobzhansky devotes much space to their refutation.&lt;/b&gt; The idea that modern man is no longer subject to natural selection is shown to be false. There is, however, a difference between primitive and modern man: the mortality differential of selection has been replaced by a fertility differential. Here the author could have perhaps stressed even more clearly that so-called Darwinian fitness consists of two drastically different components: genuine adaptive fitness and mere reproductive advantage. Dobzhansky's discussion of equality versus identity is particularly clear and constructive. &quot;The notion that all men are born...biologically alike, is a fallacy...pernicious in the long run.&quot; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
No other issue has beclouded the study of man as much as the continuing controversy between environmentalists and hereditarians. Dobzhansky does a great service by presenting much of the history of this controversy and an anthology of some of the more extreme claims. The issue is now theoretically resolved, since no intelligent student questions that man is a product both of his nature and of his environment (which includes his cultural history). &lt;b&gt;Lysenkoism is as wrong as is racism, yet we are still far from being able to partition our phenotype into the contributions made by heredity and those&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[p. 244]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;made by the environment. It is obviously impossible to investigate man as we do animals, since neither controlled breeding nor raising in artificial environments is available as a method of analysis.&lt;/b&gt; Correlation tests among twins and other relatives, which are increasingly being refined and extended by human geneticists, are beginning to give accurate estimates. Dobzhansky presents, in Chapter 4, much of the evidence that now exists for a genetic contribution not only to intelligence but also to many other human traits. Since personality traits affect susceptibility to criminality, addiction to smoking, and other social characteristics, it is not surprising that greater concordance for some of these traits is found among identical than among fraternal twins. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
These findings are still heatedly denied by some authors whose typological thinking forces them into a rigid determinism in which human fate is as inevitable as in a Greek tragedy. Many facts, such as the experience that identical twins do not necessarily behave in an identical manner, disprove the deterministic approach and open the gate to researches on methods for coping with an adverse genetic endowment. This is a far more constructive approach than the ostrich policy of denying the importance of the genotype.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theodosius Dobzhansky (1963). Genetic Entities in Hominid Evolution. Chapter in: 
&lt;i&gt;Classification and Human Evolution&lt;/i&gt;, edited by Sherwood L. Washburn. Chicago: Aldine Publishing Co., pp 347-361. 
https://ebookcentral.proquest.com/lib/auckland/detail.action?docID=1474550.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
359&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

Man behaves in this respect differently from &lt;i&gt;Drosophila&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;b&gt;Contrary to what racists so stridently proclaim, there is not a detectable trace of a loss of fitness in either the F1 or in later generations of hybrids between even the most distinctive human races.&lt;/b&gt; Nor is there any evidence of heterosis in the F1.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

360&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The genetic consequences of migration are worth more thought and study than they have thus far received. What happens when a race of a polytypic species improves its adaptedness and spreads to the areas of other races? There is no need to ascribe to our remote ancestors a degree of ferocity attained by only some of their descendants; the invaders need not have slaughtered the entire populations of the territories invaded. Genocide is less probable than genosorption, i.e., incorporation of genes of one population into the gene pool of another. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

361&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;ADDENDUM&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
This article was concluded and sent to the publisher before the appearance of The Origin of Races by C. S. Coon. Dr. Coon and I are in agreement that the now living polytypic species, &lt;i&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/i&gt;, is descended from the single polytypic Homo erectus of the mid-Pleistocene. Dr. Coon has, however, chosen to believe that &lt;i&gt;H. erectus&lt;/i&gt; was transformed into H. sapiens not once but five times, and that this transformation occurred much earlier in some places than in others. &lt;b&gt;This belief, which has made Dr. Coon's work attractive to racist pamphleteers, is neither supported by conclusive evidence nor plausible on theoretical grounds. The specific unity of mankind was maintained throughout its history by gene flow&lt;/b&gt; due to migration and the process for which the word &quot;genosorption&quot; is suggested above. Excepting through such gene flow, repeated origins of the same species are so improbable that this conjecture is not worthy of serious consideration; and given a gene flow, it becomes fallacious to say that a species has originated repeatedly, and even more fallacious to contend that it has originated five times, or any other number above one.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mayr, Ernst (1968). The Role of Systematics in Biology. &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;, 159(3815), 595-599. https://www.jstor.org/stable/1723366&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
Many new concepts arose out of this work of the taxonomist but have since diffused broadly into genetics, ecology, physiology, and other areas of biology. By far the most important of these, as I have often stressed in the past, is population thinking. Biology, as all other sciences, was permeated by typological thinking until late in the 19th century, and is still today.  &lt;b&gt;When the learning psychologist speaks of The Rat or The Monkey, or the racist of The Negro, this is typological thinking.&lt;/b&gt; The early Mendelians were pure typologists. A mutation changed The Wildtype, and the result was a new type of organism, according to De Vries a new species. I have pointed out elsewhere (4) that taxonomists began as early as the 1840's and the 1850's to collect large series of individuals, population samples as we would now say, and describe the variation in those samples. From this purely pragmatic operation emerged eventually a whole new way of thinking which replaced typological essentialism. From taxonomy, population thinking spread into adjacent fields and was in part instrumental in the development of population genetics and population cytology. This one conceptual contribution alone has been of such great benefit to vast areas of biology as to justify support for systematics.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ernst Mayr (1982). &lt;i&gt;The Growth of Biological Thought: Diversity, Evolution, and Inheritance&lt;/i&gt;. The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press. Cambridge, Massachusetts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
45&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Population Thinking versus Essentialism&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Western thinking for more than two thousand years after Plato was
dominated by essentialism. It was not until the nineteenth&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
46&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
century that a new and different way of thinking about nature began to spread,
so-called population thinking. What is population thinking and how does it
differ from essentialism? Population thinkers stress the uniqueness of
everything in the organic world. What is important for them is the individual,
not the type. They emphasize that every individual in sexually reproducing
species is uniquely different from all others, with much individuality even
existing in uniparentally reproducing ones. There is no &quot;typical&quot; individual,
and mean values are abstractions. Much of what in the past has been
designated in biology as &quot;classes&quot; are populations consisting of unique
individuals (Ghiselin, 1974b; Hull, 1976).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There was a potential for population thinking in Leibniz's theory of
monads, for Leibniz postulated that each monad was individualistically
different from every other monad, a major departure from essentialism. But
essentialism had such a strong hold in Germany that Leibniz's suggestion did
not result in any population thinking. When it finally developed elsewhere, it
had two roots; one consisted of the British animal breeders (Bakewell,
Sebright, and many others) who had come to realize that every individual in
their herds had different heritable characteristics, on the basis of which they
selected the sires and dams of the next generation. The other root was
systematics. All practicing naturalists were struck by the observation that
when collecting a &quot;series&quot; of specimens of a single species they found that no
two specimens were ever completely alike. Not only did Darwin stress this in
his barnacle work, but even Darwin's critics concurred on this point.
Wollaston (1860), for instance, wrote &quot;amongst the millions of people who
have been born into the world, we are certain that no two have ever been
precisely alike in every respect; and in a similar manner it is not too much to
affirm the same of all living creatures (however alike some of them may seem
to our uneducated eyes) that have ever existed.&quot; Similar statements were made
by many mid-nineteenth-century taxonomists. This uniqueness is true not only
for individuals but even for stages in the life cycle of any individual, and for
aggregations of individuals whether they be demes, species, or plant and
animal associations. Considering the large number of genes that are either
turned on or turned off in a given cell, it is quite possible that not even any two
cells in the body are completely identical. This uniqueness of biological
individuals means that we must approach groups of biological entities in a
very different spirit from the way we deal with groups of identical inorganic
entities. This is the basic meaning of population&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
47&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
thinking. The differences between biological individuals are real, while
the mean values which we may calculate in the comparison of groups of
individuals (species, for example) are manmade inferences. This fundamental
difference between the classes of the physical scientists and the populations of
the biologists has various consequences. For instance, he who does not
understand the uniqueness of individuals is unable to understand the working
of natural selection.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The statistics of the essentialist are quite different from those of the populationist. When we measure a physical constant -- for instance, the speed of light -- we know that under equivalent circumstances it is constant and that any variation in the observational results is due to inaccuracy of measurement, the statistics simply indicating the degree of reliability of our results. The early statistics from Petty and Graunt to Quetelet (Hilts, 1973) was essentialistic statistics, attempting to arrive at true values in order to overcome the confusing effects of variation. Quetelet, a follower of Laplace, was interested in deterministic laws. He hoped by his method to be able to calculate the characteristics of the &quot;average man,&quot; that is, to discover the &quot;essence&quot; of man. Variation was nothing but &quot;errors&quot; around the mean values.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Francis Galton was perhaps the first to realize fully that the mean value of variable biological populations is a construct. Differences in height among a group of people are real and not the result of inaccuracies of measurement. The most interesting parameter in the statistics of natural populations is the actual variation, its amount, and its nature. The amount of variation is different from character to character and from species to species. Darwin could not have arrived at a theory of natural selection if he had not adopted populational thinking. The sweeping statements in the racist literature, on the other hand, are almost invariably based on essentialistic (typological) thinking.&lt;b&gt;The sweeping statements in the racist literature, on the other hand, are almost invariably based on essentialistic (typological) thinking.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
523-524&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Ideological Resistance&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Inevitably, the concept of natural selection was eventually applied to
man. This resulted in various excesses (such as racism)&lt;/b&gt; but also in the counter
claim that an assumption of genetic differences of selective significance in
man was in conflict with the principle of equality. Extreme egalitarianism led
to the development of strongly environmentalist schools, particularly in
American anthropology and in behaviorist psychology. As noble as these
movements were in their basic ideology, and perhaps as necessary as they
were to combat racism and social prejudice, the major claims of these schools
were not substantiated by any concrete evidence but were based on an unbiological concept of equality. The situation
was made worse when Lysenkoism raised its ugly head in the USSR and when
certain Marxist groups in the western countries decided to attack genetics and
to promote environmentalism. Some of the attacks against sociobiology in
recent years originated from the same ideology. Linking Darwin's name with
Herbert Spencer's social Darwinism was also detrimental for the acceptability
of natural selection (Freeman, 1974; Nichols, 1974; Hertwig, 1921; Greene,
1977; Bannister, 1979).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;


623&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Eugenics&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The recognition that natural selection, and natural selection alone, had raised man from the level of an ape to that of a human being suggested to Galton soon after Darwin's death that one might apply this principle of selection in order to achieve a biological improvement of man. This utopian scheme, to which he gave the name eugenics, found at first many adherents. In fact, a large number of geneticists and other biologists agreed in their writings that it was a noble idea to improve mankind by facilitating the reproduction of the &quot;best&quot; members of the species and by preventing the reproduction of individuals who had genetic diseases or were otherwise inferior. Actually, two kinds of eugenics must be distinguished. Negative eugenics endeavors to reduce the number of deleterious genes in a population by preventing the reproduction of carriers of dominant genes and by reducing the reproductive rate of heterozygous carriers of recessives (where such heterozygotes can be diagnosed). Positive eugenics strives to enhance the reproductive capacity of &quot;superior&quot; individuals (Haller, 1963; Osborn, 1968). When one reads the writings of these early believers in eugenics, one is impressed by their idealism and humanity. They saw in eugenics a means to go beyond the improvements made possible by education and a rise in the standard of living. No political bias was at first attached to eugenics, and it was supported by the entire range of opinion from the far left to the far right. But this did not last long. &lt;b&gt;Eugenics soon became a tool of racists and of reactionaries. Instead of being applied strictly to population thinking, it was interpreted typologically; soon, without the show of any evidence, whole races of mankind were designated as superior or inferior. In the long run it led to the horrors of Hitler's holocaust.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
As a consequence it has become almost impossible, since 1933, to discuss eugenics objectively. This does not invalidate the fact, however, that it was through natural selection that man reached humanity, and it is equally true that we know of no method other than selection to improve the human genotype. Nevertheless, to apply artificial selection to man is impossible, at least for the time&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
624&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
being, for a number of reasons. The first one is that it is quite unknown to what extent nonphysical human characteristics have a genetic basis. Second, human society thrives on the diversity of talents and capabilities of its members; even if we had the ability to manage the selection, we would not have any idea for what particular mixture of talents we should strive. Finally, the concept that people are genetically different, even were it scientifically even better established than it is today, is not acceptable to the majority of western people.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

634&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
This is only a small sample of widely held misconceptions concerning inheritance. Inheritance, being such a conspicuous phenomenon, became the subject of a diversified folklore-&quot;science,&quot; the remnants of which can be found among laypersons even today. &lt;b&gt;Animal breeders, for instance, insisted that if a female of a pure race had once been inseminated by a male of a different race or by a mongrel, her &quot;blood&quot; would be permanently impure so that she could no longer be used for breeding purposes. This belief often was also applied to mankind, particularly in the racist literature.&lt;/b&gt; It was also widely believed that a single offspring could be fathered by several males so that a child of a female who had received several males in the period during which she had conceived would combine the characteristics of these several fathers. There was also the belief in a great plasticity of the genetic material; for example, it was believed that any accidents of the mother, like being frightened by a snake, might affect the fetus.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
881&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
4. Several authors, more or less independently, recognized the importance of Darwin's shift from competition among species to competition among individuals: Vorzimmer (1969), Herbert (1971), Ghiselin (1969; 1971-72). &lt;b&gt;The lesson that Darwin's struggle for existence is a reproductive competition among individuals was, alas, not understood at all by most of those who subsequently operated most freely with the struggle for existence, particularly racists and adherents of so-called social Darwinism (or more correctly, social Spencerism).&lt;/b&gt; This is true, for instance, for most authors cited by Greene (1977), but occasionally even Darwin expressed himself ambiguously (Greene 1981).&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mayr, Ernst (1994). Typological versus Population Thinking. Chapter 8 of: &lt;i&gt;Conceptual Issues in Evolutionary Biology&lt;/i&gt;. Elliott Sober, ed. MIT Press. 157-160&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
159&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;All racist theories are built on this [typology] foundation. &lt;/b&gt; Essentially, it asserts that every representative of a race conforms to the type and is separated from the representatives of any other race by a distinct gap.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mayr, Ernst (1995). Darwin’s Impact on Modern Thought. &lt;i&gt;Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society&lt;/i&gt;, 139(4), 317-325. https://www.jstor.org/stable/987231&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
324&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Population thinking is a major and very beneficial contribution made by Darwin. For instance, it completely refutes the typological aspects of racism.&lt;/b&gt; One can no longer make typological statements based on mean values of human population groups because we now know that every individual is different from every other individual, not only of other races, but even of his own race. Unfortunately, in our educational system and in other aspects of our culture, we are still tending to think too typologically, and do not allow sufficiently for the unique differences among individuals. This heritage from Darwin has not yet been fully adopted by our culture.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ernst Mayr (2004). &lt;i&gt;What Makes Biology Unique?: Considerations on the Autonomy of a Scientific Discipline&lt;/i&gt;. Cambridge University Press, 9/08/2004, 232 pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;

27&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Typological thinking, therefore, is unable to accommodate variation and has given rise to a misleading conception of human races. Caucasians, Africans, Asians, and Inuits are types for a typologist that differ conspicuously from other human ethnic groups and are sharply separated from them. &lt;b&gt;This mode of thinking leads to racism. Darwin completely rejected typological thinking and instead used an entirely different concept, now called &lt;i&gt;population thinking&lt;/i&gt; (see below).&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
89&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Population thinking is of tremendous importance in daily life. &lt;b&gt;For instance, the failure to apply population thinking is the major source of racism.&lt;/b&gt; Many of Darwin's associates, such as Charles Lyell and T.H. Huxley (Mayr 1982), never adopted population thinking and remained typologists all their lives. Consequently they were unable to understand and accept natural selection. Typological thinking was so firmly rooted in the thinking of the period that it is not surprising it took eighty years until, in the 1930s, the concept of natural selection was finally universally adopted by evolutionists.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

pp. 166-167:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The situation is somewhat different with the development of new concepts. When Darwin's theorizing forced the inclusion of man in the tree of common descent, it caused indeed an ideological revolution. On the other hand, as was correctly emphasized by Popper, Mendel's new paradigm of inheritance did not. Changes in concepts have far more impact than new discoveries. &lt;b&gt;For instance, the replacement of essentialistic by population thinking had a revolutionary impact in the fields of systematics, evolutionary biology, and even outside of science (in politics). This shift had a profound effect on the interpretation of gradualism, speciation, macroevolution, natural selection, and racism.&lt;/b&gt; The rejection of cosmic teleology and of the authority of the Bible have had equally drastic effects on the interpretation of evolution and adaptation. The impact of a revolutionary new concept or discovery on the prevailing paradigm is highly variable. In the case of Darwin's theory of natural selection, the ideological commitment of the preceding paradigm to essentialism, theism, teleology, and physicalism, necessitated not only the most profound revolution ever produced by a new theory but also the longest period of delay.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The publication in 1859 of Darwin's &lt;i&gt;Origin of Species&lt;/i&gt; was unique in representing a multiple scientific revolution. I am referring to the very special case of the simultaneous proposal of several revolutionary theories, such as that of common descent and of natural selection. These are really two independent scientific revolutions and either one can exist without the other. The enthusiastic acceptance of the theory of common descent and the virtual non-acceptance of the theory of natural selection in the first eighty years after 1859 definitely proves this independence. The reason for the difference in reception is that common descent was rather easily accommodated in the thinking of the period while natural selection was not.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I’ll throw in this 1997 interview, mostly for the last line on Mayr being “one of these euphoric guys.” (And for the reiteration of the deadness of eugenics.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angier, Natalie (1997). “Ernst Mayr at 93.” &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.naturalhistorymag.com/&quot;&gt;Natural History&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;, 106 (4), 8-11. May 1997.  PDF page 269 of: https://digitallibrary.amnh.org/handle/2246/6503 &lt;br /&gt;
http://hdl.handle.net/2246/6503  &lt;br /&gt;
https://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;amp;db=aph&amp;amp;AN=9705100460&amp;amp;site=ehost-live&amp;amp;scope=site&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
Ernst Mayr, one of the world's greatest evolutionary biologists, is interviewed about evolution and other aspects of biology.
&lt;br /&gt;
[...]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;How much do you think we can understand about our nature by taking the perspective of sociobiology, or evolutionary psychology as it's called nowadays? The relationship between men and women,for example?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Most of the behaviors between males and females have nothing to do with sociality. They're behaviors between two individuals, each acting with the ultimate objective to enhance individual reproductive success. This is true even of things like sibling rivalry. Most of these interactions are not social phenomena in the broad sense, and that's why I don't like to call it sociobiology. But when you come to the real social phenomena, the migrations of wildebeests or whales, you won't read a word about them in the sociobiological literature.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Where do you think the human species is going? Do you believe we can continue to evolve in a genetic sense?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There's absolutely no chance of the human species evolving. First of all, we can never speciate. We cover every niche, every spot on the earth, so there's no opportunity for isolation. Moreover, I do not feel there's any natural selection in any positive sense going on right now. &lt;b&gt;Of course, there are those who have talked about eugenics, but we all know that eugenics is impossible for many reasons. I can't see the development of man into superman or anything like that.&lt;/b&gt; Theoretically we could have cultural evolution and develop higher and better concepts. But if you have no basis for a change in genes, then unfortunately you can only develop through cultural evolution.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Why do you say &quot;unfortunately?&quot;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Because the cultural things can be lost so quickly.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;On the subject of ethics and eugenics, your own background is interesting. You left Germany in 1931, at the start of the Nazi era.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I had a very interesting life, no question about it. I came from the fourth generation in which there was a medical doctor, and I was to be a medical doctor. But I switched to zoology because I was very adventurous and wanted to see the world.. I wanted to go on an expedition. Fortunately just as I was finishing my doctorate, Lord Rothschild needed somebody in New Guinea.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Did you like being in New Guinea?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Well, it's exciting, but it's a tough life, I'll tell you that. I had malaria, I had dysentery, I had dengue, I had everything you can have. Weeks would go by and there was no one to talk to except natives, and I was always alone.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;I understand you were living off the land and eating birds of paradise, among other things. What does a bird of paradise taste like?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Most land birds really taste almost about the same. They have a soft and rather flavorful meat. I ate only one bird that was absolutely awful, and that was a cormorant. That was so fishy it was almost inedible.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Do you keep a regular schedule for work?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
More or less. I have an alarm that wakes me up at 6:15 every morning. I have a little kitchenette. I take one meal outside, and one I make myself. I'm quite active. I write, give lectures, travel abroad.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Have you had any major disappointments, any regrets?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Well, I probably do, but I'm one of these euphoric guys. I always look to the future and never look back.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Matzke</name></author><summary type="html">Bust of Ernst Mayr at the Museum für Naturkunde in Berlin. Source and license at Wikipedia. The ongoing controversy over the proposal to de-name the Ernst Mayr Award at the Society for Systematic Biology is one of many examples of the ongoing re-examination of the history of evolutionary biology with respect to racism in the 2020s. I have developed many worries about the way that the evaluation of major historical figures in evolutionary biology has been occurring. (I know that the SSB proposal formally tries to avoid having this discussion about Mayr, but evaluating the legacy of a historical figure is simply an unavoidable feature of people reaching a decision about naming/de-naming that historical figure.) Some of my main worries are:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Open Letter to the SSB Council, on a solution to the Ernst Mayr Award controversy</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/open-letter-ssb-ernst-mayr-controversy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Open Letter to the SSB Council, on a solution to the Ernst Mayr Award controversy" /><published>2022-01-19T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-01-19T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/open-letter-ssb-ernst-mayr-controversy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/open-letter-ssb-ernst-mayr-controversy.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Davis Hillis asked to have this open letter posted to PT and any other interested blogs. It contains a new proposal to try and 
resolve the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/David-Hillis-on-Ernst-Mayr.html&quot;&gt;Society for Systematic Biology’s ongoing controversy over a proposal to 
de-name the Ernst Mayr Award&lt;/a&gt; for an outstanding student presentation, allegedly because 
it is not inclusive. As &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/NickJMatzke/status/1483729373106950150&quot;&gt;I said on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, while Hillis’s proposal is not something I love, it is an adequate compromise, and 
I would support on that basis, if this proposal were put into formal language and substituted in favor of the old proposal. – Nick Matzke&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;An Open Letter to the SSB Council, on a solution to the Ernst Mayr Award controversy:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
To the SSB Council:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I have been wracking my brain trying to think of some way to turn the upcoming vote on the Ernst Mayr Award from a divisive into a uniting event for the society. Currently, the problem we face is that a major group of members will feel disenfranchised, no matter which way the vote goes. No one wants that.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;I think I’ve come up with a solution that everyone can support, and that will unite all sides. The primary motivation for changing the name of the award is to avoid any exclusion of applications from students from historically underrepresented groups. And yet, removing the name clearly offends many members who admire the outstanding contributions and service of Mayr to SSB and society in general, including his lifetime efforts to make systematics and society more welcoming for all. The latter group includes many student members, as well as members who knew and admired Mayr in life. Both groups are motivated by reasonable concerns, and everyone seems to want to make SSB more welcoming for all.&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  
My proposal has two parts: (1) change the name of the award given for the outstanding paper presented at the Annual Meeting by a student member to the Outstanding Student Presentation Award, as in the existing proposal; and (2) change the purpose and mechanism of awarding the Ernst Mayr Award in Systematic Biology, to a new award that is selected by committee, without any applications. The new award could be fashioned as a “Nobel Prize in Systematics,” or it could be an award for exemplary service to the society. But there would be no applications, and thus no feeling of exclusion by any potential applicants. Ernst Mayr would continue to be recognized for his important contributions and generous gift to the society’s endowment, and the Outstanding Student Presentation Award would remove any bias from student applications.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
  
This solution seems to meet the stated goals of all sides, and includes and welcomes all members of the society.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I hope that the Council will consider this uniting solution, as I fear that the vote will otherwise divide the society, no matter the outcome.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Sincerely,&lt;br /&gt;
David Hillis&lt;br /&gt;
SSB Trustee&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>David Hillis</name></author><summary type="html">Davis Hillis asked to have this open letter posted to PT and any other interested blogs. It contains a new proposal to try and resolve the Society for Systematic Biology’s ongoing controversy over a proposal to de-name the Ernst Mayr Award for an outstanding student presentation, allegedly because it is not inclusive. As I said on Twitter, while Hillis’s proposal is not something I love, it is an adequate compromise, and I would support on that basis, if this proposal were put into formal language and substituted in favor of the old proposal. – Nick Matzke An Open Letter to the SSB Council, on a solution to the Ernst Mayr Award controversy: To the SSB Council: I have been wracking my brain trying to think of some way to turn the upcoming vote on the Ernst Mayr Award from a divisive into a uniting event for the society. Currently, the problem we face is that a major group of members will feel disenfranchised, no matter which way the vote goes. No one wants that.</summary></entry></feed>