<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-05-10T07:51:06-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">AIG's Statement of Faith Outdoes Itself</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/aig-s-statement.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AIG's Statement of Faith Outdoes Itself" /><published>2021-05-08T13:45:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-08T13:45:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/aig-s-statement</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/aig-s-statement.html">&lt;p&gt;Dan Phelps, in a guest post on Pharyngula, observed the other day that &lt;a href=&quot;https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2021/05/08/answers-in-genesiss-statement-of-faith-becomes-more-strident/&quot;&gt;Answers in Genesis’s Statement of Faith Becomes More Strident&lt;/a&gt;, and indeed it has. Mr. Phelps has dredged up the old version of the statement of faith from the Wayback Machine and compared it with the new. You may read Mr. Phelps’s article for yourself, but in a nutshell, he notes that the new version argues that
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; No fact may be considered valid if it contradicts the &quot;scriptural record.&quot; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; The only valid marriage is that between a naturally born [sic] man and a naturally born woman.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Social justice, intersectionality, and critical race theory are anti-Biblical. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Gender and sex are the same thing, and attempts to change your &quot;sex (gender)&quot; are sinful. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Death, suffering, and &quot;natural evils&quot; such as hurricanes and earthquakes are a direct consequence of sin. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this matters, in part, because Answers in Genesis operates the Ark Park in Williamstown, Kentucky. As Mr. Phelps notes in his article and as we have reported in PT, the Ark Park on the one hand purports to be an Equal Opportunity Employer, and on the other hand requires prospective employees to sign its increasingly strident Statement of Faith. For more detail, see also &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2014/09/does-aig-lie-ab.html&quot;&gt;Does AIG lie about Affirmative Action?&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2014/09/aigs-ambivalent.html&quot;&gt;AIG’s ambivalent relation to the tax code&lt;/a&gt; (written primarily by Ed Hensley), and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2017/07/when-is-a-for-profit.html&quot;&gt;When is a for-profit corporation not for profit?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Dan Phelps, in a guest post on Pharyngula, observed the other day that Answers in Genesis’s Statement of Faith Becomes More Strident, and indeed it has. Mr. Phelps has dredged up the old version of the statement of faith from the Wayback Machine and compared it with the new. You may read Mr. Phelps’s article for yourself, but in a nutshell, he notes that the new version argues that</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Granville Sewell thinks it’s obvious</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/Granville-Sewell-thinks-its-obvious.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Granville Sewell thinks it’s obvious" /><published>2021-05-04T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-04T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/Granville-Sewell-thinks-its-obvious</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/Granville-Sewell-thinks-its-obvious.html">&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Pure_Quartz.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;By Eva K., from Wikimedia Commons.  Something Granville Sewell may not expect.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granville Sewell is at it again, and he never seems to learn.  In &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2021/04/some-problems-can-be-proved-unsolvable/&quot;&gt;a piece at the Discovery Institute’s site Evolution News &amp;amp; Science Today&lt;/a&gt; 
he argues that it is obvious that one can reject the ordinary processes of physics, chemistry, and evolution as having brought about living organisms. His piece is entitled “Some problems can be proved unsolvable”.
He mentions a mathematical theorem that was finally proven after hundreds of years (Fermat’s Last Theorem), and a task that can easily shown to be unsolvable
(covering with two-square-sized dominos a chessboard that has had two squares in opposite corners removed).  Then he argues that it is obvious that evolving present-day
life that ends up inventing iPhones can easily be seen to be impossible by natural processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
He summarizes his argument in a few sentences:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Well, I have a very simple proof that the biological problem #3 posed above is also impossible to solve, that does fit in the margin of this document. All one needs 
to do is realize that if a solution were found, we would have proved something obviously false, that a few (four, apparently) fundamental, unintelligent 
forces of physics alone could have rearranged the fundamental particles of physics into libraries full of science texts and encyclopedias, 
computers connected to monitors, keyboards, laser printers and the Internet, cars, trucks, airplanes, nuclear power plants and Apple iPhones. 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Is this really a valid proof? It seems perfectly valid to me, as I cannot think of anything in all of science that can be stated with more 
confidence than that a few unintelligent forces of physics alone could not have rearranged the basic particles of physics into Apple iPhones.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Now Sewell is a mathematician, author of a book on solving differential equations.  But he seems to accept proof-by-obviousness, a method most mathematicians
would not accept.  He should listen to them.  Instead he lays the obviousness on a bit too thick ...

&lt;!--more--&gt;

He asks whether elementary particles and the four fundamental forces of physics (there are now only two, actually) could end up with computers, iPhones, libraries,
and so on.  That sounds impossible.  But he's left out a few steps.  For example:
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Elementary particles aggregating to form larger particles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Those particles forming atoms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Atoms becoming connected by bonds to form chemicals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Chemicals interacting to form cosmic dust&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Cosmic dust forming clouds by the attraction of gravity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Gravity in dust clouds leading to clumps that become a solar system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; ... including the formation of a star and planets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Lots of geology (steps omitted)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; An early Earth with interesting organic chemicals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Origin of life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Evolution of protists and single-celled eukaryotes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Evolution of multicellular life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; Evolution of people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; People producing tools&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; People producing agriculture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; and civilization,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; and technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
See, it isn't just a direct aggregation of particles.  If we don't know all the details of those steps, few seem to think that the processes of astronomy, 
chemistry, and geology can't explain our planet without the intervention of a cosmic Designer.  Intelligent Design arguments are not very visible in physics, in chemistry, in astronomy, 
and in geology.  Those very active sciences get along fine without ID.  Sewell's proof-by-obviousness needs somewhat more focus.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">By Eva K., from Wikimedia Commons. Something Granville Sewell may not expect. Granville Sewell is at it again, and he never seems to learn. In a piece at the Discovery Institute’s site Evolution News &amp;amp; Science Today he argues that it is obvious that one can reject the ordinary processes of physics, chemistry, and evolution as having brought about living organisms. His piece is entitled “Some problems can be proved unsolvable”. He mentions a mathematical theorem that was finally proven after hundreds of years (Fermat’s Last Theorem), and a task that can easily shown to be unsolvable (covering with two-square-sized dominos a chessboard that has had two squares in opposite corners removed). Then he argues that it is obvious that evolving present-day life that ends up inventing iPhones can easily be seen to be impossible by natural processes. He summarizes his argument in a few sentences: Well, I have a very simple proof that the biological problem #3 posed above is also impossible to solve, that does fit in the margin of this document. All one needs to do is realize that if a solution were found, we would have proved something obviously false, that a few (four, apparently) fundamental, unintelligent forces of physics alone could have rearranged the fundamental particles of physics into libraries full of science texts and encyclopedias, computers connected to monitors, keyboards, laser printers and the Internet, cars, trucks, airplanes, nuclear power plants and Apple iPhones. Is this really a valid proof? It seems perfectly valid to me, as I cannot think of anything in all of science that can be stated with more confidence than that a few unintelligent forces of physics alone could not have rearranged the basic particles of physics into Apple iPhones. Now Sewell is a mathematician, author of a book on solving differential equations. But he seems to accept proof-by-obviousness, a method most mathematicians would not accept. He should listen to them. Instead he lays the obviousness on a bit too thick ...</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Crepuscular rays</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/crepuscular-rays.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Crepuscular rays" /><published>2021-04-26T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-26T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/crepuscular-rays</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/crepuscular-rays.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Sarah Wise&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Wise_Crepuscular_3_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Crepuscular rays&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://optics.kulgun.net/Rays/&quot;&gt;Crepuscular rays&lt;/a&gt;, by Sarah Wise, taken from her home near Louisville, Colo., mid-April, 2021.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We chose this splendid picture from among several equally splendid shots in part because it shows clearly the origin of crepuscular rays – just look at the mountain peaks and valleys, especially on the right. The rays are the result of light scattering by the atmosphere. On the left, you can clearly see atmospheric scattering where one of the rays roughly bisects a cloud. And finally, you can see how every cloud has a silver lining.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, I assume that crepuscular rays are the reason Moses has horns in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moses_(Michelangelo)&quot;&gt;Michelangelo’s sculpture of Moses&lt;/a&gt;: ray and horn are the same word in Biblical Hebrew, probably because the ancients simply called crepuscular rays “horns.” It seems likely to me that they envisioned Moses as having had (crepuscular) &lt;i&gt;rays&lt;/i&gt; coming out of his head.  Again incidentally, you may find other depictions of Moses with horns &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/lessons-from-history/the-intriguing-interpretation-of-horns-in-michelangelos-sculpture-moses-a1044179408b&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. There is nothing new in the author’s premise that the word was mistranslated into Greek.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Sarah Wise. Crepuscular rays, by Sarah Wise, taken from her home near Louisville, Colo., mid-April, 2021. We chose this splendid picture from among several equally splendid shots in part because it shows clearly the origin of crepuscular rays – just look at the mountain peaks and valleys, especially on the right. The rays are the result of light scattering by the atmosphere. On the left, you can clearly see atmospheric scattering where one of the rays roughly bisects a cloud. And finally, you can see how every cloud has a silver lining. Incidentally, I assume that crepuscular rays are the reason Moses has horns in Michelangelo’s sculpture of Moses: ray and horn are the same word in Biblical Hebrew, probably because the ancients simply called crepuscular rays “horns.” It seems likely to me that they envisioned Moses as having had (crepuscular) rays coming out of his head. Again incidentally, you may find other depictions of Moses with horns here. There is nothing new in the author’s premise that the word was mistranslated into Greek.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Meditation on a review of a book by Stephen Meyer</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/meditation-on-review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meditation on a review of a book by Stephen Meyer" /><published>2021-04-16T19:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-16T19:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/meditation-on-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/meditation-on-review.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Meyer_Book_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Return-God-Hypothesis-Compelling-Scientific/dp/0062071505&quot;&gt;Return of the God Hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;: Three Scientific Discoveries that Reveal the Mind Behind the Universe&lt;/i&gt;, by Stephen Meyer. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Darrel Falk, a past president of BioLogos, recently reviewed Stephen Meyer’s latest book, &lt;i&gt;Return of the God Hypothesis&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://biologos.org/articles/return-of-the-god-hypothesis-a-biologists-reflections&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Professor Falk is sympathetic with Dr. Meyer and indeed avers that their “perspective[s] on the role of God in creation” are not “much different.” The review is nevertheless negative and led to an interesting exchange on a Google Group devoted in part to The Panda’s Thumb. I should stress that as far as I know none of us on PT has read the book, but by now we have probably all read the review. At any rate, the exchange is reprinted, with permission, below the fold:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Braterman, an honorary chemistry researcher at the University of Glasgow, noticed the following quotation that Prof. Falk singled out in his review:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;To make their case for the adequacy of a strictly materialistic approach to explanation in science and philosophy, defenders of this approach must first show that “gaps” in our knowledge of the materialistic causes of key events in the history of life and the universe can be filled with knowledge of an actual materialistic process capable of producing the events in question. (p. 613).&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He inquired,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;I am not sure what a non-materialistic process would look like, but here Meyer appears to be claiming the right to invoke God of the gaps as the default explanation, placing the onus on the scientific community to prove that no gaps exist. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Am I being unfair?&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Petto, Distinguished Lecturer in BioSciences at the University of Wisconsin – Milwaukee, responded,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;In essence, yes. This is the venerable creationist tactic that claims that if we do not (yet) have an explanation of some event or phenomenon based on naturalistic (so-called &quot;materialistic&quot;) processes, then, by default, the divine intervention &lt;i&gt;has&lt;/i&gt; to be accepted as the only alternative (though ID advocates tried to muddy their embrace of the Deity, they use the same logic). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

This fallacy of dualistic thinking has strong cultural resonance, especially in the USA, where we tout the value of hearing from &quot;both sides&quot; of a controversy (as though there were only two), and it was reinforced, I think, by the fact that lawyers were among some of the more prominent voices in the movement that emerged through the 1960s. For lawyers, of course, the adversarial environment in court works almost always this way: if I can poke enough holes in your argument and conclusions, then my argument and conclusions prevail. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

And this, I think, is why so much of the creationist (and now ID) literature is about problems with or &quot;evidences&quot; against evolution without any significant demonstration that the cre/ID position has any factual or experimental support. In their minds (and in the dualistic framework that they impose on the argument), there doesn't need to be any affirmative evidence. It is enough to show that your opponent's position is untenable or unsupported or somehow defective, and you win by default. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

It may work culturally, but it fails the chief claim made by ID and earlier &quot;creation scientists&quot;: that theirs is a scientific alternative. It is, in fact, not an alternative at all, but a vague cultural default position that is not defensible on its scientific merits&amp;mdash;or lack thereof.&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Return of the God Hypothesis: Three Scientific Discoveries that Reveal the Mind Behind the Universe, by Stephen Meyer. Darrel Falk, a past president of BioLogos, recently reviewed Stephen Meyer’s latest book, Return of the God Hypothesis, here. Professor Falk is sympathetic with Dr. Meyer and indeed avers that their “perspective[s] on the role of God in creation” are not “much different.” The review is nevertheless negative and led to an interesting exchange on a Google Group devoted in part to The Panda’s Thumb. I should stress that as far as I know none of us on PT has read the book, but by now we have probably all read the review. At any rate, the exchange is reprinted, with permission, below the fold:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Flagellum research on the front burner again</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/flagellum-research.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flagellum research on the front burner again" /><published>2021-04-14T08:25:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-14T08:25:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/flagellum-research</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/flagellum-research.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Chlamydomonas_Flagellum.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chlamydomonas&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flagellum&quot;&gt;SEM image of flagellated &lt;i&gt;Chlamydomonas&lt;/i&gt; sp.&lt;/a&gt; (10000×), a single-celled green alga. &lt;small&gt;Credit: Dartmouth Electron Microscope Facility, Dartmouth College. Public domain.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have not discussed the bacterial flagellum on PT in a good long time – one of the last instances was Nick Matzke’s 2007 article, &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2007/10/full-text-of-th.html&quot;&gt;The Edge of Creationism&lt;/a&gt;, a clever pun on Michael Behe’s book title, &lt;i&gt;The Edge of Evolution&lt;/i&gt;. In that article, Dr. Matzke thoroughly debunks Dr. Behe’s contention that the flagellum could not have evolved, hence was designed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Matzke, I am pleased to note, is at it again. He is a part of an international team led by Matthew Baker to, in their words, discover “How life got moving: reconstructing and re-evolving the bacterial flagellar motor, piece-by-piece.” Their intention, according to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://newsroom.unsw.edu.au/news/general/unsw-researcher-awarded-18m-international-life-science-grant&quot;&gt; press release from the University of New South Wales&lt;/a&gt;, is “to estimate what an ancient flagellar motor – the tiny rotating wheel that powers the swimming movement of bacteria – might have looked like, and then re-engineer it for further experimentation and research.” So much for not evolving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In what must be an improbable case of convergent evolution, a team headed by Morgan Beeby at Imperial College London has been awarded a grant for a project titled “Darwin rwinDa: rewinding and rerunning evolution to study innovation in action” (no, that is not a typo). According to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/news/219213/team-investigating-evolution-bacterial-tails-wins/&quot;&gt;press release from Imperial College&lt;/a&gt;, their intention is to discover “How can gradual, Darwinian evolution build such a structure if not by inventing all necessary parts at once?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In truth, the sudden appearance &lt;i&gt;ex nihilo&lt;/i&gt; of these two projects is not entirely convergent evolution. Both teams applied for grants awarded “under the umbrella theme ‘Complex mechanisms of living organisms’” by the Human Frontier Science Program, and each received 1.4 M$ over a period of 3 a. The HFSP &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hfsp.org/hfsp-news-events/press-release-2021-hfsp-research-grants&quot;&gt;awarded 28 grants to begin in 2021&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">SEM image of flagellated Chlamydomonas sp. (10000×), a single-celled green alga. Credit: Dartmouth Electron Microscope Facility, Dartmouth College. Public domain. We have not discussed the bacterial flagellum on PT in a good long time – one of the last instances was Nick Matzke’s 2007 article, The Edge of Creationism, a clever pun on Michael Behe’s book title, The Edge of Evolution. In that article, Dr. Matzke thoroughly debunks Dr. Behe’s contention that the flagellum could not have evolved, hence was designed. Dr. Matzke, I am pleased to note, is at it again. He is a part of an international team led by Matthew Baker to, in their words, discover “How life got moving: reconstructing and re-evolving the bacterial flagellar motor, piece-by-piece.” Their intention, according to a press release from the University of New South Wales, is “to estimate what an ancient flagellar motor – the tiny rotating wheel that powers the swimming movement of bacteria – might have looked like, and then re-engineer it for further experimentation and research.” So much for not evolving. In what must be an improbable case of convergent evolution, a team headed by Morgan Beeby at Imperial College London has been awarded a grant for a project titled “Darwin rwinDa: rewinding and rerunning evolution to study innovation in action” (no, that is not a typo). According to a press release from Imperial College, their intention is to discover “How can gradual, Darwinian evolution build such a structure if not by inventing all necessary parts at once?” In truth, the sudden appearance ex nihilo of these two projects is not entirely convergent evolution. Both teams applied for grants awarded “under the umbrella theme ‘Complex mechanisms of living organisms’” by the Human Frontier Science Program, and each received 1.4 M$ over a period of 3 a. The HFSP awarded 28 grants to begin in 2021.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Setophaga coronata</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/setophaga-coronata.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Setophaga coronata" /><published>2021-04-12T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-12T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/setophaga-coronata</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/setophaga-coronata.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;David Rintoul&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Rintoul.yellow_rumped_warbler_winter_900.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Yellow-rumped warbler&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Yellow-rumped_Warbler/id&quot;&gt;Setophaga coronata&lt;/a&gt;, yellow-rumped warbler (aka myrtle warbler). Mr. Rintoul writes that the warbler &quot;was photographed on a winter day in Manhattan, Kansas. This warbler, unique among the North American wood warblers, has the ability to digest the waxy coatings of various fruits such as bayberry, cedar, and myrtle. This adaptation allows them to winter further north than most warblers, which mostly depend on insects during the winter months.&quot; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by David Rintoul. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Setophaga coronata, yellow-rumped warbler (aka myrtle warbler). Mr. Rintoul writes that the warbler &quot;was photographed on a winter day in Manhattan, Kansas. This warbler, unique among the North American wood warblers, has the ability to digest the waxy coatings of various fruits such as bayberry, cedar, and myrtle. This adaptation allows them to winter further north than most warblers, which mostly depend on insects during the winter months.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dinosaur gastrolith</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/dinosaur-gastroliths.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dinosaur gastrolith" /><published>2021-04-12T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-12T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/dinosaur-gastroliths</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/dinosaur-gastroliths.html">&lt;p&gt;Photographs by &lt;strong&gt;Dan Phelps&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Phelps_Gastroliths_Horizontal.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dinosaur gastrolith&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Probable &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gastrolith&quot;&gt;dinosaur gastrolith&lt;/a&gt;  from either the Jurassic &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morrison_Formation&quot;&gt;Morrison Formation&lt;/a&gt; or  lowermost Cretaceous &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cloverly_Formation&quot;&gt;Cloverly Formation&lt;/a&gt; of Utah. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Phelps explains,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Gastroliths are usually defined as stones that were swallowed by herbivorous dinosaurs, or other animals, to aid in digesting food. Many types of vegetarian dinosaurs did not have grinding teeth and thus swallowed their food without chewing. This process is analogous to the tiny stones swallowed by some modern birds that are kept in a gizzard to aid in the digestion of food. Other animals, such as the marine reptiles known as plesiosaurs, swallowed stones for a different reason, namely to create ballast and thus be able to dive deeper.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Usually, gastroliths are highly polished stones made of very fine-grained chert, like this specimen. Sometimes they are also made of petrified wood and even, on occasion, igneous and metamorphic rocks. Unless a gastrolith is found within an articulated dinosaur skeleton, there is always a bit of justified skepticism about any well-polished rock identified as one. There is a  possibility that this is only a rather well-polished extraformational pebble that was somehow deposited in fine-grained sediment in the Morrison/Cloverly, but this possibility doesn’t effect the point I will make below. The possible gastrolith illustrated is made out of chert and contains fossils of crinoids and other organisms. In any case, these rocks were already lithified before being deposited in younger rock formations. They contain fossils of life that existed before the Jurassic and in many cases before the Mesozoic. This is true of such pebbles whether they are true gastroliths or merely well-rounded, polished pebbles.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Most Young Earth Creationists (YEC's), such as those who built the Ark Park, claim gastroliths formed in one year during Noah’s Flood (usually claimed to have occurred in 2348 BCE). The sequence, precursors of the gastroliths formed from ancient sediment, &lt;i&gt;then&lt;/i&gt; lithified, &lt;i&gt;then&lt;/i&gt; re-eroded, &lt;i&gt;then&lt;/i&gt; partly rounded, &lt;i&gt;then&lt;/i&gt; swallowed by herbivorous dinosaurs, &lt;i&gt;then&lt;/i&gt; further polished in the dinosaur’s digestive system, is totally inconsistent with YEC claims.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

I thought of this long ago, and just discovered this &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/8QATIUy6r6s&quot;&gt;well-done YouTube video by Erika Gutsick Gibbon&lt;/a&gt; (possibly a pseudonym) explaining why gastroliths are inconsistent with YEC.&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photographs by Dan Phelps. Probable dinosaur gastrolith from either the Jurassic Morrison Formation or lowermost Cretaceous Cloverly Formation of Utah. Mr. Phelps explains,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Casey Takes a Swing at Ardipithecus—and Strikes Out</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/Casey-Takes-a-Swing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Casey Takes a Swing at Ardipithecus—and Strikes Out" /><published>2021-04-01T14:10:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-01T14:10:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/Casey-Takes-a-Swing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/Casey-Takes-a-Swing.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Ardipithecus_Ramidus.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ardipithecus ramidus&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Ardipithecus_ramidus.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Ardipithecus ramidus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; skull in National Museum of Natural Sciences of Spain. This specimen illustrates a key derived feature in the human branch of the evolutionary change in form and function of the upper canine teeth. They are relatively smaller, and do not show a wear pattern  in which the canine maintains a sharpened edge by &quot;honing&quot; the surface as it passes by the premolar in the lower jaw.&lt;small&gt;Credit: Tiia Monto, CC BY-SA 3.0.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent posting, &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2021/02/study-hands-of-ardi-indicate-a-chimp-like-tree-dweller-and-knuckle-walker/)&quot;&gt;Study: Hands of &quot;Ardi&quot; indicate a chimp-like tree-dweller and knuckle-walker&lt;/a&gt;, Casey Luskin of the Discovery Institute reports some of the findings from a recent re-analysis of the forelimb anatomy of &lt;i&gt;Ardipithecus&lt;/i&gt; and comes to the unsurprising conclusion that “Ardi” was not designed for obligate bipedal orthogrady, otherwise known as the way humans get around the world when forced to walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He swings for the fences, telling us all reasons why these findings eliminate Ardi from its status as an ancestral hominin. However, his conclusions are based on common rookie mistakes about evolutionary science in general, and hominin evolution in particular. And so, the intention to hit the ball out of the park results in a disappointing strikeout reminding me of another &lt;a href=&quot;https://poets.org/poem/casey-bat&quot;&gt;well known Casey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strike 1: Looking for Mr. Goodlink &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evolutionary science is not a search for specific ancestors that gave rise to specific descendants—even if occasionally it appears that we do find them. The proclamation that a specific fossil hominin—especially one from over 4 million years ago—is &lt;i&gt;the&lt;/i&gt; ancestor of our modern species is the stuff of press releases and news headlines, but not the serious study of paleontology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of what we can find—especially from millions of years back in our history—will be collateral relatives. Even though my paternal grandfather was removed from our family tree as a very young man, I can get a good sense of his physical characteristics because I knew his surviving relatives: his father, siblings, cousins, and nieces and nephews—his collateral relatives. Even though these relatives appear in a “side branch” relative to me, information about them allows us to sketch the history of our family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a similar way, what hominin fossils such as &lt;i&gt;Ardipithecus&lt;/i&gt; do is show us how and when ancestral members of our human family tree acquired certain morphologic traits that came to define the remaining surviving branch of the human family tree. The real question is &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; whether there is some feature that reflects the arboreal habits of the last common ancestor (LCA) of humans and other African apes. Rather the question is what features are present in &lt;i&gt;Ardipithecus&lt;/i&gt; that are found only in the evolutionary branch leading to modern hominins. Even in the light of Ardi’s retention of some morphologic features well suited to suspensory locomotor behavior (movement characterized by hanging or swinging below branches of trees), Ardi still possesses traits commonly found in hominins, but not in chimpanzees or gorillas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is unlikely that Ardi is the direct ancestor of all modern humans, but the point is that this is not why Ardipithecus is of interest. Rather, Ardipithecus helps to tell us about the journey of our branch of the evolutionary tree from the last common ancestor (LCA) with the other African apes to modern humans. The greatest value of these specimens to that inquiry is in how they shed light on that journey—even if we never find the direct lineal ancestor of all modern humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rookie mistake here is presuming that finding collateral relatives with key features different from our own means that they nullify any relationship among us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strike 2: Phylo-D’Oh&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luskin cites the paper in &lt;i&gt;Science Advances&lt;/i&gt; by T.C. Prang and others, &lt;a href=&quot;https://advances.sciencemag.org/content/7/9/eabf2474/tab-article-info&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Ardipithecus&lt;/i&gt; hand provides evidence that humans and chimpanzees evolved from an ancestor with suspensory adaptations&lt;/a&gt;, which provides a morphometric analysis of features of several hand bones of &lt;i&gt;Ardipithecus&lt;/i&gt; compared with those of other primate species. What these results tell us is how the sizes, shapes, and proportions of these bones in &lt;i&gt;Ardipithecus&lt;/i&gt; compare to those in other primates that exhibit certain locomotor behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are important analyses that show us groups of primates that share similarities in morphology. When those similarities also match up with specialized locomotor behaviors, then they suggest that the “owners” of these morphologic features were probably adept at moving through their environments in the same way.  In fact, the analysis by Prang and others confirms, rather than refutes, one of the key conclusions of the first &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/326/5949/68&quot;&gt;comprehensive evaluations of the &lt;i&gt;Ar. ramidus&lt;/i&gt; remains&lt;/a&gt; by G. Suwa and others:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The &lt;i&gt;Ar. ramidus&lt;/i&gt; postcranium indicates both substantial arboreal capability and an intermediate form of terrestrial bipedality that preceded the more fully established  &lt;i&gt;Australopithecus&lt;/i&gt; condition.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Miocene apes that we infer gave rise to the last common ancestor of humans and African apes do not give a clear picture of the emergence of the branch that led to modern descendant species. Dryopithecines appear to have been generic apes without significant anatomic specializations for “hanging” by the forelimbs (suspensory progression or locomotor behaviors)—even though all the survivving non-human ape species have these specializations. Recent work by Böhme and others, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-019-1731-0&quot;&gt;A   new Miocene    ape  and  locomotion  in the ancestor  of great  apes  and  humans&lt;/a&gt;, proposes another way of using suspensory morphology in arboreal settings: morphologic analysis of the remains of &lt;i&gt;Danuvius guggenmosi&lt;/i&gt; suggest that this species might have employed what the authors called “extended-limb clambering”—a form of movement combining standing upright with overhead grasping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These data suggest—but by no means prove—that the LCA of all modern apes probably relied on suspensory locomotor behaviors.  The key question here is why should we be surprised to see that heritage reflected in the anatomy of early hominins, especially if moving through or climbing in trees represented important behaviors for the first of our relatives to establish the hominin clade?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, if we actually watch the &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/lMC-0kG-SsM&quot;&gt;locomotor behavior of chimpanzees&lt;/a&gt;, even in the trees, we see a wide array of behaviors. Across wide trunks, chimps sometimes knuckle-walk as they do on the ground; walking on smaller tree limbs or climbing vertically, they wrap their hands around the surface; sometimes they stand and move along a branch on their feet while they reach overhead to grasp branches as they progress; and at other times, they hang below the branches and move by ricochetal brachiation—the classic “swinging from the trees” behavior popular culture associates with arboreal apes. Chimpanzees are clearly not limited to suspensory, below-the-branch locomotor behaviors (or to knuckle-walking), even if their hand and forelimb morphology are well suited for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As valuable as morphometric analyses are in helping us understand locomotor and positional behaviors, determining evolutionary relatedness, or phylogeny, is not simply a matter of anatomic or locomotor similarities. The critical data for determining the phylogenetic status of any fossil species is the appearance of anatomic features that are unique to specific branches of the evolutionary tree.  Showing anatomic similarity is not enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article by Prang and others also compared morphologic features related to suspensory locomotor behavior from species in vastly different primate clades—which means they do &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; share a recent common ancestor with the African apes. We see these anatomic changes in these species because the physical demands of similar environments often lead to convergent evolution of the features necessary to navigate the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a similar environment with similar opportunities and challenges for locomotion, primate species that are only distantly related show similar morphologies in the upper limbs. However, that does not mean that spider monkeys and gibbons are closely relatives that emerged from a common ancestor with these features, in the same way that, despite their overall morphologic similarities, we have no doubt that dolphins are not fishes, but mammals. Many anatomic and biomechanical similarities reflect environmental demands on the organism and these must be separated from those that unique identify members of different evolving lineages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rookie mistake here is using a “like-goes-with-like” classification scheme that relies on similar morphologic responses to environmental pressures rather than the features shared uniquely by members of the same branch of the evolutionary tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strike 3: “One of these things is not like the others”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chimpanzees (together with bonobos) are our closest living biologic relatives—but they are decidedly &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; our ancestors. Since the fossil record of African apes leading up to the time when the LCA is estimated to have lived (5‒7 million years ago) and for a long time afterward is limited, it is difficult to say what Ardi’s cousins were doing at the time and what they looked like.  But we can study contemporary descendants of the LCA, so that we can outline the trajectory of what had to change on the evolutionary journey from then to now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luskin’s conclusion that Ardi belongs on the chimpanzee and not the human branch of the family tree looks backward toward the LCA. He asks, in effect, “What features did Ardi have resembling those of the presumed LCA that are also shared with modern chimpanzees?” But to determine the proper phylogenetic placement of &lt;i&gt;Ardipithecus&lt;/i&gt;, we really need to look &lt;i&gt;forward&lt;/i&gt; to the anatomic changes found only in humans and not in the other apes. Only those can tell us whether this species belongs on our branch of the family tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it is not just the lineage containing humans that has changed and evolved in the last 7 million years or so; the lineage containing chimpanzees has as well.  Even if, as seems likely, the LCA of humans and chimps relied on suspensory locomotor behaviors in moving through the trees, modern chimpanzee anatomy is not frozen in time. Modern chimps have highly specialized derived locomotor adaptations, just as humans do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this: given the estimate of a divergence time between humans and chimps at 5‒7 million years ago, the estimated dates for the &lt;i&gt;Ardipithecus&lt;/i&gt; ramidus remains are no more than about 35 % (and possibly as little as 12 %) of the way along the road from LCA to the modern species. So if we had, as Suwa and others suggested, a primate retaining “substantial arboreal capability” while also being able to move effectively on the ground, how much anatomic difference from the LCA might we expect in the forelimb and hands? And how much would it vary from the anatomic changes that we would find in members of the chimpanzee branch of the evolutionary tree living at the same time as &lt;i&gt;Ardipithecus&lt;/i&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t have direct evidence in the fossil record to answer those questions definitively, especially for chimpanzees. But we do have direct fossil evidence to make it clear that it would take at least another 2 million years after &lt;i&gt;Ardipithecus&lt;/i&gt; until humans completed the transition in the skeletal features that we recognize today as the hallmarks of obligate bipedal orthogrady. In other words, Ardi is less than halfway through the transition from trees to ground, even for some estimates of an earlier time frame for the LCA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The analysis by Prang and others places the morphology of the &lt;i&gt;Ardipithecus&lt;/i&gt; hands closer to those primates that engage in suspensory behaviors. But it does not compare the features that are unrelated to arboreal locomotion. The early analysis by Suwa and others looked, for example, at features of the face and skull, for which Ardi shows several specific changes found only in humans. It should surprise no one who understands evolutionary science that some of those showed derived conditions found only in humans. Other features appeared in a form that was intermediate between those that characterize those found in modern humans and chimpanzees, and still others showed features that appeared relatively unchanged in descendants of the LCA and that we share today with the other African apes. This is how evolution works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Suwa and others placed those features known to have unique forms in humans on a continuum that included modern humans, fossil humans, and African apes, the values for &lt;i&gt;Ardipithecus&lt;/i&gt; were intermediate between those for modern chimpanzee species and australopithecines. These include changes in the skull and face that were less like those of chimpanzees and more like those that define australopithecines as humans. And one of these in particular—the relative position of the opening in the base of the skull for the connection to the spinal column (foramen magnum), which reliably indicates habitually upright positional behavior—is notably distinct from that of modern quadrupedal apes and intermediate between them and australopithecines—right where it should be for a member of an evolutionary lineage in transition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not the only feature pointing forward to the hominid branch and away from the chimpanzee branch of our evolutionary family tree. In their &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/326/5949/64&quot;&gt;comparison of &lt;i&gt;Ardipithecus&lt;/i&gt; features&lt;/a&gt; with those of later hominins, White and others identified 66 features preserve well enough to judge their evolutionary affinities. Of these, they judged 33 to be similar to that of the LCA, 7 others to be intermediate between the LCA and those unique to hominins, and 26 to represent the derived condition found only in undisputed hominins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the appearance of uniquely derived traits that confer membership in a phylogenetic clade, regardless of what other features are shared with other evolutionary relatives, and this analsysis of Ardi showed a roughly 50/50 split in those features that mark the pathway from the LCA to the human, and not the chimpanzee, branch of the family tree. And this is true even—or perhaps especially—if not every feature is highly specialized for a particular behavior, even one as important as the human way of walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rookie mistake here is to look at features that tell us mainly about navigating local environmental conditions with a suite of anatomic traits inherited from a recent ancestor, but to ignore those changes found in &lt;i&gt;Ardipithecus&lt;/i&gt; that relate to specific anatomic changes that make humans different from the other African ape lineages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ardi Wins in a Walk-Off&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was &lt;i&gt;Ardipithecus&lt;/i&gt; a knuckle-walker like modern chimps and gorillas? The headline for Luskin’s article implies that Prang and others concluded that is the case. In fact, what they concluded was that the morphology of the wrist joint and the lengths of some of the segments of the digits were similar to that of knuckle-walking chimps. But they also point out that &lt;i&gt;later&lt;/i&gt; hominins retained some of these same features of the wrist, even though there is definitive evidence that these later descendants walked upright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Ardi moved around as do modern chimps, was it because it had to or because it could? This is the main question. Humans walk upright; we are specialized to do so. However, we can climb, and we can swim. That is, we can use our bodies in ways that allow us to perform a variety of behaviors—including the quintessence of suspensory behavior, ricochetal brachiation—but we do not perform these actions as well as organisms that are especially modified to do them faster, more efficiently, and more powerfully than we can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could Ardi have used knuckle-walking? Prang and others suggest it is &lt;i&gt;possible&lt;/i&gt;, even though it is clear that its anatomical features do not require knuckle-walking. Could Ardi have walked upright? Other anatomic features and comparisons to the wide variety of locomotor behaviors in chimpanzees suggest this is also possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically what Prang and others tell us is that Ardi was not “designed for” obligate orthograde bipedal progression—and &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; that Ardi was not an early hominin species. More specifically, this analysis places &lt;i&gt;Ardipithecus&lt;/i&gt; closer to the presumed morphology of the LCA and as being less specialized for upright walking than is the case for later hominin fossil species. And at a point that early in the emergence of the humans from the LCA, is this finding really so surprising?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, and it is not more surprising than that Luskin, freshly returned to the Discovery Institute, has returned to his old pattern of misunderstanding and misrepresenting the scientific literature, based on a caricature of evolutionary science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Andrew Petto is Distinguished Lecturer Emeritus at the University of Wisconsin‒Milwaukee, where he taught anatomy in the Departments of Biological Sciences and Kinesiology.  He also lived for nearly a decade on the edge of the Mudville neighborhood of Holliston, Massachusetts, where there is a statue commemorating the main character in &lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/a5/Holliston-mudville-casey-statue.jpg/855px-Holliston-mudville-casey-statue.jpg&quot;&gt;Casey at the Bat&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew Petto</name></author><summary type="html">Ardipithecus ramidus skull in National Museum of Natural Sciences of Spain. This specimen illustrates a key derived feature in the human branch of the evolutionary change in form and function of the upper canine teeth. They are relatively smaller, and do not show a wear pattern in which the canine maintains a sharpened edge by &quot;honing&quot; the surface as it passes by the premolar in the lower jaw.Credit: Tiia Monto, CC BY-SA 3.0. In a recent posting, Study: Hands of &quot;Ardi&quot; indicate a chimp-like tree-dweller and knuckle-walker, Casey Luskin of the Discovery Institute reports some of the findings from a recent re-analysis of the forelimb anatomy of Ardipithecus and comes to the unsurprising conclusion that “Ardi” was not designed for obligate bipedal orthogrady, otherwise known as the way humans get around the world when forced to walk. He swings for the fences, telling us all reasons why these findings eliminate Ardi from its status as an ancestral hominin. However, his conclusions are based on common rookie mistakes about evolutionary science in general, and hominin evolution in particular. And so, the intention to hit the ball out of the park results in a disappointing strikeout reminding me of another well known Casey.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The (almost) universal constant pi</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/universal-constant-pi.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The (almost) universal constant pi" /><published>2021-04-01T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-01T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/universal-constant-pi</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/04/universal-constant-pi.html">&lt;p&gt;The constant pi, which &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/house-resolution.html&quot;&gt;we celebrated the other day&lt;/a&gt;, is far more versatile than is known to most scientists. For example, within 10 %,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;π = 3 = e = &amp;radic;10&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can be shown that the equality is exact, given a small correction.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
π is useful in physics as well as mathematics. The number of seconds in a year is π×10&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;. The temperature of the earth is 100π K. The speed of light is 100,000π km/s. Any oπticist knows that Wien’s law can be expressed as &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;λ&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt;T&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;1000π&amp;nbsp;μm⋅K&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, πies are called pies because they are circular. Philologists do not know the origin of the trailing “e,” and they do not know why some pies are called pizzas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, finally, π is precisely equal to 3, with no corrections, for very small circles. Indeed, it &lt;i&gt;was&lt;/i&gt; equal to 3 in Biblical times but has been increasing ever since.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">The constant pi, which we celebrated the other day, is far more versatile than is known to most scientists. For example, within 10 %, π = 3 = e = &amp;radic;10 It can be shown that the equality is exact, given a small correction. π is useful in physics as well as mathematics. The number of seconds in a year is π×107. The temperature of the earth is 100π K. The speed of light is 100,000π km/s. Any oπticist knows that Wien’s law can be expressed as λmT&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;1000π&amp;nbsp;μm⋅K Additionally, πies are called pies because they are circular. Philologists do not know the origin of the trailing “e,” and they do not know why some pies are called pizzas. And, finally, π is precisely equal to 3, with no corrections, for very small circles. Indeed, it was equal to 3 in Biblical times but has been increasing ever since.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sporophila spp.</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/Sporophila_spp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sporophila spp." /><published>2021-03-29T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-03-29T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/Sporophila_spp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/Sporophila_spp.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Sporophila_Pair_1280.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Seedeaters&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;(Left) &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tawny-bellied_seedeater&quot;&gt;Sporophila hypoxantha&lt;/a&gt;, tawny-bellied seedeater. Photograph by Dario Sanches, Creative Commons copyright CC-BY-SA-2.0.

(Right) &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ibera_seedeater&quot;&gt;Sporophila iberaensis&lt;/a&gt;, Iberá seedeater. Photograph by Hector Bottai, Creative Commons copyright CC BY-SA 4.0.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These pictures, which I gratefully borrowed from Wikipedia, are occasioned by an &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/371/6536/1312.full&quot;&gt;an article&lt;/a&gt; by Erich D. Jarvis of the Howard Hughes Medical Institute. Briefly, Dr. Jarvis describes work by Sheela Turbek and colleagues at the University of Colorado showing that &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/371/6536/eabc0256&quot;&gt;the two species pictured above are separated by female choice&lt;/a&gt;. That is, they share the same geographical region, but are mostly reproductively isolated by sexual selection mediated by plumage and song. The two species differ in three genomic regions, two of which are related to plumage, and one of which is on a sex chromosome that is found in both males and females. Most likely we are seeing speciation in real time, and eventually the two species will be wholly reproductively isolated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we go to press this morning, so to speak, &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; has posted a second &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2021/03/tiny-differences-plumage-and-song-have-split-two-nearly-identical-birds-different&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;, by Elizabeth Pennisi, giving more background and noting, among other things, that the genes that define the two species have merely been reorganized, so that evolution can be rapid. Ms. Pennisi also explains, for those not in the know, why biologists are interested in &lt;i&gt;sympatric&lt;/i&gt; speciation such as is evidenced by the seedeaters.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">(Left) Sporophila hypoxantha, tawny-bellied seedeater. Photograph by Dario Sanches, Creative Commons copyright CC-BY-SA-2.0. (Right) Sporophila iberaensis, Iberá seedeater. Photograph by Hector Bottai, Creative Commons copyright CC BY-SA 4.0. These pictures, which I gratefully borrowed from Wikipedia, are occasioned by an an article by Erich D. Jarvis of the Howard Hughes Medical Institute. Briefly, Dr. Jarvis describes work by Sheela Turbek and colleagues at the University of Colorado showing that the two species pictured above are separated by female choice. That is, they share the same geographical region, but are mostly reproductively isolated by sexual selection mediated by plumage and song. The two species differ in three genomic regions, two of which are related to plumage, and one of which is on a sex chromosome that is found in both males and females. Most likely we are seeing speciation in real time, and eventually the two species will be wholly reproductively isolated. As we go to press this morning, so to speak, Science has posted a second article, by Elizabeth Pennisi, giving more background and noting, among other things, that the genes that define the two species have merely been reorganized, so that evolution can be rapid. Ms. Pennisi also explains, for those not in the know, why biologists are interested in sympatric speciation such as is evidenced by the seedeaters.</summary></entry></feed>