<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-01-15T12:31:33-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Like father, like son: Jeffrey Dahmer's claims about evolution in light of Lionel Dahmer's creationism</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/01/like-father-like-son.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Like father, like son: Jeffrey Dahmer's claims about evolution in light of Lionel Dahmer's creationism" /><published>2024-01-10T09:42:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-01-10T09:42:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/01/like-father-like-son</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/01/like-father-like-son.html">&lt;div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Glenn Branch is deputy director of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/&quot;&gt;National Center for Science Education&lt;/a&gt;, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as &lt;/i&gt;Scientific American&lt;i&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;American Educator&lt;i&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;The American Biology Teacher&lt;i&gt;, and the &lt;/i&gt;Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics&lt;i&gt;, and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of &lt;/i&gt;Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools&lt;i&gt; (2006). He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;This essay originally appeared on &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/like-father-like-son-jeffrey-dahmers-claims-about-evolution-in-light-of-lionel-dahmers-creationism/&quot;&gt;Righting America&lt;/a&gt; on December 26, 2023, and is republished with permission.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Branch_Dahmer_Article.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jeffrey Dahmer and his victims&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Serial killer Jeffrey Dahmer and his victims. &lt;small&gt;Image via jagotutorial.com.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lionel Dahmer, the father of the notorious serial killer Jeffrey Dahmer – the &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biography.com/crime/jeffrey-dahmer&quot;&gt;Milwaukee Monster&lt;/a&gt;&quot; who killed and dismembered 17 men and boys (mostly African Americans) – died on December 5, 2023. Lionel was the author of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tatteredcover.com/book/9781635615630&quot;&gt;A Father's Story&lt;/a&gt;, a memoir of his son's youth first published in 1994. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2023/12/12/us/lionel-dahmer-dead.html&quot;&gt;obituary&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;i&gt;The New York Times&lt;/i&gt;, &quot;Mr. Dahmer described himself in his book as ‘almost totally analytical'—a chemist, comforted by the scientific predictability of his work, whose emotional life resembled a ‘broad, flat plain.'&quot; But in fact, Lionel underwent a conversion experience in 1989 that affected not only his conception of the relation between religion and science, but also how his son is remembered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6tSxuyM93Js&quot;&gt;Interviewed&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;i&gt;Dateline NBC&lt;/i&gt;'s Stone Phillips in 1994, Jeffrey characterized evolution as the idea that &quot;we all just came from the slime,&quot; described it as &quot;a complete lie … [with] no basis in science to uphold it,&quot; and contended that &quot;the whole theory cheapens life.&quot; Implicit in his rambling remarks is the following argument: evolution entails that there is no God to whom we are morally accountable; only if there is a God to whom we are morally accountable is there reason for us to behave morally; therefore, accepting evolution robs us of any reason to behave morally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the benefit of any reader inclined to take their scientific or philosophical pointers from a college drop-out like Jeffrey, it should be noted that the scientific consensus on evolution is overwhelming, with over 98 percent of American scientists accepting human evolution in a 2014 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/internet/2015/01/29/public-and-scientists-express-strikingly-different-views-about-science-related-issues/&quot;&gt;survey&lt;/a&gt;; that evolution, like science in general, is typically &lt;a href=&quot;https://nap.nationalacademies.org/read/5787/chapter/6#58&quot;&gt;regarded&lt;/a&gt; as intrinsically silent on the existence of God; and that there are a &lt;a href=&quot;https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/metaethics/&quot;&gt;plethora&lt;/a&gt; of philosophical accounts of morality in which God is not central. It's also not clear why slime is supposed to be a worse origin than the Biblical alternative, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Genesis%202&amp;amp;version=NIV&quot;&gt;the dust of the ground&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet creationists are disturbingly fond of invoking Jeffrey Dahmer. To take a few examples at random: the creationist ministries &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/search/?refinement=&amp;amp;language=en&amp;amp;q=dahmer&quot;&gt;Answers in Genesis&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://creation.com/search?q=dahmer&quot;&gt;Creation Ministries International&lt;/a&gt; discuss Jeffrey in virtually identical terms, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/trouble-paradise&quot;&gt;reflecting&lt;/a&gt; their common ancestry; a professor of philosophy at a fundamentalist university paraphrased the &lt;i&gt;Dateline NBC&lt;/i&gt; remarks while participating in a three-way &lt;a href=&quot;https://zondervanacademic.com/products/three-views-on-creation-and-evolution&quot;&gt;internecine creationist debate&lt;/a&gt;; and Jeffrey is credited by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt5661968/&quot;&gt;IMDB&lt;/a&gt; as appearing in &quot;Kent Hovind: An Atheist's Worst Nightmare,&quot; a 2006 self-promoting film from a flamboyant creationist and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnj.com/story/news/local/2015/07/10/hovind-free-jail-back-pensacola/29969745/&quot;&gt;convicted felon&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes these invocations reach a broader audience. In 2009, for example, as the Texas state board of education was conducting a revision of the state science standards, members of the radical Christian right were hoping for the retention of &quot;strengths and weaknesses&quot; language that was invoked as a pretext to undermine the teaching of evolution. The Texas Freedom Network &lt;a href=&quot;https://tfn.org/jeffrey-dahmer-believed-in-evolution/&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; at the time on a lobbying email with the unsubtle all-caps subject line &quot;JEFFREY DAHMER, SERIAL KILLER, BELIEVED IN EVOLUTION—WHY ‘WEAKNESSES' NEEDS TO STAY IN TEXAS SCIENCE STANDARDS.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But is Jeffrey's claim that he formerly believed that evolution licensed his ghastly crimes actually evidence of anything? Even if he was sincere and accurate, it would be unwarranted to generalize from his single case, as Lionel conceded in the appendix to the 2021 edition of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tatteredcover.com/book/9781635615630&quot;&gt;A Father's Story&lt;/a&gt;. And while he may have been sincere—Roy Ratliff, who ministered to him in prison, reported similar remarks from him in his own book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tatteredcover.com/book/9780976779025&quot;&gt;Dark Journey Deep Grace: Jeffrey Dahmer's Story of Faith&lt;/a&gt;—there is no reason to regard him as insightful about his own twisted psyche, and no evidence that he was interested in evolution before his imprisonment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, there is a plausible source for Jeffrey's claim independent of his own murderous career: creationism itself. In the appendix to the 2021 edition of &lt;i&gt;A Father's Story&lt;/i&gt;, Lionel revealed that from 1989 onward he was sending &quot;tapes and articles&quot; espousing creationism to his son, who (according to Lionel) ignored them until after his imprisonment. Roy Ratliff reported that while in prison Jeffrey continued to receive material from his father discussing &quot;the creation of the world and how evolution is untrue,&quot; which Jeffrey credited with bringing him to God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is inevitable that the creationist materials that Lionel plied Jeffrey with, before and after his imprisonment, contained a hefty dose of the claim that acceptance of evolution causes moral bankruptcy. Indeed, the idea that accepting evolution is connected to religious apostasy, moral turpitude, and social decay is among the so-called &lt;a href=&quot;https://shuddhashar.com/learning-from-the-american-evolution-wars/&quot;&gt;pillars of creationism&lt;/a&gt;, the main rhetorical themes used by creationists hoping to influence the public. Subsisting on such a doctrinaire diet, it is hardly surprising that Jeffrey was primed to repeat the claim during his &lt;i&gt;Dateline NBC&lt;/i&gt; interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why was Lionel sending creationist materials to Jeffrey? In the initial edition of &lt;i&gt;A Father's Story&lt;/i&gt;, Lionel was circumspect about his attitude toward evolution. He wrote that while in prison in 1992, his son used $130, anonymously donated, to purchase thirteen creationist books, neutrally adding, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;It amazed him that a scientific theory that had been received as an unarguable scientific fact during all the years of his education might rest on questionable assumptions. It seemed to delight him that so thoroughly accepted an idea could be questioned, that nothing stood on truly solid ground.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the appendix to the 2021 edition of his book, however, Lionel disclosed,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1989, I myself ‘returned' fully to God, being influenced by the urging of my son, Dave, and profoundly affected by a seminar presented by a scientist from Montgomery, Alabama, Dr. Bert Thompson.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thompson was indeed a scientist, earning a Ph.D. in microbiology from Texas A&amp;amp;M University in 1975, but he spent the bulk of his career &quot;spread[ing] young-earth creationism throughout the Churches of Christ,&quot; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tatteredcover.com/book/9780674023390&quot;&gt;as the historian Ronald L. Numbers wrote&lt;/a&gt;, including through a ministry called Apologetics Press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspired by Thompson, Lionel was briefly active in organized creationism himself, presenting a poster at the 1990 International Conference on Creationism and publishing a 1991 &lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalcommons.cedarville.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1458&amp;amp;context=icc_proceedings&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; in the conference's proceedings. The research purported to challenge the scientifically ascertained dates of dinosaur fossils from the Cretaceous: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our radiocarbon dates of dinosaur bones and the other information in this report should be alarming to the evolutionary community and should be given serious study considering our preliminary results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spoiler: the &quot;evolutionary community&quot; was &lt;a href=&quot;https://nabt.org/files/galleries/February2020ABT.pdf&quot;&gt;unmoved&lt;/a&gt; (PDF, pp. 72-79).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, in light of the proclivity of creationists to quote Jeffrey's &lt;i&gt;Dateline NBC&lt;/i&gt; interview to illustrate the claim that accepting evolution causes moral bankruptcy, the career of the second author of Lionel's paper—Dmitri A. Kouznetsov, then a superstar of Russian creationism—imploded in the mid-1990s owing to accusations of scholarly dishonesty. According to the historian Ronald L. Numbers, Kouznetsov then reinvented himself as a supposed expert on the Shroud of Turin, &quot;using fake samples from nonexistent museums,&quot; and subsequently served time for passing bad checks in Connecticut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is similarly ironic that Bert Thompson, whom Lionel credited with his return to God, was fired from Apologetics Press in 2005, amid accusations of sexual misconduct. &lt;a href=&quot;https://christianchronicle.org/longtime-director-of-apologetics-press-fired/&quot;&gt;According&lt;/a&gt; to a story in &lt;i&gt;The Christian Chronicle&lt;/i&gt;, which serves the Churches of Christ, a member of the church alleged that &quot;Thompson started sending him cards and letters when he was 13, then pressed him to go out to dinner after he turned 16, the legal age of consent in Alabama.&quot; After dinner, Thompson took the youth to his home and &quot;lured him to a bedroom, disrobed and touched him inappropriately.&quot; It was not the only such accusation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether or not Lionel was aware of or troubled by the alleged moral failings of his collaborator and his inspiration is unclear. In any case, he seems not to have been active in organized creationism after 1991, which is not surprising given the disruption of his life by his son's arrest, trial, conviction, imprisonment, and murder. But he continued to harbor doubts about the scientific bona fides of evolution, judging from the appendix to the 2021 edition of his memoir, and he still appears in propagandistic lists of scientists who accept creationism, including the list put out by &lt;a href=&quot;https://creation.com/scientists-alive-today-who-accept-the-biblical-account-of-creation&quot;&gt;Creation Ministries International&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Glenn Branch</name></author><summary type="html">Glenn Branch is deputy director of the National Center for Science Education, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher, and the Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics, and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools (2006). He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers. This essay originally appeared on Righting America on December 26, 2023, and is republished with permission. Serial killer Jeffrey Dahmer and his victims. Image via jagotutorial.com. Lionel Dahmer, the father of the notorious serial killer Jeffrey Dahmer – the &quot;Milwaukee Monster&quot; who killed and dismembered 17 men and boys (mostly African Americans) – died on December 5, 2023. Lionel was the author of A Father's Story, a memoir of his son's youth first published in 1994. According to the obituary in The New York Times, &quot;Mr. Dahmer described himself in his book as ‘almost totally analytical'—a chemist, comforted by the scientific predictability of his work, whose emotional life resembled a ‘broad, flat plain.'&quot; But in fact, Lionel underwent a conversion experience in 1989 that affected not only his conception of the relation between religion and science, but also how his son is remembered.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Structural phylogenetics and Kitzmiller vs. Dover</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/01/structural-phylogenetics-KvD.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Structural phylogenetics and Kitzmiller vs. Dover" /><published>2024-01-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-01-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/01/structural-phylogenetics-KvD</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/01/structural-phylogenetics-KvD.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/CPL_etal_2023_Fig6_PDB_trees.png&quot; alt=&quot;[Figure 1 of Puente-Lelievre, Matzke et al. 2023, Tertiary-interaction characters enable fast, model-based structural phylogenetics beyond the twilight zone, bioRxiv]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Figure 1 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.12.12.571181v1&quot;&gt;Puente-Lelievre et al. 2023, bioRxiv&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A slightly late Merry Kitzmas to all! The 2005 &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=Kitzmiller+v.+Dover%2C+panda%27s+thumb&quot;&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover Area School Board&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; case, where &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.talkorigins.org/faqs/edwards-v-aguillard.html&quot;&gt;“Intelligent Design” went on trial&lt;/a&gt; (Matzke 2006) is now 18 years old. Amazingly, 18 years is the same number of years as between the 1987 &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.talkorigins.org/faqs/edwards-v-aguillard.html&quot;&gt;Edwards v. Aguillard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Supreme Court decision and &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller&lt;/i&gt;. I would say that the prominence of antievolutionism has receded in the latter 18 years, compared to numerous other culture wars, real wars, and challenges to the fundamentals of science-informed liberal democracy that have dominated the news in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that sense, &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller&lt;/i&gt; has definitely had a positive impact. However, we should keep in mind that Alabama &lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;still&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt; has a warning label in its textbooks (see this story by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.al.com/educationlab/2023/11/alabama-to-update-science-standards-keep-evolution-disclaimer.html&quot;&gt;Trisha Crain, 2023, al.com&lt;/a&gt;), several “critical analysis” antievolution policies remain on the books (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/full/10.1126/science.aad4057&quot;&gt;Matzke 2015&lt;/a&gt;), for example the Louisiana Science Education Act of 2008 (&lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/how-mike-johnson-helped-open-door-creationism-louisiana-public-schools&quot;&gt;NCSE 2023&lt;/a&gt;), and keeps evolving (&lt;a href=&quot;http://phylo.wikidot.com/matzke-2015-science-paper-on-the-evolution-of-antievolution&quot;&gt;Matzke 2015&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/how-mike-johnson-helped-open-door-creationism-louisiana-public-schools&quot;&gt;Creation-museum-boosting young-earth creationist Mike Johnson&lt;/a&gt; is Speaker of the US House and third in line to the Presidency, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/aftermath-texass-disappointing-vote-science-textbooks&quot;&gt;Texas Board of Education is still blocking textbooks with coverage of evolution and climate change that they don’t like&lt;/a&gt;, etc.  As Rob Pennock always says, “stay vigilant!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Longtime PT readers may recall some interesting scientific publications that came out of the &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller&lt;/i&gt; case, mostly reviewing the relevant science. Examples include the evolutionary origin of the immune system (Bottaro, Inlay, and Matzke 2006, &lt;i&gt;Nature Immunology&lt;/i&gt;; see also posts at &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2006/04/pt-posters-in-n.html&quot;&gt;PT&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/annotated-bibliography-evolutionary-origin-vertebrate-immune-system&quot;&gt;NCSE&lt;/a&gt;), the evolutionary origin of complex adaptations (&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0701505104&quot;&gt;Scott and Matzke 2007&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;i&gt;PNAS&lt;/i&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2007/05/nas-sackler-col.html&quot;&gt;PT post&lt;/a&gt;), or tracking the “evolution” of antievolution bills (&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.aad4057&quot;&gt;Matzke 2016&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.aad4057&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2015/12/bonus-material.html&quot;&gt;PT post&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://phylo.wikidot.com/matzke-2015-science-paper-on-the-evolution-of-antievolution&quot;&gt;free online Supplemental Data&lt;/a&gt;). Another was on the evolution of the bacterial flagellum (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.doi.org/10.1038/nrmicro1493&quot;&gt;Pallen &amp;amp; Matzke, 2006, &lt;i&gt;Nature Reviews Microbiology&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2006/09/flagellum-evolu.html&quot;&gt;PT post&lt;/a&gt;), which I think crossed over into novel research on the origin of a complex adaptation, even though the article was mostly assembling previous findings into a coherent scenario. I have maintained an interest in the evolution of the flagellum, and I would like to present some new research that, in a roundabout way, derives from the flagellum work and from &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am part of a team on a Human Frontier Science Program research grant that is combining phylogenetic, modeling, and experimental approaches to further understanding the evolutionary origin of the bacterial flagellum.  The group is headed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://research.unsw.edu.au/people/associate-professor-matthew-baker&quot;&gt;Matt Baker at the University of New South Wales&lt;/a&gt; (UNSW) in Sydney, Australia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One challenge that has always been a barrier to using phylogenetics to understand the origins of the flagellum is the system’s great age.  It may well be that the flagellum was present in the last common ancestor of (known, extant) bacteria, which probably means the system is 2.5+ billion years old.  The other famous systems that the intelligent design (ID) movement latched onto were much younger: the eukaryotic cilium (or flagellum) is probably as old as eukaryotes, perhaps 1.5 billion years; the adaptive immune system and blood-clotting cascades arose within the vertebrates and so are less than 500 million years old.  While phylogenetics is useful for understanding the origin of all these systems, even the bacterial flagellum, it’s just harder for the flagellum, as even the best conserved homologous proteins can have amino acid (AA) sequence similarity that has decayed to 30% or less. Homology detection, sequence alignment, and accurate phylogenies all become substantially harder as AA sequence similarity decays below 30%, especially below 25% and 20% and below. Eventually similarity decays to random background similarity and homology searches, alignments, etc. return nothing convincing, or, worse, they return something that is a little bit plausible but is actually just a chance match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This zone below 30% AA sequence identity has long been known as the Twilight Zone of protein phylogenetics (this phrase goes back at least as far as Russell Doolittle in the 1980s, probably further).  The main solution when homology/alignment/phylogenetics gets difficult due to loss of signal in the characters is: find more characters, ideally characters that are more slowly evolving. We already do this in many areas: if DNA sequence similarity is saturated, we can move to AA sequence, or morphological characters, both of which tend to be more slowly evolving, and thus preserve evidence of shared ancestry (shared derived characters) for longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Protein structure phylogenetics in the Twilight Zone&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do have another source of data in the Twilight Zone, which &lt;i&gt;ought&lt;/i&gt; to be helpful: protein structure. It has long been known that protein structure is even more conserved than amino acid sequence. However, use of protein structure in phylogenetics has been limited by two things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(1) Protein structures are very hard to experimentally characterize. Techniques like protein crystallography only work on certain proteins, and require a great deal of time, effort, and expensive equipment. Therefore, protein structures have historically only been available for a small fraction of the gene/protein sequences available after the DNA sequencing revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(2) Converting a protein structure into a series of discrete characters that can be analyzed by phylogenetics software is a nontrivial problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a long time, my best idea to solve problem #2 was to kidnap a few crystallographers and other protein structure experts and lock them in a basement until they came up with a manual character coding scheme for protein structures, and then used it to produce a character matrix.  Much like paleontologists and morphologists manually describe the anatomy of their specimens and code this into a morphological character matrix for computational analysis, we could do the same thing with protein structure – at least if we can run faster than crystallographers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, two recent developments have radically changed what seems possible.  First, &lt;a href=&quot;https://alphafold.ebi.ac.uk/&quot;&gt;AlphaFold2&lt;/a&gt; and similar projects appear to have finally cracked the problem of predicting protein structure from AA sequence. While it’s not perfect, it appears to be pretty good. In 2024 (unlike 2020), we can input an AA sequence and get a pretty good structural prediction out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, bioinformaticians (namely Martin Steinegger and colleagues) have figured out a way to code some of the 3-dimensional structural features of a protein structure into a linear alphabet of characters. This was done in the program &lt;a href=&quot;https://search.foldseek.com/search&quot;&gt;Foldseek&lt;/a&gt;, used for homology searches deep into the Twilight Zone. The alphabet is called “3Di” (3-dimension).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the University of Auckland, my postdoc &lt;a href=&quot;https://profiles.auckland.ac.nz/caroline-puente-lelievre&quot;&gt;Caroline Puente-Lelievre&lt;/a&gt;, and students and colleagues, were discussing and working with Foldseek, and it very gradually dawned on us that if the Foldseek 3Di alphabet was useful for homology search, it might be useful for phylogenetic inference as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We first explored this possibility on flagellum proteins, but then we realized that we had stumbled on something that might be the basis for improved phylogenetic inference for almost any protein clade that had diverged into the Twilight Zone.  So we wrote a paper:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Puente-Lelievre, Caroline; Malik, Ashar J.; Douglas, Jordan; Ascher, David; Baker, Matthew; Allison, Jane; Poole, Anthony; Lundin, Daniel; Fullmer, Matthew; Bouckert, Remco; Kim, Hyunbin; Steinegger, Martin; Matzke, Nicholas J. (2023). Tertiary-interaction characters enable fast, model-based structural phylogenetics beyond the twilight zone. &lt;i&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/i&gt;, 571181. December 12, 2023. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.12.12.571181v1&quot;&gt;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.12.12.571181v1&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.12.12.571181&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.12.12.571181&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of this story has been told in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/NickJMatzke/status/1735089150494470339&quot;&gt;thread on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; (now “X”, ugh), also &lt;a href=&quot;https://bsky.app/profile/nickjmatzke.bsky.social/post/3kghoyoeqta23&quot;&gt;posted to Bluesky&lt;/a&gt;, but honestly, microblogging platforms are kind of lame now, they mostly require logins to read much. So I am re-posting the thread and graphics below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Twitter thread on Puente-Lelievre et al. (2023), “Tertiary-interaction characters enable fast, model-based structural phylogenetics beyond the twilight zone.” &lt;i&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tweetorial explainer on Puente-Lelievre et al (2023). We are very excited about this paper &amp;amp; its implications for phylogenetics. Here’s why! (Work stems from @HFSP grant “How life got moving: reconstructing and re-evolving the bacterial flagellar motor” &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SBSatEd/status/1380517373107666945&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/SBSatEd/status/1380517373107666945&lt;/a&gt; )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Protein structure is more conserved than amino acid (AA) sequence. There are many cases where AA identity has decayed towards undetectability, yet the 3D protein structures are superimposable (Illergård et al. 2009) &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/prot.22458&quot;&gt;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/prot.22458&lt;/a&gt; /2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Illergard_etal_2009_structure_conserved_sequence.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Structural conservation is often exploited in deep homology search and alignment, e.g. in the program Foldseek by @thesteinegger lab. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41587-023-01773-0&quot;&gt;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41587-023-01773-0&lt;/a&gt; . Caroline Puente-Lelievre &amp;amp; I were using Foldseek on deeply-diverged proteins of the bacterial flagellum. /3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Foldseek_paper.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got to thinking - like many before us - about whether we could use protein structure in phylogenetics. Eg Ashar Malik @proteinmechanic (2020) used structural distances &amp;amp; Molecular Dynamics sims to do bootstrapping for uncertainty. Took ~3 weeks. https://academic.oup.com/mbe/article/37/9/2711/5821432 /4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Malik_etal_2020.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, distance-based methods are hard to integrate into modern statistical phylogenetics, which is based on probabilistic models which enable a huge range of tools: Maximum Likelihood &amp;amp; Bayesian inference, statistical model comparison, formal measures of uncertainty, &amp;amp; speed. /5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We played with Foldseek for like a year for homology search, but slowly it dawned on us that its method - converting 3D structures into a 1D sequence of “3Di” states - might be useful not just for rapid structural homology search, but for phylogenetic inference. /6&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we thought, “Surely someone has thought of this already and therefore it’s either a dumb idea, or it’s coming out next week.” But @AucklandUni has a bunch of structural-phylogenetics-curious, &amp;amp; Caroline, &amp;amp; Jordan Douglas, organized ASPM2023 meeting &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SimonJGreenhill/status/1691570184044339573&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/SimonJGreenhill/status/1691570184044339573&lt;/a&gt; /7&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Structural_phylo_meeting.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All* the cool kids of structural phylogenetics were there: https://twitter.com/phatmattbaker/status/1735052775418183873 (*=not really all, obviously. But, a bunch of people with that interest) /8&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Structural_phylo_attendees.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At ASPM2023 we realized it was up to us to explore the idea of 3Dis-in-model-based phylogenetics. Moi @steg0s4urus &amp;amp; @thesteinegger lab had just published Foldtree, using 3Di structural alignments to improve AA-distance based phylogenies. &lt;a href=&quot;https://x.com/thesteinegger/status/1707057683600482813?s=20&quot;&gt;https://x.com/thesteinegger/status/1707057683600482813?s=20&lt;/a&gt; /9&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;March through the figures of Puente-Lelievre et al. 2023. Here’s a summary of how Foldseek turns a 3D structure file into a sequence of 3Di characters. This takes &amp;lt;1s and gives a 3Di state for each AA in a structure. The Foldseek command is “structureto3didescriptor.” /10&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/CPL_etal_2023_Fig1_foldseek_3di.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a comparison of AA and 3Di alignments for 53 PDB structures from the Ferritin-like Superfamily, used for “M20”: Malik et al.’s (2020) neighbor-joining distances tree. Coloring is percent identity. Holy moly those 3Di states are CONSERVED! /11&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/CPL_etal_2023_Fig2_alignment.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a zoom-in on part of the alignment. 3Di states seem to have different information than the AAs. If we treat these as phylogenetic characters, would they help resolve things deep in the tree, the “twilight zone” where sequence identity is 30%, 20% or lower? /12&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/CPL_etal_2023_Fig3_alignment.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foldseek has an 3DI cost matrix for alignment calculations. We turned this into a 3DI rate matrix, and tossed it and the AA+3Di characters into the standard Maximum Likelihood phylogenetics program IQtree. Do 3Di characters seem to work like other characters? Yep! /13&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/CPL_etal_2023_Table2_model_selection.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We actually ran the data 60 ways in IQtree. The short version: when you use AA+3Di characters, &amp;amp; do all the things you’re supposed to do (structural alignment, model-fitting, partitioning, etc.), you get very close matches to the M20 tree. E.g. with PDB solved structures: /14&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/CPL_etal_2023_Fig6_PDB_trees.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, if anything the PDB-derived IQtree analysis is better than M20’s tree: it makes 2 likely groups missed in M20. And: LOOK AT THE RUNTIME. M20’s MD-based bootstrapping took ~3 weeks with parallelization. IQtree took 13.7 min. for 1000 UF bootstraps. On a desktop. /15&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you thought that was cool, look at the next one. This time, we used AlphaFold-predicted structures instead of solved PDB structures. Pretty equivalent tree. But: AlphaFolds are available for…almost everything! &lt;i&gt;Anyone&lt;/i&gt; could do this on &lt;i&gt;any&lt;/i&gt; dataset! /16 https://alphafold.ebi.ac.uk/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/CPL_etal_2023_Fig7_PDB_trees.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what we got when we just ran a standard analysis - amino-acids only, and aligned just using amino acids (although with a substitution matrix, MIQS in FAMSA, specialized for divergent proteins). Messy: long-branch attraction artifacts, clades exploding, etc. /17&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/CPL_etal_2023_Fig8_AA_trees.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; this was just a proof-of-concept study, there needs to be study of the many caveats we mention in the manuscript (including philosophical!) etc. But: the future looks bright for structural phylogenetics, and anyone can try it on tough, deep phylogenetics problems! /18&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Addendum:&lt;/b&gt; Matt Baker at @UNSW aka @phatmattbaker, ringleader of the @HFSP flagellum project, 3rd ranked fencer in Australia in his group, and general amazing guy, has a thread about his path to ASPM2023 and this paper: https://twitter.com/phatmattbaker/status/1735054924512387528 https://twitter.com/phatmattbaker/status/1735052739464585430 /19&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Addendum #2:&lt;/b&gt; We don’t have a tutorial up yet, but all of the code, commands, example data files etc. are in the Supporting Information zipfile, also available on @github at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/nmatzke/3diphy&quot;&gt;https://github.com/nmatzke/3diphy&lt;/a&gt; /20&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;References&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bottaro, A., Inlay, M., and Matzke, N. (2006). “Immunology in the spotlight at the Dover “Intelligent Design’ trial.” &lt;i&gt;Nature Immunology&lt;/i&gt;. 7(5), 433-435. May 2006. &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ni0506-433&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ni0506-433&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Branch, Glenn (2023). “The aftermath of Texas’s disappointing vote on science textbooks.” &lt;i&gt;National Center for Science Education, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncse.ngo&quot;&gt;ncse.ngo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. November 27, 2023. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/aftermath-texass-disappointing-vote-science-textbooks&quot;&gt;https://ncse.ngo/aftermath-texass-disappointing-vote-science-textbooks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Branch, Glenn (2023). “How Mike Johnson Helped Open the Door to Creationism in Louisiana Public Schools.” &lt;i&gt;National Center for Science Education, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncse.ngo&quot;&gt;ncse.ngo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. December 11, 2023. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/how-mike-johnson-helped-open-door-creationism-louisiana-public-schools&quot;&gt;https://ncse.ngo/how-mike-johnson-helped-open-door-creationism-louisiana-public-schools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cain, Trisha Powell (2023). Alabama to update science standards, keep evolution disclaimer. al.com, November 15, 2023. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.al.com/educationlab/2023/11/alabama-to-update-science-standards-keep-evolution-disclaimer.html&quot;&gt;https://www.al.com/educationlab/2023/11/alabama-to-update-science-standards-keep-evolution-disclaimer.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foster, James C. (2023). “&lt;a href=&quot;https://firstamendment.mtsu.edu/article/scopes-monkey-trial/&quot;&gt;Scopes Monkey Trial&lt;/a&gt;.” &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://firstamendment.mtsu.edu/&quot;&gt;Free Speech Center&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mtsu.edu/&quot;&gt;Middle Tennessee State University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. Last updated on September 19, 2023. &lt;a href=&quot;https://firstamendment.mtsu.edu/article/scopes-monkey-trial/&quot;&gt;https://firstamendment.mtsu.edu/article/scopes-monkey-trial/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Illergård, Kristoffer; Ardell, David H.; Elofsson, Arne (2009). “Structure is three to ten times more conserved than sequence – A study of structural response in protein cores.” Proteins, 77(3), 499-508. &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/prot.22458&quot;&gt;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/prot.22458&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matzke, N. (2006). “Design on Trial: How NCSE Helped Win the &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller&lt;/i&gt; Case.” &lt;i&gt;Reports of the National Center for Science Education&lt;/i&gt;. 26(1-2), 37-44. Jan-Apr. 2006. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/design-trial&quot;&gt;https://ncse.ngo/design-trial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matzke, Nicholas (2015). “The Evolution of Antievolution Policies After &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover&lt;/i&gt;.” &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;, 351(6268), 10-12. Published online at ScienceExpress on December 17, 2015; print January 1, 2016. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/full/10.1126/science.aad4057&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.aad4057&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.aad4057&lt;/a&gt;
https://www.science.org/doi/full/10.1126/science.aad4057&lt;/a&gt; (Bonus material, media links, FAQ, etc. at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://phylo.wikidot.com/matzke-2015-science-paper-on-the-evolution-of-antievolution&quot;&gt;http://phylo.wikidot.com/matzke-2015-science-paper-on-the-evolution-of-antievolution&lt;/a&gt; )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pallen, M., and Matzke, N. (2006). “From &lt;i&gt;The Origin of Species&lt;/i&gt; to the Origin of Bacterial Flagella.” &lt;i&gt;Nature Reviews Microbiology&lt;/i&gt;. 4(10), 784-790. October 2006. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.doi.org/10.1038/nrmicro1493&quot;&gt;http://www.doi.org/10.1038/nrmicro1493&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Puente-Lelievre, Caroline; Malik, Ashar J.; Douglas, Jordan; Ascher, David; Baker, Matthew; Allison, Jane; Poole, Anthony; Lundin, Daniel; Fullmer, Matthew; Bouckert, Remco; Kim, Hyunbin; Steinegger, Martin; Matzke, Nicholas J. (2023). Tertiary-interaction characters enable fast, model-based structural phylogenetics beyond the twilight zone. &lt;i&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/i&gt;, 571181. December 12, 2023. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.12.12.571181v1&quot;&gt;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.12.12.571181v1&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.12.12.571181&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.12.12.571181&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scott, E. C., and Matzke, N. (2007). “Biological design in science classrooms.” &lt;i&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/i&gt;. 104(suppl. 1), 8669-8676. May 15, 2007. Part of the v. 104 supplement, “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pnas.org/content/vol104/suppl_1/&quot;&gt;In the Light of Evolution I: Adaptation and Complex Design&lt;/a&gt;.” Published online before print May 9, 2007. Also submitted for a Special Volume on the Arthur M. Sackler NAS Colloquium “In the Light of Evolution: Adaptation and Complex Design.” Arnold and Mabel Beckman Center, Irvine, CA, November 30 - December 2, 2006. Organized by John C. Avise and Francisco J. Ayala. &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0701505104&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0701505104&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Matzke</name></author><summary type="html">Figure 1 of Puente-Lelievre et al. 2023, bioRxiv. A slightly late Merry Kitzmas to all! The 2005 Kitzmiller v. Dover Area School Board case, where “Intelligent Design” went on trial (Matzke 2006) is now 18 years old. Amazingly, 18 years is the same number of years as between the 1987 Edwards v. Aguillard Supreme Court decision and Kitzmiller. I would say that the prominence of antievolutionism has receded in the latter 18 years, compared to numerous other culture wars, real wars, and challenges to the fundamentals of science-informed liberal democracy that have dominated the news in recent years. In that sense, Kitzmiller has definitely had a positive impact. However, we should keep in mind that Alabama still has a warning label in its textbooks (see this story by Trisha Crain, 2023, al.com), several “critical analysis” antievolution policies remain on the books (Matzke 2015), for example the Louisiana Science Education Act of 2008 (NCSE 2023), and keeps evolving (Matzke 2015), Creation-museum-boosting young-earth creationist Mike Johnson is Speaker of the US House and third in line to the Presidency, the Texas Board of Education is still blocking textbooks with coverage of evolution and climate change that they don’t like, etc. As Rob Pennock always says, “stay vigilant!” Longtime PT readers may recall some interesting scientific publications that came out of the Kitzmiller case, mostly reviewing the relevant science. Examples include the evolutionary origin of the immune system (Bottaro, Inlay, and Matzke 2006, Nature Immunology; see also posts at PT and NCSE), the evolutionary origin of complex adaptations (Scott and Matzke 2007, PNAS; PT post), or tracking the “evolution” of antievolution bills (Matzke 2016, Science; PT post; free online Supplemental Data). Another was on the evolution of the bacterial flagellum (Pallen &amp;amp; Matzke, 2006, Nature Reviews Microbiology; PT post), which I think crossed over into novel research on the origin of a complex adaptation, even though the article was mostly assembling previous findings into a coherent scenario. I have maintained an interest in the evolution of the flagellum, and I would like to present some new research that, in a roundabout way, derives from the flagellum work and from Kitzmiller.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Great Sand Dunes National Park</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/01/great-sand-dunes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Great Sand Dunes National Park" /><published>2024-01-08T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-01-08T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/01/great-sand-dunes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/01/great-sand-dunes.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;C. Joseph Long&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Long_great_sand_dunes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Great Sand Dunes&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/grsa/learn/nature/index.htm&quot;&gt;Great Sand Dunes National Park and Preserve&lt;/a&gt;. Mr. Long writes: &quot;Dunes up to 200&amp;nbsp;m are formed where wind sweeping across the cold semi-desert of southern Colorado’s San Luis Valley is funneled toward Mosca Pass in the Sangre de Cristo range on the eastern edge of the southern Rocky Mountains.  The valley itself is a deep &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Graben&quot;&gt;graben&lt;/a&gt; toward the upper end of the Rio Grande Rift with no surface drainage in its northern reaches.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by C. Joseph Long. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Great Sand Dunes National Park and Preserve. Mr. Long writes: &quot;Dunes up to 200&amp;nbsp;m are formed where wind sweeping across the cold semi-desert of southern Colorado’s San Luis Valley is funneled toward Mosca Pass in the Sangre de Cristo range on the eastern edge of the southern Rocky Mountains. The valley itself is a deep graben toward the upper end of the Rio Grande Rift with no surface drainage in its northern reaches.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Meditation on “The Snowflake: Winter's Frozen Artistry”</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/12/meditation-on-snowflake.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meditation on “The Snowflake: Winter's Frozen Artistry”" /><published>2023-12-27T13:56:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-12-27T13:56:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/12/meditation-on-snowflake</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/12/meditation-on-snowflake.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Libbrecht_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost literally, as I was finishing the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Snowflake-Kenneth-Libbrecht-ebook/dp/B01G8U33WC &quot;&gt;The Snowflake: Winter’s Frozen Artistry&lt;/a&gt;, by Kenneth Libbrecht and Rachel Wing, I heard &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2023/12/25/1217356234/just-how-big-can-a-snowflake-get-it-depends-on-what-you-mean-by-snowflake&quot;&gt;this report&lt;/a&gt; on NPR: Professor Libbrecht had discovered and photographed what, as far as anyone knows, is the largest single-crystal snowflake ever discovered – approximately 10 mm across. The snowflake was evidently larger than the field of view of Prof Libbrecht’s microscope and had to be photographed in 4 quadrants, which were later digitally stitched together. The snowflake has been accepted in the Guinness Book of World Records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the book by Libbrecht and Wing, it is short, wastes hardly a word, and was a pleasure to read. It is not a technical book, nor is it a children’s book, yet I kept thinking that much of the early chapters would be an excellent way to stimulate an interest in science in, say, medium-sized children. As of this writing, you may get the Kindle edition of the book for approximately $3, US. I read it on a Kindle Paperwhite, which gives a small, black-and-white image, so I had to look at some of the images on a computer monitor in order to get full color and resolution. The formatting on the Kindle was not wonderful, but it was manageable. More below the fold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always wondered why the arms of a snowflake, which Libbrecht and Wing call a &lt;i&gt;stellar dendrite&lt;/i&gt;, are identical or nearly so. Of course, they are not always identical but why are they &lt;i&gt;ever&lt;/i&gt; identical? Libbrecht and Wing explain succinctly that under some conditions ice forms hexagonal structures (or at least corners of hexagonal structures) and under other conditions, branching arms. As conditions change and the snowflake encounters different temperature and humidity regimes, it alternately grows smooth, flat surfaces, or facets, and branches. By stunting their growth, the facets stabilize the otherwise unstable branches. At least sometimes, the conditions are constant across the snowflake, and over a period of minutes it evolves 6 identical arms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scientifically inclined may find the chapter, “A field guide to falling snow,” especially interesting. In that chapter, we learn that, besides snowflakes, water sometimes crystallizes into hexagonal plates, needles, or hexagonal cylinders. These contribute to many atmospheric effects such as sun dogs and halos. In addition, however, they sometimes form &lt;i&gt;capped columns&lt;/i&gt;, which look like microscopic dumbbells, and even 12-branched stars. The chapter concludes with frost, rime snow, and even a picture of a dendrite coated with rime snow. Children of all ages will learn how to fossilize a snowflake in superglue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was particularly intrigued by Nakaya’s &lt;i&gt;snow crystal morphology diagram&lt;/i&gt;. Not exactly a graph, this diagram shows pictures of different kinds of ice crystal on a Cartesian plot with humidity on the vertical axis and temperature on the horizontal axis. Not surprisingly, we get plates and cylinders when the humidity is low and dendrites when the humidity is high. I found it curious that dendrites form just below freezing and well below freezing, but not between. Later in the book, Libbrecht and Wing inform us that this behavior remains a mystery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I have one quibble, it concerns the construction of the microscope. They use what appears to be a conventional microscope turret and a digital camera, but it is unclear whether the lens has been removed from the digital camera. With the right microscope objectives, you could do it either way. Some of the pictures, incidentally, are taken using something called &lt;i&gt;Rheinberg illumination&lt;/i&gt;, which is evidently oblique illumination using different colors simultaneously. I am supposed to know something about microscopy, but I will have to look that up right after I finish this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first heard of Prof. Libbrecht in 2016, when he was featured in an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/01/23/science/who-ever-said-no-two-snowflakes-were-alike.html&quot;&gt;article in the New York Times&lt;/a&gt;. Under carefully controlled conditions, he had grown pairs of identical snowflakes, thus in a sense demonstrating the falsity of the claim that no two snowflakes are identical. He very generously let us &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2017/01/Identical-snowflakes.html&quot;&gt;post a pair of twins&lt;/a&gt; on PT in 2017. It is interesting how the snowflakes freeze water vapor from the air and clear themselves a region that is free of the frozen droplets that cover the rest of the microscope slide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/DSC04970_Snowflake_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Snowflake&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;My best snowflake! A single-crystal snowflake showing what appears to be a somewhat similar doppelgänger in the background.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, I cannot resist, and I hope you will indulge me: Last year, at the very end of the season, I took a fairly fuzzy black cloth out into a cold, light snow flurry, let it chill for a while, and allowed some snowflakes to fall on it. The fuzz was to prevent the flake from landing on the cloth itself and potentially melting. I photographed some snowflakes with a handheld Sony ILCE 6000 with a 30-mm macro lens and the built-in flash (possibly with a diffuser, but I do not remember). Using some digital image processing software, I could easily crop the picture and end up with a picture of a snowflake around 600 pixels square. Not exactly the same quality as Libbrecht and Wing’s, but it could have been worse. Next time I will know enough to stretch the cloth tightly (because of the severely limited depth of field) and will probably use a short extension tube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/DSC04967_Hex_Crystal_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hexagonal plate&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Hexagonal plate, which might have been a snowflake, if only ….
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure enough, I found a handful of hexagonal plates, which I now know could have been the seed for a single-crystal snowflake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/DSC04858_Frost_Crop_1000.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frost on a window&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Frost on a window.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also fooled with some frost on a window, which (I know now) grows very differently from a snowflake and probably follows the contours of what I will call shmear on the glass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more, I recommend that you get the book and in your own small way help support &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.its.caltech.edu/~atomic/&quot;&gt;Prof. Libbrecht&lt;/a&gt;’s research at Caltech. As he says, “Really, it’s the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.snowcrystals.com/books/books.html&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;perfect gift&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Almost literally, as I was finishing the book The Snowflake: Winter’s Frozen Artistry, by Kenneth Libbrecht and Rachel Wing, I heard this report on NPR: Professor Libbrecht had discovered and photographed what, as far as anyone knows, is the largest single-crystal snowflake ever discovered – approximately 10 mm across. The snowflake was evidently larger than the field of view of Prof Libbrecht’s microscope and had to be photographed in 4 quadrants, which were later digitally stitched together. The snowflake has been accepted in the Guinness Book of World Records. As for the book by Libbrecht and Wing, it is short, wastes hardly a word, and was a pleasure to read. It is not a technical book, nor is it a children’s book, yet I kept thinking that much of the early chapters would be an excellent way to stimulate an interest in science in, say, medium-sized children. As of this writing, you may get the Kindle edition of the book for approximately $3, US. I read it on a Kindle Paperwhite, which gives a small, black-and-white image, so I had to look at some of the images on a computer monitor in order to get full color and resolution. The formatting on the Kindle was not wonderful, but it was manageable. More below the fold.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dendrocygna autumnalis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/12/dendrocygna-autumnalis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dendrocygna autumnalis" /><published>2023-12-25T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-12-25T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/12/dendrocygna-autumnalis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/12/dendrocygna-autumnalis.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/P1010992_Whistling_Duck_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Black-bellied whistling duck&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Black-bellied_Whistling-Duck/overview&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Dendrocygna autumnalis&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/a&gt; – black-bellied whistling duck, Boulder, Colorado, December, 2023. According to the range map in the link, these ducks are found almost entirely south of the US. In Central America, they are found primarily along the coasts. The link says that they are expanding northward into several southern states. Colorado seems a long way off (not to mention that it is cold and not exactly coastal). The lighting was poor (and flat), but I managed to get some pictures at ISO 1250, a number which would have been almost unheard of not so very long ago. The bird sat placidly posing for photographs, but was gone the next day. Thanks to Paul Strode for the identification.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Dendrocygna autumnalis – black-bellied whistling duck, Boulder, Colorado, December, 2023. According to the range map in the link, these ducks are found almost entirely south of the US. In Central America, they are found primarily along the coasts. The link says that they are expanding northward into several southern states. Colorado seems a long way off (not to mention that it is cold and not exactly coastal). The lighting was poor (and flat), but I managed to get some pictures at ISO 1250, a number which would have been almost unheard of not so very long ago. The bird sat placidly posing for photographs, but was gone the next day. Thanks to Paul Strode for the identification. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NCSE supports article linking Speaker of House to creationism</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/12/ncse-supports-article.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NCSE supports article linking Speaker of House to creationism" /><published>2023-12-15T15:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-12-15T15:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/12/ncse-supports-article</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/12/ncse-supports-article.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Mike_Johnson_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mike Johnson&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;United States Representative Mike Johnson, official photo.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;A week or so ago, in an article &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/12/creationism-again.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, we linked to an article in HuffPost, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huffpost.com/entry/mike-johnson-creationism-schools_n_657380ffe4b09724b4342739&quot;&gt;How Mike Johnson Helped Open the Door to Creationism in Louisiana Public Schools&lt;/a&gt;, by Paul Blumenthal. That article detailed not only how the Speaker of the House of Representatives represented the Ark Park in Kentucky, but also how he spurred the passage of laws allowing creationism into public school classrooms in Louisiana. Much of the content of that article depended on several people – Barbara Forrest, Glenn Branch, and Zach Kopplin – closely related to the National Center for Science Education, as detailed recently in the NCSE Monitor, an online magazine that I get every week in my e-mail. I feel a little bit like bragging vicariously, so here is the article from the Monitor, reprinted with permission. The original title of the article was the same as that of the HuffPost article. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The support provided to creationism by Mike Johnson (R-Louisiana), the new Speaker of the House, was the topic of a detailed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huffpost.com/entry/mike-johnson-creationism-schools_n_657380ffe4b09724b4342739&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; in HuffPost (December 9, 2023) — and people associated with NCSE were a major source of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Referring to the so-called Louisiana Science Education Act of 2008, the report summarized, “When the law faced challenges to its implementation and schools faced lawsuits for teaching creationism, Johnson, who worked as a senior litigator for the Alliance Defending Freedom and sat on the Louisiana Family Forum’s attorneys resources council, was the one to swoop in with legal memos, letters threatening lawsuits, and prayer rallies on behalf of the religious-right groups opposed to secular education.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara Forrest, a former member of NCSE’s board of directors, told HuffPost, “Johnson was always their legal go-to guy,” and Glenn Branch, NCSE’s Deputy Director, agreed, explaining that Johnson was “very involved” in the efforts of the law’s supporters to exclude a requirement that “[m]aterials that teach creationism or intelligent design or that advance the religious belief that a supernatural being created humankind shall be prohibited for use in science classes” from the regulations implementing the LSEA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report observed, “Since the law only allowed the optional introduction of supplementary materials challenging evolution with creationist theories, it has been hard to track the law’s usage in the decade-plus since its enactment.” NCSE’s Branch told HuffPost, “The same reason that makes it difficult to challenge the constitutionality of the Louisiana Science Education Act is the same reason that no one knows how effective [the law] is”: there seems to be no reliable data on the use of such materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the wake of the LSEA’s enactment, Zack Kopplin, a recipient of NCSE’s Friend of Darwin award, identified a number of Louisiana public schools in which creationism was taught. Johnson was involved in efforts to defend such schools, including in his own Bossier Parish, as Kopplin reported in Slate in 2015. Ultimately the Bossier Parish School Board was sued in 2018 over a pattern of actions violating the First Amendment’s Establishment Clause; the case was settled in 2019 with the board agreeing that there were violations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Johnson “also signed on as the lawyer for another creationist cause up north in Kentucky: the Creation Museum, which opened in 2016,” helping the proprietor of the museum, the young-earth creationist ministry Answers in Genesis, to sue the state over its withdrawal of tourism subsidies. His interactions with Answers in Genesis continued; Johnson is on record as praising the Ark Encounter and Creation Museum as “one way to bring people to this recognition of the truth, that what we read in the Bible are actual historical events.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kopplin was accorded the last word in the report. Reflecting on his personal experience with Johnson, Kopplin reported that he found him to be polite and, unlike his allies, not “incredibly personally nasty.” He added, “But he’s from the same world, with the same goals.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">United States Representative Mike Johnson, official photo. A week or so ago, in an article here, we linked to an article in HuffPost, How Mike Johnson Helped Open the Door to Creationism in Louisiana Public Schools, by Paul Blumenthal. That article detailed not only how the Speaker of the House of Representatives represented the Ark Park in Kentucky, but also how he spurred the passage of laws allowing creationism into public school classrooms in Louisiana. Much of the content of that article depended on several people – Barbara Forrest, Glenn Branch, and Zach Kopplin – closely related to the National Center for Science Education, as detailed recently in the NCSE Monitor, an online magazine that I get every week in my e-mail. I feel a little bit like bragging vicariously, so here is the article from the Monitor, reprinted with permission. The original title of the article was the same as that of the HuffPost article. The support provided to creationism by Mike Johnson (R-Louisiana), the new Speaker of the House, was the topic of a detailed report in HuffPost (December 9, 2023) — and people associated with NCSE were a major source of information. Referring to the so-called Louisiana Science Education Act of 2008, the report summarized, “When the law faced challenges to its implementation and schools faced lawsuits for teaching creationism, Johnson, who worked as a senior litigator for the Alliance Defending Freedom and sat on the Louisiana Family Forum’s attorneys resources council, was the one to swoop in with legal memos, letters threatening lawsuits, and prayer rallies on behalf of the religious-right groups opposed to secular education.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Melissodes sp.</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/12/melissodes-sp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Melissodes sp." /><published>2023-12-11T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-12-11T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/12/melissodes-sp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/12/melissodes-sp.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Jonathan Lubin&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Lubin_Melissodes_sp.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Long-horned bee&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://echinaceaproject.org/field-guides/bee/apidae/melissodes-2/&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Melissodes&lt;/i&gt; sp.&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; long-horned bee, Pasadena, California. &lt;strike&gt;Oh dear, this is embarrassing (not that anything truly embarrasses us any more): It looks like we must have had a computer crash in 2020, when this picture was submitted, and we do not know who the photographer was, except that their surname is Lubin. If that photographer is still lurking, perhaps they can supply their full name and any comment they might want to add.&lt;/strike&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Jonathan Lubin. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Melissodes sp. &amp;ndash; long-horned bee, Pasadena, California. Oh dear, this is embarrassing (not that anything truly embarrasses us any more): It looks like we must have had a computer crash in 2020, when this picture was submitted, and we do not know who the photographer was, except that their surname is Lubin. If that photographer is still lurking, perhaps they can supply their full name and any comment they might want to add.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creationism, again</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/12/creationism-again.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creationism, again" /><published>2023-12-09T14:24:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-12-09T14:24:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/12/creationism-again</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/12/creationism-again.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Dore_Light_Etching_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Etching&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Gustave Doré, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Creation_of_Light.png&quot;&gt;The Creation of Light&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;small&gt;Public domain.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since last evening, I have received three disquieting e-mails that bear on creationism, in one form or another. I will give the links in the order in which I received them. Because I have not asked permission, I will not identify any of the senders; they are of course at liberty to identify themselves in the comments section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here below the figurative fold are the three links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last night, a penpal of mine sent me an e-mail detailing how the Kentucky government is promoting creationist theme parks. Specifically, the Louisville Courier-Journal announced a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.courier-journal.com/story/entertainment/2023/12/08/ark-encounter-kentucky-faith-trail/71849424007/&quot;&gt;Religious tour of Kentucky: Faith Trail offers a new way to see the Bluegrass State&lt;/a&gt;, by Jolene Almendarez and Ana Rocío Álvarez Bríñez, subtitled,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; Some of the sites are the Ark Encounter, the Creation Museum and the Cathedral Basilica of the Assumption. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Faith Trail will be funded by a $305,000 grant from the Commonwealth of Kentucky to the Northern Kentucky Convention and Visitors Bureau. There will be 11 stops on the Faith Trail, only two of them explicitly creationist, as far as I can tell, but yes, Answers in Genesis will receive free publicity from the Commonwealth of Kentucky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, this morning another occasional penpal sent an article called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.city-journal.org/article/the-american-museum-of-natural-historys-politically-correct-creationism&quot;&gt;Politically correct creationism&lt;/a&gt;, by Elizabeth Weiss. The subtitle to the article tells you almost all you want to know or maybe do not want to know:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;New York's [American] Museum of Natural History presents indigenous origin myths and religious stories as scientific fact.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article, published in the conservative magazine &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/City_Journal&quot;&gt;City Journal&lt;/a&gt;, claims that the Museum now calls shamans “doctors,” a shortened form of witchdoctor. It is one thing to be sensitive to the religious traditions of indigenous peoples, but the museum seems to blur the distinction between fact and fiction when it writes, “By wearing masks that contained the spirits, doctors tapped into their power,” or appears to present creation myths as if they were history. I think it would be interesting if any of our readers have seen this exhibit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, finally, yet another penpal sent me &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huffpost.com/entry/mike-johnson-creationism-schools_n_657380ffe4b09724b4342739&quot;&gt; How Mike Johnson helped open the door to creationism in Louisiana public schools&lt;/a&gt;, by Paul Blumenthal in the Huffington Post. Subtitles must be all the rage these days; this article is subtitled,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The House speaker is known for his work as a Christian-right operative. This is how he became the &quot;legal go-to guy&quot; to put creationism into public schools.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike Johnson is the Speaker of the House of Representatives of the Moment. Mr. Blumenthal notes that not only did Johnson represent the Ark Park, but also the represented religious-right forces that spurred the passage of laws allowing creationism into public-school classrooms in Louisiana. He also, according to my reading of the article, bullied the state Board of Elementary and Secondary Education into allowing teachers to bring supplemental materials that teach creationism into the state’s public schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder what tomorrow’s e-mail will bring.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Gustave Doré, The Creation of Light. Public domain. Since last evening, I have received three disquieting e-mails that bear on creationism, in one form or another. I will give the links in the order in which I received them. Because I have not asked permission, I will not identify any of the senders; they are of course at liberty to identify themselves in the comments section. Here below the figurative fold are the three links:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Do we have free will? Still no</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/12/do-we-have-free-will-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do we have free will? Still no" /><published>2023-12-07T11:11:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-12-07T11:11:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/12/do-we-have-free-will-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/12/do-we-have-free-will-1.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Sapolsky_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several weeks ago, in an article entitled &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/do-we-have-free-will.html&quot;&gt;Do we have free will? No&lt;/a&gt;, I threatened to read Robert Sapolsky’s splendid book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Determined-Science-Life-without-Free-ebook/dp/B0BSKQ5ZDM/&quot;&gt;Determined: A Science of Life without Free Will&lt;/a&gt;. Well, I read it, and we still do not have free will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said in my earlier article, I had myself argued that we lack free will in my book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://people.mines.edu/mmyoung/wp-content/uploads/sites/99/2019/01/Young_No_Sense_of_Obligation.pdf&quot;&gt;No Sense of Obligation: Science and Religion in an Impersonal Universe&lt;/a&gt;. My argument was kind of bare-bones, basically that we are governed by the laws of physics and chemistry, which are deterministic (except perhaps for the occasional quantum fluctuation), so our actions must also be deterministic. Though my wording was not the best, I also argued that criminals should therefore be rehabilitated or quarantined and not punished. Sapolsky fleshes all this out in great (if not excruciating) detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sapolsky thinks that it sounds “nuts” to claim that we have no free will. Not to me: it seems to me that the claim follows from first principles. But Sapolsky devotes several chapters to describing how neurons work, how they cause us to “pull the trigger,” and, more importantly, how they make us decide whether or not to pull the trigger. Early on he remarks,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; Show me a neuron (or brain) whose generation of a behavior is independent of the sum of its biological past, and for the purposes of this book, you have demonstrated free will. The point of the first half of this book is to establish that this cannot be shown.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Sapolsky says “free will,” he does not mean that your decision was not coerced; rather he means that, given free rein, &lt;i&gt;you could have made no other decision than the one you did&lt;/i&gt;. For Sapolsky, the neuron that told you to tighten your muscle and pull some hypothetical trigger was influenced by another neuron that was itself chosen by one part of the brain telling it, “Go!” and another part of the brain telling it, “Whoa, slow down!” Which of those parts of the brain won out depended upon your own history, which itself depended on your prenatal environment, your environment growing up, your culture, and who knows what else? Where in this chain of events, asks Sapolsky, did something intervene between one neuron and the next, and tell you whether to pull the trigger or not? There is no room for such an intervention, though some &lt;i&gt;compatiblists&lt;/i&gt; – those who agree that our brains are purely deterministic but that we have free will anyway – will argue otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In successive sections called “Seconds to minutes before [you pull the trigger],” “Minutes to days before,” “Weeks to years before,” and then “Back to adolescence,” “And childhood,” and so on, Sapolsky details how your history and even your culture’s history determine your actions and decisions. Ever steal something? Maybe not, if you were brought up wealthy. But what if you were brought up poor and had to steal a loaf of bread to survive? In the first case, assuming that you were tempted, the Whoa! part of your brain won out, whereas in the second case the Go! part of your brain won out. In each case, your response was purely biochemical, I am afraid, and the wealthy person who does not steal has nothing in particular to be proud of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Sapolsky, it is not &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turtles_all_the_way_down&quot;&gt;turtles all the way down&lt;/a&gt; but rather neurons all the way to the beginning, or at least, I suppose, to the evolution of the neuron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To go into a lot more detail would require a booklet, at least. But let me note, for example, that being exposed to a disgusting smell can change your attitudes toward what Sapolsky calls “purity violations.” How can that be? Evidently the processing of stimuli that we consider &lt;i&gt;morally&lt;/i&gt; disgusting has co-opted part of the older brain region for processing &lt;i&gt;physically&lt;/i&gt; disgusting things such as spoiled or rotting food, and there is crosstalk. Experimental subjects will not tell you, “Oh, that disgusting smell influenced my decision to punish that person”; rather, they will tell you that some “recent insight” influenced their decision. Now statistically changing people’s attitudes by exposing them to disgusting smells does not disprove free will, but it goes part way toward making the case, and of course Sapolsky goes into much greater depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sapolsky treats us to chapters on chaos, emergence, and quantum mechanics. As briefly as possible, he notes that chaos is actually &lt;i&gt;deterministic&lt;/i&gt; (except possibly for the occasional quantum fluctuation), but not &lt;i&gt;calculable&lt;/i&gt; because we cannot calculate with sufficient precision. He takes to task several thinkers who have tied free will to chaos because they frankly do not understand the difference between being deterministic and being calculable – the weather, for example, is deterministic, but we cannot calculate it beyond a few days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emergent properties are properties which arise in complex systems made up of simple elements, when those simple elements combine in such a way as to create new properties that are not displayed in the simple elements themselves. One water molecule is not wet, but a sufficiently large collection of water molecules displays the property of wetness, and wetness is known as an emergent property. Another example, which Sapolsky particularly likes: certain kinds of ants (which have not the slightest understanding of bridge building and certainly no blueprints) use their bodies to build a bridge in order to span a gap in their path. That bridge is emergent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think that free will may be an emergent property of a collection of neurons, then you need to show how free will may emerge. One way you may do so, incorrectly, is by misunderstanding the distinction between deterministic and calculable; see above. Or you may assume, as Sapolsky puts it, that once you have emergent states, they can “do whatever the hell they want.” And finally, you may think that, again in Sapolsky’s words, “… an emergent state can reach down and change the fundamental nature of the [building blocks] comprising it.” It is like saying that, once they have built the bridge, those ants no longer have to behave like ants. If you want more, get the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sapolsky says he really did not want to write chapters on quantum indeterminacy. Not only does he not understand quantum indeterminacy; neither does anyone else. His description of the double-slit experiment is pretty good, except where he repeats a very common misconception: when you block one of the slits or attempt to measure which slit the electron passed through, it does not stop behaving like a wave. The double-slit pattern disappears, but we still see the diffraction pattern of a single slit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will not – cannot – go into much detail here, but I am firmly in agreement with Sapolsky when he says that if quantum indeterminacy were an important factor in governing our behavior, we would make decisions randomly, and that is not exactly my definition of free will. Mostly, we do not make decisions randomly, so the effect of quantum indeterminacy must obviously be small. Sapolsky explains why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second half of the book concerns crime and punishment or, perhaps more accurately, transgression and rehabilitation. Sapolsky asks the question, if everyone believed we had no free will, would we all run amok? I do not know the answer to that question, but I can reasonably assure you that neither Sapolsky nor I have ever run amok, and I daresay that we do not intend to. That said, Sapolsky cites some studies that show that you can&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; undermine someone's belief in free will and they feel less of a sense of agency…. And most important for our purposes, they become less ethical in their behavior, less helpful, and more aggressive. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sapolsky wittily advises us to “burn this book before anyone else stumbles upon it and has their moral compass on board.” Fortunately, the effect was small, and a meta-analysis showed no consistent effects. Sapolsky searches for evidence that religious people are nicer than atheists and comes up with a statistic that religious people are, for example, more charitable than atheists. I think that statistic is fairly well known, but Sapolsky notes that their charity extends largely to their own group; in other words, they are largely charitable toward themselves. (Indeed, I have looked at my own charitable contributions and find that about 30 % go to my synagogue, though some of that is only temporary. Other monies, which I have not quantified, go to local agencies from which I may benefit. Charity may begin at home, but sometimes it also ends at home.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sapolsky pretty well establishes that atheists and those who do not believe in free will are no better or worse than religious people and those who believe in free will. That leaves the question, though, what do free-will deniers recommend that we do with transgressors, if we believe that they do not control their own actions? Punishment seems inappropriate, but they can inflict very real loss or pain. Sapolsky provides a long history showing in detail how much we have improved since the days when we used to draw and quarter people. Also, we have improved since the days when we thought, for example, that schizophrenia was a result of poor mothering, rather than the brain disease we now know it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What then to do with transgressors? Quarantine them, the way we quarantine people with various diseases (or should I say non-mental diseases?). When he says quarantine, however, he does not mean jail in the way the US as a practical matter applies the term. To the contrary, he says we must quarantine people in a way that constrains them the least, because in the last analysis their transgressions are not their fault. He points to Norway, where prisoners live in tiny apartments with televisions and various amenities, and yet the recidivism rate is one-quarter that of the US, where people can actually learn to be better criminals in jail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulk of the book is 400 pages long, not counting notes. I thought it could have been a lot shorter. For example, the author spends a great deal of time on schizophrenia (not to mention drawing and quartering). In the middle of the last century, in the complete absence of evidence and sometimes in defiance of evidence, psychoanalysts blamed schizophrenia on mothers’ parenting. Even when schizophrenia was conclusively demonstrated to be a brain disease and treatable with drugs, psychoanalysts refused to give in. Sapolsky seems angry and heaps a great deal of well-deserved opprobrium – but according to his belief and mine, these mid-century psychoanalysts had no choice but to believe what they believed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewer’s last inch. I want to renew my complaint that the Kindle edition, which I may lease but not purchase, at $16.99 costs the same as the paperback and $4.15 less than the hardcover, both of which I may own and do whatever I want with. I read the Kindle edition, and I was less than satisfied with the figures. The book was long and there were many, many endnotes; I sometimes had the impression that the author had unearthed all this material and was, by God, going to get it in one way or another. Even on a Kindle the notes were annoying, and I skipped most of them; I imagine they would have become intolerable if you tried to read them all in the print edition. Finally, though I very much appreciated the informal style and occasional humor, and noticed very few spelling or other errors, I thought the editor should have cut out the more extreme cuss words.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Several weeks ago, in an article entitled Do we have free will? No, I threatened to read Robert Sapolsky’s splendid book, Determined: A Science of Life without Free Will. Well, I read it, and we still do not have free will. As I said in my earlier article, I had myself argued that we lack free will in my book, No Sense of Obligation: Science and Religion in an Impersonal Universe. My argument was kind of bare-bones, basically that we are governed by the laws of physics and chemistry, which are deterministic (except perhaps for the occasional quantum fluctuation), so our actions must also be deterministic. Though my wording was not the best, I also argued that criminals should therefore be rehabilitated or quarantined and not punished. Sapolsky fleshes all this out in great (if not excruciating) detail.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Amanda Townley new director at NCSE</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/amanda-townley-new-director.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amanda Townley new director at NCSE" /><published>2023-11-28T13:35:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-11-28T13:35:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/amanda-townley-new-director</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/amanda-townley-new-director.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Amanda_Townley_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Amanda Townley&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Amanda Townley, incoming director of the National Center for Science Education. &lt;small&gt;Copyright by Amanda Townley. Used with permission.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amanda Townley is set to become the third director of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/&quot;&gt;National Center for Science Education&lt;/a&gt;, succeeding present director Ann Reid and the “legendary” founder Eugenie Scott, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/brought-creationist-home-scientist-fights-evolution&quot;&gt;an article&lt;/a&gt; by Jeffrey Mervis, posted today by the magazine &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;. Dr. Townley, currently a professor of education at Georgia Southern University, is also &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.georgiasouthern.edu/my/2023/01/25/amanda-townley-ph-d-elected-president-of-national-association-of-biology-teachers/&quot;&gt;President of the National Association of Biology Teachers&lt;/a&gt;. She will assume responsibility for a staff of 11 and an annual budget of $1.5 million in December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Townley told &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; that she had been brought up in a home that embraced young-earth creationism. When the biology teacher skipped the chapter on evolution, young Amanda took it upon herself to read that chapter and thought it made a lot of sense. She decided to become an evolutionary biologist and to teach evolutionary biology. Ultimately, she helped to develop a teaching strategy known as &lt;i&gt;cultural and religious sensitivity&lt;/i&gt;, which “allows teachers and students to address their conflicting views before delving into the subject matter,” in the words of Mr. Mervis. Briefly, the teacher respects students’ views, and students are taught that their beliefs do not preclude accepting evolution. You may read more detail in the &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; article and in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/ncse-names-amanda-l-townley-next-executive-director&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; by NCSE Director of Communications Paul Oh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Amanda Townley, incoming director of the National Center for Science Education. Copyright by Amanda Townley. Used with permission. Amanda Townley is set to become the third director of the National Center for Science Education, succeeding present director Ann Reid and the “legendary” founder Eugenie Scott, according to an article by Jeffrey Mervis, posted today by the magazine Science. Dr. Townley, currently a professor of education at Georgia Southern University, is also President of the National Association of Biology Teachers. She will assume responsibility for a staff of 11 and an annual budget of $1.5 million in December. Dr. Townley told Science that she had been brought up in a home that embraced young-earth creationism. When the biology teacher skipped the chapter on evolution, young Amanda took it upon herself to read that chapter and thought it made a lot of sense. She decided to become an evolutionary biologist and to teach evolutionary biology. Ultimately, she helped to develop a teaching strategy known as cultural and religious sensitivity, which “allows teachers and students to address their conflicting views before delving into the subject matter,” in the words of Mr. Mervis. Briefly, the teacher respects students’ views, and students are taught that their beliefs do not preclude accepting evolution. You may read more detail in the Science article and in an article by NCSE Director of Communications Paul Oh. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry></feed>