<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-12-10T13:39:21-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Agave neomexicana</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/agave-neomexicana.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Agave neomexicana" /><published>2025-12-08T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-12-08T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/agave-neomexicana</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/agave-neomexicana.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Ron Wittmann&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/PXL_20250624_Wittmann_Yucca_1_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photograph of yucca flowers&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Ron Wittmann's yucca plant, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/agave-neomexicana.html&quot;&gt;Agave mexicana&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;, in full bloom on August 21, several weeks after the earlier photograph (link) taken on June 6 of this year. Mr. Wittmann tells us that the plant has not bloomed in 25 years and will not bloom again.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Ron Wittmann. Ron Wittmann's yucca plant, Agave mexicana, in full bloom on August 21, several weeks after the earlier photograph (link) taken on June 6 of this year. Mr. Wittmann tells us that the plant has not bloomed in 25 years and will not bloom again.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interstellar Comets: Creationism’s Missed Opportunity?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/interstellar-comets.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interstellar Comets: Creationism’s Missed Opportunity?" /><published>2025-12-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-12-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/interstellar-comets</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/interstellar-comets.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/3I-ATLASa.png&quot; alt=&quot;[Image of 3I/Atlas]&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;A deep image of interstellar Comet 3I/ATLAS captured by the Gemini &lt;br /&gt;Multi-Object Spectrograph (GMOS) on Gemini South at Cerro Pachón&lt;br /&gt; in Chile.  From Wikimedia CC 4.0&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On November 29, Answers In Genesis apologist and astronomer Danny Faulkner posted an article on the interstellar comet 3I/ATLAS. Dr. Faulkner’s article sensibly dismissed popular speculation (including persistent claims by Harvard professor Avi Loeb) that 3I/ATLAS and similar objects might be artificial probes or alien artifacts. But in doing so, Faulkner never addressed the only question that is cosmologically relevant for a young-earth framework: Where did this object come from? Interstellar comets are not curiosities or distractions; they are kinematic probes: natural test cases for any model purporting that the universe is only a few thousand years old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an organization that claims to be able to give “Answers” about what they call “origin science”, Answers In Genesis is suspiciously quiet about the origins of interstellar comets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-third-interstellar-comet&quot;&gt;The Third Interstellar Comet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since the rise of wide-field astronomical surveys, astronomers have kept a vigilant watch on the skies for near-Earth objects (NEOs): asteroids and comets whose orbits may bring them close to the Earth, with potential risk of impact. But beyond planetary defense, surveys also catalog a broad variety of small bodies because these minor objects carry clues about the formation and evolution of planetary systems: their orbits, compositions, and dynamics help scientists trace back when and how they formed, and how stable their source systems remain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comets in our solar system come in different flavors. Short-period comets have orbits closely bound to the Sun, often returning every few years or decades, typically originating in the Kuiper Belt or closer. Long-period comets have highly elongated but still bound orbits, often taking thousands or millions of years to complete (usually thought to arise in the distant Oort Cloud). Both of these types remain gravitationally bound to the Sun, albeit with very different orbital periods. A third, much rarer category — hyperbolic or interstellar comets — follows an unbound trajectory. Their eccentricity exceeds 1, placing them on a one-time pass through the Solar System: they arrive from interstellar space, swing past the Sun, and then depart forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2025, the world encountered only the third such confirmed interstellar visitor. The first was 1I/ʻOumuamua, discovered in October 2017, followed by 2I/Borisov, announced in August 2019. The newest, 3I/ATLAS, officially designated C/2025 N1 (ATLAS), was discovered this July by the Asteroid Terrestrial-impact Last Alert System (ATLAS) telescope in Chile. Follow-up observations soon confirmed its extremely hyperbolic orbit. Because 3I/ATLAS is active (i.e., showing a fuzzy coma and dust tail, like a “normal” comet) astronomers treat it as a genuine cometary body, not a rocky asteroid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;faulkners-cosmological-commitments&quot;&gt;Faulkner’s Cosmological Commitments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Danny Faulkner has become the predominant AIG author and speaker on issues of astronomy since the departure of Dr. Jason Lisle some years ago, writing on topics ranging from light-travel-time and starlight problems to extrasolar planets, dark matter and dark energy, planetary system formation, and the operation of modern astronomical instruments like the James Webb Space Telescope. Over the years, he has articulated a reasonably consistent set of commitments in his elucidation of a “Biblical” cosmology. In defense of a recent special creation, he has argued that divine creation is characterized by stability and order, even using this perceived order as evidence for divine design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just two years ago, while explaining the evidence for dark matter, Faulkner wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Creationists have long advanced the idea that there is design and stability in the world. For instance, some creationists speak about the stability of both planetary orbits and the orbits of the planets’ natural satellites, and even the stability of systems beyond the solar system. Which is it? Did God create a stable world, or did He create an unstable world? Are creationists willing to sacrifice the stability argument in favor of a lesser argument for relatively recent origin?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Science progresses only when we change and develop our models as new data are found. Rather than ignoring or denying the data that are invoked in support of dark matter and dark energy, recent creationists must produce their own models to interpret this data. Only through this difficult process can significant progress be made in achieving a robust, truly biblical cosmology/cosmogony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faulkner treats this concept of a stable, orderly universe as a foundational theological principle. This theme recurs throughout Faulkner’s popular writings, lectures, and technical papers, where orbital regularity, galactic coherence, and the long-term persistence of planetary systems are repeatedly cited as marks of divine design cutting against the perceived “chaos” of stellar evolution. Stability is not merely descriptive in his framework; it functions as a theological constraint on cosmological interpretation: a necessary feature of a created universe that must remain physically intelligible rather than dynamically deceptive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, comets have long been held up by creationists as part of their broadly-debunked suite of “evidences” for a young earth. Faulkner has frequently argued that because active comets lose material with each solar passage, a population persisting over millions or billions of years would require continuous replenishment, something he claims has never been convincingly demonstrated. Instead, he maintains that the observed numbers of comets are best explained by recent creation, with gradual depletion through sublimation and gravitational scattering accounting for their observed fading. Similar arguments appear across AiG publications, where both short-period and long-period comets are presented as transient populations inconsistent with deep time and therefore evidence for a young solar system — arguments that explicitly rely on the physical loss and ejection of comets as natural dynamical processes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Comets have little mass, so each close pass to the sun greatly reduces a comet’s size, and eventually comets fade away. They can’t survive billions of years.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Two other mechanisms can destroy comets—ejections from the solar system and collisions with planets. Ejections happen as comets pass too close to the large planets, particularly Jupiter, and the planets’ gravity kicks them out of the solar system. While ejections have been observed many times, the first observed collision was in 1994, when Comet Shoemaker-Levi IX slammed into Jupiter.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Given the loss rates, it’s easy to compute a maximum age of comets. That maximum age is only a few million years. Obviously, their prevalence makes sense if the entire solar system was created just a few thousand years ago, but not if it arose billions of years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, these commitments form a coherent cosmological picture. Comets originate as real members of real star systems. Gravitational processes can eject them from those systems. After ejection, these bodies travel under ordinary Newtonian mechanics. Their motions are real and physically meaningful, not illusory or metaphorical. Crucially, nothing in Faulkner’s published framework permits comets to materialize mid-flight or exist without physical origin. Their histories, at least in principle, should be observationally tractable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-creationist-cosmology-predicts&quot;&gt;What Creationist Cosmology Predicts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Faulkner takes his own worldview seriously, he has to acknowledge that interstellar comets carry direct and testable implications. Any such object must originate from a previously existing stellar or planetary system that formed part of God’s stable created order. Once ejected, its motion through space becomes a straightforward problem of classical kinematics. Velocity multiplied by time yields a maximum travel distance. Trajectories point backward to source regions. Each interstellar comet should therefore act as a natural tracer pointing toward the location of its parent system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under a genuine 6,000-year cosmology, the implications are clear. Because Faulkner’s universe is so young, any object traveling at tens of kilometers per second could only have come from a very small local neighborhood around the Sun. Unlike scientific cosmology—which recognizes that the galaxy and universe are billions of years old—young-earth models compress physical possibility into an extremely confined volume of space. Interstellar comets, rather than being awkward anomalies, should therefore become some of the most powerful discovery tools available to creationist astronomers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-physics-of-3iatlas&quot;&gt;The Physics of 3I/ATLAS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The physics of 3I/ATLAS are simple and uncontroversial. Its perihelion velocity was measured at approximately 68.3 kilometers per second. Combining that value with the object’s hyperbolic eccentricity allows computation of its hyperbolic excess velocity, the speed it had when effectively outside the Sun’s gravitational influence. This velocity is about 58 kilometers per second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even on a very generous 6,000-year timescale, an object traveling at that constant speed could traverse only about 10^13 kilometers: just under 1.2 light-years. This figure establishes a firm upper bound: under young-earth cosmology, any natural parent system for 3I/ATLAS must lie within a sphere extending less than 1.2 light-years from Earth, and the comet’s incoming trajectory must align with that location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know, however, that no such star systems are presently catalogued. Proxima Centauri, Alpha Centauri, and Barnard’s Star—the nearest known stellar neighbors—lie at distances several times that limit, and none align with 3I/ATLAS’s observed arrival direction anyway. Within Faulkner’s framework, therefore, 3I/ATLAS could not plausibly have originated from any known star system. This realization should drive young-earth cosmology to an obvious and specific prediction: there must exist one or more yet-undiscovered star systems, brown dwarfs, or massive planetary bodies within 1.2 light-years of Earth lying along the comet’s trajectory that served as its point of ejection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If creationists adhered seriously to their own cosmology, this conclusion would be exhilarating rather than inconvenient. Each interstellar comet would provide a geometric “search cone” on the sky defining where the undiscovered parent object must lie. Reducing the universe to a 6,000-year age compresses the allowed volume so tightly that the relevant search zones become modest and tractable. Modern infrared surveys, and especially the James Webb Space Telescope, are capable of detecting extremely faint stellar and substellar objects that earlier instruments might have missed. Creationists should be pressing for dedicated sky surveys in the predicted regions, attempting to identify their missing neighbors before secular astronomy stumbles across them incidentally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success would be a spectacular triumph: direct empirical confirmation of a major young-earth prediction. That is the essence of scientific testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;an-expanding-pattern&quot;&gt;An Expanding Pattern&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The predictive pressure strengthens when the earlier interstellar visitors are included. 1I/’Oumuamua and 2I/Borisov entered the solar system with even lower excess velocities than 3I/ATLAS, meaning that under young-earth time limits they must have originated from even closer parent systems than 3I/ATLAS requires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 1I/ʻOumuamua, with a hyperbolic excess velocity of roughly 26.3 km/s, even a full 6,000-year transit would limit its origin to a distance of about 0.55 light-years, and its steep orbital inclination of 122.7° places its incoming direction far from alignment with any known nearby stellar system. For 2I/Borisov, traveling somewhat faster at approximately 32 km/s, the maximum 6,000-year travel distance increases only to around 0.65 light-years, with its 44° inclination likewise incompatible with the directions of known nearby stars. In both cases, the required parent systems would need to lie even closer to the Sun than the hypothetical source implied by 3I/ATLAS — within fractions of a light-year along their respective inbound trajectories — yet no such stellar or substellar objects are known to exist in those regions of the sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sky volume of possible sources for 1I/’Oumuamua and 2I/Borisov therefore becomes smaller still. Under a functioning young-earth research program, these objects should already have yielded a growing catalog of predicted nearby systems awaiting observational confirmation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet nothing of the sort exists. No sky-cone analyses have been published. No target fields have been identified. No JWST proposals have been announced. No predictions have been offered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is only silence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;theological-retreat&quot;&gt;Theological Retreat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this sort of silence is not all that surprising. Pursuing these predictions would almost certainly lead to failure, and that failure would constitute a direct and visible refutation of young-earth cosmology. Instead, the problem of origin is quietly avoided altogether. If pressed, Faulkner would likely be forced to argue a nonsensical origin: the comet did not come from anywhere; it was simply created already traveling through space, with a trajectory tracing back toward a nonexistent point of origin, like a real bullet fired from an imaginary gun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This explanation is not a theoretical lifeline—it is an intellectual collapse. Faulkner has insisted that cosmic stability and lawful dynamics testify to the Creator’s design. “Created in transit” abandons those commitments. If moving bodies are not products of physical histories but fabricated with fictitious kinematics, then trajectories cease to encode past motion. Velocities become meaningless numbers with no historical content. Astronomy itself loses any capacity to infer origins or causes. Every observation can be dismissed as a specially arranged appearance, immune to test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interstellar comets offer perhaps the most direct empirical test yet available for young-earth cosmology. If its advocates truly believed their claims about cosmic stability, real celestial mechanics, and comets originating within star systems, they would treat objects like 3I/ATLAS as opportunities for bold prediction. Instead, these opportunities are ignored, because serious engagement would expose the model to decisive risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with young-earth astronomy is not that it makes incorrect predictions. It is that it refuses to make predictions at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Special thanks to Dan Phelps for calling attention to Faulkner’s silence on the origins of interstellar comets and to the University of Kentucky’s Dr. Thomas Troland for discussions on the kinematics of comet ejection.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;FIGURE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
For clearly-visible image &lt;a href=&quot;/uploads/2025/interstellar.png&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;click here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This infographic visualizes the kinematic challenge posed by interstellar comets to a recently-created cosmos. The main panel (5 ly scale) shows the nearest eight known stellar neighbors (yellow) and the trajectories of 1I/ʻOumuamua, 2I/Borisov, and 3I/ATLAS (grey lines). The white segments highlight the maximum distance each comet could have traveled in 6,029 years. Critically, these segments terminate far short of every known star, forcing the young-earth model to predict three undiscovered source bodies located precisely at the end of the white lines. The inset panel (0.5 ly scale) contains an additional inset zoomed in to 400X the main panel to show these source termination points relative to the outer solar system, where the trajectories of the planets and outgoing space probes are visible.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>David MacMillan</name></author><summary type="html">A deep image of interstellar Comet 3I/ATLAS captured by the Gemini Multi-Object Spectrograph (GMOS) on Gemini South at Cerro Pachón in Chile. From Wikimedia CC 4.0   On November 29, Answers In Genesis apologist and astronomer Danny Faulkner posted an article on the interstellar comet 3I/ATLAS. Dr. Faulkner’s article sensibly dismissed popular speculation (including persistent claims by Harvard professor Avi Loeb) that 3I/ATLAS and similar objects might be artificial probes or alien artifacts. But in doing so, Faulkner never addressed the only question that is cosmologically relevant for a young-earth framework: Where did this object come from? Interstellar comets are not curiosities or distractions; they are kinematic probes: natural test cases for any model purporting that the universe is only a few thousand years old. For an organization that claims to be able to give “Answers” about what they call “origin science”, Answers In Genesis is suspiciously quiet about the origins of interstellar comets. The Third Interstellar Comet Ever since the rise of wide-field astronomical surveys, astronomers have kept a vigilant watch on the skies for near-Earth objects (NEOs): asteroids and comets whose orbits may bring them close to the Earth, with potential risk of impact. But beyond planetary defense, surveys also catalog a broad variety of small bodies because these minor objects carry clues about the formation and evolution of planetary systems: their orbits, compositions, and dynamics help scientists trace back when and how they formed, and how stable their source systems remain. Comets in our solar system come in different flavors. Short-period comets have orbits closely bound to the Sun, often returning every few years or decades, typically originating in the Kuiper Belt or closer. Long-period comets have highly elongated but still bound orbits, often taking thousands or millions of years to complete (usually thought to arise in the distant Oort Cloud). Both of these types remain gravitationally bound to the Sun, albeit with very different orbital periods. A third, much rarer category — hyperbolic or interstellar comets — follows an unbound trajectory. Their eccentricity exceeds 1, placing them on a one-time pass through the Solar System: they arrive from interstellar space, swing past the Sun, and then depart forever. In 2025, the world encountered only the third such confirmed interstellar visitor. The first was 1I/ʻOumuamua, discovered in October 2017, followed by 2I/Borisov, announced in August 2019. The newest, 3I/ATLAS, officially designated C/2025 N1 (ATLAS), was discovered this July by the Asteroid Terrestrial-impact Last Alert System (ATLAS) telescope in Chile. Follow-up observations soon confirmed its extremely hyperbolic orbit. Because 3I/ATLAS is active (i.e., showing a fuzzy coma and dust tail, like a “normal” comet) astronomers treat it as a genuine cometary body, not a rocky asteroid. Faulkner’s Cosmological Commitments Dr. Danny Faulkner has become the predominant AIG author and speaker on issues of astronomy since the departure of Dr. Jason Lisle some years ago, writing on topics ranging from light-travel-time and starlight problems to extrasolar planets, dark matter and dark energy, planetary system formation, and the operation of modern astronomical instruments like the James Webb Space Telescope. Over the years, he has articulated a reasonably consistent set of commitments in his elucidation of a “Biblical” cosmology. In defense of a recent special creation, he has argued that divine creation is characterized by stability and order, even using this perceived order as evidence for divine design.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Spider with box elder bug</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/spider-with-box-elder.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spider with box elder bug" /><published>2025-11-24T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-11-24T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/spider-with-box-elder</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/spider-with-box-elder.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/DSC06129_Spider_Box_Elder_Bug_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spider attacking a box elder bug trapped in the spiderweb&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Spider about to lunch on a box elder bug, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boisea_trivittata&quot;&gt;Boisea trivittata&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. If the bug is approximately 1&amp;nbsp;cm long, the spider must be a few millimeters. The spider repeatedly dashed in, perhaps to sting the bug, and then dashed out nervously, before settling in to dine. If anyone can identify the spider I will edit the post (the image is too small for BugGuide). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another shot of a box elder bug below the fold:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/IMG_6211_Box_Elder_Bug_600_2.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Incidentally, a snapshot of a box elder bug that I posted in 2008, before the Big Computer Crash. It shows the markings on the bug better than the picture with the spider.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Spider about to lunch on a box elder bug, Boisea trivittata. If the bug is approximately 1&amp;nbsp;cm long, the spider must be a few millimeters. The spider repeatedly dashed in, perhaps to sting the bug, and then dashed out nervously, before settling in to dine. If anyone can identify the spider I will edit the post (the image is too small for BugGuide). Another shot of a box elder bug below the fold:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Darwin Comes to Town: a meditation</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/darwin-comes-to-town.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Darwin Comes to Town: a meditation" /><published>2025-11-17T10:05:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-11-17T10:05:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/darwin-comes-to-town</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/darwin-comes-to-town.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Schilthuizen_Darwin_Comes_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently came across this fascinating book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Darwin-Comes-Town-Jungle-Evolution/dp/1250127823&quot;&gt;Darwin Comes to Town: How the Urban Jungle Drives Evolution&lt;/a&gt;, by the biologist Menno Schilthuizen of the Naturalis Biodiversity Center and the University of Leiden. Years ago, probably about when it appeared in 2001, I read Prof. Schilthuizen’s equally fascinating book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Frogs-Flies-Dandelions-Speciation-Evolution/dp/0198503938&quot;&gt;Frogs, Flies, and Dandelions&lt;/a&gt;, about the origins and definitions of species (indeed, the difficulty of defining species at all). So naturally I snapped up &lt;i&gt;Darwin Comes to Town&lt;/i&gt;. The title is a pun, in that the book is about the evolution of organisms that have either adapted to cities or towns, or have adopted cities or towns. I will not review the book, but will pen 3 or 4 paragraphs about chapters that for one reason or another especially interested me. If you want more, read the book!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first organism that Schilthuizen describes in detail is a &lt;i&gt;Culex molestus&lt;/i&gt; mosquito that he discovers in the London Underground. Outside the Underground, evidently the mosquito feeds on birds, has an interesting sex life that involves large swarms, and also hibernates. Inside the Underground, it has learned to feed on humans, “seek [its] sexual pleasures in confined spaces,” and not hibernate. Its genes spread from city to city, presumably by plane, train, or car, and it interbreeds with its above-ground relatives. All this happened, Schilthuizen assures us, very recently, probably only since humans began digging tunnels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was still reading the book, I came across a very short article in a &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; magazine newsletter, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.aed2501&quot;&gt;Cultivating a pest&lt;/a&gt;, by Corinne Simonti. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ady4515&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; by Yuki Haba et al. recently reported that, contrary to what Schilthuizen has written, these mosquitoes, which they call &lt;i&gt;Culex pipiens&lt;/i&gt; form &lt;i&gt;molestus&lt;/i&gt;, have a much longer association with us humans, and probably date back to the ancient Middle East. As I was reading these references, I cattily wondered how a biblical literalist, for example, would have responded if such a well-established “fact” had been disestablished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some time ago, in 2005, I became something of a minor expert on the peppered moth and posted an article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://skepticalinquirer.org/2005/03/moonshine-2/&quot;&gt;Moonshine: Why the Peppered Moth Remains an Icon of Evolution&lt;/a&gt;, with my colleague Ian Musgrave (who deserves all the credit for the &lt;i&gt;Moonshine&lt;/i&gt; title; you may have to read the article to learn why). A short chapter, Urban Myths, told the story of the peppered moth clearly and concisely, including the “controversy” instigated by the journalist Judith Hooper. Hooper’s book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Moths-Men-Evolutionary-Tale/dp/0393051218&quot;&gt;Of Moths and Men: An Evolutionary Tale&lt;/a&gt;, was, in Schilthuizen’s words, well-researched, but then without evidence she accused an important moth researcher, Bernard Kettlewell, of fraud. Musgrave and I took up her claims and showed that Hooper did not understand the vagaries of fieldwork in biology and almost without doubt Kettlewell had not committed fraud. Unfortunately, our paper was not published in a technical journal (I frankly do not remember why not), and Schilthuizen was unaware of it; I thought perhaps he might otherwise have been harder on Hooper. (Incidentally, for a discussion of creationists’ response to the case of the peppered moth, see the article by Paul Braterman, &lt;a href=&quot;https://3quarksdaily.com/3quarksdaily/2013/08/creationism-as-conspiracy-theory-the-case-of-the-peppered-moth.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is lots more in this book, but I want to get to the last part, where Schilthuizen discusses exotic or non-native species. He suggests, frankly, that they are here to stay and that eventually all cities will have very similar floras and faunas because they are intertwined by modern transportation. This contention leads him to the conclusion, which many will find contentious, that we might as well give in, embrace non-native species and even plant them when it seems appropriate. As a person who passionately hates field bindweed (&lt;i&gt;Convolvulus arvensis&lt;/i&gt;), I will be curious to know what others think of his proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, of course, reader’s last inch: I thought the book was uncommonly well written and used anecdotes such as his own interactions with the experts to great advantage. Not once that I recall was I bored or thought he should get on to the next topic already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Prof. Schilthuizen recommended to me his latest book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Urban-Naturalist-Make-Scientific-Playground/dp/0262049090&quot;&gt;The Urban Naturalist: How to Make the City Your Scientific Playground&lt;/a&gt;, which was published last April and is sort of a sequel. You may be sure that it is on my list.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I recently came across this fascinating book, Darwin Comes to Town: How the Urban Jungle Drives Evolution, by the biologist Menno Schilthuizen of the Naturalis Biodiversity Center and the University of Leiden. Years ago, probably about when it appeared in 2001, I read Prof. Schilthuizen’s equally fascinating book, Frogs, Flies, and Dandelions, about the origins and definitions of species (indeed, the difficulty of defining species at all). So naturally I snapped up Darwin Comes to Town. The title is a pun, in that the book is about the evolution of organisms that have either adapted to cities or towns, or have adopted cities or towns. I will not review the book, but will pen 3 or 4 paragraphs about chapters that for one reason or another especially interested me. If you want more, read the book!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The DI’s Science and Culture News announces that a “Darwinist” changed his mind</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/Darwinist-changes-his-mind.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The DI’s Science and Culture News announces that a “Darwinist” changed his mind" /><published>2025-11-16T18:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2025-11-16T18:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/Darwinist-changes-his-mind</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/Darwinist-changes-his-mind.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Master_Tom.png&quot; alt=&quot;[Master Tom in Sydenham]&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Discovery Institute’s website “Science and Culture” (formerly Evolution 
News and Views) had a dramatic story of conversion recently.  A &lt;a href=&quot;https://scienceandculture.com/2025/10/he-taught-darwinism-for-decades-then-changed-his-mind/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; entitled “He Taught Darwinism for Decades (Then Changed His Mind)” by
Andrew McDiarmid on 30 October 2025.  It announced that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For decades, British professor and author Neil Thomas was a card-carrying Darwinist. It wasn’t until after he retired from academia that he had the repose to think about things objectively. 
Then one day, in a scientific flash of inspiration, he came to the conclusion that the standard Darwinian story was “rubbish.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is that Neil Thomas has written two books, published by 
the DI’s publishing outfit, Discovery Institute Press:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/1637120036&quot;&gt;Taking Leave of Darwin: A longtime Agnostic Discovers the Case for Design&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/False-Messiah-Darwinism-That-Failed/dp/163712080X&quot;&gt;False Messiah: Darwinism as The God That Failed&lt;/a&gt;.  He has also 
made numbers of posts at Science and Culture since 2021, see them &lt;a href=&quot;https://scienceandculture.com/author/nthomas/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  He was intervewed in a 
two-part (&lt;a href=&quot;https://idthefuture.com/2127/&quot;&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://idthefuture.com/2128/&quot;&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;) series by Jonathan Witt in 2021 and by Andrew McDiarmid in 2025.
in the DI’s series “ID The Future”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thomas cannot understand how biologists ever believed Darwin’s mechanism of natural 
selection.  So: has someone who has been devoted to teaching biology students about 
Darwin and natural selection recently changed his mind?  If so, should we pay close 
attention to his arguments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well …
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hasten to say that I have not read these two books, though I have listened to the 
two podcast interviews.  In the podcasts, Thomas expresses his scepticism about 
the origin of Life, and about whether natural selection can account for the 
complexity of humans.  But he does not explain why natural selection cannot account 
for adaptations of biological organisms once life has arisen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at a couple of the arguments Thomas uses against “Darwinism”.  First, McDiarmid 
quotes Thomas as saying “This Darwinism business, it’s rubbish isn’t it?”  And he summarizes 
Thomas’s argument, saying&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;First, Thomas criticizes Darwin’s cardinal principle of natural selection as intellectually incoherent and empty of meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and then he continues with Thomas’s conclusion that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the term essentially refers to preservation; it is conservative, cannot create, and certainly cannot select.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pratts&quot;&gt;PRATTs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are two PRATTs (Points Refuted A Thousand Times).  They are truly “moldy 
oldies”.  The first seems to be the assertion that “survival of the fittest” is meaningless 
because fitness is defined as having survived.  In reality, the moment we compare 
phenotypes or genotypes to see which have the higher fitness, fitness is meaningful 
and not a vacuous concept.  I am not the first to make this point, but for more 
explanation &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Fitness-Tautology.html&quot;&gt;see my 2020 post on this here at PT&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for “preservation”, if there are more than one genotype in the population, 
and one is preserved more than the others, then it will increase in 
frequency.  So the composition of the population can change, particularly 
if the genotype(s) “preserved” are not the most frequent ones.  Again, the 
idea that natural selection cannot change the population is a PRATT, and 
again, I have heard it enough times that I joined the many people who 
have refuted that argument.  See &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/diexperts.html&quot;&gt;my 2023 post here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Neil Thomas seems to have little understanding of how natural 
selection works.  That would be shocking if he were teaching “Darwinism” 
for many years, as a biologist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;not-a-biologist&quot;&gt;Not a biologist!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, Neil Thomas is not a biologist.  Not even close.  This is no 
secret: in his biographical material at S&amp;amp;C News, which appears 
at the end of each of his posts there, he is described thusly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Neil Thomas is a Reader Emeritus in the University of Durham, England and a longtime member of the British Rationalist Association. He studied Classical Studies and European Languages at the universities of Oxford, Munich and Cardiff before taking up his post in the German section of the School of European Languages and Literatures at Durham University in 1976. There his teaching involved a broad spectrum of specialisms including Germanic philology, medieval literature, the literature and philosophy of the Enlightenment and modern German history and literature. He also taught modules on the propagandist use of the German language used both by the Nazis and by the functionaries of the old German Democratic Republic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;useful-but-not-new&quot;&gt;Useful, but not new&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should add that Thomas spends most of his posts at S&amp;amp;CN 
describing the intellectual atmosphere preceding and during 
publication of Charles Darwin’s books.  He points to many 
predecessors, going back to the Greeks and Romans, and concludes 
that Victorian society was ready for a secular explanation 
of how adaptation could come about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is right about that, but his point is hardly new.  There is 
some implication in Thomas’s posts that “Darwinists” have 
insisted that Darwin was the first evolutionary thinker.  That 
is totally wrong: there have been numerous books, for decades 
exploring Darwin’s predecessors.  Stephen Jay Gould had many 
columns on the subject.  There is an extensive Wikipedia page 
on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_evolutionary_thought&quot;&gt;History of Evolutionary Thought&lt;/a&gt;.
Peter Bowler’s book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Evolution-History-Idea-Anniversary-Preface/dp/0520261283&quot;&gt;Evolution, the History of an Idea&lt;/a&gt;,
is a good summary.  We have also posted yearly celebrations of 
Lamarck, Darwin’s most important predeccessor &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/HappybirthdayLamarck.html&quot;&gt;here at Panda’s 
Thumb&lt;/a&gt;, 
the most recent also discussing Lamarck’s predecessor and 
patron Georges Buffon.  These posts will be found on or near August 1 of 
each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A particular favorite of mine is an older popularization 
by John Greene, provocatively titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Death-Adam-Evolution-Western-Thought/&quot;&gt;The Death of Adam: Evolution and Its Impact on Western Thought&lt;/a&gt;.
It points out the connection between the major advances in other 
fields, such as astronomy, which led to a search for 
unifying mechanisms, even in biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thomas seems most upset about this change, the rise to 
dominance of secular science which searches for 
mechanisms in our everyday world.  He seems to think 
that recent arguments by the Discovery Institute are 
invalidating this.  He’s welcome to his opinion, but 
I don’t think his arguments will bear much weight.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">  The Discovery Institute’s website “Science and Culture” (formerly Evolution News and Views) had a dramatic story of conversion recently. A post entitled “He Taught Darwinism for Decades (Then Changed His Mind)” by Andrew McDiarmid on 30 October 2025. It announced that For decades, British professor and author Neil Thomas was a card-carrying Darwinist. It wasn’t until after he retired from academia that he had the repose to think about things objectively. Then one day, in a scientific flash of inspiration, he came to the conclusion that the standard Darwinian story was “rubbish.” The result is that Neil Thomas has written two books, published by the DI’s publishing outfit, Discovery Institute Press: Taking Leave of Darwin: A longtime Agnostic Discovers the Case for Design and False Messiah: Darwinism as The God That Failed. He has also made numbers of posts at Science and Culture since 2021, see them here. He was intervewed in a two-part (part 1 and part 2) series by Jonathan Witt in 2021 and by Andrew McDiarmid in 2025. in the DI’s series “ID The Future”. Thomas cannot understand how biologists ever believed Darwin’s mechanism of natural selection. So: has someone who has been devoted to teaching biology students about Darwin and natural selection recently changed his mind? If so, should we pay close attention to his arguments? Well …</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Aurora borealis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/aurora-borealis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aurora borealis" /><published>2025-11-12T09:15:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-11-12T09:15:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/aurora-borealis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/aurora-borealis.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Vivian Dullien&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/IMG_0772_Vivian_Aurora_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aurora borealis&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2025/11/12/nx-s1-5274739/northern-lights-aurora-borealis-solar-storms&quot;&gt;Aurora borealis&lt;/a&gt; seen last night at 10 pm in Boulder, Colorado. 1-s exposure at F/1.8 with a smart phone  at ISO 4000, exposure bias 0.1.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Vivian Dullien. Aurora borealis seen last night at 10 pm in Boulder, Colorado. 1-s exposure at F/1.8 with a smart phone at ISO 4000, exposure bias 0.1.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Anolis carolinensis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/anolis-carolinensis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Anolis carolinensis" /><published>2025-11-10T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-11-10T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/anolis%20carolinensis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/anolis-carolinensis.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Denelsbeck_Anolis_carolinensis2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ring of Brodgar (henge)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://herpsofnc.org/green-anole/&quot;&gt;Anolis carolinensis&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Carolina or green anole. Mr. Denelsbeck writes that this anole &quot;regrew its detached tail, but forked &amp;ndash; I've seen photos but this was the first that I'd found an example of myself, right on the downspout by the front door last November [2023]. Unfortunately, despite keeping a wary eye out, I have not spotted it since. Based on some scarring, this might have been the same one that I found without a tail back in April of that year, which if true, would give a rough time frame of how long it takes to regrow. Canon 7D, Canon 18-135 STM, handheld, cropped.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Al Denelsbeck. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Anolis carolinensis &amp;ndash; Carolina or green anole. Mr. Denelsbeck writes that this anole &quot;regrew its detached tail, but forked &amp;ndash; I've seen photos but this was the first that I'd found an example of myself, right on the downspout by the front door last November [2023]. Unfortunately, despite keeping a wary eye out, I have not spotted it since. Based on some scarring, this might have been the same one that I found without a tail back in April of that year, which if true, would give a rough time frame of how long it takes to regrow. Canon 7D, Canon 18-135 STM, handheld, cropped.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Video: Something Weird Happens When You Simulate Lifeless Molecules</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/video-something-weird.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Video: Something Weird Happens When You Simulate Lifeless Molecules" /><published>2025-11-03T15:04:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-11-03T15:04:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/video-something-weird</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/video-something-weird.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Veritasium_Frontis_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A frame from the video, showing differently colored fish&quot; /&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am going to step out of my lane again and tout this video, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XX7PdJIGiCw&quot;&gt;Something Weird Happens When You Simulate Lifeless Molecules&lt;/a&gt;, by Veritasium. What happens is that you get (simulated) life, natural selection, and so on. Professional biologists will no doubt find something to carp about. I did not especially like the term, “survival of the fittest,” when I think he really meant “natural selection.” My first impression was that he may have been conflating origin of life with evolution, though they are certainly closely related. He kind of pushes the selfish gene theory, but also states some criticisms and states flatly that genetic drift can sometimes overcome natural selection. He notes that his model is an oversimplification, but then, as he says, all scientific models are oversimplifications. I will let a real biologist discuss whether evolution takes place at the level of the gene, the individual, or indeed the group. As for me, I thought it was a splendid video which in a half-hour or so gave a clear understanding of how life can develop from non-life and go on to evolve into, well, endless forms most beautiful and most wonderful, several of which make cameo appearances in the video.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I am going to step out of my lane again and tout this video, Something Weird Happens When You Simulate Lifeless Molecules, by Veritasium. What happens is that you get (simulated) life, natural selection, and so on. Professional biologists will no doubt find something to carp about. I did not especially like the term, “survival of the fittest,” when I think he really meant “natural selection.” My first impression was that he may have been conflating origin of life with evolution, though they are certainly closely related. He kind of pushes the selfish gene theory, but also states some criticisms and states flatly that genetic drift can sometimes overcome natural selection. He notes that his model is an oversimplification, but then, as he says, all scientific models are oversimplifications. I will let a real biologist discuss whether evolution takes place at the level of the gene, the individual, or indeed the group. As for me, I thought it was a splendid video which in a half-hour or so gave a clear understanding of how life can develop from non-life and go on to evolve into, well, endless forms most beautiful and most wonderful, several of which make cameo appearances in the video.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Looking Down the Tree – Exploring the Origins of Our Species: book report</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/looking-down-the-tree-report.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Looking Down the Tree – Exploring the Origins of Our Species: book report" /><published>2025-10-31T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-10-31T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/looking-down-the-tree-report</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/looking-down-the-tree-report.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Cruzan_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover.&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Looking-Down-Tree-Evolutionary-Biology/dp/0197805167/&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Looking down the Tree – The Evolutionary Biology of Human Origins&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by Mitch Cruzan, Oxford University Press, October, 2025.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;We got news of Mitch Cruzan’s new book on human origins and invited him to write a short introduction, which you may see &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/looking-down-the-tree-preview.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. In the meantime, the publisher graciously sent a review copy, and I report on the book below.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mitch Cruzan is Professor of Biology at Portland State University and has by his reckoning been teaching evolutionary biology for 15 years. I recently read an advance copy of his new book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Looking-Down-Tree-Evolutionary-Biology/dp/0197805167/&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Looking down the Tree – The Evolutionary Biology of Human Origins&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Although I suppose I am a fellow traveler, I am not a biologist, and occasionally something went over my head. I wondered, therefore, who the book’s intended audience was. Not unlike a paleontologist, I searched within the book and immediately found on page 15, “You probably know about DNA from your biology courses.” I frankly thought that he should have aimed higher: it would not have taken much additional explanation to prepare a more popular book and not what I think amounts to a supplementary college text. Indeed, I thought that it would have been useful to have defined terms such as apocrine gland, homologous, and recombination for readers who have never had a biology course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cruzan argues convincingly that to understand our phenotypes, you have to look at our past, not our present. He thus begins each chapter with an anecdote from the daily life of a fictitious hominid he names Launua. Launua belongs to a clan that is barely surviving, having comparatively recently ventured into the savanna. Her clan is inbred (presumably not so much that it is deleterious) and held together by kin selection, or inclusive fitness. Cruzan sometimes seems to conflate inbreeding with kin selection and remarks that inbred populations display kin selection. Each chapter ends with a useful summary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cruzan asks, for example, why we have opposable thumbs. Not, as I understand it, because we need them for grasping, but initially because our upright posture necessitated an elongation of our big toes (not all our toes), and our hands followed along because they use the same regulatory genes. Here he uses the large thumb to introduce the concept of an exaptation, though later he uses the obsolete but more descriptive term preadaptation. Cruzan thinks,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The single most influential event in the history of our lineage was the transition to savannas and selection for bipedalism, which caused correlated changes in the hands of our ancestors.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cruzan argues that we lost our hair in favor of evaporative cooling. He argues further that we have hair on our heads for thermal regulation, which made me wonder why males (European males, anyway) often have heavy beards, not to mention more body hair than females. He does not discuss other animals that live on the savanna and are covered with hair. He uses head and body lice, which live in our hair, to cleverly deduce that we probably wore clothing made of woven fabric about 100,000 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A colleague of mine once remarked that if you want to get students’ attention, just say “testicle.” Cruzan tests this hypothesis in spades and explains in some detail why human males have large penises compared to other apes, and human females have correspondingly long vaginas. &lt;small&gt;(Spoiler alert: it is the other way around and comes about because of our large heads, not sexual selection.)&lt;/small&gt; I was not completely convinced by his claim that the human female breasts and buttocks are primarily for storing fat; anyone who has ever seen a picture of a baboon in estrus might propose a different hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grandmother hypothesis postulates that menopause evolved so that grandmothers would be available to help raise their grandchildren. In discussing this hypothesis, Cruzan claims that human females ovulate about once a month and thus run out of eggs. That seemed to me to be an anachronism; in nature, before contraception, they spent most of their adult lives pregnant or lactating, and possibly ovulated no more than a dozen or two times in their entire lives. Cruzan goes on to note, interestingly, that exclusive homosexuality is almost unique to humans and suggests that it is subject to selection even though homosexual men do not reproduce. Rather, he thinks they were helpers, similarly to the grandmothers. The argument is slightly abstruse and depends on the fact that humans have a constant sex drive, as opposed to the periodic sex drive in other animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final chapter is somewhat depressing, in a way. Cruzan observes that “many millions—probably billions—of individuals had to die [we all die; I think he means die prematurely] as small improvements accumulated generation after generation over the past four to six million years.” He goes on to say that today we “buffer” ourselves against natural selection by extending the lives of those who would otherwise not survive, and a decline in fitness is inevitable: “[D]eleterious mutations will continue to accumulate in populations with access to modern medicine,” and these mutations will become a challenge. Though he does not quite commit himself, he points out, “[S]ome evolutionary biologists have warned that we can expect declines in health and longevity in future generations.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that the file I got was something along the lines of a galley proof, but still I did not find a lot of errors. The figures did not all stand on their own, and I thought that nearly every one would have profited from a detailed caption, as well as more-specific discussions in the text. Phrases such as “You may remember from a previous chapter” would have been more useful had they cited the actual chapter. “Gene genealogy” seems very awkward to me and probably should have been “genetic genealogy”; Google’s search engine agreed by a score of 430,000 to 29,000. The text alternated between “descendent” and the more common “descendant”; I hope that problem was fixed before the book went to press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to know more? Get the book, read it – and, of course, comment below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgement&lt;/strong&gt;. Andrew Petto, Senior Lecturer Emeritus at the University of Wisconsin–Milwaukee, lavished many words commenting on this essay (though he did not read the book) and explained several topics that had been unclear to me. Any errors are my own or may be blamed on my speech-recognition program.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Looking down the Tree – The Evolutionary Biology of Human Origins, by Mitch Cruzan, Oxford University Press, October, 2025. We got news of Mitch Cruzan’s new book on human origins and invited him to write a short introduction, which you may see here. In the meantime, the publisher graciously sent a review copy, and I report on the book below. Mitch Cruzan is Professor of Biology at Portland State University and has by his reckoning been teaching evolutionary biology for 15 years. I recently read an advance copy of his new book, Looking down the Tree – The Evolutionary Biology of Human Origins. Although I suppose I am a fellow traveler, I am not a biologist, and occasionally something went over my head. I wondered, therefore, who the book’s intended audience was. Not unlike a paleontologist, I searched within the book and immediately found on page 15, “You probably know about DNA from your biology courses.” I frankly thought that he should have aimed higher: it would not have taken much additional explanation to prepare a more popular book and not what I think amounts to a supplementary college text. Indeed, I thought that it would have been useful to have defined terms such as apocrine gland, homologous, and recombination for readers who have never had a biology course. Cruzan argues convincingly that to understand our phenotypes, you have to look at our past, not our present. He thus begins each chapter with an anecdote from the daily life of a fictitious hominid he names Launua. Launua belongs to a clan that is barely surviving, having comparatively recently ventured into the savanna. Her clan is inbred (presumably not so much that it is deleterious) and held together by kin selection, or inclusive fitness. Cruzan sometimes seems to conflate inbreeding with kin selection and remarks that inbred populations display kin selection. Each chapter ends with a useful summary. Cruzan asks, for example, why we have opposable thumbs. Not, as I understand it, because we need them for grasping, but initially because our upright posture necessitated an elongation of our big toes (not all our toes), and our hands followed along because they use the same regulatory genes. Here he uses the large thumb to introduce the concept of an exaptation, though later he uses the obsolete but more descriptive term preadaptation. Cruzan thinks,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Looking Down the Tree – Exploring the Origins of Our Species</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/looking-down-the-tree-preview.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Looking Down the Tree – Exploring the Origins of Our Species" /><published>2025-10-29T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-10-29T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/looking-down-the-tree-preview</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/looking-down-the-tree-preview.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Cruzan_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover.&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Looking-Down-Tree-Evolutionary-Biology/dp/0197805167/&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Looking down the Tree – The Evolutionary Biology of Human Origins&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by Mitch Cruzan, Oxford University Press, October, 2025.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Mitch Cruzan is Professor of Biology at Portland State University. He received his BA and MA in Biology from California State University, Fullerton, and his PhD from Stony Brook University. He is currently an associate editor for Molecular Ecology, a leading journal in the field. He has published more than 80 papers in the primary literature and an advanced textbook, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Evolutionary-Biology-Perspective-Mitchell-Cruzan/dp/0190882670&quot;&gt;Evolutionary Biology: A Plant Perspective&lt;/a&gt;. His latest book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Looking-Down-Tree-Evolutionary-Biology/dp/B0FQYC1Q57&quot;&gt;Looking Down the Tree – Exploring the Origins of Our Species&lt;/a&gt;, is due to be published in a few days, and we have invited him to offer a preview here.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have offered an introductory course on evolution annually over the last 15 years. I always saved in-depth discussions of human evolution to the end for two reasons. First, to discuss human evolution in a meaningful way, we need to have a good understanding of evolutionary principles and processes. Second, I thought it was a good highlight for the course to end on. Each year, I incorporated new information and new ideas about human origins. Much of this content came from the questions that students asked; they weren’t satisfied to look a series of fossil remains or boring details about human genomics. They wanted to know more about the origins of our unique appearance and behaviors, and particularly secondary sexual characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does anyone take on a particular subject for a non-fiction book? You might ask, what could a plant evolutionary biologist such as myself possibly have to say about human evolution? Some reviewers actually said that I had no business writing this book. But evolutionary biology consists of a set of principles and processes that can be applied to any organism. Yes, it helps to have knowledge of the biology of a species, but for humans, that information is readily available. For me, developing the material was a natural process as I explored aspects of human evolution, along with the students in my introductory evolution lectures. By the time the pandemic hit, I had developed what I thought was a unique story of the origin of human traits – one that made sense in the context of the habitats our ancestors inhabited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book is not just a rehash of previous statements and ideas. By integrating information from disparate fields such as paleontology, anthropology, and genomics, I have drawn unique conclusions about the origins of human traits and behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading previous books and sources discussing human evolution on the web was frustrating because of how much misinformation was available. It was also frustrating that many inferences were made from observations of humans in modern societies, which is irrelevant to the origin of human traits. I decided to do something to counteract the wide range of – sometimes crazy – ideas. But I did not want to present information in a dry, dictatorial monograph. I thought that it was important to share what I had learned with as broad an audience as possible and to make it engaging enough to hold the attention of someone with little background in biology. To accomplish this, I made sure to keep things simple while being as accurate as possible. It was a tricky balance, but I managed to keep the writing at the high school level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also strived to provide adequate levels of detail without including too much tangential information, so the end product is relatively short. In addition, I use a conversational writing style to lead the reader through the evidence with logical arguments so they will understand how we come to conclusions – how we do science. To vividly illustrate the challenges and struggles our ancestors experienced, I include a fictional story of someone who lived around 70,000 years ago. I use vignettes from her life to introduce the content of each chapter and to exemplify the evolutionary principles discussed. I expect not all readers will appreciate this approach, but those who don’t can just skip the vignettes without missing the majority of content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that readers will find my discussions of the origins of unique human traits thought provoking and enlightening. I was not involved in collecting the data that I cite, but realize that sometimes you need to step back to see the connections that are not obvious from the perspective of individual research silos. By the end of the book, I hope readers will come to understand the origins of human traits and connections among them. Like those of any other animal, our unique appearance and behaviors are products of natural selection as our ancestors struggled to survive in the harsh and challenging environments they inhabited.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mitch Cruzan</name></author><summary type="html">Looking down the Tree – The Evolutionary Biology of Human Origins, by Mitch Cruzan, Oxford University Press, October, 2025. Mitch Cruzan is Professor of Biology at Portland State University. He received his BA and MA in Biology from California State University, Fullerton, and his PhD from Stony Brook University. He is currently an associate editor for Molecular Ecology, a leading journal in the field. He has published more than 80 papers in the primary literature and an advanced textbook, Evolutionary Biology: A Plant Perspective. His latest book, Looking Down the Tree – Exploring the Origins of Our Species, is due to be published in a few days, and we have invited him to offer a preview here. I have offered an introductory course on evolution annually over the last 15 years. I always saved in-depth discussions of human evolution to the end for two reasons. First, to discuss human evolution in a meaningful way, we need to have a good understanding of evolutionary principles and processes. Second, I thought it was a good highlight for the course to end on. Each year, I incorporated new information and new ideas about human origins. Much of this content came from the questions that students asked; they weren’t satisfied to look a series of fossil remains or boring details about human genomics. They wanted to know more about the origins of our unique appearance and behaviors, and particularly secondary sexual characteristics. Why does anyone take on a particular subject for a non-fiction book? You might ask, what could a plant evolutionary biologist such as myself possibly have to say about human evolution? Some reviewers actually said that I had no business writing this book. But evolutionary biology consists of a set of principles and processes that can be applied to any organism. Yes, it helps to have knowledge of the biology of a species, but for humans, that information is readily available. For me, developing the material was a natural process as I explored aspects of human evolution, along with the students in my introductory evolution lectures. By the time the pandemic hit, I had developed what I thought was a unique story of the origin of human traits – one that made sense in the context of the habitats our ancestors inhabited. This book is not just a rehash of previous statements and ideas. By integrating information from disparate fields such as paleontology, anthropology, and genomics, I have drawn unique conclusions about the origins of human traits and behaviors.</summary></entry></feed>