<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-12-17T11:31:42-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Teaching indigenous “ways of knowing” as science</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/indigenous-ways-of-knowing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Teaching indigenous “ways of knowing” as science" /><published>2021-12-13T11:12:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-12-13T11:12:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/indigenous-ways-of-knowing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/indigenous-ways-of-knowing.html">&lt;p&gt;For readers who have not been following this controversy, I thought I would point out Jerry Coyne’s article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2021/12/13/new-zealand-authorities-stand-firm-in-desire-to-teach-maori-ways-of-knowing-alongside-science-in-high-schools-and-colleges/&quot;&gt; New Zealand’s intention to teach Maori “ways of knowing”&lt;/a&gt; alongside science in schools and universities. Dr. Coyne has been following the situation for some time now, but the article I cite, his latest as of now, provides a good summary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scare quotes (“ways of knowing”) are Dr. Coyne’s, but to my mind they are entirely justified. True, the Maori and other indigenous peoples have learned a great deal about their environments, but much of what they “know” is palpably untrue. Indeed, many indigenous peoples, including the ancient Hebrews, tell what are essentially creationist myths and are therefore demonstrably false. These myths are also generally mutually exclusive. They may be appropriate in anthropology or history classes, but they are not science and do not belong in a science class, except conceivably alongside phlogiston in a unit on the history of science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New Zealand policy, though obviously well-intentioned, is frankly pandering. It leads to the following question: Must we teach Iroquois “ways of knowing” in New York, Navajo “ways of knowing” in &lt;strike&gt;New Mexico&lt;/strike&gt; Arizona, and astrology in Boulder, Colorado – all as if they were science?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">For readers who have not been following this controversy, I thought I would point out Jerry Coyne’s article on New Zealand’s intention to teach Maori “ways of knowing” alongside science in schools and universities. Dr. Coyne has been following the situation for some time now, but the article I cite, his latest as of now, provides a good summary. The scare quotes (“ways of knowing”) are Dr. Coyne’s, but to my mind they are entirely justified. True, the Maori and other indigenous peoples have learned a great deal about their environments, but much of what they “know” is palpably untrue. Indeed, many indigenous peoples, including the ancient Hebrews, tell what are essentially creationist myths and are therefore demonstrably false. These myths are also generally mutually exclusive. They may be appropriate in anthropology or history classes, but they are not science and do not belong in a science class, except conceivably alongside phlogiston in a unit on the history of science. The New Zealand policy, though obviously well-intentioned, is frankly pandering. It leads to the following question: Must we teach Iroquois “ways of knowing” in New York, Navajo “ways of knowing” in New Mexico Arizona, and astrology in Boulder, Colorado – all as if they were science?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">De-naming the Huxley College of the Environment: Comments to the WWU Board</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="De-naming the Huxley College of the Environment: Comments to the WWU Board" /><published>2021-12-09T08:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-12-09T08:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments.html">&lt;p&gt;At 3 pm on Thursday, December 9, 2021, the Western Washington University Board of Directors is having a final hearing on the proposed de-naming of the Huxley College of the Environment. In a late twist, the Board has apparently abandoned its earlier Legacy Review Task Force Report on Huxley, presumably after all of the historical mistake and distortions were pointed out. Instead, it commissioned a last-minute “&lt;a href=&quot;https://trustees.wwu.edu/meeting-materials&quot;&gt;Ad Hoc Committee Report&lt;/a&gt;”, which retreats on most of the anti-Huxley claims, and semi-acknowledges Huxley’s numerous progressive achievements, but in the end still recommends de-naming Huxley because, it judges, student perceptions trump context and truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all matters, because the WWU fight is pretty clearly an initial skirmish in a debate that will continue with the proposed denaming of the Huxley Building at Imperial College London, and other Huxley awards, lectures, and Darwiniana.  Win or lose at WWU, it is important to develop and publicize the evidence and arguments against this kind of thing. What is at stake? Huxley, Darwin, and a great number of other progressive reformers who helped enlighten our society, and, frankly, who helped to develop our modern anti-racist views, will be wiped from the public sphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of us are giving comments today. Mine are posted below. The speakers are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gragg Miller&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/people/s.j.warren&quot;&gt;Stephen Warren, Professor of Astrophysics at Imperial College London&lt;/a&gt; -- &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments.html#Warren&quot;&gt;link to comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meg Town, WWU alum and public school science teacher who has encountered similar disinformation efforts by creationists. Teacher in Washington state in a 1995 fight with creationists in 1995. -- &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments.html#MegTown&quot;&gt;link to comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://unidirectory.auckland.ac.nz/profile/nmat471&quot;&gt;Nick Matzke, Senior Lecturer in Biological Sciences, University of Auckland, New Zealand&lt;/a&gt; -- &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments.html#MatzkeComments&quot;&gt;link to comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mike Town, WWU/Huxley alum, high school science teacher, NSF Einstein Fellow, and member of the Teacher Advisory Council for the National Academies of Science.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://huxley.wwu.edu/people/steve-hollenhorst&quot;&gt;Steve Hollenhorst, Professor and Former Dean, Huxley College of the Environment, Western Washington University&lt;/a&gt; -- &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments.html#Hollenhorst&quot;&gt;link to comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://biology.wwu.edu/people/leaf&quot;&gt;David Leaf, Professor Emeritus, Biology, Western Washington.University&lt;/a&gt;. Coauthor of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://wp.wwu.edu/huxley-legacy/&quot;&gt;Response to the Legacy Review Task Force Report&lt;/a&gt; -- &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments.html#DavidLeaf&quot;&gt;link to comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The live link to listen at 3pm PST will be: &lt;a href=&quot;https://wp.wwu.edu/live/&quot;&gt;https://wp.wwu.edu/live/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My comments below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;These comments represent my personal views, not those of current or previous employers. The documentation for my claims can be found in the links in my essay on this matter:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Updated: Creationists and advocates of social justice unite to take down T.H. Huxley, a leader in educational inclusion
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html&quot;&gt;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html&lt;/a&gt; &amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Text (5 minutes to read):&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for giving me an opportunity to speak. My name is Nick Matzke, I am a Senior Lecturer in Biology at the University of Auckland, but until recently my whole career was in the USA. I am interested in society’s treatment of Thomas Henry Huxley because I have worked in the fields of science education and evolutionary science for almost 20 years. Part of that work involved the 2005 &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover&lt;/i&gt; trial, where I discovered the creationist ancestry of the so-called “intelligent design” movement, promoted by the Discovery Institute of Seattle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huxley is an inspiration for me as the original public advocate for science, science education, and science-informed liberalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;MatzkeComments&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my science-education work, I have seen first-hand the damage that can be done when ideology trumps careful scholarship. Misinformation spreads, trust in science declines, particularly in vulnerable communities - as we have seen with vaccine hesitancy, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Western’s case, we have the bizarre situation where the discussion of Huxley was dominated for over a year by social justice activists relying on anti-Huxley propaganda found on right-wing creationist and conspiracist websites, including a Discovery Institute author. Thankfully, this has finally been tacitly admitted, with the last-minute “Ad Hoc” committee report excising nearly all of the claims now proven false about Huxley being a polygenist, scientific racist, social Darwinist, eugenicist, etc. Nevertheless, this new Report still recommends the de-naming of Huxley, based on nothing but the premise that student perceptions of Huxley trump the actual facts and context of Huxley’s record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is that Huxley was not just a scientist, a progressive, an advocate for diversity and inclusion in science and science education. He was also, in the main, an anti-racist, a radical who said “the North is justified in any expenditure of blood or of money” to eliminate slavery. He was someone who pushed his culture to be better. Due diligence has not been done until the Board accepts a report that includes Huxley’s complete record on race. This absolutely &lt;i&gt;must&lt;/i&gt; include Huxley’s long battle with the scientific racist James Hunt and his Anthropological Society; and Huxley’s membership on the Jamaica Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If “James Hunt” and the “Jamaica Committee” are not familiar to you, that may be because no pro-denaming document issued by Western has yet succeeded in even discussing them! Here is a brief summary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October 1865, just after the end of the US Civil War, hundreds of Black protestors in the British colony of Jamaica marched for justice, land reform, and the vote. The British governor of Jamaica, Edward Eyre, declared martial law and authorized reprisals that killed &lt;a href=&quot;https://victorianweb.org/history/empire/westindies/eyreaffair.html&quot;&gt;439 Black Jamaicans&lt;/a&gt;, including the illegal hanging of former slave George Gordon, a member of the Jamaica House of Assembly (and nowadays a &lt;a href=&quot;https://jis.gov.jm/information/heroes/george-william-gordon/&quot;&gt;National Hero of Jamaica&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A massive multiyear controversy broke out in Britain over the carnage, but the British government refused to even prosecute Governor Eyre. The Jamaica Committee was formed to privately prosecute Eyre for murder. It was soon led by John Stuart Mill, and Huxley signed up, along with other scientists and radicals. When Darwin himself joined, Huxley wrote to thank him for joining, quote, “the right (that is &lt;u&gt;my&lt;/u&gt;) side.” (emphasis original)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ad Hoc Committee Report suggests that, quote, “Huxley’s views were firmly within the mainstream of Victorian thought,” unquote. The massive opposition to the Jamaica Committee gives lie to that claim. The Governor Eyre Defense Fund was supported by John Tyndall, John Ruskin, Thomas Carlyle, Alfred Tennyson, 40 generals, 26 admirals, 400 clergy, 6 bishops, 20 Ministers of Parliament, 71 peers of the House of Lords, and 30,000 others, including Charles Dickens. That’s right: if, during this Christmas season, you see Charles Dickens’ story about Ebenezer Scrooge, A Christmas Carol, you should keep in mind that Dickens was on the wrong side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jamaica Committee had only 800 supporters, so the Victorian elites were 40:1 against Huxley and his colleagues. Huxley took a stand against all of these elites. This is who you are de-naming, if you de-name Huxley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huxley took flack for his stand. James Hunt went after him. Hunt had been fighting with Huxley since 1863 over whether or not Black people were a transitional species between apes and whites – Huxley used words like “nonsense”, “quack”, “thoroughly disgusted”, and “imposter” in response to Hunt. When Huxley joined the Jamaica Committee, Hunt accused him of, quote, “equal-rights mania” and, quote, “Negro-mania”, and joked that Huxley would soon be saying that gorilla-hunters should be prosecuted for murder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hunt and his friends wanted to “cancel” Huxley and devote anthropology to studying the hierarchical “laws of race.” If you de-name Huxley, you are accomplishing something that Hunt never could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for the history of science and of Britain, it was Huxley that crushed Hunt. Virulent racism dominated Darwinism in countries like Germany, but its influence was weaker in the U.K., in part because of Huxley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, as we all know, the effort to dename Huxley College took off in the wake of the murder of George Floyd and the Black Lives Matter protests. And it is understandable, in the heat of legitimate rage against racial injustice and the rabid bigotry of the Trump era, that getting rid of Huxley, because his antiracism was imperfect, can seem like a way to “do something”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But consider this: what was the Jamaica Committee, if not an early expression of the principle that Black Lives Matter – that law enforcement is subject to the same laws as everyone else, that racists who murder Black people should be held accountable under the law, and that Black people deserve the same rights as everyone else? Huxley was already there in 1865, and defended that position against massive opposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does it serve justice to treat T.H. Huxley as if he were James Hunt or Governor Eyre, when he actually was their vehement opponent?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you de-name Huxley, you are de-naming an anti-racist ally, perceived as such at the time by both sides, who defended the principle that Black Lives Matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;(Other testimony)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Warren&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Comments from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/people/s.j.warren&quot;&gt;Stephen Warren, Professor of Astrophysics at Imperial College London&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello I am Stephen Warren&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am Professor of Astrophysics at Imperial College&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for letting me speak to you today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is night time at Imperial, but when I am sitting in my office I am 10 yds from the bust of Huxley, and 100yds from archeopteryx, the fossil Huxley used to show that birds evolved from small dinosaurs. At Imperial, Thomas Huxley is the scientist of whom we are most proud, more than our  Nobel Prize winners. As you know he was a great scientist, a great social reformer, and an unsurpassed educator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like you we have been examining our history and we have inherited directly from you the criticism of Huxley’s 1865 essay Emancipation: Black and White. Because of his alleged belief, in this essay, in a hierarchy of races, our History Group has recommended that the Huxley Building be renamed, and that his bust be hidden away in an archive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you might think I would be pretty annoyed with WWU for starting this problem off, but in a minute I am going to thank you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First let me tell you a little bit about what is happening here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been an very strong negative reaction to the suggestion of renaming:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;major articles have appeared in our national newspapers: &lt;i&gt;The Times&lt;/i&gt;,&lt;i&gt;The Guardian&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;The Telegraph&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;many leading scientists, including Nobel Prize winner Sir Paul Nurse, another 4 knights of the realm, and some 20 Fellows of the Royal Society have denounced the recommendations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a greatgrandson of Thomas Huxley has added his voice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and leading historians have criticised our History Group for poor scholarship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really, most people cannot understand why Imperial wants to cancel their greatest scientist, and given this reaction at the moment I am rather confident that the name will stay on the building, but one can’t be certain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now despite this rather taking over my life the reason I want to thank you is that I have learned such an enormous amount from this process, and it is this educational process that I want to focus on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe all of us have probably gone through similar steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started out being shocked in reading the first three paragraphs of Emancipation Black and White; and then I started to understand better the society Huxley lived in; and then I steadily developed a growing admiration for Huxley’s contributions to many social causes, including of course:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the abolition of slavery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;justice for Gordon in the Jamaica revolt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fighting the scientific racism of the polygenists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;university education for women&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;free education for the working classes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proper historians already knew this, but finally I reached the point, 180 degrees from where I started, where I appreciated that in reality Huxley is truly the greatest Victorian champion of inclusion: inclusion in race, inclusion in gender, and inclusion in class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If today we understand and appreciate better the importance of inclusion, let us thank Huxley for getting us half way there, rather than censor him for not getting all the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read carefully the report of the ad hoc legacy review committee. This is a clear, fair, and measured synthesis of a mass of material. And it seems clear to me that the Board have also gone through this process of understanding Huxley’s greatness as a champion of inclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in reading your report, where you seem to show all this, I was surprised and disappointed to read on the penultimate page `The Ad Hoc Committee recommends removal of the Huxley name.’ Because in doing this you are denying the opportunity for your students to receive the benefits of going through the same educational process that you have enjoyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice is set out starkly in your report starting at the bottom of p4. You can take the safe route: safe for the students and safe for the university, and cancel Huxley. The students lose because they don’t learn about Huxley, they don’t learn from Huxley, they don’t learn the lessons of history, and they don’t overcome this challenge. Or you can take the more difficult route: keep Huxley and teach all about him. The students win for all the reasons given, and the university wins because it faces up to its educational duty. I believe your students are strong enough for the challenge, and all will be grateful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fifty years is actually a long time, so Huxley is part of your history. The name was a wise choice, because he was a great scientist, and also because he was the greatest Victorian pioneer of inclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;MegTown&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Comments from Meg Town, a teacher who was involved in a 1995 battle with the Discovery Institute in Sultan School District, Washington state&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;WWU Board of Trustees Statement&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My name is Meg Town.  Thank you for the opportunity to speak.
I am against the de-naming of Huxley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a BA in environmental biology from the University of Colorado; and a master’s in education UW&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My teaching credentials are from Western&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am endorsed in biology, the physical sciences and mathematics and taught for 30 years in Washington state public school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 3 years I was privileged to work with Upward Bound under the direction of Bernie Thomas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am married to Mike Town a distinguished Huxley College alumnus, and half of my estate is currently endowed to Huxley College, in part to provide scholarships to underrepresented students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Why I’m here.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not the first time the wedge strategy has been used in Washington state to divide the public and undermine science education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my very first course at Western, Dr. Perak gave me a deep understanding of the nature of science and paradigm shifts. Science builds and refines models based on new evidence. The evidence requires rigor, repeated tests and peer review before it becomes accepted. All data is reviewed.  It cannot be cherry picked. This process is conducted in public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My intersection with attacks on science from the same people amplifying the false claim of racism against TH Huxley came about in the fall of 1995, shortly after the release of the Washington State Science Standards AKA the Science EALRs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was appointed head of the science adoption committee for the Sultan School District.  The committee consisted of teachers, an administrator, a school board member, and members of the community. I was teaching middle school science; the high school biology teacher declined the invite as she did not want to tangle with the expected attacks on her teaching of evolution.
Indeed, the school board member along with some members of the community attempted to insert the teaching of Intelligent Design (Creationism) into the science curriculum and curricular materials.  They received help and materials from the Discovery Institute of Seattle and other national creationism organizations to promote creation science and the textbook &lt;i&gt;Of Pandas and People&lt;/i&gt;. The leaders are familiar to you-Morris, Gisch, Glumaz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same folks amplifying the false claims against TH Huxley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tactics:  at a school board meeting, the husband of the school board member on my committee used a copied speech that linked the teaching of evolution with the reason for rapists.  Then he pointed at me and declared, “and there she is!” Coincidentally, The John Birch Society held a meeting in Everett.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This soon became a bigger than just about preserving science.  It was about civil rights. Indigenous members of the community enlightened me to the fact that they didn’t support science because they assimilated evolution as their way of knowing. They did not want the teaching of the Judeo-Christian creation myth in their children’s public-school classrooms.  The preservation of the Judeo-Christian Culture is the stated goal of the Discovery Institute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To counter the creationist movement and the incorrect portrayal of science to the school board and the adoption committee, I engaged with the ACLU and the National Center for Science Education to gain legal, cultural, and content understandings.  Local churches, doctors and science supporters wrote letters in support of science standards and materials without the insertion of Intelligent Design/Creationist ideas and materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a community forum on the issue, attended by 500 people, the school board fortunately unanimously adopted science only standards and materials. Dover Schools in Pennsylvania were not so lucky.  They were involved in a lawsuit stemming from the same time that was decided in 2005.  The court case decided the use of Of Pandas and People which promotes Intelligent Design, Creationism renamed, was not science and violated the establishment clause of the constitution. Disclaimers of evolution were also disallowed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sultan School District experienced a painful and unnecessary chapter in the battle against pseudoscience.  Creationists did succeed in dividing the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next fall there was a turnover of three school board members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next spring, I was involuntarily transferred to teaching math. I left to teach in the Northshore School District.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biology teacher retrained as a firefighter where she could be received as a hero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to today, the same folks are successfully inserting themselves in current challenges facing our public academic institutions.  States are adopting anti-science education legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very true that many students do not have equitable access to university programs.  There are real barriers that need to be identified and removed to correct this disparity.  Changing the name of Huxley, by adopting the false narrative that he was racist is not going to correct the equity issues.
As a teacher from era of the internet, I learned over time that it was far too easy for my students to base their conclusions on a few clicks. My refrain: “Where did you hear it and why do you believe it?” I ask that you please backcheck the sources you are using to make your decision for this public institution. A lack of due diligence can come back to harm Western and the students.  No one has this intent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Student voices do need to be heard and elevated. You have an opportunity to identify and alter policies, practices and behaviors that underly the issues of inequity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow the lead of TH Huxley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He served on the London school board and promoted &lt;b&gt;policies&lt;/b&gt; to expand public access to education and to train science teachers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;In practice&lt;/b&gt;, he taught at a working-class institution akin to Western rather than the elite Cambridge or Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;In behavior&lt;/b&gt;, he consistently wrote and spoke publicly, to the commons, in favor of abolition; the inclusion of women in education; the protection of due process for all; and in support of science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please do not diminish the integrity of Western by de-naming Huxley based on an inaccurate and incomplete portrayal of the man.  Rather, examine the &lt;b&gt;barriers&lt;/b&gt; for students. Work through a public process with students, staff and community to improve access and safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;If in the journey&lt;/b&gt; toward a more equitable institution, the renaming of Huxley will promote a new and improved mission/vision. Do so.  But follow a process with merit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not without notice that a school board in a small rural community was able to see through the rhetoric of the Discovery Institute and others to preserve the integrity of their science program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank again you for your time and considerations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Hollenhorst&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Comments from &lt;a href=&quot;https://huxley.wwu.edu/people/steve-hollenhorst&quot;&gt;Steve Hollenhorst, Professor and Former Dean, Huxley College of the Environment, Western Washington University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you, trustee Meyer. The Ad Hoc Committee states that it grounded its conclusions on the Yale Principles on Renaming, which place the principal legacy of the individual as a primary criterion. Let’s look at that legacy for Thomas H. Huxley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huxley’s legacy, simply, is that evolutionary science is true, and all the immeasurable good that followed from that transformation in the way we see the world, from medical science that combats disease with high tech vaccines and treatment, to life sciences that enable us to feed the world, saving and improving the lives of billions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Western’s legacy, sadly, will be as the public higher education institution to elevate creationist disinformation from the darkest fringe corners of American thought, giving it the legitimacy they’ve long sought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huxley’s legacy is that common descent applies to humans, and scientific justification for the oneness - and equality - of all humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our legacy will be advancing the creationist wedge strategy to undermine science, and how we fell into that trap. We commend the Committee for removing – if not actually acknowledging – the most scurrilous accusations in the Task Force Report. Yet it still includes fringe claims that Huxley held hierarchal views of race, derived from a Lyndon LaRouche operative, Discovery Institute author, and creationist historian. This despite abundant evidence of Huxley’s moral journey from typical Victorian to radical anti-racist, where he rejected such physical hierarchies, arguing instead that they were culturally imposed and enforced–often violently–by an oppressive society. Is that not an early description of what we now call systemic racism?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huxley’s legacy is democratizing an inclusive approach to science education, regardless of race, gender, or class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our legacy, is this exclusionary and divisive decision process, denying a voice for science on the task force, and all requests to meet with the task force, while affording both to Huxley critics. For me, this is the saddest moment in this story, because it set us on a censure path, where biases went unchecked, and distortions and lies internalized to confirm those biases. It’s where we failed our students by underestimating their ability to engage in a journey of learning and discover on this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, our legacy will be this denaming resolution itself, which once passed, will be proclaimed by every creationist group to advance their wedge strategy. Whatever you do, I implore you to not do it with a resolution that affirms their talking points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process has horribly divided the Huxley College community. A just-completed survey of the faculty and staff, conducted by the college leadership, is far from a ringing endorsement of either denaming or this process. My sense is that before all of this, most folks were open to a name change that could bring us into the next 50 years. After this process,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only 44% think the name of the college should be changed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In fact, a solid majority 55% feel Huxley’s views on race were progressive for the time,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And only 40% think it appropriate to use 21st century standards to judge him&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where there is strong agreement, with nearly two thirds or more agreeing, is that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Huxley should be admired for his contributions to both science and social causes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that sources in the task report were inappropriate because of their anti-science agenda&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that the creationist narrative should be denounced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that what is lost in denaming is as important as what is gained.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could have, and still can, follow a more constructive and unifying path. As Dr. Matzke urges, study this further, let’s learn from and incorporate the work going on at Imperial College. They’ve learned a lot from us, and now we can learn from them. At the same time, constitute a study group, inclusive of both social justice and science voices, tasked with mapping a forward-looking and aspirational future for the college. Re-engage our students on this. Through mutual learning, we can develop a collective set of actions to realize our DEI goals, of which a new name could be a part. I for one would support it, and it would bring the college together again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the path we’re on, I fear we will fracture further, our alumni and students will be driven away, and the college will not survive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;DavidLeaf&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Comments from &lt;a href=&quot;https://biology.wwu.edu/people/leaf&quot;&gt;David Leaf, Professor Emeritus, Biology, Western Washington.University&lt;/a&gt;. Coauthor of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://wp.wwu.edu/huxley-legacy/&quot;&gt;Response to the Legacy Review Task Force Report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;David Leaf’s Comments&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the Board of Trustees for the opportunity to comment about denaming Huxley College of the Environment. Also thanks to the Ad Hoc Committee of the Board for their work in producing a memorandum that clearly and carefully illustrates the challenges of balancing the contemporary norms of inclusion and equity with fairly evaluating historical figures. I am a retired professor of Biology at Western. I have taught courses comparing Intelligent Design Creationism with Evolution, so I am well-acquainted with creationist arguments, including arguments linking supporters of Darwinian evolution with racism. And of course, Huxley was the prominent supporter of Darwin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also worked to increase inclusion on campus. I was one of the co-authors of a successful grant proposal to the Howard Hughes Medical Institute to increase inclusion in STEM. And I had the privilege of serving on the University Strategic Plan Committee which placed inclusion as a core element of the Strategic plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am encouraged by the emphasis in memorandum about the importance of mitigating harm after a final decision about denaming. One potential harm with denaming is that it may be used by creationists to claim that Darwin’s theory of evolution is itself racist and to challenge the teaching of Darwinian evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, it is important that instructors in Biology and ESCI can clearly articulate the reasoning used to Board of Trustees to justify the denaming. This need may have been anticipated by Ad Hoc Committee with the suggestion that the Board of Trustees can mitigate the harm of denaming by clearly communicating the competing interests they needed to balance and the complexities of evaluating the issue of whether Huxley was racist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The breadth of opinion offered by the expert scholars solicited by the Legacy Review Task Force clearly indicate these complexities. While the memorandum from the Ad Hoc Committee avoids getting into weeds about the disagreements between the expert scholars, this disagreement is itself the best indication of how complex it is evaluate Huxley. Inclusion of the opinions of all the expert scholars on one or two key questions, such as whether Huxley contributed to Scientific Racism can serve as strong examples of the complexity in evaluating Huxley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the expert scholars opinions, Nicholas Rupke’s evaluation of Huxley was notable as both an outlier in many respects as well as receiving apparently greater emphasis in the memorandum footnotes. Including opinions from all of other expert scholars could help to insulate the Board from criticism of cherry picking the expert opinions, a charge that could jeopardize the perception of the Board’s fairness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would recommend not referring to Rupke’s version of Huxley’s Rule. There is no mention of Huxley’s Rule in the History of Science literature, except in Rupke’s own publications. The Huxley’s Rule known in biology refers to a rule about genetic recombination devised by Julian Huxley, TH Huxley’s grandson. Also, other expert scholars disagree with the Rupke’s premise - that Huxley’s comparative anatomical work on humans and apes led to Scientific Racism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks again for considering these remarks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Matzke</name></author><summary type="html">At 3 pm on Thursday, December 9, 2021, the Western Washington University Board of Directors is having a final hearing on the proposed de-naming of the Huxley College of the Environment. In a late twist, the Board has apparently abandoned its earlier Legacy Review Task Force Report on Huxley, presumably after all of the historical mistake and distortions were pointed out. Instead, it commissioned a last-minute “Ad Hoc Committee Report”, which retreats on most of the anti-Huxley claims, and semi-acknowledges Huxley’s numerous progressive achievements, but in the end still recommends de-naming Huxley because, it judges, student perceptions trump context and truth. This all matters, because the WWU fight is pretty clearly an initial skirmish in a debate that will continue with the proposed denaming of the Huxley Building at Imperial College London, and other Huxley awards, lectures, and Darwiniana. Win or lose at WWU, it is important to develop and publicize the evidence and arguments against this kind of thing. What is at stake? Huxley, Darwin, and a great number of other progressive reformers who helped enlighten our society, and, frankly, who helped to develop our modern anti-racist views, will be wiped from the public sphere. A number of us are giving comments today. Mine are posted below. The speakers are: Gragg Miller Stephen Warren, Professor of Astrophysics at Imperial College London -- link to comments Meg Town, WWU alum and public school science teacher who has encountered similar disinformation efforts by creationists. Teacher in Washington state in a 1995 fight with creationists in 1995. -- link to comments Nick Matzke, Senior Lecturer in Biological Sciences, University of Auckland, New Zealand -- link to comments Mike Town, WWU/Huxley alum, high school science teacher, NSF Einstein Fellow, and member of the Teacher Advisory Council for the National Academies of Science. Steve Hollenhorst, Professor and Former Dean, Huxley College of the Environment, Western Washington University -- link to comments David Leaf, Professor Emeritus, Biology, Western Washington.University. Coauthor of the Response to the Legacy Review Task Force Report -- link to comments The live link to listen at 3pm PST will be: https://wp.wwu.edu/live/ My comments below: These comments represent my personal views, not those of current or previous employers. The documentation for my claims can be found in the links in my essay on this matter: Updated: Creationists and advocates of social justice unite to take down T.H. Huxley, a leader in educational inclusion http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html &amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; Text (5 minutes to read): Thank you for giving me an opportunity to speak. My name is Nick Matzke, I am a Senior Lecturer in Biology at the University of Auckland, but until recently my whole career was in the USA. I am interested in society’s treatment of Thomas Henry Huxley because I have worked in the fields of science education and evolutionary science for almost 20 years. Part of that work involved the 2005 Kitzmiller v. Dover trial, where I discovered the creationist ancestry of the so-called “intelligent design” movement, promoted by the Discovery Institute of Seattle. Huxley is an inspiration for me as the original public advocate for science, science education, and science-informed liberalism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Acronicta americana</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/acronicta_americana.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Acronicta americana" /><published>2021-12-06T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-12-06T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/acronicta_americana</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/acronicta_americana.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Rachel Shannon&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Rachel_Dagger_Moth_Larva_PXL_20210814_161718313_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dagger moth larva&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acronicta_americana&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Acronicta americana&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; American dagger moth larva, Boulder, Colorado, August, 2021.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Rachel Shannon. Acronicta americana &amp;ndash; American dagger moth larva, Boulder, Colorado, August, 2021.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Genetic Lottery: book review</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/genetic-lottery.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Genetic Lottery: book review" /><published>2021-12-03T08:55:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-12-03T08:55:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/genetic-lottery</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/genetic-lottery.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Harden_Genetics_Cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is perhaps a caricature to claim that conservatives think all inequality is genetic, so there is nothing we can do about it. It is probably less of a caricature to claim that liberals think no inequality is genetic, so all we have to worry about is environmental. At least one purpose of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Genetic-Lottery-Matters-Social-Equality/dp/0691190801&quot;&gt;The Genetic Lottery&lt;/a&gt; by Kathryn Paige Harden, Professor of Psychology at the University of Texas at Austin, is apparently to convince liberals that people’s differing genetic inheritances may contribute to inequality (see also a &amp;lt;a href=https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2021/09/13/can-progressives-be-convinced-that-genetics-matters&amp;gt;profile of the author&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; by Gideon Lewis-Krauss in &lt;i&gt;The New Yorker&lt;/i&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not know why liberals and minority groups (they are overlapping sets) are afraid of research linking, for example, genes and intelligence, but I can guess along with Dr. Harden that it is related to their justifiable fear of eugenics. Comparing Dr. Harden’s work to eugenics is a bit like conflating nuclear power with nuclear bombs; it is right to be afraid of one, but not necessarily the other, and certainly not to be afraid of one because of the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Harden’s book is in two parts: “Taking Genetics Seriously” and “Taking Equality Seriously.” The first is a mostly scientific discussion of the relation between genes and various traits such as intelligence, which she claims partly determine your income and status. I found it a useful primer. The second part is more political and cries for mostly unspecified actions designed to increase the status of those who may be tacitly discriminated against because of a poor genetic inheritance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After dispensing with the candidate-gene hypothesis (a single gene for a complex trait), Dr. Harden moves on to the &lt;i&gt;genome-wide association study&lt;/i&gt;, or GWAS (pronounced gee-wass). The GWAS at first may sound like data dredging, but I think it is not. Rather, the GWAS samples the genomes of countless individuals and deduces which genes, and there are many, correlate with the trait in question. (They are actually single-nucleotide polymorphisms, or SNP’s, but never mind.) Researchers can then calculate a &lt;i&gt;polygenic index&lt;/i&gt; for that trait in a given individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A person with a high polygenic index for height is apt to be tall, though not necessarily tall. Likewise, a person with low polygenic index for height is apt to be short, though not necessarily short. Dr. Harden claims that liberals have no trouble accepting these two statements, but will balk if we replace &lt;i&gt;height&lt;/i&gt; with, for example, &lt;i&gt;intelligence&lt;/i&gt;. She discusses intelligence (IQ) tests and acknowledges that early on they were instruments of eugenics but observes that IQ correlates, for example, with success in school, job performance, and even life span. She insists that we can reject eugenics without rejecting intelligence tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, she is at pains to point out that the vast majority of GWAS research has been carried out on people of White [her capitalization], European descent and cannot be used to demonstrate that one ethnic group may be higher in one trait than another, because different circumstances may cause different genes to correlate with a given trait, such as education. She is pretty convincing claiming that race, at least in the United States, is socially constructed, but frankly, as a Jewish male with a Jewish wife, I might under some conditions want to be screened for Tay-Sachs disease or cystic fibrosis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found the second part of the book interesting, but perhaps a little frustrating. Dr. Harden establishes that a high polygenic index for, say, education correlates with an advanced degree but that a low polygenic index does not preclude an advanced degree. Those who inherit a high polygenic index nevertheless are lucky and have won the “lottery” in the title of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Harden argues, correctly in my judgment, that tracking in U.S. high schools may be part of what she calls a &lt;i&gt;causal chain&lt;/i&gt; that mediates between genes and educational success. Students who get into the wrong track, perhaps in part because of their genes, may find certain options closed to them. The solution to this problem is difficult and cannot be found in genetics. Consequently, at one point she flirts with a kind of utilitarian solution whereby students are chosen by lottery; a lottery, even if carried out among students who are prescreened, runs the danger of punishing the most qualified. It is, nevertheless, not inconsistent with her claim that what genes you get are entirely a matter of luck, and I suppose that sometimes your luck might be bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will not go into detail, but the author takes on Richard Herrnstein and Charles Murray, the authors of &lt;i&gt;The Bell Curve&lt;/i&gt;, which she considers inegalitarian because they consider some traits to be better than others and people who hold those traits to be superior. On the flip side, she takes issue with Robert Plomin of King’s College London, who thinks that your genetic makeup is more decisive than she does. She also cites a number of philosophers, in particular John Rawls, and argues, with him, that the truly egalitarian society would look out for the least advantaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, like the biologist and blogger &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2021/11/19/my-review-of-a-genetics-and-social-policy-book-in-the-washington-post/&quot;&gt;Jerry Coyne&lt;/a&gt;, I was mildly bemused by her ducking the question of whether the universe is deterministic. Like Dr. Coyne, I think it is. That does not stop us from applying statistical methods to the study of gases or even the roll of the dice, both of which are deterministic. In the same way, I see no reason it should stop us from applying statistical methods to genetics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I want to note that the book is well written and clear. The author draws effective analogies to illuminate her discussions, as when she compares calculating a polygenic index with rating restaurants in different cities. If all you look at is one spice (analogous to a single candidate gene), you will get a biased or wrong answer; you have to look at a variety of factors and quantify them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read the book on a Kindle, which was satisfactory except for some of the figures, for which I had to turn to my computer. When I put my editor’s hat on, I found little else to complain about. All in all, with my physicist’s hat and my editor’s hat stacked firmly one on top of the other, I can recommend the book wholeheartedly, though frankly the first part more so than the second.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">It is perhaps a caricature to claim that conservatives think all inequality is genetic, so there is nothing we can do about it. It is probably less of a caricature to claim that liberals think no inequality is genetic, so all we have to worry about is environmental. At least one purpose of The Genetic Lottery by Kathryn Paige Harden, Professor of Psychology at the University of Texas at Austin, is apparently to convince liberals that people’s differing genetic inheritances may contribute to inequality (see also a &amp;lt;a href=https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2021/09/13/can-progressives-be-convinced-that-genetics-matters&amp;gt;profile of the author&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; by Gideon Lewis-Krauss in The New Yorker). I do not know why liberals and minority groups (they are overlapping sets) are afraid of research linking, for example, genes and intelligence, but I can guess along with Dr. Harden that it is related to their justifiable fear of eugenics. Comparing Dr. Harden’s work to eugenics is a bit like conflating nuclear power with nuclear bombs; it is right to be afraid of one, but not necessarily the other, and certainly not to be afraid of one because of the other. Dr. Harden’s book is in two parts: “Taking Genetics Seriously” and “Taking Equality Seriously.” The first is a mostly scientific discussion of the relation between genes and various traits such as intelligence, which she claims partly determine your income and status. I found it a useful primer. The second part is more political and cries for mostly unspecified actions designed to increase the status of those who may be tacitly discriminated against because of a poor genetic inheritance.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">William Dembski on why ID has and has not succeeded</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/Dembski-Gauging-Success.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="William Dembski on why ID has and has not succeeded" /><published>2021-11-30T18:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-11-30T18:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/Dembski-Gauging-Success</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/Dembski-Gauging-Success.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/DembskiGaugingSuccess.png&quot; alt=&quot;[Dembski Youtube]&quot; /&gt;
William Dembski summarizes the status of ID (link to YouTube video is below)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Discovery Institute had released a YouTube video of William Dembski’s 30-minute talk last March at the
DI’s Dallas Conference on Science and Faith.  This conference &lt;strike&gt;, whose other talks have not yet been made
available,&lt;/strike&gt; was supposed to occur on February 20 but was postponed until March 13 and made into mostly a virtual
conference.  There was an in-person gathering at the Denton Bible Church, and Dembski’s
talk looks like it was in-person.  The
other speakers were Marcos Eberlin, Stephen Meyer, Casey Luskin, and Melissa Cain Travis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interest in this talk is mainly in what he describes as the current state of the Intelligent
Design movement.  He feels that its intellectual arguments have been a substantial success, but
that society has mostly not been persuaded to accept them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will find the Youtube video of his 30-minute talk on “Gauging the Success of Intelligent
Design” &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/mDD7pARRfm4&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.   Take a look.  The talk is only 30 minutes
long.  Which arguments does he consider to be valid?  The part about how successful ID
has been starts 20 minutes in, but there is much before that that illuminates his
perspective …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I see there is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A broad endorsement of Michael Behe’s arguments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The assertion that there is much that looks like Design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A statement that information cannot appear in genomes without having been first created by Design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular he says that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So I think we’ve got a good case.  We’ve got a theoretical case in terms of design detection, which has been developed even further in terms of ideas called conservation of information or evolutionary informatics where the idea is that insofar as evolution can work at all, it is because there has to be prior information, basically the design problem has to be folded in there from the start.  It’s not that you get something for nothing.  And this is the beauty, from as far as the material[ist?] is concerned.  It’s kind of a socialism of biology: you get a free lunch,  You don’t have to do the design work because you get the design up because natural selection is so brilliant, can do all of this.  And what intelligent design is saying, no, you’ve got to do the accounting, and at the end of the day all the bills need to be paid. The currency of those bills is information, and you’ve got to account for it, the type of information you need to build these systems, you cannot simply get them for free.  It requires an act of intelligence.  …. My sense is that we have the better case by far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So I do think that we have been successful [in] the Intelligent Design movement at uncovering the truth of design in nature and giving it scientific teeth. I think that’s been important ….  that there is real solid scientific evidence for design in nature … Darwinian processes don’t have the power to create these sorts of systems, and we can show you why it breaks down, why the math doesn’t work, why the evidence from biology doesn’t work.  So in that sense I think we’ve been successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remainder of his argument is that ID has not been successful in persuading people, and that a better
sales job needs to be done.  The implication is that this is because there has been unfair treatment of
the ID argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But don’t just read these quotes, listen to the whole thing and let us know what you hear and what you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Correction: the talks at the 2021 Dallas Conference on Science and Faith are all available on YouTube, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLR8eQzfCOiS0JHtYZoI4K-NsoFZh2QcOG&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;here&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or just use YouTube’s search: Dallas Conference on Science and Faith 2021&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">William Dembski summarizes the status of ID (link to YouTube video is below) The Discovery Institute had released a YouTube video of William Dembski’s 30-minute talk last March at the DI’s Dallas Conference on Science and Faith. This conference , whose other talks have not yet been made available, was supposed to occur on February 20 but was postponed until March 13 and made into mostly a virtual conference. There was an in-person gathering at the Denton Bible Church, and Dembski’s talk looks like it was in-person. The other speakers were Marcos Eberlin, Stephen Meyer, Casey Luskin, and Melissa Cain Travis. The interest in this talk is mainly in what he describes as the current state of the Intelligent Design movement. He feels that its intellectual arguments have been a substantial success, but that society has mostly not been persuaded to accept them. You will find the Youtube video of his 30-minute talk on “Gauging the Success of Intelligent Design” here. Take a look. The talk is only 30 minutes long. Which arguments does he consider to be valid? The part about how successful ID has been starts 20 minutes in, but there is much before that that illuminates his perspective …</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sun dog</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/sun-dog.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sun dog" /><published>2021-11-22T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-11-22T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/sun-dog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/sun-dog.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Nicky Turner&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Nicky_Turner_Sun_Dog_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sun dog&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sun_dog&quot;&gt;Sun dog&lt;/a&gt;. The photographer writes, &quot;The picture was taken on the terrace here at our house, &lt;a href=&quot;https://villasantalucia.net/&quot;&gt;Villa Santa Lucia&lt;/a&gt;, about 15 km south of Livorno on the Etruscan coast of Italy,&quot; October, 2021.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sun dog is formed from refraction by hexagonal ice crystals held with their axes vertical by hydrodynamic forces (drop a small scrap of paper, and you will see how it remains mostly horizontal). If the air is not still and the crystals are not oriented, you may see the full &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/22%C2%B0_halo&quot;&gt;22&amp;deg; halo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Nicky Turner. Sun dog. The photographer writes, &quot;The picture was taken on the terrace here at our house, Villa Santa Lucia, about 15 km south of Livorno on the Etruscan coast of Italy,&quot; October, 2021. The sun dog is formed from refraction by hexagonal ice crystals held with their axes vertical by hydrodynamic forces (drop a small scrap of paper, and you will see how it remains mostly horizontal). If the air is not still and the crystals are not oriented, you may see the full 22&amp;deg; halo.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Your brain as a walnut</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/your-brain-as-walnut.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Your brain as a walnut" /><published>2021-11-19T10:55:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-11-19T10:55:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/your-brain-as-walnut</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/your-brain-as-walnut.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Josh_Axe_Moron_6.53_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Josh Axe in action&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6Swksd9ivRs&quot;&gt;Josh Axe in action&lt;/a&gt;. Here he seems to think that a reduction of 1/4 is 40&amp;nbsp;%. &lt;small&gt;Credit: Addicted Tolgnerance, &quot;Dr. Josh Axe is a Moron,&quot; fair use.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other day, I (MY) received note from the Kentucky paleontologist Dan Phelps. The note was an anguished letter that he had sent to the PBS affiliate Kentucky Educational Television and was headed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;big&gt;If someone dies, what will KET say?&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What anguished Mr. Phelps was the station’s airing of a program called “Ancient Remedies” by a quack nutritionist (or something) called Josh Axe. It seems that KET is not the only affiliate that runs his “advice”: so do Rhode Island PBS, New Hampshire PBS, Arizona Public Media, Duluth-Superior Area Educational Television, Kansas Public Television, Blue Ridge PBS, Delta College Public Media, PBS Western Reserve, and I suppose more, but I gave up looking. In my own area, it looks like PBS12, Colorado Public Television, carries the program, but Rocky Mountain PBS does not. May we suggest that after you read this post you check your own PBS affiliate and if appropriate complain about their airing this nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had never heard of Josh Axe, so I looked him up and watched – no, endured an hour-long program &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FxIbJEhMrzQ&quot;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;. I did not take notes, but what I came away with was&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Cancer is a psychosomatic disease (my interpretation of what he said)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Certain personality types and get breast cancer on the left side, others on the right, depending on some mumbo jumbo about qi (chi)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The plural of anecdote is data; Chinese medicine is 5000 (?) years old and has accumulated plenty of data (he does not seem to have heard of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confirmation_bias&quot;&gt;confirmation bias&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Western medicine believes in evidence (again, my interpretation; I do not remember his precise wording)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And, finally, like cures like, so walnuts are good for your brain, or something like that, reminiscent of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homeopathy&quot;&gt;homeopathy&lt;/a&gt;, only worse &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now yield the floor to my colleague Dan Phelps, who started this discussion with the following letter to KET:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back in August, during a fundraiser, Kentucky &lt;i&gt;Educational&lt;/i&gt; Television aired an infomercial for “Dr. Josh Axe,” a chiropractor. He touted his version of “ancient remedies.” Every ten seconds or so of his spiel, the camera did a close-up of the grinning/nodding zombies in the audience nodding their heads in total agreement. Some of the things he said concerning diet made sense, but why couldn’t the PBS station get someone reputable to say that? Most of the “ancient remedies” touted seem to be based on symbolism. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Tomatoes have four chambers, just like your heart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mushrooms are the same shape as adrenal glands&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carrots in section look like the eyes' irises&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walnuts look like brains&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celery looks like bones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beets are the color of blood …&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;The color of the food will tell you what part of the body it will heal&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

The website “The Encyclopedia of American Loons” did a &lt;a href=&quot;http://americanloons.blogspot.com/2021/10/2487-josh-axe.html&quot;&gt;nice entry on Axe.&lt;/a&gt;  

Today I was looking at KET’s schedule and found they are showing more of Axe’s infomercials in late November.

Why KET? Why? If someone dies, what will KET say?&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To clarify (MY again), in the interview that I watched, Mr. Axe stated explicitly that walnuts were good for your brain because they looked like your brain. He added that people who accepted the theory of evolution would not understand, because when God created the universe, he set it up that way deliberately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kali Mattheus, a Programming Specialist at KET, blissfully unaware that there’s no degree known as doctor of natural medicine, responded thus:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Thank you for your additional comments. We appreciate your thoughts and concerns. After your initial email we reviewed the program and talked with the distributor. We confirmed [that] Dr. Axe’s credentials as a doctor of natural medicine and certified nutrition specialist more than qualify him to speak on the subject of diet. Also, as mentioned in a previous email there are disclaimers recommending viewers speak with their primary care physicians prior to making any changes to their diets. We will continue to review programs as they are submitted.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Phelps broadcasts a lot of his e-mails; Vincent M. Cassone, Jack and Linda Gill Professor of Biology at the University of Kentucky, which I take to be an endowed chair, was incensed by Mr. Mattheus’s response and wrote,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am stunned by your answer to Mr. Dan Phelps, a highly regarded science educator, expressing his concern about false and probably deliberately misleading statements made by chiropractor Josh Axe on your station, which, based upon your name, presumes to be educational. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, contrary to your statements otherwise, Josh Axe has virtually no credentials in terms of medical advice, including diet. A very quick perusal of Dr. Axe’s websites shows he is a chiropractor, which qualifies him to adjust the spine, and is a practitioner of “naturopathic medicine” in Tennessee, which has proven to be quackery over and over. He even lists a fake university, Exodus Clinic, as the institution where he received his “doctor of natural medicine.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among his “credentials” on his website, he lists his height and weight. I suspect these data are the most accurate of his credentials. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the dietary advice has some support in mainstream diet fields, but adherence to a keto diet is not supported by many registered dieticians, who actually have credentials to prescribe dietary advice. Secondly, many of the statements he has made on his program, as catalogued by Mr. Phelps, are categorically false. Tomatoes do not &lt;i&gt;always&lt;/i&gt; have four chambers. The most common anatomy among tomatoes has 5 seed “chambers.” Mushrooms do &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; look like adrenal glands. Carrots in cross-section do &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; look like irises.  Etc., etc. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These inaccuracies could just be curious, even humorous. &lt;i&gt;However&lt;/i&gt;, statements proposed by Mr. Axe are &lt;i&gt;dangerous&lt;/i&gt;. He video lectures that “cancer is caused by two things: Deficiency and Toxicity.” He actually says that Splenda (sucralose) can break down into chlorine. This is patently untrue. &lt;/p&gt;
 
&lt;p&gt;I am stunned, very disappointed, that your station would promote this ridiculous accumulation of ignorance. I’m outraged. I strongly encourage you to see &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/6Swksd9ivRs&quot;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt; that completely debunks Axe. [Reproduced with permission.] &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I (MY) watched the video, and it does. I usually shy away from invective, but I can only conclude that Mr. Axe has a walnut for a brain. Or else he is a conscious faker.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps and Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Josh Axe in action. Here he seems to think that a reduction of 1/4 is 40&amp;nbsp;%. Credit: Addicted Tolgnerance, &quot;Dr. Josh Axe is a Moron,&quot; fair use. The other day, I (MY) received note from the Kentucky paleontologist Dan Phelps. The note was an anguished letter that he had sent to the PBS affiliate Kentucky Educational Television and was headed If someone dies, what will KET say? What anguished Mr. Phelps was the station’s airing of a program called “Ancient Remedies” by a quack nutritionist (or something) called Josh Axe. It seems that KET is not the only affiliate that runs his “advice”: so do Rhode Island PBS, New Hampshire PBS, Arizona Public Media, Duluth-Superior Area Educational Television, Kansas Public Television, Blue Ridge PBS, Delta College Public Media, PBS Western Reserve, and I suppose more, but I gave up looking. In my own area, it looks like PBS12, Colorado Public Television, carries the program, but Rocky Mountain PBS does not. May we suggest that after you read this post you check your own PBS affiliate and if appropriate complain about their airing this nonsense. I had never heard of Josh Axe, so I looked him up and watched – no, endured an hour-long program here. I did not take notes, but what I came away with was Cancer is a psychosomatic disease (my interpretation of what he said) Certain personality types and get breast cancer on the left side, others on the right, depending on some mumbo jumbo about qi (chi) The plural of anecdote is data; Chinese medicine is 5000 (?) years old and has accumulated plenty of data (he does not seem to have heard of confirmation bias) Western medicine believes in evidence (again, my interpretation; I do not remember his precise wording) And, finally, like cures like, so walnuts are good for your brain, or something like that, reminiscent of homeopathy, only worse I now yield the floor to my colleague Dan Phelps, who started this discussion with the following letter to KET:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fired for endangering others</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/fired-for-endangering.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fired for endangering others" /><published>2021-11-08T12:50:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-11-08T12:50:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/fired-for-endangering</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/fired-for-endangering.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Fired_For_My_Beliefs.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Man holding sign&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An observant reader sent us &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/aigkenham/photos/4898302493533401&quot;&gt;this picture&lt;/a&gt;, which was the subject of a tweet by Ken Ham of AIG, and noted that the caption should have been&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;big&gt;&quot;Fired because my beliefs endangered the health and safety of others.&quot;&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He further commented,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seriously, it doesn't bother AiG to fire or not to hire people because they don't believe what the organization requires (this behavior is legal under the Civil Rights Act, BTW, if carefully structured). SO why do they take such umbrage when someone else does the same thing?&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;And, there certainly is a clear and present danger to acting on these [anti-vaccination] beliefs, whereas I would be hard pressed to find such a danger among, say, other Christian denominations that do not follow the bizarre twists that AiG insists on. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may read about First Liberty Institute (mentioned in the figure) &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_Liberty_Institute&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">An observant reader sent us this picture, which was the subject of a tweet by Ken Ham of AIG, and noted that the caption should have been &quot;Fired because my beliefs endangered the health and safety of others.&quot; He further commented, Seriously, it doesn't bother AiG to fire or not to hire people because they don't believe what the organization requires (this behavior is legal under the Civil Rights Act, BTW, if carefully structured). SO why do they take such umbrage when someone else does the same thing? And, there certainly is a clear and present danger to acting on these [anti-vaccination] beliefs, whereas I would be hard pressed to find such a danger among, say, other Christian denominations that do not follow the bizarre twists that AiG insists on. You may read about First Liberty Institute (mentioned in the figure) here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">White rainbow</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/white-rainbow.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="White rainbow" /><published>2021-11-08T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-11-08T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/white-rainbow</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/white-rainbow.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Paul Strode&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Strode_White_Rainbow_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;White rainbow&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fog_bow&quot;&gt;White rainbow, or fog bow&lt;/a&gt;, overlooking the Flatirons, Boulder Colorado, October, 2021. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This splendid picture by Paul Strode shows a white rainbow, or a fog bow. The white rainbow is seen when the droplets are very small, as in a fog. In that case the angle of diffraction is at least much as the angle of refraction, so the colors overlap, and the rainbow appears white. M. Minnaert, in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Nature-Light-Colour-Dover-Sciences/dp/0486201961/&quot;&gt;The nature of light and color in the open air&lt;/a&gt; (&amp;#167;128), notes that the width of the white rainbow may be as much as twice the width of the ordinary rainbow. Additionally, the colors may be reversed, because red light is diffracted more than blue, whereas it is refracted less. In Dr. Strode's picture, we see a &quot;conventional&quot; rainbow at the left merging into a white arc where, presumably, the droplets are smaller. The arc is about the same width as the colored section, which hints that the droplets are sized so that diffraction barely covers refraction. In consequence, we do not see any color, reversed or otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, contrary to popular descriptions &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.popsci.com/where-do-white-rainbows-come-from/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and (especially) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.realsimple.com/holidays-entertaining/entertaining/seasonal-events/white-rainbow&quot;&gt;there&lt;/a&gt;, the light is always refracted by the droplets, but sometimes diffraction plays a role as well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Paul Strode. White rainbow, or fog bow, overlooking the Flatirons, Boulder Colorado, October, 2021. This splendid picture by Paul Strode shows a white rainbow, or a fog bow. The white rainbow is seen when the droplets are very small, as in a fog. In that case the angle of diffraction is at least much as the angle of refraction, so the colors overlap, and the rainbow appears white. M. Minnaert, in The nature of light and color in the open air (&amp;#167;128), notes that the width of the white rainbow may be as much as twice the width of the ordinary rainbow. Additionally, the colors may be reversed, because red light is diffracted more than blue, whereas it is refracted less. In Dr. Strode's picture, we see a &quot;conventional&quot; rainbow at the left merging into a white arc where, presumably, the droplets are smaller. The arc is about the same width as the colored section, which hints that the droplets are sized so that diffraction barely covers refraction. In consequence, we do not see any color, reversed or otherwise. Incidentally, contrary to popular descriptions here and (especially) there, the light is always refracted by the droplets, but sometimes diffraction plays a role as well.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is common descent untestable?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/is-common-descent-untestable.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is common descent untestable?" /><published>2021-11-06T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-11-06T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/is-common-descent-untestable</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/is-common-descent-untestable.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/300Px-Pay_the_bill.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Paying the bill]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Illustration EN&amp;amp;ST uses for &quot;paying the bill&quot;, from Wikimedia Commons&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ever-astonishing site Evolution News and Science Today has astonished once again.  Finding a paper in the
scientific literature which provides evidence for a horizontal gene transfer event, they declare that
this shows that &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2021/11/case-study-inadvertently-shows-why-universal-common-descent-is-untestable/&quot;&gt;common descent is an untestable
concept&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper is in the journal Molecular Biology and Evolution: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mbe/advance-article/doi/10.1093/molbev/msab317/6420225&quot;&gt;Citrullination was introduced into animals by horizontal gene transfer from
cyanobacteria&lt;/a&gt;  (Disclosure: I have
published in that journal, and served as President of its parent society).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper straightforwardly provides evidence from molecular phylogenies and functional studies that the enzyme
peptidylarginine deaminase has a distribution discordant with the overall phylogeny of life, in that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The animal and cyanobacterial PADI proteins share functionally relevant primary and tertiary synapomorphic sequences
that are distinct from a second PADI type present in fungi and actinobacteria …. The consilience of evidence
indicates that PADIs were introduced from cyanobacteria into animals by horizontal gene transfer (HGT).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aha! exclaims EN&amp;amp;ST. About Universal Common Descent, they note that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;UCD is often held to be testable via the counterfactual of “genes and proteins might have been discovered in
 groups where they should not exist”. In other words, if we observed genes and proteins occurring in the TOL,
 with unequivocal homology to the same sequences found elsewhere in phylogenetically distant or divergent groups, UCD
 would be in trouble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And indeed they think that horizontal gene transfer is an added assumption that needs to be verified, and that if we
invoke it in this way, UCD is in trouble:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;UCD’s big entourage only becomes a problem when its members always pay the fines for UCD’s failed
predictions, pick up UCD’s tab at restaurants and hotels, and generally cover the empirical shortfalls of UCD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and they end with the declaration that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If ever anyone needed evidence of the
untestability of UCD, papers like this provide it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The even-more-astonishing Denyse O’Leary (“News” at Uncommon Descent) also &lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/darwinism/a-friend-says-this-paper-illustrates-that-universal-common-descent-is-untestable/&quot;&gt;made the same point&lt;/a&gt;,
attributing it to “a friend”; one of the two of them also seems to be a friend of EN&amp;amp;ST.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could argue with these dramatic conclusions, but the commenters here at PT might well do a better job.  So let’s hear what
you have to say.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Illustration EN&amp;amp;ST uses for &quot;paying the bill&quot;, from Wikimedia Commons The ever-astonishing site Evolution News and Science Today has astonished once again. Finding a paper in the scientific literature which provides evidence for a horizontal gene transfer event, they declare that this shows that common descent is an untestable concept The paper is in the journal Molecular Biology and Evolution: Citrullination was introduced into animals by horizontal gene transfer from cyanobacteria (Disclosure: I have published in that journal, and served as President of its parent society). The paper straightforwardly provides evidence from molecular phylogenies and functional studies that the enzyme peptidylarginine deaminase has a distribution discordant with the overall phylogeny of life, in that The animal and cyanobacterial PADI proteins share functionally relevant primary and tertiary synapomorphic sequences that are distinct from a second PADI type present in fungi and actinobacteria …. The consilience of evidence indicates that PADIs were introduced from cyanobacteria into animals by horizontal gene transfer (HGT). Aha! exclaims EN&amp;amp;ST. About Universal Common Descent, they note that UCD is often held to be testable via the counterfactual of “genes and proteins might have been discovered in groups where they should not exist”. In other words, if we observed genes and proteins occurring in the TOL, with unequivocal homology to the same sequences found elsewhere in phylogenetically distant or divergent groups, UCD would be in trouble. And indeed they think that horizontal gene transfer is an added assumption that needs to be verified, and that if we invoke it in this way, UCD is in trouble: UCD’s big entourage only becomes a problem when its members always pay the fines for UCD’s failed predictions, pick up UCD’s tab at restaurants and hotels, and generally cover the empirical shortfalls of UCD. and they end with the declaration that If ever anyone needed evidence of the untestability of UCD, papers like this provide it. The even-more-astonishing Denyse O’Leary (“News” at Uncommon Descent) also made the same point, attributing it to “a friend”; one of the two of them also seems to be a friend of EN&amp;amp;ST.</summary></entry></feed>