<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-07-12T04:36:49-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">The 100th Anniversary of the Scopes Monkey Trial is Here!</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/Scopes100_in_Nashville.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 100th Anniversary of the Scopes Monkey Trial is Here!" /><published>2025-07-09T18:01:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-09T18:01:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/Scopes100_in_Nashville</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/Scopes100_in_Nashville.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Matzke_Scopes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Nick Matzke at the Dayton County Courthouse, site of the 1925 Scopes Monkey Trial]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Nick Matzke at the Dayton County Courthouse where the Scopes Trial was held in 1925. (photo from ~2014)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One-hundred years ago, on a hot and humid summer day in the Tennessee River Valley in southeast Tennessee, teacher John Scopes, the ACLU, Clarence Darrow, and various lawyers and scientists tried to challenge the state of Tennessee’s ban on teaching human evolution. The national press descended on Dayton, and the audio was broadcast across the country in the first “Trial of the Century.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expert testimony was blocked, and Darrow, Scopes’s defense attorney, in frustration, asked to call prosecutor William Jennings Bryan (leader of the anti-evolution crusade, three-time presidential candidate, former Secretary of State, and populist politician) as a witness. Somehow this was allowed, and due to the heat, the proceedings were moved out onto the lawn. Darrow examined Bryan on the Bible and evolution, Bryan held his own, both sides concluded they were right, the national press lampooned the fundamentalists, but Scopes was convicted and fined (overturned on a technicality in 1927), and Bryan’s laws against teaching evolution remained on the books in many states and local jurisdictions until overturned by the 1968 &lt;i&gt;Epperson v. Arkansas&lt;/i&gt; Supreme Court case. The term “creation science” emerged right around then (Matzke 2009), rebranding Flood Geology and young-earth creationism as science. As that strategy failed in the 1981 &lt;i&gt;McLean vs. Arkansas&lt;/i&gt; case, creationists began work on a book called “Creation Biology”, which later became &lt;i&gt;Of Pandas and People&lt;/i&gt;, the original vehicle promoting “intelligent design” in schools.  The history of &lt;i&gt;Pandas&lt;/i&gt; was uncovered in the 2005 &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover&lt;/i&gt; case, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2005/11/missing-link-cd.html&quot;&gt;covered right here on the Panda’s Thumb blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so here we are in 2025! Today, I am finishing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hfsp.org/aam&quot;&gt;2025 Human Frontier Science Program (HFSP) meeting&lt;/a&gt; in Melbourne, Australia, where myself and collaborators talked about our research (my bit: a &lt;a href=&quot;http://phylo.wikidot.com/local--files/nicholas-j-matzke/Matzke_2025_HFSP_poster_v5.pdf&quot;&gt;Structural Phylogenetics of the Bacterial Flagellum&lt;/a&gt; poster). And I am getting on the plane and flying to Dallas, then Nashville, for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/KvDv19.html&quot;&gt;Scopes 100th meeting at Vanderbilt&lt;/a&gt;, which will also have a bunch of the people involved in &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover&lt;/i&gt;. While the antievolution issue has receded somewhat, challenges to science and science education are ever-present and can come from either political side, so I think the lessons of the Scopes Trial and its descendants are ever present. The main question is whether or not we will learn from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all of that, I am flying to Oklahoma to visit my 101-year old grandmother, who was born before the Scopes Trial and has seen everything since. Ironically she played a nontrivial role in my personal history, as it was my grandmother that sent me creationist books when I was a kid, which (as I eventually worked out) meant there were two radically different views of the history of life and humans out there. I remember being interested enough that I read Doug Futuyma’s (1982) &lt;i&gt;Science on Trial: The Case for Evolution&lt;/i&gt; in high school (perhaps 1991 or so). So when I got to college and took a course on Postmodernism and Science (in 1995), and discovered that the fundamentalists in the class actually really liked postmodernism even though it was a Leftist idea, I was well-prepared to make the case for evolution and science for both sides. In 1996, Behe’s book &lt;i&gt;Darwin’s Black Box&lt;/i&gt; was published and the ID movement was taking off. Around 1999 I got heavily involved in the online pro-evolution groups, and got to know (online) such talk.origins stalwarts as Wes Elsberry, John Wilkins, and Ian Musgrave.  In 2002 and 2003 I wrote some weighty talk.origins and talkdesign.org FAQs on favorite ID arguments, this lead to my working at NCSE, then the &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller&lt;/i&gt; case happened, then I got into Berkeley and got a Ph.D., then a series of postdocs and eventually I somehow got a job in New Zealand and occasionally find myself involved in not entirely dissimilar debates there. And also somehow found collaborators that wanted to work on the bacterial flagellum, and somehow happened on some new methods using protein structure to enhance phylogenies that are letting us make progress that was previously not imaginable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been quite a ride and I can’t quite believe it all happened the way it did. It seems like it would be a halfway-decent book, but as I now have 3 young daughters, good luck with that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I will try to blog the high points of the Scopes meeting and get some photos of participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S.: There has been some great press coverage of the &lt;i&gt;Scopes&lt;/i&gt; 100th, here are some of the links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NPR story on 100 years after Scopes, quoting Ken Miller
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/player/embed/nx-s1-5430760/nx-s1-5513367-1?fbclid=IwY2xjawLckNVleHRuA2FlbQIxMABicmlkETA2RDJLcDFaOGJFV1hueVVaAR4OSnbXt6oKbnutC83LrsdVgIKcYz8zSgJL0e958GUIS0hDTxn7v4HHaAw4CQ_aem_9Qj38T4Fq9IB3W8NP2pm_Q&quot;&gt;https://www.npr.org/player/embed/nx-s1-5430760/nx-s1-5513367-1?fbclid=IwY2xjawLckNVleHRuA2FlbQIxMABicmlkETA2RDJLcDFaOGJFV1hueVVaAR4OSnbXt6oKbnutC83LrsdVgIKcYz8zSgJL0e958GUIS0hDTxn7v4HHaAw4CQ_aem_9Qj38T4Fq9IB3W8NP2pm_Q&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NPR stories on 80 years after &lt;i&gt;Scopes&lt;/i&gt;, quoting…Ken Miller!
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/series/4726537/the-scopes-monkey-trial-80-years-later&quot;&gt;https://www.npr.org/series/4726537/the-scopes-monkey-trial-80-years-later&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some amazing video clips of the the &lt;i&gt;Scopes&lt;/i&gt; Trial, which I had forgotten existed, have been posted to Twitter, e.g.: &lt;a href=&quot;https://x.com/frad_fradi/status/1943268572634968422&quot;&gt;https://x.com/frad_fradi/status/1943268572634968422&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;b&gt;A century after a man was convicted of teaching evolution, the debate on religion in schools rages&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://apnews.com/article/religion-schools-church-state-scopes-monkey-trial-054773ed76ef36836e2f180d8d8d2802?utm_source=twitter&amp;amp;utm_medium=share&quot;&gt;https://apnews.com/article/religion-schools-church-state-scopes-monkey-trial-054773ed76ef36836e2f180d8d8d2802?utm_source=twitter&amp;amp;utm_medium=share&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
100 years after Scopes ‘Monkey Trial,’ religion in public schools hits courts again&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pennlive.com/nation-world/2025/07/100-years-after-scopes-monkey-trial-religion-in-public-schools-hits-courts-again.html?utm_campaign=pennlive_sf&amp;amp;utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_source=twitter&quot;&gt;https://www.pennlive.com/nation-world/2025/07/100-years-after-scopes-monkey-trial-religion-in-public-schools-hits-courts-again.html?utm_campaign=pennlive_sf&amp;amp;utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_source=twitter&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
Though a brief legal circus, the trial inflamed social divisions. Conservatives and fundamentalists in the Midwest and South felt mocked by those they considered liberal, East Coast elites. “They were humiliated,” Tuttle says. “That’s internalized, and it carries through.”
&lt;br /&gt;
In the 1940s, tensions flared with a school funding case before the Supreme Court. They returned in the 1960s when the justices ruled against school-sponsored prayer and Bible readings. It was upsetting, Tuttle says, to conservative Christians who saw schools as a source of morality.
&lt;br /&gt;
“The link you see with the Scopes case is a sense of alienation and devaluing of what civic experience means to them,” he says.
&lt;br /&gt;
Suzanne Rosenblith, an expert on religion in public education at the University at Buffalo in New York, sees the wave of court cases as primarily First Amendment tensions.
&lt;br /&gt;
“Your argument for removing something can be seen as ensuring that Congress makes no law respecting the establishment of religion. And my wanting something included, that’s my way of exercising my right to religious freedom,” she says. “And it could be on the same issue.”
&lt;br /&gt;
A lesson to be learned from the last 100 years, Rosenblith says, is that America remains a pluralist democracy and needs to be approached as such.
&lt;br /&gt;
“All sides are going to win some and lose some,” she says. “But how can we treat each other, especially those with whom we disagree on these significant issues, how do we treat each other more seriously?”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;b&gt;100 years after Scopes Monkey Trial, a new religious culture war emerges in Oklahoma&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
https://www.oklahoman.com/story/news/education/2025/07/10/ryan-walters-oklahoma-culture-war-religious-charter-school-bible-mandate/84076370007/
&lt;br /&gt;
A century after the famed Scopes Monkey Trial in Tennessee brought the concept of teaching evolution in public schools into a courtroom, thus testing cultural and religious norms of that era, another state is pushing to put the Bible back into the regular classroom rotation.
&lt;br /&gt;
Led by firebrand state schools Superintendent Ryan Walters, Oklahoma is forcing courts — as they did in Tennessee in 1925 — to wrestle with the thorny question of just how much religion is permissible in public schools.
&lt;br /&gt;
From a U.S. Supreme Court case involving what would have been the first public religious charter school in the nation, to a Bible-teaching edict issued for schools by Walters, to new social studies academic standards infused with references to Christianity and 2020 election-denial language, Oklahoma — a ruby-red state politically — is at the center of a national conversation about Christian nationalism being taught to students.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Science, scripture &amp;amp; Scopes: 100 years since Dayton, Tennessee trial captivated the nation&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://chattanoogacw.com/news/local/science-scripture-and-scopes-100-years-later-evolution-creationism-debate-darwin-schools-rhea-county-tennessee-1925-inherit-the-wind-clarence-darrow-william-jennings-bryan-john-scopes-schoolteacher&quot;&gt;https://chattanoogacw.com/news/local/science-scripture-and-scopes-100-years-later-evolution-creationism-debate-darwin-schools-rhea-county-tennessee-1925-inherit-the-wind-clarence-darrow-william-jennings-bryan-john-scopes-schoolteacher&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

[This story has lots of great photos / videos, and quotes from locals]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;b&gt;Trial of the century: Why 100 years later, the Scopes case still matters&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tennessean.com/story/news/education/2025/07/10/scopes-monkey-trial-100th-anniversary-dayton-tennessee/83395548007/&quot;&gt;https://www.tennessean.com/story/news/education/2025/07/10/scopes-monkey-trial-100th-anniversary-dayton-tennessee/83395548007/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

The trial that followed was heated. Spectators swarmed in from around the country to see the legendary lawyers battle over creationism, evolution and the role of religion in government.&lt;br /&gt;

The courtroom was so overcrowded at one point that town officials warned the building might collapse, prompting the judge to set up a temporary court outside to appease the masses.&lt;br /&gt;


Audiences across the country tuned in to the trial as well, both through radio and newspaper. The trial was the first to be broadcast live on radio in American history, with Chicago's WGN Radio spending $1,000 a day — equivalent to over $18,000 a day in today's economy — to run cables from Chicago, Illinois to Dayton, Tennessee to provide live gavel-to-gavel coverage of the &quot;trial of the century.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;

Famous journalist and commentator Henry Louis “H.L.” Mencken, who wrote for the Baltimore Sun at the time of the trial, wrote daily columns for the paper covering the ordeal and famously dubbed the proceedings as &quot;The Monkey Trial.”&lt;br /&gt;

The expansive audience placed pressure on the lawyers. After facing significant roadblocks in his defense, Darrow changed tactics and called Bryan to the stand in an attempt to prove Bryan’s literal interpretation of the Bible was unfit to base laws on.&lt;br /&gt;

Clarence Darrow questions William Jennings Bryan in Scopes trial.
“Bryan had a lot of difficulty with (Darrow’s questions), and many of them were not very subtle or sophisticated questions,” Branch said. “One of the questions that Darrow asked was ‘Where did Cain, the second son of Adam and Eve, find his wife?’ And Bryan had no kind of answer for this. He said ‘I leave the atheist to look for her.’”&lt;br /&gt;

The grueling examination left Bryan scrambling and humiliated.&lt;br /&gt;

“Darrow was quite relentless, and in many people's opinion, especially the big city reporters, Bryan came across not only as ignorant, but as complacent about his ignorance,” Branch said.&lt;br /&gt;


In Darrow’s closing arguments, he asked the jury to return a guilty verdict so he could try the case on appeal — where he would have more room to argue the law itself was unconstitutional. And in a clever legal maneuver, Darrow denied Bryan the chance to give his own closing argument that he had been anticipating for weeks.&lt;br /&gt;

After only nine minutes of deliberation, the jury returned the desired guilty verdict. And while Scopes got away with paying a $100 fine, about $1,800 in today's dollars, Bryan left the court disgraced. He died just five days later on a Sunday afternoon − in Dayton.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;b&gt;How Theater Helps Us Remember the Scopes Monkey Trial 100 Years Later&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;https://time.com/7294045/theater-scopes-monkey-trial-100-years/
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
One hundred years ago today, live radio began broadcasting what would be soon termed the “trial of the century.”&lt;br /&gt;

The state of Tennessee had charged a high school biology teacher, John Scopes, with violating the Butler Act, which prohibited “the teaching of the Evolution Theory in all...public schools.”&lt;br /&gt;

Americans remember the Scopes Trial, or the “Monkey Trial,” as it was popularly dubbed, as a landmark fight for freedom of thought and a heroic stance against “ignorance” (as defense attorney Clarence Darrow put it). The trial resonated nationally because it brought the question of the place of science and religion in education to the forefront of public debate. Science, as defended by Scopes' legal team for 11 days, made the more compelling case to radio listeners across the country.&lt;br /&gt;

What is often forgotten, however, is that Scopes lost, personally and legally. State legislators didn’t repeal the Butler Act until 1967 and he never taught again in Tennessee or anywhere else. When Scopes tried to earn a PhD, as he recounted in his memoirs, the president “of one of most respected universities” wrote: “Your name has been removed from consideration...you can take your atheistic marbles and play elsewhere.”&lt;br /&gt;

The selective public memory reflects how two Ohio playwrights, Jerome Lawrence and Robert E. Lee, rewrote the history for their 1955 play Inherit the Wind. They transformed the Scopes trial from a specific historical moment into a legendary and heroic dissent from mainstream orthodoxy. The play is a reminder of theater’s power to demonstrate the meanings inherent in our daily lives by bringing structure and intent to what we experience as a chaotic jumble of events. Inherit the Wind is a perfect example of how theater can change the distant past into a very relevant and urgent present.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there are some essays. Here, the New York Times tries to give advice to Democrats. It actually suggests bringing back some Bryan-style populism. I’m not sure that’s the right lesson. I’d look more to Darrow – be rigorously skeptical of everything, even “your own” side, and acknowledge that public disagreement and debate are good, not bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;b&gt;This ‘Trial of the Century’ Is 100. Its Lessons Could Save the Democrats.&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2025/07/10/opinion/scopes-monkey-trial-democrats.html?smid=nytcore-ios-share&amp;amp;referringSource=articleShare&quot;&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2025/07/10/opinion/scopes-monkey-trial-democrats.html?smid=nytcore-ios-share&amp;amp;referringSource=articleShare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is a less-good piece, it points out the historical inaccuracies of Inherit the Wind (but these have been pointed out many times before), but then it claims that William Jennings Bryan was against eugenics, which is actually incorrect; Bryan endorsed eugenics in the early 1920s, and it was the cynical civil libertarian activist Clarence Darrow that came out hard and early against eugenics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;b&gt;Modernist Folklore: Sowing The Narrative and Inheriting The Wind&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://decadentserpent.com/2025/07/10/modernist-folklore-sowing-the-narrative-and-inheriting-the-wind/&quot;&gt;https://decadentserpent.com/2025/07/10/modernist-folklore-sowing-the-narrative-and-inheriting-the-wind/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author doesn’t like “modernism”, presumably he’s coming from a conservative religious viewpoint, although ironically you can see quite similar arguments on the postmodernist part of the Left.  I kind of like modernism and its morality plays like &lt;i&gt;Inherit the Wind&lt;/i&gt;. We could (and have) done worse. Sue me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;References&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matzke et al. (2025). Structural Phylogenetics of the Bacterial Flagellum. Poster at the 2025 annual meeting of the Human Frontier Science Program, 2025-07-08. &lt;a href=&quot;http://phylo.wikidot.com/local--files/nicholas-j-matzke/Matzke_2025_HFSP_poster_v5.pdf&quot;&gt;http://phylo.wikidot.com/local–files/nicholas-j-matzke/Matzke_2025_HFSP_poster_v5.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matzke, N. (2009). “But Isn’t It Creationism? The beginnings of ‘intelligent design’ and Of Pandas and People in the midst of the Arkansas and Louisiana litigation.” But Is It Science?: The Philosophical Question in the Creation/Evolution Controversy, Updated Edition, edited by Robert Pennock and Michael Ruse. Prometheus Books, Amherst, New York, pp. 377-413. 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://phylo.wdfiles.com/local--files/nicholas-j-matzke/Matzke_2009_ID_origins_But_Is_It_Science.pdf&quot;&gt;https://phylo.wdfiles.com/local–files/nicholas-j-matzke/Matzke_2009_ID_origins_But_Is_It_Science.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vanderbilt-university-scopes-trial-symposium-july-12-13-2025&quot;&gt;Vanderbilt University, Scopes Trial Symposium, July 12-13, 2025&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/2025-07-12_Scopes_Trial_Symposium_at_Vanderbilt.png&quot; alt=&quot;[Vanderbilt Scopes Trial Symposium schedule, July 12-13, 2025]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Vanderbilt Scopes Trial Symposium schedule, July 12-13, 2025&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vanderbilt.edu/evolution/scopes-symposium/&quot;&gt;Scopes &quot;Monkey&quot; Trial Centennial Symposium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Vanderbilt University, July 12-13, 2025&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vanderbilt.edu/evolution/scopes-symposium/&quot;&gt;https://www.vanderbilt.edu/evolution/scopes-symposium/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
...following on from...&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;ISEMPH 2025 Meeting&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
International Society for Evolution, Medicine, and Public Health&lt;br /&gt;
Vanderbilt University, July 8-10, 2025&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The weekend following the ISEMPH conference (7/12/25 – 7/13/25), we will host an academic symposium featuring dozens of wonderful guest speakers from around the world. This event is sponsored in part by the National Center for Science Education. Leading experts (Ed Larson, Randy Moore, and Adam Laats) on all things Scopes will speak about the history of the trial. Next, we’ll hear about issues facing teachers today as they try to navigate teaching evolution (Barbara Forrest, Kenneth Miller, Amanda Townley). Then, we will hear from folks at the forefront of their evolution-focused fields about their research (Sean Carroll, Jonathan Losos, Marlene Zuk, Stephen Brusatte, and Briana Pobiner). We’ll finish off Day 1 with a roundtable discussion on evolutionary science in the 21st century.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Day 2 will kick off with evolutionary research in fields other than biology, such as medicine (Paul Turner), agriculture (Sophien Kamoun), and the law (Owen Jones). After that, we’ll have another section on teaching evolution in a broader sense (Gale Sinatra, Patricia Hawley, Corrie Moreau, Riley Black, and Joseph Graves, Jr.). Our last proper session will be on the relationship of evolution and religion (Jamie Jensen, Katy Hinman, Liz Barnes and Lee Meadows). We’ll end with a second roundtable discussion on the future of evolution education.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Matzke</name></author><summary type="html">Nick Matzke at the Dayton County Courthouse where the Scopes Trial was held in 1925. (photo from ~2014) One-hundred years ago, on a hot and humid summer day in the Tennessee River Valley in southeast Tennessee, teacher John Scopes, the ACLU, Clarence Darrow, and various lawyers and scientists tried to challenge the state of Tennessee’s ban on teaching human evolution. The national press descended on Dayton, and the audio was broadcast across the country in the first “Trial of the Century.” The expert testimony was blocked, and Darrow, Scopes’s defense attorney, in frustration, asked to call prosecutor William Jennings Bryan (leader of the anti-evolution crusade, three-time presidential candidate, former Secretary of State, and populist politician) as a witness. Somehow this was allowed, and due to the heat, the proceedings were moved out onto the lawn. Darrow examined Bryan on the Bible and evolution, Bryan held his own, both sides concluded they were right, the national press lampooned the fundamentalists, but Scopes was convicted and fined (overturned on a technicality in 1927), and Bryan’s laws against teaching evolution remained on the books in many states and local jurisdictions until overturned by the 1968 Epperson v. Arkansas Supreme Court case. The term “creation science” emerged right around then (Matzke 2009), rebranding Flood Geology and young-earth creationism as science. As that strategy failed in the 1981 McLean vs. Arkansas case, creationists began work on a book called “Creation Biology”, which later became Of Pandas and People, the original vehicle promoting “intelligent design” in schools. The history of Pandas was uncovered in the 2005 Kitzmiller v. Dover case, covered right here on the Panda’s Thumb blog. And so here we are in 2025! Today, I am finishing the 2025 Human Frontier Science Program (HFSP) meeting in Melbourne, Australia, where myself and collaborators talked about our research (my bit: a Structural Phylogenetics of the Bacterial Flagellum poster). And I am getting on the plane and flying to Dallas, then Nashville, for the Scopes 100th meeting at Vanderbilt, which will also have a bunch of the people involved in Kitzmiller v. Dover. While the antievolution issue has receded somewhat, challenges to science and science education are ever-present and can come from either political side, so I think the lessons of the Scopes Trial and its descendants are ever present. The main question is whether or not we will learn from them.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Anhinga melanogaster</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/anhinga-melanogaster.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Anhinga melanogaster" /><published>2025-07-07T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-07T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/anhinga-melanogaster</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/anhinga-melanogaster.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;John Harshman&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Winner&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Harshman_Anhinga.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Anhinga (bird)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oriental_darter&quot;&gt;Anhinga melanogaster&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; oriental darter, Keoladeo National Park, Rajasthan, India. Mr. Harshman writes, &quot;Immature bird sunning and preening with a background of duckweed. There are four species in the family Anhingidae, and they are all nearly identical. I particularly like the way the curved neck shows the cervical vertebrae so clearly.&quot; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by John Harshman. Photography Contest, Winner. Anhinga melanogaster &amp;ndash; oriental darter, Keoladeo National Park, Rajasthan, India. Mr. Harshman writes, &quot;Immature bird sunning and preening with a background of duckweed. There are four species in the family Anhingidae, and they are all nearly identical. I particularly like the way the curved neck shows the cervical vertebrae so clearly.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Polyxenida sp.</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/polyxenida.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Polyxenida sp." /><published>2025-07-06T10:45:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-06T10:45:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/polyxenida</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/polyxenida.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/DSC06036_Millipede_Polyxenida_Crop.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bristly millipede.&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyxenida&quot;&gt;Polyxenida&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; sp. – bristly millipede, Boulder, Colorado, July, 2025. This fearsome creature is about 3&amp;nbsp;mm long. I managed to get one lucky shot and then could not find it again.&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;header&gt;&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/Photography-Contest-XVI-Finalists.html&quot;&gt;Photography Contest XVI: Finalists&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/header&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voting ends in 15 min, at noon, MDT (UTC - 6).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Polyxenida sp. – bristly millipede, Boulder, Colorado, July, 2025. This fearsome creature is about 3&amp;nbsp;mm long. I managed to get one lucky shot and then could not find it again. Photography Contest XVI: Finalists Voting ends in 15 min, at noon, MDT (UTC - 6).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nature SelectingA children's book explaining evolution</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/nature-selecting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nature SelectingA children's book explaining evolution" /><published>2025-07-05T12:29:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-05T12:29:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/nature-selecting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/nature-selecting.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Nature_Selecting_Cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book Cover&quot; /&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is an unashamed plug for the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lsu.edu/mns/news-and-publications/chakrabarty_evolution.pdf&quot;&gt;Nature Selecting&lt;/a&gt;, subtitled “A children’s book explaining evolution,” by Prosanta Chakrabarty, professor of biology and curator of fish at Louisiana State University, and illustrated by Anjai Noël, who just graduated from Sherwood Middle School in Baton Rouge, Louisiana, and is Prof. Chakrabarty’s 14-year-old daughter. The book cover, left, shows one of Ms. Noël’s delightful illustrations. Prof. Chakrabarty is also the author of the 2023 book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Explaining-through-Evolution-Prosanta-Chakrabarty/dp/0262546256/&quot;&gt;Explaining Life through Evolution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, the present work, Nature Selecting, is available only as a PDF and at no cost. It is worth much more than that, and I hope they will eventually print it on paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Michael Zimmerman and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theclergyletterproject.org/&quot;&gt;Clergy Letter Project&lt;/a&gt; for alerting us to this publication.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">This post is an unashamed plug for the book Nature Selecting, subtitled “A children’s book explaining evolution,” by Prosanta Chakrabarty, professor of biology and curator of fish at Louisiana State University, and illustrated by Anjai Noël, who just graduated from Sherwood Middle School in Baton Rouge, Louisiana, and is Prof. Chakrabarty’s 14-year-old daughter. The book cover, left, shows one of Ms. Noël’s delightful illustrations. Prof. Chakrabarty is also the author of the 2023 book Explaining Life through Evolution. As far as I can tell, the present work, Nature Selecting, is available only as a PDF and at no cost. It is worth much more than that, and I hope they will eventually print it on paper. Thanks to Michael Zimmerman and the Clergy Letter Project for alerting us to this publication.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">1 in 4 Americans Reject Evolution</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/1-in-4-americans-reject.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="1 in 4 Americans Reject Evolution" /><published>2025-07-03T14:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-03T14:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/1-in-4-americans-reject</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/1-in-4-americans-reject.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Scopes_Trial_Darrow_Bryan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Darrow and Brian at the trial&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Clarence Darrow (left) and William Jennings Bryan (right) during the Scopes trial in 1925. &lt;small&gt;Public domain. Brown Brothers, via &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Scopes_trial.jpg&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;. Photographer unknown.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full title of this article by William Trollinger and Susan Trollinger is &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/1-in-4-americans-reject-evolution-a-century-after-the-scopes-monkey-trial-spotlighted-the-clash-between-science-and-religion/&quot;&gt;1 in 4 Americans Reject Evolution, A Century after the Scopes Monkey Trial Spotlighted the Clash between Science and Religion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trollinger and Trollinger give a brief outline of the trial and some of its antecedents; what happened at the trial is comparatively well known, and you can read it for yourself. They point out, in particular, that Clarence Darrow’s famed (or perhaps notorious) “interrogation” of William Jennings Bryan made it obvious that a literal reading of the six-day creation myth in Genesis 1-2 was incompatible with modern science. Additionally, news stories, particularly by H.L. Mencken, portrayed religious fundamentalists as ignorant fools and led many to believe that such biblical literalism would soon disappear. It did not, though I think you could say it went underground for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fundamentalists, note Trollinger and Trollinger, needed scientific evidence to support their belief in a young earth. In 1961, they found it in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.prpbooks.com/book/genesis-flood-the&quot;&gt;The Genesis Flood: The Biblical Record and its Scientific Implications&lt;/a&gt; (the link is to a 50th anniversary edition published by P&amp;amp;R [Presbyterian and Reformed] Publishing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trollinger and Trollinger note that today approximately one-quarter of all Americans are young-earth creationists and reject much of modern biology and modern geology, not to mention modern cosmology. Answers in Genesis, which is strictly YEC, is now the world’s largest creationist organization. We report occasionally on AIG’s Ark Park, most recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/state-police-proselytized.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, so I will not dwell on it. Trollinger and Trollinger note that the Ark Park and other museums such as the Creation Museum attract millions of visitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse, though, they point to “an ever-expanding network of fundamentalist schools and homeschools that present young Earth creationism as true science.” Yet more worse, they say that at least 15 states have school choice programs which use tax money to pay for private and home schools. I would add only that these private schools take scarce funds from public schools that need them badly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young-earth creationism is not dead; it is not even sick (OK, it &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; sick, but it is not at death’s door). With a little help from old-earth creationisms, not least intelligent-design creationism, creationism writ large may be &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/01/is-intelligent-design.html&quot;&gt;making a comeback&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Clarence Darrow (left) and William Jennings Bryan (right) during the Scopes trial in 1925. Public domain. Brown Brothers, via Wikimedia Commons. Photographer unknown. The full title of this article by William Trollinger and Susan Trollinger is 1 in 4 Americans Reject Evolution, A Century after the Scopes Monkey Trial Spotlighted the Clash between Science and Religion. Trollinger and Trollinger give a brief outline of the trial and some of its antecedents; what happened at the trial is comparatively well known, and you can read it for yourself. They point out, in particular, that Clarence Darrow’s famed (or perhaps notorious) “interrogation” of William Jennings Bryan made it obvious that a literal reading of the six-day creation myth in Genesis 1-2 was incompatible with modern science. Additionally, news stories, particularly by H.L. Mencken, portrayed religious fundamentalists as ignorant fools and led many to believe that such biblical literalism would soon disappear. It did not, though I think you could say it went underground for some time. The fundamentalists, note Trollinger and Trollinger, needed scientific evidence to support their belief in a young earth. In 1961, they found it in The Genesis Flood: The Biblical Record and its Scientific Implications (the link is to a 50th anniversary edition published by P&amp;amp;R [Presbyterian and Reformed] Publishing). Trollinger and Trollinger note that today approximately one-quarter of all Americans are young-earth creationists and reject much of modern biology and modern geology, not to mention modern cosmology. Answers in Genesis, which is strictly YEC, is now the world’s largest creationist organization. We report occasionally on AIG’s Ark Park, most recently here, so I will not dwell on it. Trollinger and Trollinger note that the Ark Park and other museums such as the Creation Museum attract millions of visitors. Worse, though, they point to “an ever-expanding network of fundamentalist schools and homeschools that present young Earth creationism as true science.” Yet more worse, they say that at least 15 states have school choice programs which use tax money to pay for private and home schools. I would add only that these private schools take scarce funds from public schools that need them badly. Young-earth creationism is not dead; it is not even sick (OK, it is sick, but it is not at death’s door). With a little help from old-earth creationisms, not least intelligent-design creationism, creationism writ large may be making a comeback.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How the Scopes Trial Was Almost Scooped</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/scopes-trial-almost-scooped.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How the Scopes Trial Was Almost Scooped" /><published>2025-07-01T11:55:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-07-01T11:55:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/scopes-trial-almost-scooped</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/07/scopes-trial-almost-scooped.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Billy_The_Kid_Museum.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Billy the Kid Museum&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Billy the Kid Museum in Fort Sumner, New Mexico, where a &quot;monkey trial&quot; could have taken place in 1922. &lt;small&gt;Photograph by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/8638651@N07/&quot;&gt;Kevin Standlee&lt;/a&gt;. CC BY-NC-SA 2.0.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt; Glenn Branch is deputy director of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/&quot;&gt;National Center for Science Education&lt;/a&gt;, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as &lt;/i&gt;Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher, &lt;i&gt;and the &lt;/i&gt;Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics; &lt;i&gt;and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of &lt;/i&gt;Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools (2006). &lt;i&gt;He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1925, a young teacher in Dayton, Tennessee, was convicted of violating a state law that forbade the state’s educators “to teach any theory that denies the story of the Divine Creation of man as taught in the Bible, and to teach instead that man has descended from a lower order of animals.” Especially now, as its centennial year is being commemorated in various ways across the nation, the Scopes “monkey” trial is widely known. But the details of a similar controversy in New Mexico three years earlier deserve to be remembered as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Famously, the antievolution crusade of the 1920s was launched by William Jennings Bryan, a politician of national stature, who began to encourage the passage of bans on the teaching of evolution at both the state and the local level early in the decade. Probably as a result, in the summer of 1922, the school board in Fort Sumner, New Mexico — perhaps most famous as the site where the outlaw &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Billy_the_Kid&quot;&gt;Billy the Kid&lt;/a&gt; was shot and killed — adopted a resolution forbidding the teaching of evolution in the town’s schools, and calling for the resignation of any offending teacher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fort Sumner’s superintendent of schools, F. E. (for Finis Ewing: he was evidently named after the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finis_Ewing&quot;&gt;founder&lt;/a&gt; of the Cumberland Presbyterian Church) Dean, was summering in his home state of Missouri when he received a copy of the resolution. He decided that it would not be useful to argue about the resolution at a distance, planning instead on his return to Fort Sumner to argue in person to the board that “I had not been teaching the…doctrine of evolution in the form attributed to me” and moreover to explain that the antievolution resolution was unworkable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A good many of the texts used in every high school teach evolution,” Dean later explained in the local newspaper, the &lt;i&gt;Fort Sumner Leader&lt;/i&gt;. “In fact, all modern science, even in elementary texts …, is written from the evolutionary point of view. It is even true[,] as LeConte says, that evolution is more than half of modern thought.” (Not quite: in his &lt;a href=&quot;https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044106203474&amp;amp;seq=7&quot;&gt;Evolution and its Relation to Religious Thought&lt;/a&gt; (1889), Joseph LeConte wrote that evolution “is literally one half of all science.”) Dean added, “[T]here is no entering even the vestibule of modern thought except thru [sic] a knowledge of evolution.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While still in Missouri, Dean wrote to the New Mexico superintendent of schools to ask whether the board could legally insist on the resignation of any teacher who taught evolution. The superintendent referred the question to the state attorney general’s office, which answered that it could not. But the board got wind of Dean’s inquiry, and demanded his immediate resignation “on the ground of my manifest insincerity in agreeing to the resolution and then going over their heads to the Attorney General,” as Dean later explained in the &lt;i&gt;Fort Sumner Leader&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Dean, certain members of the board sent him letters “assuring me of the friendly feeling of the Board for me” and blaming the resolution on “public sentiment.” Yet, he was told, “my usefulness was at an end in Fort Sumner and that if I insisted on holding to my contract and returning the school would be torn to pieces.” Unable to return immediately to defend himself, Dean decided to acquiesce, explaining, “I have pioneered long enough. … If the community wants this sort of injustice done to itself, or will even stand for it, it is none of my affairs.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The front page of the next issue of the &lt;i&gt;Fort Sumner Leader&lt;/i&gt;, published August 18, 1922, was almost entirely consumed with reactions to Dean’s resignation. The Alumni Association of the Fort Sumner High School expressed its “love and appreciation” for Dean, and reassured him, and the public, that “we HAVE NOT learned from your teachings that the ‘Mottled ape is our grand-father.’ [Emphasis in original. I don’t recognize the allusion seemingly indicated by the quotation marks.] Neither has it shattered our faith in the bible and made infidels of us.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not everybody was supportive. Someone, possibly a minister, with the surname of Smith — the initials are unclear: possibly P. L. S. — wrote in opposition to evolution, invoking various authorities, including “Dr. [Robert] Etheridge, Fossiologist [a word sadly no longer in vogue!] of the British Museum,” “Prof. [Lionel Smith] Beale, of King’s College, London,” and the British biologist William Bateson, who supposedly rejected evolution. Smith added, “Woodrow Wilson does not believe that man came from the beast. So I suppose he is a back number [i.e, out of date].”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Smith’s contribution, a vestige of the Fort Sumner controversy would later appear in the Scopes trial. Dean apparently asked his former teacher Winterton C. Curtis, a professor of zoology at the University of Missouri, to investigate Smith’s authorities. Etheridge and Beale were both dead, but Curtis duly wrote not only to his fellow scientist Bateson but also to the former president Wilson, who replied, “Of course, like every other man of intelligence and education, I do believe in organic evolution. It surprises me that at this late date such questions should be raised.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three years later, when Curtis was among the expert witnesses for the defense in the Scopes trial, he included the reply from Wilson (who died in 1924) in his affidavit, prefaced by the explanation “Evolution has been generally accepted by the intellectually competent who have taken the trouble to inform themselves with an open mind. The following letter was written in response to a request to state his position, it having been alleged that he was not a believer in organic evolution.” But because the judge decided to exclude expert witness testimony, Wilson’s reply played no role in the Scopes trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only scholar to have taken note of Dean, A. G. Cock (in his “&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/jhered/article-abstract/80/2/96/902887?redirectedFrom=PDF&quot;&gt;Bateson’s Two Toronto Addresses, 1921: 2. Evolutionary Faith&lt;/a&gt;,” published in the &lt;i&gt;Journal of Heredity&lt;/i&gt; in 1989), suggests, “Dean deserves to be remembered, along with John T. Scopes, as an early hero of the continuing fight for the right to teach evolution in U.S. schools.” But Cock wasn’t able to follow Dean’s career further: after Curtis told Bateson in November 1922 that Dean hadn’t secured a new position yet, “at least as far as the sources available to me disclose, he disappears from the record.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was luckier, having found Dean’s obituary in the &lt;i&gt;Arizona Independent Republic&lt;/i&gt; for April 11, 1941. Apparently Dean moved to Arizona in late 1922 or 1923, where he taught in St. David for two years, served as a principal in Benson for seven years, and served as a superintendent of schools in Williams for seven years. After he was discharged from the latter position, he left the education field, engaging in the real estate business and operating a bookstore. He died on April 9, 1941, at the age of 64, owing to complications after a fall in which he broke a left thigh bone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It isn’t clear why Dean decided to resign from his position in Fort Sumner. He thought that the majority of townsfolk were on his side, and he seems to have been right: the local parent-teacher association adopted resolutions protesting his treatment and urging the board to revoke its resolution and refuse his resignation. His health may have played a role: although he was only 47, he complained that he was “worn out” by the controversy. But if he had fought the board, the resulting trial might have scooped the Scopes trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, it is perfectly reasonable to imagine that in 2022 we might have devoted great attention to the centenary of the Dean “monkey” trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Reposted from “&lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/how-the-scopes-trial-was-almost-scooped/&quot;&gt;How the Scopes Trial Was Almost Scooped&lt;/a&gt;,” by Glenn Branch, with permission of the author and of William Trollinger of the Righting America blog.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Glenn Branch</name></author><summary type="html">The Billy the Kid Museum in Fort Sumner, New Mexico, where a &quot;monkey trial&quot; could have taken place in 1922. Photograph by Kevin Standlee. CC BY-NC-SA 2.0. Glenn Branch is deputy director of the National Center for Science Education, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher, and the Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics; and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools (2006). He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers. In 1925, a young teacher in Dayton, Tennessee, was convicted of violating a state law that forbade the state’s educators “to teach any theory that denies the story of the Divine Creation of man as taught in the Bible, and to teach instead that man has descended from a lower order of animals.” Especially now, as its centennial year is being commemorated in various ways across the nation, the Scopes “monkey” trial is widely known. But the details of a similar controversy in New Mexico three years earlier deserve to be remembered as well. Famously, the antievolution crusade of the 1920s was launched by William Jennings Bryan, a politician of national stature, who began to encourage the passage of bans on the teaching of evolution at both the state and the local level early in the decade. Probably as a result, in the summer of 1922, the school board in Fort Sumner, New Mexico — perhaps most famous as the site where the outlaw Billy the Kid was shot and killed — adopted a resolution forbidding the teaching of evolution in the town’s schools, and calling for the resignation of any offending teacher. Fort Sumner’s superintendent of schools, F. E. (for Finis Ewing: he was evidently named after the founder of the Cumberland Presbyterian Church) Dean, was summering in his home state of Missouri when he received a copy of the resolution. He decided that it would not be useful to argue about the resolution at a distance, planning instead on his return to Fort Sumner to argue in person to the board that “I had not been teaching the…doctrine of evolution in the form attributed to me” and moreover to explain that the antievolution resolution was unworkable.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ichneumonid sp.</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/ichneumonid-sp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ichneumonid sp." /><published>2025-06-30T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-30T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/ichneumonid-sp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/ichneumonid-sp.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/DSC06009_Ichneumonid_Wasp_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ichneumonid wasp&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ichneumonidae&quot;&gt;Ichneumonidae&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; ichneumon wasp, fairly frisky, wandering around the house, Boulder, Colorado, June, 2025.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Please do not forget to vote:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;header&gt;&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/Photography-Contest-XVI-Finalists.html&quot;&gt;Photography Contest XVI: Finalists&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/header&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voting continues through Sunday, July 6, at noon, MDT (UTC - 7).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Ichneumonidae &amp;ndash; ichneumon wasp, fairly frisky, wandering around the house, Boulder, Colorado, June, 2025. Please do not forget to vote: Photography Contest XVI: Finalists Voting continues through Sunday, July 6, at noon, MDT (UTC - 7).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest XVI: Finalists</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/Photography-Contest-XVI-Finalists.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest XVI: Finalists" /><published>2025-06-23T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-23T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/Photography%20Contest-XVI-Finalists</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/Photography-Contest-XVI-Finalists.html">&lt;p&gt;Here are the finalists of the 2025 photography contest. It was nice to see some old friends, though new names would have been welcome. With assistance from Our Wife and Harshest Critic, we chose 7, which we display below the Figurative Fold. We chose the photographs more on the basis of their pictorial quality than on their scientific interest. Any text submitted by the photographers has been omitted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The finalists are presented in alphabetical order of last name. Please look through their photographs before voting for your favorite. Polling will close Sunday, July 6 (the 4th being a holiday in the US), at approximately noon MDT, and we will display the winner at noon Monday, July 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please remember that this is a photography contest, not a popularity contest, and discourage your friends from enlisting others specifically to vote for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Philip Abrams&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Abrams_Eurasian_Jay_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Eurasian jay&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wildlondon.org.uk/wildlife-explorer/birds/crows-and-shrikes/jay&quot;&gt;Garrulus glandarius&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; Eurasian jay, Chelsea, London, iPhone 15.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Denelsbeck_Ginkgo_biloba.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ginkgo leaf&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ginkgo_biloba&quot;&gt;Ginkgo biloba&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; ginkgo leaf after a heavy rain, Canon 7D.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Joel Eissenberg&lt;/strong&gt;.

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Eissenberg_Archilestes grandis.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Damselfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_spreadwing&quot;&gt;Archilestes grandis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; damselfly spotted at the Denver zoo.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;John Harshman&lt;/strong&gt;.
  
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Harshman_Anhinga.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Anhinga (bird)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oriental_darter&quot;&gt;Anhinga melanogaster&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; Oriental darter, Keoladeo National Park, Rajasthan, India.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;C. Joseph Long&lt;/strong&gt;.

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Long_Antigone_canadensis.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sandhill crane&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandhill_crane&quot;&gt;Antigone (formerly Grus) canadensis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; sandhill crane, Bernardo State Wildlife Refuge, Rio Grande Valley, New Mexico.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Malcolm Schongalla&lt;/strong&gt;.

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Schongalla_Rangifer_tarandus_skull.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Caribou skull&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barren-ground_caribou&quot;&gt;Rangifer tarandus groenlandicus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; barren-ground caribou, Russell Glacier on the West Coast of Greenland, June, 2022.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;John Trawick&lt;/strong&gt;.

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Trawick_Apis_mellifera_Echium_candicans.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;ldquo;Pride of Madeira&amp;rdquo; (flower)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smgrowers.com/products/plants/plantdisplay.asp?plant_id=543&quot;&gt;Echium candicans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; &quot;Pride of Madeira,&quot; with &lt;i&gt;Apis mellifera&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; European honeybee.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLScYL25zz4LVzQz7di3g-UIJI1vtyLfr93nZFXbC36fO59v_HA/viewform?embedded=true&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;650&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot;&gt;Loading…&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Here are the finalists of the 2025 photography contest. It was nice to see some old friends, though new names would have been welcome. With assistance from Our Wife and Harshest Critic, we chose 7, which we display below the Figurative Fold. We chose the photographs more on the basis of their pictorial quality than on their scientific interest. Any text submitted by the photographers has been omitted. The finalists are presented in alphabetical order of last name. Please look through their photographs before voting for your favorite. Polling will close Sunday, July 6 (the 4th being a holiday in the US), at approximately noon MDT, and we will display the winner at noon Monday, July 7. Please remember that this is a photography contest, not a popularity contest, and discourage your friends from enlisting others specifically to vote for you.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pipilo maculatus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/pipilo-maculatus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pipilo maculatus" /><published>2025-06-16T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-16T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/pipilo-maculatus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/pipilo-maculatus.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/P1031649_Towhee_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spotted towhee&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spotted_towhee&quot;&gt;Pipilo maculatus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; spotted towhee, not exactly in his natural environment.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Please do not forget &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;header&gt;&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/photography-contest-xvi.html&quot;&gt;Photography Contest XVI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/header&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contest remains open for entries through &lt;i&gt;this coming Friday&lt;/i&gt;, June 20.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Pipilo maculatus &amp;ndash; spotted towhee, not exactly in his natural environment. Please do not forget Photography Contest XVI The contest remains open for entries through this coming Friday, June 20.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Agave neomexicana</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/agave-neomexicana.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Agave neomexicana" /><published>2025-06-09T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-09T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/agave-neomexicana</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/agave-neomexicana.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/P1031638_Yucca_Agave_neomexicana_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;New Mexico century plant&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agave_americana&quot;&gt;Agave neomexicana&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; New Mexico century plant (also known as &lt;i&gt;Agave parryi&lt;/i&gt; ssp. &lt;i&gt;neomexicana&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; Parry's agave. The &lt;i&gt;H. sapiens&lt;/i&gt; in the picture, Ron Wittmann, tells us that some botanists recognize it as a distinct species, whereas others do not). The plant has not bloomed in at least 25 years. The pointy, gray-green leaves at the bottom of the stalk are the agave leaves.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Please do not forget &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;header&gt;&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/photography-contest-xvi.html&quot;&gt;Photography Contest XVI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/header&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contest remains open for entries through Friday, June 20.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Agave neomexicana &amp;ndash; New Mexico century plant (also known as Agave parryi ssp. neomexicana &amp;ndash; Parry's agave. The H. sapiens in the picture, Ron Wittmann, tells us that some botanists recognize it as a distinct species, whereas others do not). The plant has not bloomed in at least 25 years. The pointy, gray-green leaves at the bottom of the stalk are the agave leaves. Please do not forget Photography Contest XVI The contest remains open for entries through Friday, June 20.</summary></entry></feed>