<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-12-20T08:31:36-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Merry 20th Kitzmas! Thoughts on the 20th anniversary of Kitzmiller v. Dover</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/KvDv20.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Merry 20th Kitzmas! Thoughts on the 20th anniversary of Kitzmiller v. Dover" /><published>2025-12-20T00:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2025-12-20T00:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/KvDv20</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/KvDv20.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Matzke_Scopes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Nick Matzke at the Dayton County Courthouse, site of the 1925 Scopes Monkey Trial]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Nick Matzke at the Dayton County Courthouse where the Scopes Trial was held in 1925. (photo from ~2014)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The year 2025 is the 20th anniversary of the &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover&lt;/i&gt; case. Celebrations were held &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/KvDv19.html&quot;&gt;throughout the year&lt;/a&gt; as part of the 100th anniversary of &lt;i&gt;Scopes&lt;/i&gt;. I got to attend the July 2025 Nashville Scopes Trial event on the campus of Vanderbilt University, where I got to reconnect with many Doverians and other veterans of the evolution wars. Many of those talks are now online on YouTube.  Just after that, I also got to see my 100-year old grandmother one last time. She passed away soon after at the age of 101. Her life spanned the entire American creation/evolution debate from 1924-2025. Ironically, grandma sending me creationism books when I was a kid in the 1980s is part of what got me into the creation/evolution debate in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t the first time I’ve found my family history and the creationism debate crashing together: back in 2009, I gave a talk to the University of Oklahoma Zoology Department as part of their series for the 150th anniversary of the &lt;i&gt;Origin of Species&lt;/i&gt;, then found myself sharing a bed-and-breakfast with Richard Dawkins who was giving a talk to the whole University. In the space of 24 hours I found myself dining with my creationist grandma and someone who was basically her arch-nemesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We invite readers to give their own reflections on Dover, the science/creationism debate and subsequent developments, or personal updates in the comments below. Also, if they like, Kitzmiller participants can send me comments for me to add as edits to the main post (this may take a bit, as I’m now on holiday with the Aussie side of the family; the kids tell me there is a koala down the road).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will post several updates from this year which I hope you will enjoy. I should have blogged these at the time, but, well, 3 kids and a day job!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matzke, Nicholas J. (2025). The biology class you WISHED You Could Have Taken. Talk for: Bay Area Skeptics, host Eugenie C. Scott. June 14, 2025. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b7UKOqCn9ao&amp;amp;t=13s&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b7UKOqCn9ao&amp;amp;t=13s&lt;/a&gt;
Slides: &lt;a href=&quot;http://phylo.wikidot.com/local--files/nicholas-j-matzke/Matzke_ID_flagellum_v7.pptx&quot;&gt;http://phylo.wikidot.com/local–files/nicholas-j-matzke/Matzke_ID_flagellum_v7.pptx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matzke, Nicholas J. (2025). “Science at a Crossroads.” Preface, pp. 6-9 of: Bartholomew, Robert E. (2025). &lt;i&gt;The Science of the Māori Lunar Calendar: Separating Fact from Folklore: A Scientific Appraisal of the Maramataka&lt;/i&gt;. Auckland, New Zealand: Robert Bartholomew. pp. 1-90. ISBN 9780473737030. &lt;a href=&quot;https://aotearoabooks.co.nz/the-science-of-the-maori-lunar-calendar/&quot;&gt;https://aotearoabooks.co.nz/the-science-of-the-maori-lunar-calendar/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matzke, Nicholas J. (2025). Interview: Matauranga Maori, der Mond, Neuseeland und die Wissenschaft. (In English: Mātauranga Māori, the Moon, New Zealand, and Science.) Interviewer: Andreas Edmüller. &lt;i&gt;Der Skeptiker&lt;/i&gt; 3325, 3/2025, pp. 146-149. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwup.org/produkt/skeptiker-3-2025/#tab-id-2&quot;&gt;https://www.gwup.org/produkt/skeptiker-3-2025/#tab-id-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matzke, Nicholas J. (2025). Mendel was of his time, but Mendelism is modern. Review of: Kostas Kampourakis, &lt;i&gt;How We Get Mendel Wrong, and Why It Matters: Challenging the Narrative of Mendelian Genetics&lt;/i&gt;, Boca Raton: CRC Press, 2024, ISBN 9781032456904, 250 pp. &lt;i&gt;Journal of Historical Biology&lt;/i&gt;, accepted August 10, 2025. DOI: &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10739-025-09835-6&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10739-025-09835-6&lt;/a&gt; . Sharable Link: &lt;a href=&quot;https://rdcu.be/eH3Zu&quot;&gt;https://rdcu.be/eH3Zu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Update on antievolution legislation. I had intended to update the Matzke (2015) analysis of the “evolution of antievolution legislation.”  I have progressed this through the data coding stage, but now it’s the holidays so it will take a bit longer to do the phylogenetics. However, it’s interesting to paste all the bills since 2015 together to see the wacky stuff that is still proposed, and sometimes passed (like in West Virginia in 2024; see my comments in Science on that, published just before I wrote a letter to &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; on a similar scale of weirdness in science education coming from the other political side, in New Zealand).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matzke, Nicholas J. (2025). The biology class you WISHED You Could Have Taken. Talk for: Bay Area Skeptics, host Eugenie C. Scott. June 14, 2025. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b7UKOqCn9ao&amp;amp;t=13s&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b7UKOqCn9ao&amp;amp;t=13s&lt;/a&gt;
Slides: &lt;a href=&quot;http://phylo.wikidot.com/local--files/nicholas-j-matzke/Matzke_ID_flagellum_v7.pptx&quot;&gt;http://phylo.wikidot.com/local–files/nicholas-j-matzke/Matzke_ID_flagellum_v7.pptx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/12/KvDv19.html&quot;&gt;I wrote&lt;/a&gt;, “I expect that many are glum about current politics and science, but I recall a similar feeling in 2004, and that &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover&lt;/i&gt; was one of the early signs that committed citizens could move events in a pro-science direction. May 2025 be another such time!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot particularly say that 2025 has panned out well in this regard. Sometimes the creation/evolution battle, which was largely conducted via books, blogs, talk.origins and talkdesign FAQs, plucky nonprofits and the occasional court case, almost seems like “An elegant [debate] for a more civilized age,”  (to misquote Obi-Wan Kenobi), compared to the chaos reigning now in science-related public policy matters. I’m sure that much of this is that the heat of the emotions of the time fades after 20 years, but it does seem like threats to science and science education have been proliferating – disturbingly, sometimes on both sides of the political spectrum, as polarization and information bubbles intensify, any science that is inconvenient or unhelpful in some political battle comes under pressure to conform to the hand that feeds it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My talk reviewed the heady events of 2005, but towards the end I comment on some of the subsequent developments, and I give my own view on the importance of scientists maintaining critical thinking about “our own side”. This ability was, I think, one skill I made some use of during the &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller&lt;/i&gt; case – while I think we would have won regardless, episodes like the “hey maybe there are creationist drafts of the &lt;i&gt;Pandas&lt;/i&gt; book” and the evolutionary immunology cross-examination stemmed in part from taking a closer look at places where our own evolutionist side tended to give a somewhat easy answer, when a more deeply researched answer (and in the end one even more damaging to ID) was available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in recent years, incidents in New Zealand and elsewhere have convinced me that increasing polarization has damaged our instinct for critical thinking about the arguments “on our own side.”  One result has been a decline in respect for science not just on the political right, but also on substantial parts of the political left, where we’ve seen a resurgence of 1990s-style postmodernist attacks on science. Even Alan Sokal, famous for his hoax of the postmodernist journal &lt;i&gt;Social Text&lt;/i&gt;, has re-emerged to note the phenomenon. (See e.g. Science and Ideology by Alan Sokal PhD, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X9cYJYXR1KE&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X9cYJYXR1KE&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;matzke-2025-science-at-a-crossroads-preface-to-the-science-of-the-māori-lunar-calendar-separating-fact-from-folklore-a-scientific-appraisal-of-the-maramataka&quot;&gt;Matzke (2025) “Science at a Crossroads.” Preface to: The Science of the Māori Lunar Calendar: Separating Fact from Folklore: A Scientific Appraisal of the Maramataka&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matzke, Nicholas J. (2025). “Science at a Crossroads.” Preface, pp. 6-9 of: Bartholomew, Robert E. (2025). &lt;i&gt;The Science of the Māori Lunar Calendar: Separating Fact from Folklore: A Scientific Appraisal of the Maramataka&lt;/i&gt;. Auckland, New Zealand: Robert Bartholomew. pp. 1-90. ISBN 9780473737030. &lt;a href=&quot;https://aotearoabooks.co.nz/the-science-of-the-maori-lunar-calendar/&quot;&gt;https://aotearoabooks.co.nz/the-science-of-the-maori-lunar-calendar/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bashed this out this Preface during the 2025 NZ Phylogenomics Meeting, after receiving a draft of a new book by longtime skeptic Robert Bartholomew. Bartholomew’s book constitutes one of the only public skeptical looks at some of the overreaches of the indigenous knowledge movement in New Zealand. (Note for clarity: yes, there are legitimate ways to include well-tested indigenous knowledge in science and science education. But it is, unfortunately, also true that there has been a great deal of avoidance of critical thinking in this space, and a fair amount of dubious stuff has been produced and even promoted by important educational and governmental institutions.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
(Original version, submitted February 2025. The final published version may differ slightly. Citation:
Matzke, Nicholas J. (2025). &quot;Science at a Crossroads.&quot; Preface, pp. 6-9 of: Bartholomew, Robert E. (2025). The Science of the Māori Lunar Calendar: Separating Fact from Folklore: A Scientific Appraisal of the Maramataka. Auckland, New Zealand: Robert Bartholomew. pp. 1-90. ISBN 9780473737030. https://aotearoabooks.co.nz/the-science-of-the-maori-lunar-calendar/ )
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Preface: Science at a crossroads&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;b&gt;By Nicholas J. Matzke&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Robert Bartholomew's &lt;i&gt;The Science of the Māori Lunar Calendar: Separating Fact from Folklore&lt;/i&gt; gives a scientific review of claims being made in New Zealand about mātauranga Māori (Māori indigenous knowledge), maramataka (the Māori lunar calendar), and its claimed connections to a variety of topics including human health.  The book comes at a time when science is at a crossroads internationally and in New Zealand. While few admit to being anti-science, strong forces on both the political Left and Right have been working to try and bend science towards &quot;higher&quot; objectives. Typically, the Right thinks that the only science research worth doing, and worth funding, is applied research that benefits the economy. Lately, and peculiarly, some on the Left have tended to agree with the Right that the research worth funding should be applied research, just with different objectives, typically aimed towards social justice.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Several valuable things are lost with the mania for trying to pound the square peg of science into the round holes of economic or social progress. First, most industrialised countries have long recognised that some research funding needs to be reserved for basic research: science pursued for its own sake, motivated by important unsolved questions internal to the field in question, rather than motivated by external prerogatives. Basic research leads to fundamental advances in understanding how nature works, a good in its own right, as well as happening to provide the basis for many applied benefits, although often not benefits that are predicable ahead of time or the benefits that a government minister would like to conjure up in time for the next election. Examples are innumerable, but to list one from recent history: New Zealand's response to the 2020 SARS-CoV-2 coronavirus pandemic was assisted by rapid sequencing of viral genomes, coupled with phylogenetic analyses inferring the likely time and directionality of transmission events. This entire chain of applied science was built on decades of advances in basic science, ranging from the discovery of the double-helix structure of DNA through to PCR-based DNA sequencing (PCR, polymerase chain reaction, is a way of duplicating tiny quantities of DNA, a process made practical by a polymerase enzyme that can work at high temperatures, which was discovered in a bacterium living in hot springs) through to the computational tools used to align DNA sequences and then infer phylogenetic trees. Phylogenetics was not invented to fight viruses, instead, the conceptual bases for it were developed by biologists in fields like entomology and ichthyology who were looking for better and more objective ways to taxonomically classify their insects and fishes. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Second, most governments already strongly prioritise funding applied research over basic research. Research money spent on medicine, agriculture, defense, and the like far outstrips that reserved for basic, blue-skies research. Taking the small fraction of research funding devoted to fundamental research, and bending that towards the political priorities of the day, is a case of over-coordination trending towards enforcement of conformity. Diversity has a value in science research funding as elsewhere. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Third, when basic research funding mechanisms are perceived to have been captured by one political side, there is great risk when an election brings the other side to power. The funding may be summarily cut, and/or repurposed to the objectives of the new government. This might be good short-term politics, but it is a bad way to maintain a healthy science ecosystem, wherein a nation can participate in the global cutting-edge.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Unfortunately, this latter situation seems to have just occurred in New Zealand.  Under the Labour governments of 2017-2023, extensive efforts were made to bend science and science education towards objectives like decolonisation and promotion of mātauranga Māori. While these goals may well have merit -- and the government of course legitimately funds all kinds of things beyond science, such as the arts, recreation, cultural institutions, etc. -- trying to take programmes designed to promote basic science research and education and lean heavily on them to also promote indigenisation objectives was bound to produce some grinding of gears. Several are well-described in Bartholomew's book. Beyond what has been publicly reported, I can say that from personal experience and conversations with colleagues that many applicants for the Marsden Fund in recent years have felt a great deal of pressure to try to find some connection, any connection, between their basic research interests and the Marsden Fund's Vision Mātauranga (VM) priorities.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Marsden Fund is New Zealand's primary competitive grant for funding basic, blue-skies research, similar to the Australia Research Council Discovery Projects and the US National Science Foundation grants. Vision Mātauranga, as initially proposed (in 2005), came across as a reasonable and common-sense request for applicants to describe situations where their basic research happened to have relevance for Māori priorities (in health, economics, environment, or indigenous knowledge). While, technically, this push towards applied research leaned away from the core Marsden purpose of blue-skies research, this was softened by VM statements only being needed &quot;if relevant&quot; to the proposed research, and not as a requirement. However, under the 2017-2023 Labour government's apparent policy to promote Mātauranga Māori in virtually all educational and governmental institutions, at all levels and all subjects, and with a generally chilled atmosphere towards any critical thinking about this objective or its application, it was not surprising that many perceived VM as a de facto requirement. While the effect of this seems to have been limited in &quot;hard science&quot; Marsden subject panels -- astrophysics and genome evolution models are tough topics to spin towards social goals -- based on conversations with colleagues, the amount of worry and anxiety induced in science grant writers was substantial. However, the stress levels of scientists is a minor concern compared to what seems to have occurred in other Marsden subject panels, such as humanities and social sciences, which funded almost exclusively applied research, and almost exclusively reflecting the previous Labour government's priorities. The risks of this became apparent in late 2024 when Judith Collins, the science minister under the new, conservative-leading government, summarily cut funding for these panels, defending her actions with descriptions of the funded projects, and stating she didn't want it coming from her science budget. She also imposed on the Marsden Fund a new requirement that 50% of funded research have economy-benefitting applications. Many complaints and protests followed, but Collins' undermining of basic science research funding was simply walking through a door already pushed wide open by Labour. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In 2025, drastic attacks on science funding are currently taking place in the USA under the Trump administration. These are far more extreme than in New Zealand, but some of the underlying drivers are similar, such as the perception that science is only worth funding if it is bent to the political priorities of those in power. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I say: a pox on both your houses. Both Left and Right need to back the heck off and leave basic science research funding and basic science education to the scientists. The guiding goal of blue-skies research funding should be to answer fundamental questions about how nature works, and the guiding goal of science education should be to teach the fundamentals of the best science available, in an age-appropriate way. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A final reason to maintain the political independence of science research funding and science education is to maintain the expertise and skill sets required to think carefully and critically about science-related claims being made in the public sphere. A variety of such claims have been made in the mātauranga Māori discussion in New Zealand, some reasonable and some dubious, yet the chilled atmosphere surrounding indigenous knowledge claims at universities and in government agencies has often impeded critical review. This benefits no one in the long run. For example, one episode discussed by Bartholomew concerns the idea that suicide rates in Māori correlate with phases of the Moon. This claim received quite a bit of positive attention via media and workshops, as an example of how indigenous knowledge can benefit medicine. However, statistical examination of suicide data seems to show no correlation with Moon phase in Māori or any other New Zealand population. Skepticism has an important role to play in society and policy, and it should not be dismissed or suppressed in an attempt to get everyone on the bandwagon of a particular political or social programme.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I recommend The Science of the Māori Lunar Calendar as a thorough examination of the current status of claims made about these topics, and I hope we see more of it in New Zealand. This work should not be viewed as an attack on the status or mana of Māori, Māori knowledge, or maramataka. One key point that I find is constantly misunderstood in the discussion of indigenous knowledge and science in New Zealand is how &quot;status&quot; works in science. In many spheres of human activity, challenging the statements or opinions of an authority is viewed as lowering their status. But science is counterintuitive here. In science, claims gain status by being challenged. The highest-status claims in science are the ones that have received the most challenges, the most empirical testing. The claims that survive all this testing are considered the most robust and the most reliable. If a claim is challenged and shown to be incorrect, well, at least we have learned something, and human knowledge has increased. To a scientist, there is something much worse than being wrong - being &quot;not even wrong.&quot; Claims that insulate themselves from empirical testing, whether through vagueness, reliance on mystical untestable entities, or through assertions of authority, are those given the lowest status by scientists. So, bring on the testing!
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;matzke-2025-mātauranga-māori-the-moon-new-zealand-and-science&quot;&gt;Matzke (2025) Mātauranga Māori, the Moon, New Zealand, and Science&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matzke, Nicholas J. (2025). Interview: Matauranga Maori, der Mond, Neuseeland und die Wissenschaft. (In English: Mātauranga Māori, the Moon, New Zealand, and Science.) Interviewer: Andreas Edmüller. &lt;i&gt;Der Skeptiker&lt;/i&gt; 3325, 3/2025, pp. 146-149. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwup.org/produkt/skeptiker-3-2025/#tab-id-2&quot;&gt;https://www.gwup.org/produkt/skeptiker-3-2025/#tab-id-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
Short Bio: Who is Nick Matzke?
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Nick Matzke is a Senior Lecturer and Rutherford Discovery Fellow at the School of Biological Sciences, University of Auckland, New Zealand. From 2004-2007 he was a Public Information Project Director at the National Center for Science Education, and was heavily involved in the 2004-2005 &lt;u&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover&lt;/u&gt; trial in Pennsylvania about the constitutionality of teaching &quot;intelligent design&quot; creationism in public school biology classes. &lt;/i&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
 
&lt;b&gt;Why should German Skeptics take an interest in the Maori Moon Calendar - after all, there are 18147 km between Auckland and Munich (and we have our own moon calendars)? &lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
(NOTE: In English, at least, the currently official spelling is Mātauranga Māori. The ā indicates a longer “ah” sound. Whether this is considered necessary, or it is in there because it is considered helpful, I don’t know. It may not matter in German.)
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Māori lunar calendar, or “maramataka,” was long used by used by Māori to plan farming, fishing, ceremonies, etc. However, recently it has become part of what can only be described as an indigenous knowledge “craze” in New Zealand. The maramataka has been promoted uncritically as very important for health, spiritual health, science, and science education. Much of the promotion is top-down, with mainstream media, government, and the education system pushing it. However, many maramataka-based claims are unsupported, wrong, or even amount to astrology.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;


&lt;b&gt;How would you characterize Matauranga Maori, what is it?&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Mātauranga Māori is often used as a synonym for “Māori indigenous knowledge.” Simple examples might be traditional medicinal uses of native plants, or knowledge of the ecology and behavior of native species. These kinds of things are largely noncontroversial. However, a broader meaning of the term is also used, where Mātauranga Māori includes the traditional Māori language, customs, tribal law, spiritual beliefs, and even worldview. Then there is an even broader meaning, which includes not just the traditional views, but also any knowledge or other beliefs developed or accepted by Māori in modern times. Some MM advocates will therefore say that MM includes modern science. Others will include modern-day legal and political claims. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;b&gt;Let’s look at the background. There is a very lively debate for decades now in NZ about Matauranga Maori - what are its key issues?&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There is supposedly a history of discrimination against Mātauranga Māori, where Māori beliefs and knowledge were unfairly dismissed as “myths and legends” by British colonizers, and this knowledge was allegedly suppressed through official means. While there certainly must have been some of this, the actual history looks to be a good deal more complicated than that. For example, extensive efforts were made by scholars to record and compile information from Māori elders. There is similar complexity about the 1907 “Tohunga Suppression Act” (Tohunga  = Māori traditional healing techiniques), which is the most-mentioned example of official suppression of Mātauranga Māori. However, the record is clear that many prominent Māori leaders and politicians supported the Act at the time, and they were reacting in part to cases where people had been harmed by Tohunga practices.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
As for the modern debate, I would say it has gradually ramped up as a follow-on from efforts to preserve the Māori language which began in the 1980s-1990s. It hit a peak during the Labour government led by Jacinda Ardern from 2017-2023, where it became part of a wave of top-down efforts to promote a left-activist agenda through basically all institutions in New Zealand. Common buzzwords were decolonization, co-governance, and having all institutions (government departments, universities, even private companies and nonprofits) be “Tiriti-led”. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
(Tiriti = the Māori language version of “Treaty.” The Treaty of Waitangi was signed in 1840 between the British Crown and the chiefs of many Māori tribes. Its meaning has been fought about ever since. Using the term “Tiriti” tends to mean that the Māori-language version of the Treaty is to be taken as authoritative, and more specifically that the modern activist interpretation of this language is to be taken as authoritative. In reality, all of these moves are disputed by other political parties.)
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
During the 2017-2023 Labour government, extensive efforts were made to include Mātauranga Māori, in the broad sense, in almost every sphere, whether it made any sense or not. For example, in addition to the widespread promotion of maramataka as widely scientifically useful, there were references to Māori gods in weather bulletins and in airplane safety videos. Any number of news articles promoted the importance of Mātauranga Māori for scientific, medical, or engineering research, sometimes reasonably, but often seeming to be more hype and “stretch” than substance. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The hottest controversies came in science education. In the secondary schools, the Labour government launched its “NCEA Change Process” where the Ministry of Education set out to reform NZ’s NCEA system for giving qualifications in various subjects. This process included a policy, “Mana Orite: Equal Status for Mātauranga Māori,” which basically declared by governmental fiat that Mātauranga Māori was equally valid as “Western knowledge,” no matter the subject. Such a statement might conceivably be true, or at least arguable, in subjects in the arts. But it is deeply problematic when applied to the hard sciences. In addition, there were some other subjects which were forced to strive to include Mātauranga Māori where it was not an obvious fit. One example, included in Ministry of Education teacher training videos on mana orite, was about including Mātauranga Māori in…Japanese language classes. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I, and many scientists, got involved when we learned that the NCEA Chemistry and Biology course for 14-15 year-old students had, under the “mana orite” policy, had included the concept of “mauri” in basic chemistry.  For example:  “Mauri is present in all matter. All particles have their own mauri and presence as part of a larger whole, for example within a molecule, polymer, salt, or metal. When matter is broken into smaller particles each particle remains as part of the taiao [environment], for example when a substance is burnt or dissolved the particles remain, with their own mauri.”
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The glossary for the course provided this definition of mauri:
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“The vital essence, life force of everything: be it a physical object, living thing or ecosystem.”
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
This is vitalism. Vitalism was famously debunked during the 1800s, as organic chemistry developed, and experiments (many of them done by German scientists!) showed that biology was fundamentally just very complex chemistry. The most famous episode was when the German chemist Friedrich Wöhler synthesized the organic molecule urea from inorganic compounds in 1828. This is often mentioned in chemistry textbooks (I should note that the actual history of vitalism was a gradual decline as chemistry explained more and more; Wöhler’s work was just an early example that later got oversimplified). 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
To any physical scientist, it seemed unlikely that a Ministry of Education chemistry curriculum for 14-year olds would be the place that would bring vitalism back into science. As New Zealand chemistry professor Paul Kilmartin said, “One question is whether using mauri in the sense of life-supporting capacity implies all of this additional meaning. If it does, then I would want to ask, Who discovered this binding force between the physical and the spiritual? And what evidence was involved in its discovery? If this binding force is real, then everyone needs to know about it. It needs to be in the chemistry syllabus of every country, not just in New Zealand.”
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Finding this level of mistake in a science curriculum is like finding a science curriculum endorsing Flat-Earthism or creationism. A great many things have to go wrong for this to make it to the Pilot classroom stage. It turns out that science teachers did object to this content, vociferously, but they were overridden by the Ministry of Education, which said it was doing so on the basis of the mana orite policy. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Eventually, the house of cards fell down. In late 2022, mauri and some (not all) of other problematic material was stripped from the NCEA curriculum. In 2023, Labour lost the election, although chaos in the educational reform was (sadly) only a very minor issue compared to the economy. However, the new government has indefinitely paused the NCEA change process.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;b&gt;How do things stand presently? (A look at the close alliance between woke and MM would be helpful for German readers, also the curriculum-issue which even surfaced in &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;.)&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I would say that, mostly due to the election of a center-right government, we are seeing some rollback of the excesses of 2017-2023. The secondary school science curriculum now seems tob e heading in a more reasonable direction. However, there is a long hangover. The universities all became “Tiriti-led”, and as part of this, the University of Auckland implemented a new, required first-year course, “Waipapa Taumata Rau,” (WTR, the new Māori name for the University of Auckland) based on “knowledge systems,” a term which seems to have been adopted largely to be able to say “science is just one knowledge system, and Mātauranga Māori is another, equally valid one.” All critical thinking about the problems with this formulation is avoided, and the course is very ideological, taking modern left-activist political positions and treating them as the one true understanding of New Zealand history and law. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
However, it appears that the WTR course is on the rocks. Students have been complaining online about being forced to pay for a course that has little relevance to their degrees, and either teaches the same basics of NZ history that they have gotten many times previously in primary and secondary school, or takes controversial political positions while avoiding the debates that are normally expected at the university level. For example, the science WTR course at Auckland, while it did not go as far as the NCEA Chemistry course, still mentions mauri/life force, “ancestral forces”, and Māori creation myths as part of mātauranga Māori. It does so while claiming that mātauranga Māori and science are distinct “knowledge systems.” The difference between belief and knowledge, surely an absolutely crucial distinction to think about at university, is completely avoided.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
It is not clear what the future holds, but things are changing. In late 2024, the Provost (in charge of student education) resigned under a cloud due to other problems with the curriculum transformation, and the Provost position was abolished. Recently the Vice Chancellor herself announced her resignations. The newly-appointed Dean of Science, after only months on the job, was moved up to be Pro-Vice Chancellor for Education. Presumably there will be a re-think of the curriculum decisions made in 2020-2021, now often acknowledged as the “peak woke” period.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;b&gt;Which place do you see for Matauranga Maori in schools and universities in NZ?&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In my view, a rational policy would be to bring Mātauranga Māori into classrooms where useful and relevant. There are some obvious topics, for example, ecology, where there is surely useful indigenous knowledge that can be helpful to teach about, both to teach ecology, and to make the point that Māori were as smart as anyone else, able to survive in a challenging environment by using their wits and skills. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
But trying to force Mātauranga Māori into courses where there really is genuinely little connection is very likely to backfire and/or miseducate students, as the mauri example showed. There is even a substantial risk of hurting the cause of Māori education. One of the rationales of Mana Orite was to increase the comfort and interest of Māori students in the sciences – but if weakly-evidenced and/or supernatural views are introduced in science class as “Māori knowledge,” then Māori students (and teachers) are faced with either having to defend these views against skeptics, or of stating that the government has been pushing pseudoscience on students in pursuit of some poorly thought-out progressive policy objective.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Trying to jam Mātauranga Māori into classes where it is not relevant causes all kinds of problems.  I find it strange that this is the direction the New Zealand government took. It would make more sense to have a class unit on something like the “traditioanl Maori worldview,” and explain, on its own terms, the basics of traditional Māori cosmology, the significance of its creation myths, etc.  This could best be done in a context rather like comparative religion, where students learn about the beliefs of various world religions as a matter of basic cultural literacy. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;b&gt;The debate is often pictured as a racist conflict - is that true?&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Unfortunately, the racism accusation is often thrown at anyone skeptical of any of the above.  This accusation, or even just fear of it, very effectively suppressed discussion and debate early on. However, episodes like the mauri affair were so clearly dubious on their own terms that the racism charge had little sticking power. This was particularly so once various prominent Māori spoke up and said that they didn’t agree with this distortion of basic science either. This really cut the legs out from under any accusers.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;b&gt;How would you characterize the quality of the public debate on Matauranga Maori - and where do you see room for improvement?&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The quality of the public debate is still low. In New Zealand, it seems like many of the important debates actually happen behind the scenes. This is unfortunate, as it initially gives activists the upper hand as they construct an information bubble around policymakers, university leaders, etc. However, eventually word gets around, and it appears that traditional pragmatism, long a value of both Māori and non- Māori New Zealanders, may be coming to the fore.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Probably the group doing the best work in New Zealand to improve things is the New Zealand Free Speech Union.  This is not because they address Mātauranga Māori specifically. Instead, it is because FSU pushes back on any attempts to shut down legitimate debate, cancel speakers, etc. After several years of campaigning, the government has agreed to pass stronger academic freedom and institutional neutrality policies for universities, and many libraries and city councils have discovered that their tinpot attempts to censor anyone departing from “woke” views will fail when challenged in court.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;b&gt;What role do the NZ Skeptics play in the whole affair?&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Unfortunately, the NZ Skeptics that I am aware of seem to be pretty doctrinaire adherents of whatever the current progressive left orthodoxy is, and have completely avoided engaging on the very obvious problems like those mentioned above -- even though they are classic “skeptics” topics.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;b&gt;What can we in Germany learn from all this?&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I would say the most important thing of all is to build, and support, something like the Free Speech Union, as is found in the UK, NZ, etc. Skeptics arguments and evidence will win the day, as long as skepticism is not instantly suppressed by institutions and media.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;b&gt;How can Skeptics from Germany and Europe support you and your friends? &lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The most important thing is to push for free speech and institutional neutrality, and to apply these principles to specific hot button issues – claims about indigenous knowledge are one, but other obvious ones are politics, gender, etc. The truth will win out, if given a chance to be heard.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
One other lesson from the New Zealand episode is that Skeptics ought to try to retain some intellectual distance from the political Left and Right.  At least in the USA, this problem started on the Right but has somehow rebounded on the Left. Here is what I mean: in recent decades the political Right committed many flagrant sins against science and skepticism: creationism/intelligent design, global warming denialism, sometimes flirtation with scientific racism, etc.; as well as various astounding forms of brazen political lying, e.g. Trump's birtherism about Obama, and lying about election fraud.  
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
As a result, it became routine to say that the Democratic Party was the party of science, the &quot;reality-based community,&quot; etc. It was the Left that put on the March for Science in 2016 to push back in Trumpism version 1.0.  And naturally, when the Right is the group offending science and reason so consistently, it is natural for Skeptics to develop the view that the Left is rational and the Right is irrational. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I am afraid, though, that what has happened especially during the Trump-Biden-Trump years is that the political polarization got so bad, along with online siloing, the decline of traditional media, and groupthink in the governmental and nongovernmental organizations, that sometimes pretty loony ideas got accepted on the Left without proper due diligence and critical debate.  All of this was exacerbated by &quot;cancel culture&quot;, &quot;no platforming&quot;, &quot;identify politics&quot;, and the rest. So now we often have similar problems on the Left as we have had on the Right -- bizarre, counterfactual orthodoxies being enforced through language games and bullying, while open debate on the merits is avoided or even suppressed. I think these problems have repeated in all Anglophone countries, and probably more broadly than that in our digital age. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

There are clear signs of these issues in the often uncritical, top-down promotion of Mātauranga Māori through the institutions and educational systems in New Zealand. Similar pushes are occurring in Australia, Canada, and many US states. Another, even more obvious one is flagrant sex denialism and sexism in the service of what we might call “gender identity supremacism” (the idea that self-declared “gender identity” can and should trump biological sex in every policy and discussion). Leftist attempts to limit freedom of speech and academic freedom are a third -- and another case of mirroring the Right of decades past. All of these ought to be actively debated by skeptics groups in particular.  Perhaps the policy should be, &quot;Critical thinking about the claims of all political sides, even (and especially) the political side we generally agree with.&quot;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;matzke-2025--mendel-was-of-his-time-but-mendelism-is-modern-review-of-kostas-kampourakis-how-we-get-mendel-wrong-and-why-it-matters-challenging-the-narrative-of-mendelian-genetics&quot;&gt;Matzke (2025)  Mendel was of his time, but Mendelism is modern. Review of: Kostas Kampourakis, How We Get Mendel Wrong, and Why It Matters: Challenging the Narrative of Mendelian Genetics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matzke, Nicholas J. (2025). Mendel was of his time, but Mendelism is modern. Review of: Kostas Kampourakis, &lt;i&gt;How We Get Mendel Wrong, and Why It Matters: Challenging the Narrative of Mendelian Genetics&lt;/i&gt;, Boca Raton: CRC Press, 2024, ISBN 9781032456904, 250 pp. &lt;i&gt;Journal of Historical Biology&lt;/i&gt;, accepted August 10, 2025. DOI: &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10739-025-09835-6&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10739-025-09835-6&lt;/a&gt; . Sharable Link: &lt;a href=&quot;https://rdcu.be/eH3Zu&quot;&gt;https://rdcu.be/eH3Zu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
Mendel was not a monk, he was a friar. This is one of the many myths that Kam- pourakis seeks to dethrone. As the title promises, Kampourakis also explains why this matters: monks are stereotypically secluded, leading to the misconception that Mendel was a lone genius working in isolation to produce his famous 1866 paper on inheritance of traits in peas. Mendel was indeed based at a monastery in Brno (now in the Czech Republic, then a crown land of Austria). However, unlike monks, friars are devoted to service to laypeople rather than asceticism, and in Brno, one form of service was research in plant and animal breeding. A previous abbot of the monastery, Napp, participated in or led various regional breeding societies from at the least the 1820s. Mendel attended lectures by Napp and colleagues from the 1840s, and studied botany and math at the University of Vienna from 1851 to 1853. One of his profes- sors was Franz Unger, a botanist who anonymously floated proto-evolutionary ideas in 1851, provoking accusations of paganism and materialism; Unger’s orthodoxy was defended via a lawsuit and student petition. Unger also argued that both pollen and ovule contributed to the embryo, against the view that embryos developed only from the pollen cell. When Mendel returned to Brno, he was motivated to begin experi- ments relevant to these very live academic controversies. Mendel was thus a scientist of his time.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Kampourakis works hard to distinguish what Mendel argued at the time from the accretions that have been added in the light of subsequent knowledge. In short, Men- del did give us the concepts of “dominant” and “recessive” traits, the importance of quantifying the frequency of traits in the F1 and F2 generations, and the crucial generalization to unit ratios as indication of an underlying mechanism. However, he did all this in a framework where “trait” was the unit of analysis, and parental and hybrid traits could exist. He did not explicitly postulate “factors,” nor the Laws attributed to him. The classic 9:3:3:1 phenotype ratio from an F2 dihybrid cross is actually from Bateson; Mendel’s ratio was a more complex 1:1:1:1:2:2:2:2:4, cor- responding to what we (but not Mendel) call genotypes. Certainly it seems a short walk from here to textbook Mendelism, but those steps were not taken until the early 1900s. After some detours into the attempts of Darwin and others to construct a par- ticulate theory of heredity in the later 1800s, Kampourakis moves to the reception of Mendel’s work on hybrids, exculpating Nägeli from accusations of misdirecting Mendel. Mendel had already resolved to study hybrids in Hieracium (hawkweed) in 1866, rather than Nägeli suggesting this, but unfortunately Hieracium can produce seeds asexually (clones) as well as sexually, frustrating efforts to find ratios similar to those in peas. Kampourakis notes that Mendel (1866) was cited fourteen times before 1900, including by Nägeli and in a reference book on hybridization, and he credits Nägeli with being a positive influence on Weismann. Reviewing Mendel’s alleged “rediscovery” in 1900, Kampourakis suggests it might be “less heroic and romantic than what we would have liked it to be” (p. 77), in line with his overall theme that sci- entists typically act and think reasonably within the context of their field and time. In the turn-of-the-century context, with researchers on the hunt for a particulate theory of heredity, Mendel’s paper focused minds when re-read by other researchers who discovered unit ratios in hybrid crosses.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Kampourakis devotes longer chapters to the post-1900 development of Mendel- ism, the origin of the “gene” concept and its placement on chromosomes. Then, somewhat peculiarly, Kampourakis delves into the well-trodden ground of eugenics and Nazi racial hygiene. His framing is to examine how Mendelian genetics was employed in later versions of eugenics (early eugenics did not use particulate inheri- tance, and could even be Lamarckian), and he highlights the famous case of “feeble- mindedness,” where Mendelian assumptions were applied without good evidence. The view was strongly criticized from 1925 in the US (one could argue, although Kampourakis does not, that an advantage of Mendelian assertions is that they are highly testable), but nevertheless taken up widely in Germany. However, it does not appear that Kampourakis succeeds in demonstrating a strong connection between Mendelism and Nazi race science. He shows some examples where Punnett Squares and the like appear in race science educational materials. But the dominant Nazi rhetoric seems to be about “blood” and proportions of Jewish ancestry, harkening back to the older view of blending inheritance. Vague similarity between a pedigree chart showing continuous proportions of racial mixing (p. 188) and one showing a hypothetical Mendelian discrete trait (p. 186), or an argument that “it is easy to imag- ine how the teacher ... could combine the teaching of racial science and the teaching of Mendelian genetics to talk about racial purity” (p. 194) do not establish very much, except that Mendelism and race science both involve heredity. Kampourakis even admits the challenges that Nazi educators faced due to the fact that alleged “Nordic” traits (blond, blue eyes, long head) were not universal in German students; he says, “experts advised teachers to note that all ‘Aryan’ Germans had a significant portion of Nordic blood inside them, notwithstanding their appearance” (p. 194). Mendel schmendel! A stronger case could be made if there were examples of Nazis claiming that “Jewishness” or other race categories were Mendelian traits, but such thinking seems to have been too crude even for Nazi Germany, which of course was terrifying in part because of its advanced science.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Kampourakis, however, does not finish there. In the final chapter, he bootstraps from eugenics and Nazis to criticism of genetic essentialism (the language that there is a “gene-for” everything), and from that to the stunning assertion that “Mendel’s work cannot provide useful lessons for today’s genetics ... we had better drop Men- delian genetics altogether from the genetics curriculum: it is simply too inaccurate” (p. 207). What he has in mind is that most traits are polygenic (true) and involve com- plex biochemical and developmental chains of causation between DNA and pheno- type (true). But deleting Mendelism on this basis is rather like deleting atoms and the Periodic Table from chemistry because, after all, most matter we observe around us consists of complex amalgamations of compounds rather than pure elements. It also neglects that “today’s genetics,” while acknowledging all of this complexity, never- theless retains Mendelism at its conceptual, and operational, core. A spectacular new example (Feng et al. 2025) traces Mendel’s seven pea traits from DNA sequence, to chromosome position (conveniently allotted to Pisum’s seven chromosomes, except one trait that has a second locus), to biochemical and developmental mechanism. In evolutionary research, the modern importance of Mendelism ranges from routine tests for departures from Hardy-Weinberg Equilibrium in populations (Neamatzadeh et al. 2024), to genetic diversity measures in living and ancient DNA that rely on heterozygosity measured along diploid chromosomes (Prüfer et al. 2014), to genetic sex-determination mechanisms and their evolutionary impact on the sex chromosome of the heterogametic sex (the Y chromosome of marsupial and placental mammals is a highly reduced version of the X; Abbott et al. 2017; to Genome-Wide Association Studies (GWAS) which are based on correlating phenotypes with heterozygous and homozygous genotypes at individual loci.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Even the problems with standard GWAS illustrate the point further. Traits like Educational Attainment and other socioeconomic variables have been claimed, in scientific articles and the media, to have genetic causes demonstrated by GWAS. However, many of these correlations are spurious or dramatically overestimated, due to confounders like unmodeled population structure, or nongenetic inheritance of wealth and education. Admittedly, these problems are not rare, and are pernicious. However, even here, it is Mendel(ism) that has come to the rescue! In sibling-based GWAS, unlike standard GWAS, what is examined is the correlation of differences in traits between siblings with the differences in alleles between siblings. “Mendelian randomization,” conveniently provided by meiosis, provides a natural experiment not available in standard GWAS. And, interestingly, when the results of standard and sib-based GWAS are compared, the heritability estimates of various physical traits remain approximately constant, while the genetic contribution to variability in Educational Attainment drops to the floor (Mostafavi et al. 2020; Howe et al. 2022). Kampourakis is to be congratulated for correcting many myths about Mendel, but it seems clear that Mendelism is here to stay.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
References&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Abbott, Jessica K., K. Anna, Nordén, and Bengt Hansson. 2017. Sex chromosome evolution: Historical insights and future perspectives. Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences 420162806. https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2016.2806&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Feng, C., B. Chen., and J. Hofer et al. 2025. Genomic and genetic insights into mendel’s pea genes. Nature 642:980–989. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-08891-6&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Howe, L. J., M. G. Nivard, and T. T. Morris et al. 2022. Within-sibship genome-wide association analyses decrease bias in estimates of direct genetic effects. Nature Genetics 54:581–592. https://doi.org/10. 1038/s41588-022-01062-7&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Mostafavi, Hakhamanesh, Arbel Harpak, Ipsita Agarwal, Dalton Conley, Jonathan K. Pritchard, and Molly Przeworski. 2020. Variable prediction accuracy of polygenic scores within an ancestry group. eLife 9:e48376. https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.48376&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Neamatzadeh, H., S. A. Dastgheib, and M. Mazaheri et al. 2024. Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium in meta- analysis studies and large-scale genomic sequencing era. Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention 25:2229–2235. https://doi.org/10.31557/APJCP.2024.25.7.2229&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Prüfer, K., F. Racimo, and N. Patterson et al. 2014. The complete genome sequence of a neanderthal from the Altai mountains. Nature 505:43–49. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature12886&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;matzke-2025-update-on-the-evolution-of-antievolution-legislation&quot;&gt;Matzke (2025) Update on the evolution of antievolution legislation.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Update on antievolution legislation. I had intended to update the Matzke (2015) analysis of the “evolution of antievolution legislation.”  I have progressed this through the data coding stage, but now it’s the holidays so it will take a bit longer to do the phylogenetics. However, it’s interesting to paste all the bills since 2015 together to see the wacky stuff that is still proposed, and sometimes passed (like in West Virginia in 2024; see my comments in Science on that, published just before I wrote a letter to &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; on a similar scale of weirdness in science education coming from the other political side, in New Zealand).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have put the text file here: &lt;a href=&quot;/uploads/2025/2015-2025_antievo_bills.txt&quot;&gt;2015-2025_antievo_bills.txt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;References&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matzke, Nicholas (2015). The Evolution of Antievolution Policies After &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;, 351(6268), 10-12. Published online at ScienceExpress on December 17, 2015; print January 1, 2016. DOI: &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.aad4057&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.aad4057&lt;/a&gt; (Bonus material, media links, FAQ, etc. at: http://phylo.wikidot.com/matzke-2015-science-paper-on-the-evolution-of-antievolution )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matzke, Nicholas J. (2025). The biology class you WISHED You Could Have Taken. Talk for: Bay Area Skeptics, host Eugenie C. Scott. June 14, 2025. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b7UKOqCn9ao&amp;amp;t=13s&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b7UKOqCn9ao&amp;amp;t=13s&lt;/a&gt;
Slides: &lt;a href=&quot;http://phylo.wikidot.com/local--files/nicholas-j-matzke/Matzke_ID_flagellum_v7.pptx&quot;&gt;http://phylo.wikidot.com/local–files/nicholas-j-matzke/Matzke_ID_flagellum_v7.pptx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matzke, Nicholas J. (2025). “Science at a Crossroads.” Preface, pp. 6-9 of: Bartholomew, Robert E. (2025). &lt;i&gt;The Science of the Māori Lunar Calendar: Separating Fact from Folklore: A Scientific Appraisal of the Maramataka&lt;/i&gt;. Auckland, New Zealand: Robert Bartholomew. pp. 1-90. ISBN 9780473737030. &lt;a href=&quot;https://aotearoabooks.co.nz/the-science-of-the-maori-lunar-calendar/&quot;&gt;https://aotearoabooks.co.nz/the-science-of-the-maori-lunar-calendar/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matzke, Nicholas J. (2025). Interview: Matauranga Maori, der Mond, Neuseeland und die Wissenschaft. (In English: Mātauranga Māori, the Moon, New Zealand, and Science.) Interviewer: Andreas Edmüller. &lt;i&gt;Der Skeptiker&lt;/i&gt; 3325, 3/2025, pp. 146-149. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwup.org/produkt/skeptiker-3-2025/#tab-id-2&quot;&gt;https://www.gwup.org/produkt/skeptiker-3-2025/#tab-id-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matzke, Nicholas J. (2025). Mendel was of his time, but Mendelism is modern. Review of: Kostas Kampourakis, &lt;i&gt;How We Get Mendel Wrong, and Why It Matters: Challenging the Narrative of Mendelian Genetics&lt;/i&gt;, Boca Raton: CRC Press, 2024, ISBN 9781032456904, 250 pp. &lt;i&gt;Journal of Historical Biology&lt;/i&gt;, accepted August 10, 2025. DOI: &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10739-025-09835-6&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10739-025-09835-6&lt;/a&gt; . Sharable Link: &lt;a href=&quot;https://rdcu.be/eH3Zu&quot;&gt;https://rdcu.be/eH3Zu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Matzke</name></author><summary type="html">Nick Matzke at the Dayton County Courthouse where the Scopes Trial was held in 1925. (photo from ~2014) The year 2025 is the 20th anniversary of the Kitzmiller v. Dover case. Celebrations were held throughout the year as part of the 100th anniversary of Scopes. I got to attend the July 2025 Nashville Scopes Trial event on the campus of Vanderbilt University, where I got to reconnect with many Doverians and other veterans of the evolution wars. Many of those talks are now online on YouTube. Just after that, I also got to see my 100-year old grandmother one last time. She passed away soon after at the age of 101. Her life spanned the entire American creation/evolution debate from 1924-2025. Ironically, grandma sending me creationism books when I was a kid in the 1980s is part of what got me into the creation/evolution debate in the first place. This wasn’t the first time I’ve found my family history and the creationism debate crashing together: back in 2009, I gave a talk to the University of Oklahoma Zoology Department as part of their series for the 150th anniversary of the Origin of Species, then found myself sharing a bed-and-breakfast with Richard Dawkins who was giving a talk to the whole University. In the space of 24 hours I found myself dining with my creationist grandma and someone who was basically her arch-nemesis. We invite readers to give their own reflections on Dover, the science/creationism debate and subsequent developments, or personal updates in the comments below. Also, if they like, Kitzmiller participants can send me comments for me to add as edits to the main post (this may take a bit, as I’m now on holiday with the Aussie side of the family; the kids tell me there is a koala down the road). I will post several updates from this year which I hope you will enjoy. I should have blogged these at the time, but, well, 3 kids and a day job! Matzke, Nicholas J. (2025). The biology class you WISHED You Could Have Taken. Talk for: Bay Area Skeptics, host Eugenie C. Scott. June 14, 2025. https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b7UKOqCn9ao&amp;amp;t=13s Slides: http://phylo.wikidot.com/local–files/nicholas-j-matzke/Matzke_ID_flagellum_v7.pptx Matzke, Nicholas J. (2025). “Science at a Crossroads.” Preface, pp. 6-9 of: Bartholomew, Robert E. (2025). The Science of the Māori Lunar Calendar: Separating Fact from Folklore: A Scientific Appraisal of the Maramataka. Auckland, New Zealand: Robert Bartholomew. pp. 1-90. ISBN 9780473737030. https://aotearoabooks.co.nz/the-science-of-the-maori-lunar-calendar/ Matzke, Nicholas J. (2025). Interview: Matauranga Maori, der Mond, Neuseeland und die Wissenschaft. (In English: Mātauranga Māori, the Moon, New Zealand, and Science.) Interviewer: Andreas Edmüller. Der Skeptiker 3325, 3/2025, pp. 146-149. https://www.gwup.org/produkt/skeptiker-3-2025/#tab-id-2 Matzke, Nicholas J. (2025). Mendel was of his time, but Mendelism is modern. Review of: Kostas Kampourakis, How We Get Mendel Wrong, and Why It Matters: Challenging the Narrative of Mendelian Genetics, Boca Raton: CRC Press, 2024, ISBN 9781032456904, 250 pp. Journal of Historical Biology, accepted August 10, 2025. DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10739-025-09835-6 . Sharable Link: https://rdcu.be/eH3Zu Update on antievolution legislation. I had intended to update the Matzke (2015) analysis of the “evolution of antievolution legislation.” I have progressed this through the data coding stage, but now it’s the holidays so it will take a bit longer to do the phylogenetics. However, it’s interesting to paste all the bills since 2015 together to see the wacky stuff that is still proposed, and sometimes passed (like in West Virginia in 2024; see my comments in Science on that, published just before I wrote a letter to Science on a similar scale of weirdness in science education coming from the other political side, in New Zealand).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Evil mad scientists steal credit</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/stealingcredit.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evil mad scientists steal credit" /><published>2025-12-16T18:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-12-16T18:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/stealingcredit</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/stealingcredit.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;uploads/2025/evilmadscientist.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Evil Mad Scientist]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
(Actually, Evil Mad Scientist Laboratories is a business selling open-source&lt;br /&gt;
electronic equipment, describing themselves as &quot;Making the world a better&lt;br /&gt; 
place, one evil mad scientist at a time.&quot;)  Credit: Wikimedia Creative Commons.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately, the Discovery Institute’s ID site Science and Culture has had almost 
no arguments that would convince any scientist that Intelligent Design 
contributed to the diversity of life.  Michael Behe’s arguments are the 
same as before, and William Dembski’s latest versions of his specified 
complexity argument leaves out any discussion of why having a large 
value (of his Algorithmic Specified Complexity) cannot be achieved by 
ordinary evolutionary processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at S&amp;amp;C they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; getting a bit angry at evolutionary biologists. For 
stealing credit that belongs to ID advocates.  A post on December 12, 
is titled “All the Evidence Points to Design, but the Credit Goes to … You Know What”. 
Even more remarkably, its author is “Science and Culture”.  This makes it 
an official statement by the site.  Or else none of their people want to 
take credit or blame for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They simply point to an article at BioEssays on “spatiotemporal cues in 
cell division”, in particular to its last paragraph, which contains the 
sentence (boldface text is S&amp;amp;C’s emphasis):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why evolution selected chromosomes&lt;/strong&gt; as a platform to integrate different signals 
is easily explained by the need to concentrate mitotic regulators (and their control) 
which would otherwise dilute in a vast cytoplasmic ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and S&amp;amp;C’s comment is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many years ago, William Dembski said that one of the most objectionable aspects of modern evolutionary theory was the undeserved, unearned credit it steals from the exquisite, transcendentally elegant work of the Designer. Put more bluntly, evolution is a credit thief, a lowdown sleazy embezzler. If we could personify evolution, we’d have ChatGPT make a drawing of the word as a convict with a prison serial number across its chest.
But if you just put your thumb over the word “evolution” in the phrase we highlighted, all the evidence for design is still there, and it’s just too cool for words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See, all the wonderful details of biological systems must be evidence for Intelligent Design, 
it’s so obvious that they figure anyone can see this.  If a biologist lapses into 
teleological language that personifies evolution, this must mean they acknowledge 
that Design Intervention happened, but are too scared to admit it, and give credit to 
a personified Evolution instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the matter can be looked at another way …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evolutionary biologists would mostly not bother to pay attention, 
but those that did would notice that S&amp;amp;C is impressed by 
lots of phenotypes and behaviors that are the result of natural 
selection.  They would notice that the BioEssays article yields 
to an unfortunate temptation to personify natural selection, in 
a burst of enthusiasm at the end of the article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As to who is stealing credit, it is clear that S&amp;amp;C is.  But this 
is mostly silly, rather than distressing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">(Actually, Evil Mad Scientist Laboratories is a business selling open-source electronic equipment, describing themselves as &quot;Making the world a better place, one evil mad scientist at a time.&quot;) Credit: Wikimedia Creative Commons. &amp;nbsp; Lately, the Discovery Institute’s ID site Science and Culture has had almost no arguments that would convince any scientist that Intelligent Design contributed to the diversity of life. Michael Behe’s arguments are the same as before, and William Dembski’s latest versions of his specified complexity argument leaves out any discussion of why having a large value (of his Algorithmic Specified Complexity) cannot be achieved by ordinary evolutionary processes. But at S&amp;amp;C they are getting a bit angry at evolutionary biologists. For stealing credit that belongs to ID advocates. A post on December 12, is titled “All the Evidence Points to Design, but the Credit Goes to … You Know What”. Even more remarkably, its author is “Science and Culture”. This makes it an official statement by the site. Or else none of their people want to take credit or blame for it. They simply point to an article at BioEssays on “spatiotemporal cues in cell division”, in particular to its last paragraph, which contains the sentence (boldface text is S&amp;amp;C’s emphasis): Why evolution selected chromosomes as a platform to integrate different signals is easily explained by the need to concentrate mitotic regulators (and their control) which would otherwise dilute in a vast cytoplasmic ocean. and S&amp;amp;C’s comment is Many years ago, William Dembski said that one of the most objectionable aspects of modern evolutionary theory was the undeserved, unearned credit it steals from the exquisite, transcendentally elegant work of the Designer. Put more bluntly, evolution is a credit thief, a lowdown sleazy embezzler. If we could personify evolution, we’d have ChatGPT make a drawing of the word as a convict with a prison serial number across its chest. But if you just put your thumb over the word “evolution” in the phrase we highlighted, all the evidence for design is still there, and it’s just too cool for words. See, all the wonderful details of biological systems must be evidence for Intelligent Design, it’s so obvious that they figure anyone can see this. If a biologist lapses into teleological language that personifies evolution, this must mean they acknowledge that Design Intervention happened, but are too scared to admit it, and give credit to a personified Evolution instead. Well, the matter can be looked at another way …</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The deadly fact that doomed intelligent design</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/deadly-fact-doomed-intelligent-desogn.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The deadly fact that doomed intelligent design" /><published>2025-12-15T21:12:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-12-15T21:12:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/deadly-fact-doomed-intelligent-desogn</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/deadly-fact-doomed-intelligent-desogn.html">&lt;p&gt;Judge John Jones III of Dover, Pennsylvania, fame is now president of Dickinson College in Carlisle, Pennsylvania. A certain little bird told us today of an interview with President Jones reported by Seth Kaplan of television station WHTM in Harrisburg: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.abc27.com/news/the-deadly-fact-that-doomed-intelligent-design-in-dover-schools-20-years-ago-this-month/&quot;&gt;The ‘deadly’ fact that doomed ‘intelligent design’ in Dover schools 20 years ago this month&lt;/a&gt;. The interview was interesting, in part because President Jones, as the little bird put it, discusses the case itself, not legal matters. In particular, President Jones pointed out many problems with the defense’s case, including,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Side-by-side comparisons between the version of “Of Pandas and People” on the school library shelf and a previous version: “The prior edition had the words ‘creation science,’ and they simply changed those words in the in the (sic) later edition of the book to to ‘intelligent design’ — pretty deadly if you’re trying to say that that intelligent design is not the successor to creation science,” Jones said.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“When asked who the designer was, they [defense witnesses] were compelled in honesty to say that they felt the designer was God,” Jones said. “Fair enough, but that makes it difficult to uphold as a scientific concept.”&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Kaplan’s article, linked above, is worth reading in its entirety.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Judge John Jones III of Dover, Pennsylvania, fame is now president of Dickinson College in Carlisle, Pennsylvania. A certain little bird told us today of an interview with President Jones reported by Seth Kaplan of television station WHTM in Harrisburg: The ‘deadly’ fact that doomed ‘intelligent design’ in Dover schools 20 years ago this month. The interview was interesting, in part because President Jones, as the little bird put it, discusses the case itself, not legal matters. In particular, President Jones pointed out many problems with the defense’s case, including, Side-by-side comparisons between the version of “Of Pandas and People” on the school library shelf and a previous version: “The prior edition had the words ‘creation science,’ and they simply changed those words in the in the (sic) later edition of the book to to ‘intelligent design’ — pretty deadly if you’re trying to say that that intelligent design is not the successor to creation science,” Jones said. “When asked who the designer was, they [defense witnesses] were compelled in honesty to say that they felt the designer was God,” Jones said. “Fair enough, but that makes it difficult to uphold as a scientific concept.” Mr. Kaplan’s article, linked above, is worth reading in its entirety.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Agave neomexicana</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/agave-neomexicana.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Agave neomexicana" /><published>2025-12-08T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-12-08T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/agave-neomexicana</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/agave-neomexicana.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Ron Wittmann&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/PXL_20250624_Wittmann_Yucca_1_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photograph of yucca flowers&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Ron Wittmann's yucca plant, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/06/agave-neomexicana.html&quot;&gt;Agave mexicana&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;, in full bloom on August 21, several weeks after the earlier photograph (link) taken on June 6 of this year. Mr. Wittmann tells us that the plant has not bloomed in 25 years and will not bloom again.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Ron Wittmann. Ron Wittmann's yucca plant, Agave mexicana, in full bloom on August 21, several weeks after the earlier photograph (link) taken on June 6 of this year. Mr. Wittmann tells us that the plant has not bloomed in 25 years and will not bloom again.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interstellar Comets: Creationism’s Missed Opportunity?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/interstellar-comets.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interstellar Comets: Creationism’s Missed Opportunity?" /><published>2025-12-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-12-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/interstellar-comets</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/12/interstellar-comets.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/3I-ATLASa.png&quot; alt=&quot;[Image of 3I/Atlas]&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;A deep image of interstellar Comet 3I/ATLAS captured by the Gemini &lt;br /&gt;Multi-Object Spectrograph (GMOS) on Gemini South at Cerro Pachón&lt;br /&gt; in Chile.  From Wikimedia CC 4.0&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On November 29, Answers In Genesis apologist and astronomer Danny Faulkner posted an article on the interstellar comet 3I/ATLAS. Dr. Faulkner’s article sensibly dismissed popular speculation (including persistent claims by Harvard professor Avi Loeb) that 3I/ATLAS and similar objects might be artificial probes or alien artifacts. But in doing so, Faulkner never addressed the only question that is cosmologically relevant for a young-earth framework: Where did this object come from? Interstellar comets are not curiosities or distractions; they are kinematic probes: natural test cases for any model purporting that the universe is only a few thousand years old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an organization that claims to be able to give “Answers” about what they call “origin science”, Answers In Genesis is suspiciously quiet about the origins of interstellar comets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-third-interstellar-comet&quot;&gt;The Third Interstellar Comet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since the rise of wide-field astronomical surveys, astronomers have kept a vigilant watch on the skies for near-Earth objects (NEOs): asteroids and comets whose orbits may bring them close to the Earth, with potential risk of impact. But beyond planetary defense, surveys also catalog a broad variety of small bodies because these minor objects carry clues about the formation and evolution of planetary systems: their orbits, compositions, and dynamics help scientists trace back when and how they formed, and how stable their source systems remain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comets in our solar system come in different flavors. Short-period comets have orbits closely bound to the Sun, often returning every few years or decades, typically originating in the Kuiper Belt or closer. Long-period comets have highly elongated but still bound orbits, often taking thousands or millions of years to complete (usually thought to arise in the distant Oort Cloud). Both of these types remain gravitationally bound to the Sun, albeit with very different orbital periods. A third, much rarer category — hyperbolic or interstellar comets — follows an unbound trajectory. Their eccentricity exceeds 1, placing them on a one-time pass through the Solar System: they arrive from interstellar space, swing past the Sun, and then depart forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2025, the world encountered only the third such confirmed interstellar visitor. The first was 1I/ʻOumuamua, discovered in October 2017, followed by 2I/Borisov, announced in August 2019. The newest, 3I/ATLAS, officially designated C/2025 N1 (ATLAS), was discovered this July by the Asteroid Terrestrial-impact Last Alert System (ATLAS) telescope in Chile. Follow-up observations soon confirmed its extremely hyperbolic orbit. Because 3I/ATLAS is active (i.e., showing a fuzzy coma and dust tail, like a “normal” comet) astronomers treat it as a genuine cometary body, not a rocky asteroid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;faulkners-cosmological-commitments&quot;&gt;Faulkner’s Cosmological Commitments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Danny Faulkner has become the predominant AIG author and speaker on issues of astronomy since the departure of Dr. Jason Lisle some years ago, writing on topics ranging from light-travel-time and starlight problems to extrasolar planets, dark matter and dark energy, planetary system formation, and the operation of modern astronomical instruments like the James Webb Space Telescope. Over the years, he has articulated a reasonably consistent set of commitments in his elucidation of a “Biblical” cosmology. In defense of a recent special creation, he has argued that divine creation is characterized by stability and order, even using this perceived order as evidence for divine design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just two years ago, while explaining the evidence for dark matter, Faulkner wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Creationists have long advanced the idea that there is design and stability in the world. For instance, some creationists speak about the stability of both planetary orbits and the orbits of the planets’ natural satellites, and even the stability of systems beyond the solar system. Which is it? Did God create a stable world, or did He create an unstable world? Are creationists willing to sacrifice the stability argument in favor of a lesser argument for relatively recent origin?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Science progresses only when we change and develop our models as new data are found. Rather than ignoring or denying the data that are invoked in support of dark matter and dark energy, recent creationists must produce their own models to interpret this data. Only through this difficult process can significant progress be made in achieving a robust, truly biblical cosmology/cosmogony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faulkner treats this concept of a stable, orderly universe as a foundational theological principle. This theme recurs throughout Faulkner’s popular writings, lectures, and technical papers, where orbital regularity, galactic coherence, and the long-term persistence of planetary systems are repeatedly cited as marks of divine design cutting against the perceived “chaos” of stellar evolution. Stability is not merely descriptive in his framework; it functions as a theological constraint on cosmological interpretation: a necessary feature of a created universe that must remain physically intelligible rather than dynamically deceptive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, comets have long been held up by creationists as part of their broadly-debunked suite of “evidences” for a young earth. Faulkner has frequently argued that because active comets lose material with each solar passage, a population persisting over millions or billions of years would require continuous replenishment, something he claims has never been convincingly demonstrated. Instead, he maintains that the observed numbers of comets are best explained by recent creation, with gradual depletion through sublimation and gravitational scattering accounting for their observed fading. Similar arguments appear across AiG publications, where both short-period and long-period comets are presented as transient populations inconsistent with deep time and therefore evidence for a young solar system — arguments that explicitly rely on the physical loss and ejection of comets as natural dynamical processes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Comets have little mass, so each close pass to the sun greatly reduces a comet’s size, and eventually comets fade away. They can’t survive billions of years.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Two other mechanisms can destroy comets—ejections from the solar system and collisions with planets. Ejections happen as comets pass too close to the large planets, particularly Jupiter, and the planets’ gravity kicks them out of the solar system. While ejections have been observed many times, the first observed collision was in 1994, when Comet Shoemaker-Levi IX slammed into Jupiter.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Given the loss rates, it’s easy to compute a maximum age of comets. That maximum age is only a few million years. Obviously, their prevalence makes sense if the entire solar system was created just a few thousand years ago, but not if it arose billions of years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, these commitments form a coherent cosmological picture. Comets originate as real members of real star systems. Gravitational processes can eject them from those systems. After ejection, these bodies travel under ordinary Newtonian mechanics. Their motions are real and physically meaningful, not illusory or metaphorical. Crucially, nothing in Faulkner’s published framework permits comets to materialize mid-flight or exist without physical origin. Their histories, at least in principle, should be observationally tractable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-creationist-cosmology-predicts&quot;&gt;What Creationist Cosmology Predicts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Faulkner takes his own worldview seriously, he has to acknowledge that interstellar comets carry direct and testable implications. Any such object must originate from a previously existing stellar or planetary system that formed part of God’s stable created order. Once ejected, its motion through space becomes a straightforward problem of classical kinematics. Velocity multiplied by time yields a maximum travel distance. Trajectories point backward to source regions. Each interstellar comet should therefore act as a natural tracer pointing toward the location of its parent system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under a genuine 6,000-year cosmology, the implications are clear. Because Faulkner’s universe is so young, any object traveling at tens of kilometers per second could only have come from a very small local neighborhood around the Sun. Unlike scientific cosmology—which recognizes that the galaxy and universe are billions of years old—young-earth models compress physical possibility into an extremely confined volume of space. Interstellar comets, rather than being awkward anomalies, should therefore become some of the most powerful discovery tools available to creationist astronomers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-physics-of-3iatlas&quot;&gt;The Physics of 3I/ATLAS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The physics of 3I/ATLAS are simple and uncontroversial. Its perihelion velocity was measured at approximately 68.3 kilometers per second. Combining that value with the object’s hyperbolic eccentricity allows computation of its hyperbolic excess velocity, the speed it had when effectively outside the Sun’s gravitational influence. This velocity is about 58 kilometers per second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even on a very generous 6,000-year timescale, an object traveling at that constant speed could traverse only about 10^13 kilometers: just under 1.2 light-years. This figure establishes a firm upper bound: under young-earth cosmology, any natural parent system for 3I/ATLAS must lie within a sphere extending less than 1.2 light-years from Earth, and the comet’s incoming trajectory must align with that location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know, however, that no such star systems are presently catalogued. Proxima Centauri, Alpha Centauri, and Barnard’s Star—the nearest known stellar neighbors—lie at distances several times that limit, and none align with 3I/ATLAS’s observed arrival direction anyway. Within Faulkner’s framework, therefore, 3I/ATLAS could not plausibly have originated from any known star system. This realization should drive young-earth cosmology to an obvious and specific prediction: there must exist one or more yet-undiscovered star systems, brown dwarfs, or massive planetary bodies within 1.2 light-years of Earth lying along the comet’s trajectory that served as its point of ejection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If creationists adhered seriously to their own cosmology, this conclusion would be exhilarating rather than inconvenient. Each interstellar comet would provide a geometric “search cone” on the sky defining where the undiscovered parent object must lie. Reducing the universe to a 6,000-year age compresses the allowed volume so tightly that the relevant search zones become modest and tractable. Modern infrared surveys, and especially the James Webb Space Telescope, are capable of detecting extremely faint stellar and substellar objects that earlier instruments might have missed. Creationists should be pressing for dedicated sky surveys in the predicted regions, attempting to identify their missing neighbors before secular astronomy stumbles across them incidentally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success would be a spectacular triumph: direct empirical confirmation of a major young-earth prediction. That is the essence of scientific testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;an-expanding-pattern&quot;&gt;An Expanding Pattern&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The predictive pressure strengthens when the earlier interstellar visitors are included. 1I/’Oumuamua and 2I/Borisov entered the solar system with even lower excess velocities than 3I/ATLAS, meaning that under young-earth time limits they must have originated from even closer parent systems than 3I/ATLAS requires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 1I/ʻOumuamua, with a hyperbolic excess velocity of roughly 26.3 km/s, even a full 6,000-year transit would limit its origin to a distance of about 0.55 light-years, and its steep orbital inclination of 122.7° places its incoming direction far from alignment with any known nearby stellar system. For 2I/Borisov, traveling somewhat faster at approximately 32 km/s, the maximum 6,000-year travel distance increases only to around 0.65 light-years, with its 44° inclination likewise incompatible with the directions of known nearby stars. In both cases, the required parent systems would need to lie even closer to the Sun than the hypothetical source implied by 3I/ATLAS — within fractions of a light-year along their respective inbound trajectories — yet no such stellar or substellar objects are known to exist in those regions of the sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sky volume of possible sources for 1I/’Oumuamua and 2I/Borisov therefore becomes smaller still. Under a functioning young-earth research program, these objects should already have yielded a growing catalog of predicted nearby systems awaiting observational confirmation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet nothing of the sort exists. No sky-cone analyses have been published. No target fields have been identified. No JWST proposals have been announced. No predictions have been offered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is only silence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;theological-retreat&quot;&gt;Theological Retreat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this sort of silence is not all that surprising. Pursuing these predictions would almost certainly lead to failure, and that failure would constitute a direct and visible refutation of young-earth cosmology. Instead, the problem of origin is quietly avoided altogether. If pressed, Faulkner would likely be forced to argue a nonsensical origin: the comet did not come from anywhere; it was simply created already traveling through space, with a trajectory tracing back toward a nonexistent point of origin, like a real bullet fired from an imaginary gun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This explanation is not a theoretical lifeline—it is an intellectual collapse. Faulkner has insisted that cosmic stability and lawful dynamics testify to the Creator’s design. “Created in transit” abandons those commitments. If moving bodies are not products of physical histories but fabricated with fictitious kinematics, then trajectories cease to encode past motion. Velocities become meaningless numbers with no historical content. Astronomy itself loses any capacity to infer origins or causes. Every observation can be dismissed as a specially arranged appearance, immune to test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interstellar comets offer perhaps the most direct empirical test yet available for young-earth cosmology. If its advocates truly believed their claims about cosmic stability, real celestial mechanics, and comets originating within star systems, they would treat objects like 3I/ATLAS as opportunities for bold prediction. Instead, these opportunities are ignored, because serious engagement would expose the model to decisive risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with young-earth astronomy is not that it makes incorrect predictions. It is that it refuses to make predictions at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Special thanks to Dan Phelps for calling attention to Faulkner’s silence on the origins of interstellar comets and to the University of Kentucky’s Dr. Thomas Troland for discussions on the kinematics of comet ejection.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;FIGURE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
For clearly-visible image &lt;a href=&quot;/uploads/2025/interstellar.png&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;click here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This infographic visualizes the kinematic challenge posed by interstellar comets to a recently-created cosmos. The main panel (5 ly scale) shows the nearest eight known stellar neighbors (yellow) and the trajectories of 1I/ʻOumuamua, 2I/Borisov, and 3I/ATLAS (grey lines). The white segments highlight the maximum distance each comet could have traveled in 6,029 years. Critically, these segments terminate far short of every known star, forcing the young-earth model to predict three undiscovered source bodies located precisely at the end of the white lines. The inset panel (0.5 ly scale) contains an additional inset zoomed in to 400X the main panel to show these source termination points relative to the outer solar system, where the trajectories of the planets and outgoing space probes are visible.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>David MacMillan</name></author><summary type="html">A deep image of interstellar Comet 3I/ATLAS captured by the Gemini Multi-Object Spectrograph (GMOS) on Gemini South at Cerro Pachón in Chile. From Wikimedia CC 4.0   On November 29, Answers In Genesis apologist and astronomer Danny Faulkner posted an article on the interstellar comet 3I/ATLAS. Dr. Faulkner’s article sensibly dismissed popular speculation (including persistent claims by Harvard professor Avi Loeb) that 3I/ATLAS and similar objects might be artificial probes or alien artifacts. But in doing so, Faulkner never addressed the only question that is cosmologically relevant for a young-earth framework: Where did this object come from? Interstellar comets are not curiosities or distractions; they are kinematic probes: natural test cases for any model purporting that the universe is only a few thousand years old. For an organization that claims to be able to give “Answers” about what they call “origin science”, Answers In Genesis is suspiciously quiet about the origins of interstellar comets. The Third Interstellar Comet Ever since the rise of wide-field astronomical surveys, astronomers have kept a vigilant watch on the skies for near-Earth objects (NEOs): asteroids and comets whose orbits may bring them close to the Earth, with potential risk of impact. But beyond planetary defense, surveys also catalog a broad variety of small bodies because these minor objects carry clues about the formation and evolution of planetary systems: their orbits, compositions, and dynamics help scientists trace back when and how they formed, and how stable their source systems remain. Comets in our solar system come in different flavors. Short-period comets have orbits closely bound to the Sun, often returning every few years or decades, typically originating in the Kuiper Belt or closer. Long-period comets have highly elongated but still bound orbits, often taking thousands or millions of years to complete (usually thought to arise in the distant Oort Cloud). Both of these types remain gravitationally bound to the Sun, albeit with very different orbital periods. A third, much rarer category — hyperbolic or interstellar comets — follows an unbound trajectory. Their eccentricity exceeds 1, placing them on a one-time pass through the Solar System: they arrive from interstellar space, swing past the Sun, and then depart forever. In 2025, the world encountered only the third such confirmed interstellar visitor. The first was 1I/ʻOumuamua, discovered in October 2017, followed by 2I/Borisov, announced in August 2019. The newest, 3I/ATLAS, officially designated C/2025 N1 (ATLAS), was discovered this July by the Asteroid Terrestrial-impact Last Alert System (ATLAS) telescope in Chile. Follow-up observations soon confirmed its extremely hyperbolic orbit. Because 3I/ATLAS is active (i.e., showing a fuzzy coma and dust tail, like a “normal” comet) astronomers treat it as a genuine cometary body, not a rocky asteroid. Faulkner’s Cosmological Commitments Dr. Danny Faulkner has become the predominant AIG author and speaker on issues of astronomy since the departure of Dr. Jason Lisle some years ago, writing on topics ranging from light-travel-time and starlight problems to extrasolar planets, dark matter and dark energy, planetary system formation, and the operation of modern astronomical instruments like the James Webb Space Telescope. Over the years, he has articulated a reasonably consistent set of commitments in his elucidation of a “Biblical” cosmology. In defense of a recent special creation, he has argued that divine creation is characterized by stability and order, even using this perceived order as evidence for divine design.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Spider with box elder bug</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/spider-with-box-elder.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spider with box elder bug" /><published>2025-11-24T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-11-24T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/spider-with-box-elder</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/spider-with-box-elder.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/DSC06129_Spider_Box_Elder_Bug_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spider attacking a box elder bug trapped in the spiderweb&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Spider about to lunch on a box elder bug, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boisea_trivittata&quot;&gt;Boisea trivittata&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. If the bug is approximately 1&amp;nbsp;cm long, the spider must be a few millimeters. The spider repeatedly dashed in, perhaps to sting the bug, and then dashed out nervously, before settling in to dine. If anyone can identify the spider I will edit the post (the image is too small for BugGuide). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another shot of a box elder bug below the fold:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/IMG_6211_Box_Elder_Bug_600_2.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Incidentally, a snapshot of a box elder bug that I posted in 2008, before the Big Computer Crash. It shows the markings on the bug better than the picture with the spider.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Spider about to lunch on a box elder bug, Boisea trivittata. If the bug is approximately 1&amp;nbsp;cm long, the spider must be a few millimeters. The spider repeatedly dashed in, perhaps to sting the bug, and then dashed out nervously, before settling in to dine. If anyone can identify the spider I will edit the post (the image is too small for BugGuide). Another shot of a box elder bug below the fold:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Darwin Comes to Town: a meditation</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/darwin-comes-to-town.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Darwin Comes to Town: a meditation" /><published>2025-11-17T10:05:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-11-17T10:05:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/darwin-comes-to-town</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/darwin-comes-to-town.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Schilthuizen_Darwin_Comes_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently came across this fascinating book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Darwin-Comes-Town-Jungle-Evolution/dp/1250127823&quot;&gt;Darwin Comes to Town: How the Urban Jungle Drives Evolution&lt;/a&gt;, by the biologist Menno Schilthuizen of the Naturalis Biodiversity Center and the University of Leiden. Years ago, probably about when it appeared in 2001, I read Prof. Schilthuizen’s equally fascinating book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Frogs-Flies-Dandelions-Speciation-Evolution/dp/0198503938&quot;&gt;Frogs, Flies, and Dandelions&lt;/a&gt;, about the origins and definitions of species (indeed, the difficulty of defining species at all). So naturally I snapped up &lt;i&gt;Darwin Comes to Town&lt;/i&gt;. The title is a pun, in that the book is about the evolution of organisms that have either adapted to cities or towns, or have adopted cities or towns. I will not review the book, but will pen 3 or 4 paragraphs about chapters that for one reason or another especially interested me. If you want more, read the book!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first organism that Schilthuizen describes in detail is a &lt;i&gt;Culex molestus&lt;/i&gt; mosquito that he discovers in the London Underground. Outside the Underground, evidently the mosquito feeds on birds, has an interesting sex life that involves large swarms, and also hibernates. Inside the Underground, it has learned to feed on humans, “seek [its] sexual pleasures in confined spaces,” and not hibernate. Its genes spread from city to city, presumably by plane, train, or car, and it interbreeds with its above-ground relatives. All this happened, Schilthuizen assures us, very recently, probably only since humans began digging tunnels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was still reading the book, I came across a very short article in a &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; magazine newsletter, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.aed2501&quot;&gt;Cultivating a pest&lt;/a&gt;, by Corinne Simonti. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ady4515&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; by Yuki Haba et al. recently reported that, contrary to what Schilthuizen has written, these mosquitoes, which they call &lt;i&gt;Culex pipiens&lt;/i&gt; form &lt;i&gt;molestus&lt;/i&gt;, have a much longer association with us humans, and probably date back to the ancient Middle East. As I was reading these references, I cattily wondered how a biblical literalist, for example, would have responded if such a well-established “fact” had been disestablished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some time ago, in 2005, I became something of a minor expert on the peppered moth and posted an article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://skepticalinquirer.org/2005/03/moonshine-2/&quot;&gt;Moonshine: Why the Peppered Moth Remains an Icon of Evolution&lt;/a&gt;, with my colleague Ian Musgrave (who deserves all the credit for the &lt;i&gt;Moonshine&lt;/i&gt; title; you may have to read the article to learn why). A short chapter, Urban Myths, told the story of the peppered moth clearly and concisely, including the “controversy” instigated by the journalist Judith Hooper. Hooper’s book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Moths-Men-Evolutionary-Tale/dp/0393051218&quot;&gt;Of Moths and Men: An Evolutionary Tale&lt;/a&gt;, was, in Schilthuizen’s words, well-researched, but then without evidence she accused an important moth researcher, Bernard Kettlewell, of fraud. Musgrave and I took up her claims and showed that Hooper did not understand the vagaries of fieldwork in biology and almost without doubt Kettlewell had not committed fraud. Unfortunately, our paper was not published in a technical journal (I frankly do not remember why not), and Schilthuizen was unaware of it; I thought perhaps he might otherwise have been harder on Hooper. (Incidentally, for a discussion of creationists’ response to the case of the peppered moth, see the article by Paul Braterman, &lt;a href=&quot;https://3quarksdaily.com/3quarksdaily/2013/08/creationism-as-conspiracy-theory-the-case-of-the-peppered-moth.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is lots more in this book, but I want to get to the last part, where Schilthuizen discusses exotic or non-native species. He suggests, frankly, that they are here to stay and that eventually all cities will have very similar floras and faunas because they are intertwined by modern transportation. This contention leads him to the conclusion, which many will find contentious, that we might as well give in, embrace non-native species and even plant them when it seems appropriate. As a person who passionately hates field bindweed (&lt;i&gt;Convolvulus arvensis&lt;/i&gt;), I will be curious to know what others think of his proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, of course, reader’s last inch: I thought the book was uncommonly well written and used anecdotes such as his own interactions with the experts to great advantage. Not once that I recall was I bored or thought he should get on to the next topic already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Prof. Schilthuizen recommended to me his latest book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Urban-Naturalist-Make-Scientific-Playground/dp/0262049090&quot;&gt;The Urban Naturalist: How to Make the City Your Scientific Playground&lt;/a&gt;, which was published last April and is sort of a sequel. You may be sure that it is on my list.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I recently came across this fascinating book, Darwin Comes to Town: How the Urban Jungle Drives Evolution, by the biologist Menno Schilthuizen of the Naturalis Biodiversity Center and the University of Leiden. Years ago, probably about when it appeared in 2001, I read Prof. Schilthuizen’s equally fascinating book, Frogs, Flies, and Dandelions, about the origins and definitions of species (indeed, the difficulty of defining species at all). So naturally I snapped up Darwin Comes to Town. The title is a pun, in that the book is about the evolution of organisms that have either adapted to cities or towns, or have adopted cities or towns. I will not review the book, but will pen 3 or 4 paragraphs about chapters that for one reason or another especially interested me. If you want more, read the book!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The DI’s Science and Culture News announces that a “Darwinist” changed his mind</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/Darwinist-changes-his-mind.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The DI’s Science and Culture News announces that a “Darwinist” changed his mind" /><published>2025-11-16T18:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2025-11-16T18:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/Darwinist-changes-his-mind</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/Darwinist-changes-his-mind.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Master_Tom.png&quot; alt=&quot;[Master Tom in Sydenham]&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Discovery Institute’s website “Science and Culture” (formerly Evolution 
News and Views) had a dramatic story of conversion recently.  A &lt;a href=&quot;https://scienceandculture.com/2025/10/he-taught-darwinism-for-decades-then-changed-his-mind/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; entitled “He Taught Darwinism for Decades (Then Changed His Mind)” by
Andrew McDiarmid on 30 October 2025.  It announced that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For decades, British professor and author Neil Thomas was a card-carrying Darwinist. It wasn’t until after he retired from academia that he had the repose to think about things objectively. 
Then one day, in a scientific flash of inspiration, he came to the conclusion that the standard Darwinian story was “rubbish.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is that Neil Thomas has written two books, published by 
the DI’s publishing outfit, Discovery Institute Press:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/1637120036&quot;&gt;Taking Leave of Darwin: A longtime Agnostic Discovers the Case for Design&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/False-Messiah-Darwinism-That-Failed/dp/163712080X&quot;&gt;False Messiah: Darwinism as The God That Failed&lt;/a&gt;.  He has also 
made numbers of posts at Science and Culture since 2021, see them &lt;a href=&quot;https://scienceandculture.com/author/nthomas/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  He was intervewed in a 
two-part (&lt;a href=&quot;https://idthefuture.com/2127/&quot;&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://idthefuture.com/2128/&quot;&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;) series by Jonathan Witt in 2021 and by Andrew McDiarmid in 2025.
in the DI’s series “ID The Future”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thomas cannot understand how biologists ever believed Darwin’s mechanism of natural 
selection.  So: has someone who has been devoted to teaching biology students about 
Darwin and natural selection recently changed his mind?  If so, should we pay close 
attention to his arguments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well …
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hasten to say that I have not read these two books, though I have listened to the 
two podcast interviews.  In the podcasts, Thomas expresses his scepticism about 
the origin of Life, and about whether natural selection can account for the 
complexity of humans.  But he does not explain why natural selection cannot account 
for adaptations of biological organisms once life has arisen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at a couple of the arguments Thomas uses against “Darwinism”.  First, McDiarmid 
quotes Thomas as saying “This Darwinism business, it’s rubbish isn’t it?”  And he summarizes 
Thomas’s argument, saying&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;First, Thomas criticizes Darwin’s cardinal principle of natural selection as intellectually incoherent and empty of meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and then he continues with Thomas’s conclusion that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the term essentially refers to preservation; it is conservative, cannot create, and certainly cannot select.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pratts&quot;&gt;PRATTs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are two PRATTs (Points Refuted A Thousand Times).  They are truly “moldy 
oldies”.  The first seems to be the assertion that “survival of the fittest” is meaningless 
because fitness is defined as having survived.  In reality, the moment we compare 
phenotypes or genotypes to see which have the higher fitness, fitness is meaningful 
and not a vacuous concept.  I am not the first to make this point, but for more 
explanation &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Fitness-Tautology.html&quot;&gt;see my 2020 post on this here at PT&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for “preservation”, if there are more than one genotype in the population, 
and one is preserved more than the others, then it will increase in 
frequency.  So the composition of the population can change, particularly 
if the genotype(s) “preserved” are not the most frequent ones.  Again, the 
idea that natural selection cannot change the population is a PRATT, and 
again, I have heard it enough times that I joined the many people who 
have refuted that argument.  See &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/diexperts.html&quot;&gt;my 2023 post here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Neil Thomas seems to have little understanding of how natural 
selection works.  That would be shocking if he were teaching “Darwinism” 
for many years, as a biologist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;not-a-biologist&quot;&gt;Not a biologist!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, Neil Thomas is not a biologist.  Not even close.  This is no 
secret: in his biographical material at S&amp;amp;C News, which appears 
at the end of each of his posts there, he is described thusly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Neil Thomas is a Reader Emeritus in the University of Durham, England and a longtime member of the British Rationalist Association. He studied Classical Studies and European Languages at the universities of Oxford, Munich and Cardiff before taking up his post in the German section of the School of European Languages and Literatures at Durham University in 1976. There his teaching involved a broad spectrum of specialisms including Germanic philology, medieval literature, the literature and philosophy of the Enlightenment and modern German history and literature. He also taught modules on the propagandist use of the German language used both by the Nazis and by the functionaries of the old German Democratic Republic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;useful-but-not-new&quot;&gt;Useful, but not new&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should add that Thomas spends most of his posts at S&amp;amp;CN 
describing the intellectual atmosphere preceding and during 
publication of Charles Darwin’s books.  He points to many 
predecessors, going back to the Greeks and Romans, and concludes 
that Victorian society was ready for a secular explanation 
of how adaptation could come about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is right about that, but his point is hardly new.  There is 
some implication in Thomas’s posts that “Darwinists” have 
insisted that Darwin was the first evolutionary thinker.  That 
is totally wrong: there have been numerous books, for decades 
exploring Darwin’s predecessors.  Stephen Jay Gould had many 
columns on the subject.  There is an extensive Wikipedia page 
on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_evolutionary_thought&quot;&gt;History of Evolutionary Thought&lt;/a&gt;.
Peter Bowler’s book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Evolution-History-Idea-Anniversary-Preface/dp/0520261283&quot;&gt;Evolution, the History of an Idea&lt;/a&gt;,
is a good summary.  We have also posted yearly celebrations of 
Lamarck, Darwin’s most important predeccessor &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/08/HappybirthdayLamarck.html&quot;&gt;here at Panda’s 
Thumb&lt;/a&gt;, 
the most recent also discussing Lamarck’s predecessor and 
patron Georges Buffon.  These posts will be found on or near August 1 of 
each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A particular favorite of mine is an older popularization 
by John Greene, provocatively titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Death-Adam-Evolution-Western-Thought/&quot;&gt;The Death of Adam: Evolution and Its Impact on Western Thought&lt;/a&gt;.
It points out the connection between the major advances in other 
fields, such as astronomy, which led to a search for 
unifying mechanisms, even in biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thomas seems most upset about this change, the rise to 
dominance of secular science which searches for 
mechanisms in our everyday world.  He seems to think 
that recent arguments by the Discovery Institute are 
invalidating this.  He’s welcome to his opinion, but 
I don’t think his arguments will bear much weight.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">  The Discovery Institute’s website “Science and Culture” (formerly Evolution News and Views) had a dramatic story of conversion recently. A post entitled “He Taught Darwinism for Decades (Then Changed His Mind)” by Andrew McDiarmid on 30 October 2025. It announced that For decades, British professor and author Neil Thomas was a card-carrying Darwinist. It wasn’t until after he retired from academia that he had the repose to think about things objectively. Then one day, in a scientific flash of inspiration, he came to the conclusion that the standard Darwinian story was “rubbish.” The result is that Neil Thomas has written two books, published by the DI’s publishing outfit, Discovery Institute Press: Taking Leave of Darwin: A longtime Agnostic Discovers the Case for Design and False Messiah: Darwinism as The God That Failed. He has also made numbers of posts at Science and Culture since 2021, see them here. He was intervewed in a two-part (part 1 and part 2) series by Jonathan Witt in 2021 and by Andrew McDiarmid in 2025. in the DI’s series “ID The Future”. Thomas cannot understand how biologists ever believed Darwin’s mechanism of natural selection. So: has someone who has been devoted to teaching biology students about Darwin and natural selection recently changed his mind? If so, should we pay close attention to his arguments? Well …</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Aurora borealis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/aurora-borealis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aurora borealis" /><published>2025-11-12T09:15:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-11-12T09:15:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/aurora-borealis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/aurora-borealis.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Vivian Dullien&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/IMG_0772_Vivian_Aurora_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aurora borealis&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2025/11/12/nx-s1-5274739/northern-lights-aurora-borealis-solar-storms&quot;&gt;Aurora borealis&lt;/a&gt; seen last night at 10 pm in Boulder, Colorado. 1-s exposure at F/1.8 with a smart phone  at ISO 4000, exposure bias 0.1.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Vivian Dullien. Aurora borealis seen last night at 10 pm in Boulder, Colorado. 1-s exposure at F/1.8 with a smart phone at ISO 4000, exposure bias 0.1.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Anolis carolinensis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/anolis-carolinensis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Anolis carolinensis" /><published>2025-11-10T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-11-10T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/anolis%20carolinensis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/anolis-carolinensis.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Denelsbeck_Anolis_carolinensis2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ring of Brodgar (henge)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://herpsofnc.org/green-anole/&quot;&gt;Anolis carolinensis&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Carolina or green anole. Mr. Denelsbeck writes that this anole &quot;regrew its detached tail, but forked &amp;ndash; I've seen photos but this was the first that I'd found an example of myself, right on the downspout by the front door last November [2023]. Unfortunately, despite keeping a wary eye out, I have not spotted it since. Based on some scarring, this might have been the same one that I found without a tail back in April of that year, which if true, would give a rough time frame of how long it takes to regrow. Canon 7D, Canon 18-135 STM, handheld, cropped.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Al Denelsbeck. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Anolis carolinensis &amp;ndash; Carolina or green anole. Mr. Denelsbeck writes that this anole &quot;regrew its detached tail, but forked &amp;ndash; I've seen photos but this was the first that I'd found an example of myself, right on the downspout by the front door last November [2023]. Unfortunately, despite keeping a wary eye out, I have not spotted it since. Based on some scarring, this might have been the same one that I found without a tail back in April of that year, which if true, would give a rough time frame of how long it takes to regrow. Canon 7D, Canon 18-135 STM, handheld, cropped.&quot;</summary></entry></feed>