<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-09-02T23:26:44-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">A belated happy birthday to Lamarck</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/belated-happy-birhtday-lamarck.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A belated happy birthday to Lamarck" /><published>2020-08-30T08:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-30T08:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/belated-happy-birhtday-lamarck</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/belated-happy-birhtday-lamarck.html">&lt;p&gt;Since 2009 I have posted every year a happy birthday greeting to the first evolutionary biologist, the
Chevalier de Lamarck.  Jean Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet, Chevalier de Lamarck, was born on 1 August 1744,
so now more than 276 years ago.  In my opinion he was the first true evolutionary biologist – he argued for
common ancestry of animals, and he actually had a proposed mechanism that biased change in the direction of
adaptation of a species to its environment.  He was wrong about the mechanism, but right about the need for
one.  He was also a great figure in invertebrate systematics, in which he made great strides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I’ve said all that before, and in addition this year the birthday notice is late.  No apologies for that,
the Pandas Thumb Crew spent his birthday desperately struggling to bring PT back up after a hardware failure of
its server.  We’ve talked about many aspects of his life, good and bad.  Is there anything important spo far
left unsaid?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually yes.  That he invoked an inherent complexifying force, and that it was quietly abandoned by
Lamarckians in subsequent decades.  An interesting story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/380px-Jean-Baptiste_de_Lamarck.jpg&quot; width=&quot;380&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;By Charles Thévenin, 1802 or 1803, Public Domain, https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=19173092
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People today think of Lamarck as a crackpot, which he was not.  They think of him as the great inventor and
advocate of the inheritance of acquired characteristics.  Whenever someone suggest that a phenotypic
modification of a species could be inherited, everyone succumbs to the temptation of calling it “Lamarckian”.
Actually they’re wrong on both scores.  Lamarck was by no means the first to suggest that acquired
characteristics – it’s an idea that goes back at least to the ancient Greeks, and most likely far beyond them.
No one in Lamarck’s time would be surprised by Lamarck’s use of the phenomenon – they all always knew it was
true.  So they would not think of him as having done anything of interest by using it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, the modifications Lamarck was talking about were not the direct effects of environment, but effects
of use and disuse.  When we use our muscles they tend to get bigger.  To Lamarck, it was that use that had the
effect in modifying the legacy passed on the next generation.  A bird tried to fly faster, so its offspring’s
wings were bigger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s another phenomenon in Lamarck’s theory, one that most people don’t know of.  This is that in
addition to the effects of use and disuse, there a whole other force at work in Lamarck’s theory.  And that is
the inherent complexifying force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, for example, is a summary by Lamarck contrasting the existing theory with his own:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion adopted hitherto:&lt;/em&gt; Nature (or her Author) in creating animals, foresaw all the possible kinds of environment in which they would have to live, and endowed each species with a fixed organisation and with a definite and invariable shape, which compel each species to live in the places and climates where we actually find them, and there to maintain the habits which we know in them.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My individual conclusion:&lt;/em&gt; Nature has produced all the species of animals in succession, beginning with the most imperfect or simplest, and ending her work with the most perfect, so as to create a gradually increasing complexity in their organisation; these animals have spread at large throughout all the habitable regions of the globe, and every species has derived from its environment the habits that we find in it and the structural modifications which observation shows us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note the production of animals “in succession” from implext to most perfect in a scale of “gradually increasing complexity”.  Although Lamarck drew one of the very first phylogenies, his thought was also dominated by a Great Chain of Being from simplest to most complex.  In fact, he believed that animal species climbed this scale continually, and if one became extinct, this was temporary, because it would arise again from animals further down on the scale of perfection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we not hear of this?  I think that it is simply that, as the 19th century wore on, with dramatic
developments in physics and chemistry, an inherent complexifying force seemed more and more unlikely,  In the aftermath of Darwin’s work, Lamarckian views were still around and advocated by his intellectual descendants.  But the more mystical aspects of the theory were quietly dropped.  Scientists no longer wanted to consider an inherent
complexifying force, or even effects of use and disuse.  The former was dropped, the latter became the direct
effects of the environment on the organism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today any effect of environment on the organism, such as epigenetic modifications, is called “Lamarckian”, usually quite inaccurately.  There is not going to be a true revival of Lamarckian views, as they would involve mystical trends towards complexity, and effects of will power on inheritance.  Neither has much appeal on light of modern physics.  Nevertheless, Happy Birthday to Jean-Baptiste, the first true evolutionary biologist.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Since 2009 I have posted every year a happy birthday greeting to the first evolutionary biologist, the Chevalier de Lamarck. Jean Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet, Chevalier de Lamarck, was born on 1 August 1744, so now more than 276 years ago. In my opinion he was the first true evolutionary biologist – he argued for common ancestry of animals, and he actually had a proposed mechanism that biased change in the direction of adaptation of a species to its environment. He was wrong about the mechanism, but right about the need for one. He was also a great figure in invertebrate systematics, in which he made great strides. Well, I’ve said all that before, and in addition this year the birthday notice is late. No apologies for that, the Pandas Thumb Crew spent his birthday desperately struggling to bring PT back up after a hardware failure of its server. We’ve talked about many aspects of his life, good and bad. Is there anything important spo far left unsaid? Actually yes. That he invoked an inherent complexifying force, and that it was quietly abandoned by Lamarckians in subsequent decades. An interesting story.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest XII: Finalists</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/finalists-xii.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest XII: Finalists" /><published>2020-08-25T07:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-25T07:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/finalists-xii</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/finalists-xii.html">&lt;p&gt;Here are the finalists of the 2020 photography contest. We received 21 photographs, all of which were excellent, as you will no doubt see during the coming months. With assistance from our wife, we chose 6 finalists and then added one rather than bite the bullet and break a tie. We display the &lt;em&gt;7&lt;/em&gt; finalists below the proverbial fold. We chose the photographs more on the basis of their pictorial quality than on their scientific interest. The text, if any, was written by the photographers and lightly edited for consistency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The finalists are presented in alphabetical order of last name. Please look through their photographs before voting for your favorite. Polling will close &lt;em&gt;Tuesday&lt;/em&gt;, September 8, at approximately &lt;em&gt;8&lt;/em&gt; a.m. MDT, and we will display the winner at noon that day. (Monday is Labor Day in the US.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please remember that this is a photography contest, not a popularity contest, and discourage your friends from enlisting others specifically to vote for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Domestic pigeon, by &lt;strong&gt;Muharrem Gorkem&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Gorkem_DomesticPigeon1_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pigeon&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
The photographer writes, &quot;A domestic pigeon, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domestic_pigeon&quot;&gt;Columba livia domestica&lt;/a&gt;, on her evening tour just before my apartment.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Common gray moth, by &lt;strong&gt;James Kocher&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Kocher_CommonGrayMoth1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Common gray moth&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anavitrinella_pampinaria&quot;&gt;Anavitrinella pampinaria&lt;/a&gt;, common gray moth, resting on block of limestone masonry &amp;ndash; &quot;a nice example of camouflage (cryptic) coloration, St. Louis, Missouri.&quot; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black-headed grosbeak, by &lt;strong&gt;Mark Lee&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Lee_BlackheadedGrosbeak.JPEG&quot; alt=&quot;Grosbeak&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Black-headed_Grosbeak/id&quot;&gt;Pheucticus melanocephalus&lt;/a&gt;, black-headed grosbeak, Palo Duro Canyon State Park, Texas.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roseate spoonbill, by &lt;strong&gt;C. Joseph Long&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Long_roseate_spoonbill.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Roseate spoonbill&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roseate_spoonbill&quot;&gt;Platalea ajaja L.&lt;/a&gt;, with young. The photographer writes, &quot;This shot was taken at the Alligator Farm in St. Augustine, Florida.  This is a popular place (among the birds, as well as humans) because, while nestlings that fall to the surface are lost, the nests are safe from such predators as raccoons, bobcats, and snakes due to the inaccessibility of the trees’ bases.  The color is due, as in flamingos, to carotenoids in the diet.  According to Wikipedia, the roseate’s closest relative is the yellow-billed spoonbill, which is found in southeast Australia.  They do get around.&quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green hyalite, by &lt;strong&gt;Alan Rice&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Rice_Alan_Green_Hyalite-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hyalite&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyalite&quot;&gt;Hyalite&lt;/a&gt; glowing green, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fluorescence&quot;&gt;fluorescing&lt;/a&gt;, under ultraviolet light (ultraviolet C 100–280&amp;nbsp;nm). The photographer writes, &quot;Hyalite is a form of opal with a glassy and clear appearance. My brother builds ultraviolet lights for mineral exploration and is silhouetted by the abundant hyalite. This sample is deep underground in a tungsten mine in Nevada, USA.&quot; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giant ichneumon wasp and mystery visitor, by &lt;strong&gt;Mark Sturtevant&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Sturtevant.Giant_Ichneumon_wasp_and_mystery_visitor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Giant ichneumon wasp&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insectidentification.org/insect-description.asp?identification=Giant-Ichneumon-Wasp-Megarhyssa-Atrata&quot;&gt;Megarhyssa atrata&lt;/a&gt;, giant ichneumon wasp. The photographer writes, &quot;This large female ichneumon wasp is using her long ovipositor to drill into wood in order to lay an egg on a wood-boring sawfly larva. The smaller wasp riding her is probably a male in the genus &lt;i&gt;Rhysella&lt;/i&gt;, and he appears to be mightily confused about his prospects for mating and passing on his genes.&quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gatekeeper butterfly, by &lt;strong&gt;Marilyn Susek&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Susek_Gatekeeper-Butterfly.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Butterfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ukbutterflies.co.uk/species.php?species=tithonus&quot;&gt;Pyronia tithonus&lt;/a&gt;, gatekeeper butterfly. The photographer writes, &quot;This butterfly was taken at my garden in Rotherham, S. Yorkshire, UK. I noticed that the under wing of this Gatekeeper is not the same as other photos of gatekeeper butterflies. It is sitting on an Echinacea.&quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdjFWQnqMJD-8-EhfT8o57nQpuMMGScRSu3K1qqL9ePvmLl-Q/viewform?embedded=true&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;618&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot;&gt;Loading…&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Here are the finalists of the 2020 photography contest. We received 21 photographs, all of which were excellent, as you will no doubt see during the coming months. With assistance from our wife, we chose 6 finalists and then added one rather than bite the bullet and break a tie. We display the 7 finalists below the proverbial fold. We chose the photographs more on the basis of their pictorial quality than on their scientific interest. The text, if any, was written by the photographers and lightly edited for consistency. The finalists are presented in alphabetical order of last name. Please look through their photographs before voting for your favorite. Polling will close Tuesday, September 8, at approximately 8 a.m. MDT, and we will display the winner at noon that day. (Monday is Labor Day in the US.) Please remember that this is a photography contest, not a popularity contest, and discourage your friends from enlisting others specifically to vote for you.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography contest XII – entries close</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/contest-xii-entries-close.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography contest XII – entries close" /><published>2020-08-24T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-24T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/contest-xii-entries-close</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/contest-xii-entries-close.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/DSC03492_Close-Up_Lens_Cucumber.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Thorns on cucumber stem&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cucumber&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Cucumis sativus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – cucumber. &lt;small&gt;No, not an entry, but what is a post without a picture?&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The  period for submitting entries to the photography contest ends now, August 24, at noon Mountain Daylight Time (6 h earlier than UTC).  As of this writing, we have received 21 submissions from 9 photographers. We will select finalists and post a poll as soon as possible, but not later than next Monday, August 31. Voting will close the following week, on &lt;i&gt;Tuesday&lt;/i&gt;, September 8 at &lt;i&gt;8&lt;/i&gt; a.m., MDT, and  the winning photograph will be posted at noon that day.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Cucumis sativus – cucumber. No, not an entry, but what is a post without a picture? The period for submitting entries to the photography contest ends now, August 24, at noon Mountain Daylight Time (6 h earlier than UTC). As of this writing, we have received 21 submissions from 9 photographers. We will select finalists and post a poll as soon as possible, but not later than next Monday, August 31. Voting will close the following week, on Tuesday, September 8 at 8 a.m., MDT, and the winning photograph will be posted at noon that day.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ark Sails the Coronavirus Seas</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/ark-sails-coronavirus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ark Sails the Coronavirus Seas" /><published>2020-08-23T11:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-23T11:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/ark-sails-coronavirus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/ark-sails-coronavirus.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Attendance_At_Ark_Park_Graph.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Monthly attendance graph&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Monthly attendance at the Ark Park since its opening in July, 2017, in thousands. The numbers are estimates based on tax payments and may exclude holders of lifetime passes and children.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ark Encounter’s attendance for July, 2020, totals 57,632, according to a recent Kentucky Open Records Act (KORA) request. Of course this figure doesn’t include the hordes (eye roll) of children and lifetime members Ken Ham claims are pouring into the park and need not buy a ticket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest figure is a bit more than a third of some previous years’ July attendance figures (see the graph, above). This low number is understandable considering the current coronavirus pandemic. These numbers do not suggest any massive increase in attendance due to the opening of their new &lt;a href=&quot;https://arkencounter.com/virtual-reality/&quot;&gt;virtual-reality&lt;/a&gt; (virtual unreality?) theater adjacent to the Ark-shaped building. Apparently, in the new VR theater one can climb into a special “Truth Traveller” pod and don the latest high-tech VR glasses, then see Noah herding dinosaurs onto the Ark (ain’t “science“ and technology great?).  The VR show will cost $14.99 at present (supposedly this is an introductory offer; the price is going up soon) on top of the $49.95 adult ticket to see Mr. Ham’s fantasy. I suspect the VR glasses will be a nightmare to clean between showings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to say whether they are hurting due to the coronavirus pandemic; Ken Ham’s fundraiser last spring to “reopen the Ark” netted well over $1.1 million. Moreover, Crosswater Canyon, the non-profit owned by the Answers in Genesis ministry, received between $1 million and 2 million in Paycheck Protection Program (PPP) money. Their gate receipts for 2018 and 2019, however, must have been in the $30-40 million range, and they will not achieve those receipts again for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;––-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Matt Young will be the moderator of this thread. He produced the graph at the top of the page, but the data are entirely the result of persistent effort by Dan Phelps. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Monthly attendance at the Ark Park since its opening in July, 2017, in thousands. The numbers are estimates based on tax payments and may exclude holders of lifetime passes and children. The Ark Encounter’s attendance for July, 2020, totals 57,632, according to a recent Kentucky Open Records Act (KORA) request. Of course this figure doesn’t include the hordes (eye roll) of children and lifetime members Ken Ham claims are pouring into the park and need not buy a ticket. The latest figure is a bit more than a third of some previous years’ July attendance figures (see the graph, above). This low number is understandable considering the current coronavirus pandemic. These numbers do not suggest any massive increase in attendance due to the opening of their new virtual-reality (virtual unreality?) theater adjacent to the Ark-shaped building. Apparently, in the new VR theater one can climb into a special “Truth Traveller” pod and don the latest high-tech VR glasses, then see Noah herding dinosaurs onto the Ark (ain’t “science“ and technology great?). The VR show will cost $14.99 at present (supposedly this is an introductory offer; the price is going up soon) on top of the $49.95 adult ticket to see Mr. Ham’s fantasy. I suspect the VR glasses will be a nightmare to clean between showings. It is hard to say whether they are hurting due to the coronavirus pandemic; Ken Ham’s fundraiser last spring to “reopen the Ark” netted well over $1.1 million. Moreover, Crosswater Canyon, the non-profit owned by the Answers in Genesis ministry, received between $1 million and 2 million in Paycheck Protection Program (PPP) money. Their gate receipts for 2018 and 2019, however, must have been in the $30-40 million range, and they will not achieve those receipts again for some time. ––- Matt Young will be the moderator of this thread. He produced the graph at the top of the page, but the data are entirely the result of persistent effort by Dan Phelps.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Out of Africa</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/out-of-africa.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Out of Africa" /><published>2020-08-18T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-18T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/out-of-africa</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/out-of-africa.html">&lt;p&gt;We have all become amateur epidemiologists, and I frankly thought there would be hell to pay when the Covid epidemic finally reached Africa. According to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/369/6505/756&quot;&gt;news article&lt;/a&gt; by journalist Linda Nordling of Cape Town South Africa, writing in &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;, Africa&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;seems to have weathered the pandemic relatively well so far, with fewer than one confirmed case for every thousand people and just 23,000 deaths. Yet several antibody surveys suggest far more Africans have been infected with the coronavirus—a discrepancy that is puzzling scientists around the continent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/369/6504/624&quot;&gt;more technical article&lt;/a&gt; by Moustapha Mbow and colleagues, much of which I thought I understood, led to a similar conclusion. Several explanations have been proposed, including the simple fact that Africans are on the whole younger than, say, Europeans and Americans. The explanation may also be genetic. Another hypothesis, however, is that Africans are infected with various parasites, which ramp up their immune systems so that they can effectively fight new pathogens. Mbow and colleagues cite the “hygiene hypothesis” and suggest that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;early and chronic exposure to pathogens leading to relentless immune cell activation in harsh environments induces a strong regulatory immune response to counteract excessive inflammation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I give succor to any anti-vaxxers, let me state that this hypothesis in no way militates against vaccinating for measles, mumps, chickenpox, pertussis (or whooping cough), polio, or all the other deadly childhood diseases that were commonplace when I was in grade school and do not appear every hundred years or so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A day or so after my physician advised me to get a flu shot, I ran across two articles, one by reporter Kelly Servick &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2020/08/how-will-covid-19-affect-coming-flu-season-scientists-struggle-clues&quot;&gt;in Science&lt;/a&gt; and another by reporters Lesley Wroughton and Max Bearak &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/africa/south-africa-coronavirus-flu-season/2020/08/17/bd8aaaca-e084-11ea-82d8-5e55d47e90ca_story.html&quot;&gt;in the Washington Post&lt;/a&gt;. These articles noted that there has been almost no flu season in South Africa this year, and the Post quoted Cheryl Cohen of South Africa’s Institute for Communicable Diseases to the effect that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The main explanation is that measures against coronavirus are having an impact on flu transmission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That explanation, if it holds up, will be good news to those who are concerned about a flu epidemic piggybacked on top of the current Sars epidemic. It would be better news if the United States were taking stronger measures against the coronavirus, but God forbid I should make a political statement like that.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">We have all become amateur epidemiologists, and I frankly thought there would be hell to pay when the Covid epidemic finally reached Africa. According to a news article by journalist Linda Nordling of Cape Town South Africa, writing in Science, Africa seems to have weathered the pandemic relatively well so far, with fewer than one confirmed case for every thousand people and just 23,000 deaths. Yet several antibody surveys suggest far more Africans have been infected with the coronavirus—a discrepancy that is puzzling scientists around the continent. A more technical article by Moustapha Mbow and colleagues, much of which I thought I understood, led to a similar conclusion. Several explanations have been proposed, including the simple fact that Africans are on the whole younger than, say, Europeans and Americans. The explanation may also be genetic. Another hypothesis, however, is that Africans are infected with various parasites, which ramp up their immune systems so that they can effectively fight new pathogens. Mbow and colleagues cite the “hygiene hypothesis” and suggest that early and chronic exposure to pathogens leading to relentless immune cell activation in harsh environments induces a strong regulatory immune response to counteract excessive inflammation. Before I give succor to any anti-vaxxers, let me state that this hypothesis in no way militates against vaccinating for measles, mumps, chickenpox, pertussis (or whooping cough), polio, or all the other deadly childhood diseases that were commonplace when I was in grade school and do not appear every hundred years or so. A day or so after my physician advised me to get a flu shot, I ran across two articles, one by reporter Kelly Servick in Science and another by reporters Lesley Wroughton and Max Bearak in the Washington Post. These articles noted that there has been almost no flu season in South Africa this year, and the Post quoted Cheryl Cohen of South Africa’s Institute for Communicable Diseases to the effect that The main explanation is that measures against coronavirus are having an impact on flu transmission. That explanation, if it holds up, will be good news to those who are concerned about a flu epidemic piggybacked on top of the current Sars epidemic. It would be better news if the United States were taking stronger measures against the coronavirus, but God forbid I should make a political statement like that.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography contest XII reopens</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/photography-contest-reopens.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography contest XII reopens" /><published>2020-08-15T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-15T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/photography-contest-reopens</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/photography-contest-reopens.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/DSC03531_Tri-X_Box_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tri-X film&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A box of Kodak Tri-X film that has seen better days. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to announce that the 12th annual Panda’s Thumb photography contest has reopened. Owing to the long delay, we have elected to extend the entry period by approximately one week, until Monday, August 24, at 12:00 noon, Mountain Daylight Saving Time. You may find the rules &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/photography-contest-xii.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who have already entered the contest have been extremely patient. We have therefore decided, consistently with the last-stated rule, to allow them each one extra entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As in previous years, we plan to choose a handful of finalists and ask our readers to vote for their favorites. We will post a poll on or before August 31 and display the winner on September 7.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">A box of Kodak Tri-X film that has seen better days. We are pleased to announce that the 12th annual Panda’s Thumb photography contest has reopened. Owing to the long delay, we have elected to extend the entry period by approximately one week, until Monday, August 24, at 12:00 noon, Mountain Daylight Saving Time. You may find the rules here. Those who have already entered the contest have been extremely patient. We have therefore decided, consistently with the last-stated rule, to allow them each one extra entry. As in previous years, we plan to choose a handful of finalists and ask our readers to vote for their favorites. We will post a poll on or before August 31 and display the winner on September 7.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Glenn Morton, 1950-2020</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/glenn-morton.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Glenn Morton, 1950-2020" /><published>2020-08-14T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-14T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/glenn-morton</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/glenn-morton.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Glenn_Morton_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Glenn Morton&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Glenn Morton, 1950-2020.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jonathan Kane&lt;/b&gt; is a science writer who has written five previous posts for Panda’s Thumb from 2016 to 2019 (they are listed in the Archives for those years). He is the editor and primary author of &lt;/em&gt;God’s Word or Human Reason? An Inside Perspective on Creationism&lt;em&gt;, co-authored with Emily Willoughby, T. Michael Keesey, Glenn Morton, and James R. Comer, published December 2016 by Inkwater Press, with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/1629016381/&quot;&gt;new edition&lt;/a&gt; published in spring of this year. Matt Young is this post’s moderator.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sad to announce that Glenn Morton, the geophysicist and former creation scientist who eventually became a critic of creationism, and who coined the term “Morton’s Demon”, died on August 5 after a long battle with cancer. He was 70.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of his geophysics career, Morton worked for several petroleum exploration companies, including ARCO, Oryx, and Kerr-McGee. Early in his career Morton was a young-Earth creationist, albeit one whose work required him to deal with vast amounts of geological data, and in the 1970s he became known as a creation scientist who sought ways of reconciling this data with young-Earth models. Morton’s 1980 paper “&lt;a href=&quot;https://crs-alchemy-attachments.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/pdf/crsq-1980-volume-17-number-3.pdf&quot;&gt;Prolegomena to the study of the sediments&lt;/a&gt;”, published in Volume 17, issue 3 of &lt;em&gt;Creation Research Society Quarterly&lt;/em&gt; (under the name “Robert Morton”), was the first creationist paper to raise the issue of how the relative thickness of sediment on continental platforms compared to that in oceans was a challenge to Flood Geology models. His 1982 paper “&lt;a href=&quot;https://crs-alchemy-attachments.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/pdf/crsq-1982-volume-19-number-2.pdf&quot;&gt;Fossil succession&lt;/a&gt;”, published in Volume 19, issue 2 of the same journal, raised several ways that traditional Flood Geology models cannot adequately explain the stratigraphic data, and introduced the alternative diluvialist model that’s now known as Recolonization Theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morton, who was not afraid to criticize other professional creationists for their lack of rigor, soon became known as a maverick among creation scientists. In Robert Schadewald’s summary of the 1986 International Conference on Creationism, published in Volume 6, issue 5 of &lt;em&gt;NCSE Reports&lt;/em&gt;, Schadewald describes a presentation by Morton titled “Geological Challenges to a Young Earth”. By this point Morton was what he called a “middle-Earth creationist” - someone who still sought to interpret the book of Genesis as literal history, but who recognized that a 6,000 year old Earth was incompatible with geological data. Morton’s presentation was negatively received by most of the conference’s other attendees, and Morton asked Schadewald (perhaps only half seriously) to “catch any tomatoes that came sailing over”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of the 1980s, Morton’s growing disillusion with the creation science community led to a complete withdrawal of publishing papers in that area - and eventually, by 1994, to his abandoning creationism entirely. From the 1990s onward, Morton was a prominent critic of creationist arguments in the field of geology, and his earlier years as a creation scientist gave him an intimate familiarity with these arguments. Morton’s transformation from a young-Earth creationist to a critic of creationism is described in his article &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.asa3.org/ASA/PSCF/2000/PSCF6-00Morton.html&quot;&gt;The Transformation of a young-Earth creationist&lt;/a&gt;, originally published in &lt;em&gt;Perspectives on Science and Christian Faith&lt;/em&gt; in June 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After his transformation, Morton regularly wrote criticism of creationist models for journals and websites related to the creation/evolution controversy, including &lt;em&gt;NCSE reports&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Perspectives on Science and Christian Faith&lt;/em&gt;, and the Talk.Origins website and newsgroup. Probably his most influential article is the one that coined the term “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.talkorigins.org/origins/postmonth/feb02.html&quot;&gt;Morton’s Demon&lt;/a&gt;”, which describes a type of confirmation bias that is particularly strong among creationists. Morton also is the author of what is arguably the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.talkorigins.org/faqs/geocolumn/&quot;&gt;definitive refutation&lt;/a&gt; of the creationist argument that the entire geologic column cannot be found in a single location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite his opposition to creationism, Morton never quite became a conventional evolution advocate. In his books &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=5UhHDwAAQBAJ&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Foundation, Fall and Flood&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (1995) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=80hHDwAAQBAJ&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adam, Apes and Anthropology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (1997), Morton presented the view that Adam and Eve were early hominins, and that the flood described in the book of Genesis was the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zanclean_flood&quot;&gt;Zanclean flood&lt;/a&gt;, which filled the Mediterranean Sea basin 5.33 million years ago. In Morton’s view, the Zanclean flood is the only flood for which geological evidence exists that was large enough to match the description given in Genesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first got to know Glenn Morton in 2007, while I was working on my own book criticizing the creationist movement, &lt;em&gt;God’s Word or Human Reason?: An Inside Perspective on Creationism&lt;/em&gt; (the first edition is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Gods-Word-Human-Reason-Perspective/dp/1629013722&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and the recently released second edition is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/1629016381/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). I invited Morton to write the book’s chapter about stratigraphy because I considered him the most qualified person to critique creationist arguments in that area. Morton’s chapter for this book, eventually published in December 2016, was his final anti-creationism publication. The book also republished, in slightly expanded form, Morton’s personal account of his abandonment of young-Earth creationism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the book’s publication date neared, Morton informed me that he was becoming increasingly disillusioned with the anti-creationism movement and took down his personal website, where many of his writings could be found. He explained to me that although he still opposed YEC and stood by his earlier arguments against it, he was upset by the way people had begun using his writings to attack religion in general, which was a use of his writings that he did not approve of. However, he continued to support my book project, because the book took a clearly defined neutral stance with respect to religion, and after its publication he told me that the eventual product lived up to his expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morton’s final book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Eden-Was-Here-Evidence-Historicity-ebook/dp/B08F2Z7Z5H&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eden Was Here&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, was published only a few days before his death. This book seeks to identify the location of the Garden of Eden from an evolutionary and old-Earth standpoint. As a Christian theistic evolutionist, Morton placed a great deal of importance on reconciling details from the book of Genesis with geological and evolutionary science. In a &lt;a href=&quot;http://themigrantmind.blogspot.com/2019/06/why-historicity-is-important.html&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; from June 9 of this year, Morton explained why he considered it important for people and events discussed in the Bible to have a historical basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of PT’s readers who think of Genesis as a collection of myths, or as a moral and spiritual text that was not intended by its author to have a historical basis, may regard this endeavor as having been a waste of time. But it is impossible to deny the importance of Morton’s criticism of creationist models, or his importance as the most prominent example ever to exist of a professional creation scientist who eventually abandoned creationism. While I personally disagree with many of Morton’s ideas about the intended meaning of Genesis with respect to the Garden of Eden and the Flood, I also find something to admire in his determination to come up with his own set of models that matched his beliefs. Until the end of his life, Morton never was willing to let anyone else pressure him to change what he believed, whether that pressure came from creationists or anyone else.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jonathan Kane</name></author><summary type="html">Glenn Morton, 1950-2020. Jonathan Kane is a science writer who has written five previous posts for Panda’s Thumb from 2016 to 2019 (they are listed in the Archives for those years). He is the editor and primary author of God’s Word or Human Reason? An Inside Perspective on Creationism, co-authored with Emily Willoughby, T. Michael Keesey, Glenn Morton, and James R. Comer, published December 2016 by Inkwater Press, with a new edition published in spring of this year. Matt Young is this post’s moderator. I’m sad to announce that Glenn Morton, the geophysicist and former creation scientist who eventually became a critic of creationism, and who coined the term “Morton’s Demon”, died on August 5 after a long battle with cancer. He was 70.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ed Brayton Passed Away</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/Brayton.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ed Brayton Passed Away" /><published>2020-08-13T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-13T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/Brayton</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/Brayton.html">&lt;p&gt;Ed Brayton was an amazing man and one of the founders of Pandasthumb. I’m saddened to report that after a long battle with his health, he died last night. It happened a few days after &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patheos.com/blogs/dispatches/2020/08/10/saying-goodbye-for-the-last-time/&quot;&gt;he decided to enter hospice care&lt;/a&gt;. He died on his own terms and as peacefully as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all grateful to have known him and been influenced by him. His voice will be missed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reed A. Cartwright</name></author><summary type="html">Ed Brayton was an amazing man and one of the founders of Pandasthumb. I’m saddened to report that after a long battle with his health, he died last night. It happened a few days after he decided to enter hospice care. He died on his own terms and as peacefully as possible. We are all grateful to have known him and been influenced by him. His voice will be missed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">We are almost back</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/we-are-almost-back.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We are almost back" /><published>2020-08-07T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-07T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/we-are-almost-back</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/we-are-almost-back.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[Added 14th of August:  comments now work correctly, so Panda’s Thumb is now back “on the air” as of the 11th.  The outage was 56 days, or 8 weeks.]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

Panda's Thumb has been down since the 16th of June, owing to a hardware failure in its server machine.
Reed has been working to fix that, and I have been adapting the site to be served by Github Pages.  This
has been possible since it was already using a locally-served version of Github Pages since 2016,
in its previous configuration.
&lt;p&gt;

Currently most features of PT work.  The comments do not appear at the end of articles, even though
the count of the number of comments appears for each article on the front page of the site, and the
Recent Comments list appears correctly.  Current and archived posts are available.
We hope to get comments working very soon.  In the meantime,
please be patient, and watch this space.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">[Added 14th of August: comments now work correctly, so Panda’s Thumb is now back “on the air” as of the 11th. The outage was 56 days, or 8 weeks.] Panda's Thumb has been down since the 16th of June, owing to a hardware failure in its server machine. Reed has been working to fix that, and I have been adapting the site to be served by Github Pages. This has been possible since it was already using a locally-served version of Github Pages since 2016, in its previous configuration. Currently most features of PT work. The comments do not appear at the end of articles, even though the count of the number of comments appears for each article on the front page of the site, and the Recent Comments list appears correctly. Current and archived posts are available. We hope to get comments working very soon. In the meantime, please be patient, and watch this space.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reason for optimism in the evolution wars</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/reason-for-optimism-evolution-wars.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reason for optimism in the evolution wars" /><published>2020-06-13T12:13:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-13T12:13:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/reason-for-optimism-evolution-wars</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/06/reason-for-optimism-evolution-wars.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Plutzer_2020_Graph.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Graph&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&quot;Teachers classified by the scientific accuracy of the messages reportedly conveyed to students, 2007 and 2019.&quot; Note, in particular, that the number of teachers who teach evolution as settled science has increased from around 50 to nearly 70&amp;nbsp;%, whereas the number who give mixed messages or outright teach creationism has decreased. &lt;small&gt;Plutzer, E., Branch, G. &amp;amp; Reid, A. Teaching evolution in U.S. public schools: a continuing challenge. &lt;i&gt;Evo Edu Outreach&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;13&lt;/strong&gt;, 14 (2020). https://doi.org/10.1186/s12052-020-00126-8. Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0).&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of this article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution-outreach.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12052-020-00126-8&quot;&gt;Teaching evolution in U.S. public schools: a continuing challenge&lt;/a&gt;, seems to me a little sterile and possibly unduly pessimistic. The main conclusions of the article are given in the figure: The fraction of teachers who teach evolution has increased from 50 to nearly 70 % in the 12 years since an &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.0060124&quot;&gt;earlier survey&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, the fraction who teach creationism has fallen, and the fraction who give “mixed messages” has fallen precipitously, from the low 20’s to the low teens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among other conclusions, the authors credit the Next Generation Science Standards for the improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article is too detailed to regurgitate here, but it is easy to read (and free!). The authors, for example, compare responses from teachers in states that have adopted the NGSS or a similar &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nap.edu/catalog/13165/a-framework-for-k-12-science-education-practices-crosscutting-concepts&quot;&gt;Framework&lt;/a&gt; with teachers in the remaining states before crediting NGSS with the improvements. They looked at other data to conclude that the improvements were not the result of new teachers being hired after &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kitzmiller_v._Dover_Area_School_District&quot;&gt;Kitzmiller&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; and NGSS. Rather, older teachers, on the job before &lt;i&gt;Kitzmiller&lt;/i&gt;, took advantage of professional-development courses and improved their teaching of evolution and increased the time they devoted to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the fraction of teachers who “strongly disagreed” with the statement, “I emphasize that intelligent design is a valid, scientific alternative to Darwinian explanations for the origin of species,” increased from 20 to 43 % in the 12 years between the polls. Likewise, the fraction who strongly disagreed with the statement, “I emphasize that many reputable scientists view creationism or intelligent design as valid alternatives to Darwinian theory,” increased from 13 to 20 %. Only 3 % “strongly agreed” with the either statement, a number that remained constant across the 12 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I thought it was a pretty good decade or so.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">&quot;Teachers classified by the scientific accuracy of the messages reportedly conveyed to students, 2007 and 2019.&quot; Note, in particular, that the number of teachers who teach evolution as settled science has increased from around 50 to nearly 70&amp;nbsp;%, whereas the number who give mixed messages or outright teach creationism has decreased. Plutzer, E., Branch, G. &amp;amp; Reid, A. Teaching evolution in U.S. public schools: a continuing challenge. Evo Edu Outreach 13, 14 (2020). https://doi.org/10.1186/s12052-020-00126-8. Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0). The title of this article, Teaching evolution in U.S. public schools: a continuing challenge, seems to me a little sterile and possibly unduly pessimistic. The main conclusions of the article are given in the figure: The fraction of teachers who teach evolution has increased from 50 to nearly 70 % in the 12 years since an earlier survey. Additionally, the fraction who teach creationism has fallen, and the fraction who give “mixed messages” has fallen precipitously, from the low 20’s to the low teens. Among other conclusions, the authors credit the Next Generation Science Standards for the improvement.</summary></entry></feed>