<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-03-03T00:31:39-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Ailuropoda melanoleuca</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/ailuropoda-melanoleuca.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ailuropoda melanoleuca" /><published>2023-02-27T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-02-27T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/ailuropoda-melanoleuca</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/ailuropoda-melanoleuca.html">&lt;p&gt;Photographs by &lt;strong&gt;Dan Phelps&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Phelps_Panda_Bill_Obverse_900.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Obverse side of bill&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Counterfeit* bill showing image of &lt;i&gt;Ailuropoda melanoleuca&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; giant panda. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giant_panda&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; You may purchase similar bills for less than $2 apiece &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ebay.com/itm/113578496561&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. As Mr. Phelps notes, at least it is not a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/aig-counterfeit-money.html&quot;&gt;religious tract&lt;/a&gt;. The panda in the center is, of course, Prof. Steve Steve, who (though we have not heard from him in quite a while) steadfastly maintains that &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2015/07/why-are-giant-p.html&quot;&gt;he is not lazy&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;small&gt;*&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/counterfeit&quot;&gt;Sense 2b&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Phelps_Panda_Bill_Reverse_900.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reverse side of bill&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The reverse side of the bill.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photographs by Dan Phelps. Counterfeit* bill showing image of Ailuropoda melanoleuca &amp;ndash; giant panda. You may purchase similar bills for less than $2 apiece here. As Mr. Phelps notes, at least it is not a religious tract. The panda in the center is, of course, Prof. Steve Steve, who (though we have not heard from him in quite a while) steadfastly maintains that he is not lazy. *Sense 2b.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Science Advocate Frank Lovell: A Remembrance</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/science-advocate-Frank-Lovell.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science Advocate Frank Lovell: A Remembrance" /><published>2023-02-22T13:01:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-02-22T13:01:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/science-advocate-Frank-Lovell</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/science-advocate-Frank-Lovell.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Guest post by Tom Wheeler in remembrance of his friend, Frank Lovell. We extend our sincere condolences to Mr. Wheeler and to Mr. Lovell’s family.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Wheeler_Fig_1_FrankFaceBook_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frank's Facebook photograph&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Frank Lovell's Facebook profile picture.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frank Lovell, an outstanding defender of evolution and promoter of public understanding of science, died on January 26, 2023, from injuries suffered in a fall. He was 79 years old. He is survived by his wife Debbie and children Annie Lovell, Frank Lovell III, Alicia Lovell (Dennis Nalley) and Simon Lovell (Sneha Thapa) (1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Born in Ashland Kentucky, he served four years in the United States Army. He then studied physical organic chemistry at the University of Louisville and University of Kentucky, receiving a bachelor’s degree from the latter. A 30-year career with General Electric in Louisville followed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frank’s anti-creationism efforts began in 1982 with letters to the editor; he estimated that he wrote a couple of dozen letters in the next couple of years (2). In 1983, I had a letter of my own published, critiquing a creationist op-ed. A couple of days later, I received a letter from Frank, praising my letter and including a copy of the letter he had written personally to the creationist. He invited me to join him in fighting creationism. This was the beginning of an extensive collaboration that would continue until I moved away from Louisville in 2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frank and I decided to form a new Committee of Correspondence in the Louisville area, the Kentucky Committee for Science Education. This was to complement the existing Committee for Effective Action in Science Education (CEASE) in Lexington, founded by Drs. Eugenie Scott and Wayne Davis of the University of Kentucky. Unlike the case in Lexington, where proposed teaching of creationism in public schools led to the formation of CEASE, there did not appear to be a similar threat in Louisville. Rather, our focus was on the public presentations (letters to the editor, public talks, media presentations, etc.) of local creationists, particularly ministers of the Church of Christ. (Frank designed a letterhead with a KCSE logo, and issued documents on behalf of the group, but in reality it just consisted of the two of us.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-right-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 40px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Wheeler_Fig_2_FrankPoster_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frank at a poster session&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Poster session, 1986.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frank described our efforts in a presentation at a 1988 AAAS meeting, which can be seen in a YouTube video (2). These included letters to the editor; correspondence with local creationist speakers and other individuals; a poster presentation; handouts distributed at talks related to evolution; and public talks of our own. We engaged extensively with one biology-trained preacher, and even got invited to give a couple of talks at his church. Throughout this we tried to document errors in materials of prominent young-Earth creationists, and hold the locals accountable for not repeating arguments that had been shown to be false. The bulk of this correspondence was Frank’s work; his scholarly output was impressive, especially in light of all his other interests (as noted below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1985, the local pastors challenged us to a public debate. I decided that, given the pitfalls of debating creationists and the amount of time required to debate properly, it was not something I wanted to do. However, Frank accepted the challenge, and a four-night debate was arranged (3). I assisted Frank. The creationists brought in Dr. H.E. “Buddy” Payne from Florida College. Frank made a vigorous attack on the young Earth model as promoted by the Institute for Creation Research. However, Payne refused to take a stand on the age of the Earth, leaving him free to attack standard findings from geology and evolution without having to defend anything. As I noted (3), “Overall, Payne’s superior public speaking ability probably helped make his presentation more persuasive to the audience, which appeared to be mostly sympathetic to creationism.” Frank acknowledged that it was “a very humbling, character building experience” (2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also corresponded with both nationally known creationists and scientific experts in analyzing and responding to creationist claims. These included meteoritic dust on the moon (4) and Grand Canyon lava flows. Frank also assisted me in my detailed rebuttal to D. James Kennedy’s presentations on “The John Ankerberg Show.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another of Frank’s activities was attending creationist conferences, often with Robert Schadewald. They frequently met informally with creationists at lunch. As Schadewald wrote (5), “…our interactions with the creationists invariably were cordial or better…We both felt that these exchanges were the best part of the conference.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have less information about Frank’s activities after I left Louisville in 2006, but I believe that he continued to defend evolution with similar enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Wheeler_Fig_3_FrankShermer_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frank with Michael Shermer&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Frank with Michael Shermer, before Shermer’s debate with William Dembski, 2006.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was also active in combating other forms of pseudoscience besides creationism. When the Committee for the Scientific Investigation of Claims of the Paranormal (CSICOP) issued a call for local groups to coordinate with its goals, we volunteered KCSE to be such a group. Simultaneous, Dr. Robert A. Baker of the University of Kentucky offered to form a group. We decided to defer to Dr. Baker’s leadership and joined his new Kentucky Association of Science Educators and Skeptics (KASES). Later, Frank accepted my invitation to join the Kentucky Council Against Health Fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frank’s activities were not restricted to critiquing bad science; he was an active promoter of scientific knowledge and science education. He was a long-time member of the Louisville Astronomical Society, serving at various times as President, Chairman of the Board, Editor, and Librarian. He served nearly 30 years as a member of the Board of Directors of the Louisville Regional Science Fair, and at different times was Head Judge for physics, Head Judge for team projects, Judging Committee Coordinator, and Fair Co-director.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another major interest of Frank’s was philosophy and religion. I recall that he described himself as “an atheist of the agnostic variety,” meaning he could not disprove the existence of God, but found no compelling reason to believe. He was an active member of the Louisville Freethought Society, participating in weekly meetups and staffing a booth at the Kentucky State Fair each year. As he did with creationists, he carried on extensive correspondence with preachers and lay individuals concerning religious topics, and gave public talks. One of these that I attended was a two-night debate with a local minister. He expressed his views on science and religion as follows: “Where ever objective knowledge is incomplete, there is a place for religious ‘faith’ (for any who feel need for religious ‘faith,’ at any rate); but where ever objective knowledge and religious ‘faith’ conflict, it is religious ‘faith’ (not objective knowledge) which should be modified or abandoned. That is the only rational way that there can be no conflict between science and religion.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Wheeler_Fig_4_FrankAstro_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frank with Deborah Warren and Daniel Phelps&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Frank with Deborah Warren of the Louisville Astronomical Society and guest speaker Daniel Phelps, January 2023.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was a regular participant on FreeThought Channel, including a major interview (6). His fellow panelists have posted a remembrance (7).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frank had a large following on Facebook, where he regularly posted on new scientific developments, philosophical questions, and videos of musical performances that he felt especially enjoyable. The announcement of his death on his Facebook page was met with an outpouring of condolences from around the world. Here is one typical comment: “I deeply appreciated his intelligence, integrity, humanity, warmth and tolerance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Thomas J. Wheeler was a biochemistry professor at the University of Louisville for 25 years, followed by a second career as a high school science teacher in Scranton, PA. He is now retired and living in the Chicago area.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Matt Young will be the moderator of this thread.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ferncreekfuneralhome.com/obituary/frank-lovell&quot;&gt;Frank Lovell obituary&lt;/a&gt; 2023. Fern Creek Funeral Home&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5kp0pTB1yuE&quot;&gt;National Center for Science Education. Do’s and Dont’s Debating Creationists: Part 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wheeler TJ. Lovell-Payne Debate, Aug. 12-16, 1985. Creation/Evolution Newsletter, 1986. 6(1):16-17&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wheeler TJ. More on Creationists and Meteoritic Dust. Creation/Evolution Newsletter, 1987. 7(4):14-15&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Schadewald R. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/1998-international-conference-creationism&quot;&gt;The 1998 International Conference on Creationism&lt;/a&gt;. Reports of the National Center for Science Education, 1998. 18(3)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1xTdvU4Bm-o&quot;&gt;Ask an Atheist with guest Frank Lovell&lt;/a&gt;. FreeThought Channel&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B3MfRTD7EVw&quot;&gt;Eulogy to Frank from the VotN panel&lt;/a&gt;. FreeThought Channel&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Thomas J. Wheeler</name></author><summary type="html">Guest post by Tom Wheeler in remembrance of his friend, Frank Lovell. We extend our sincere condolences to Mr. Wheeler and to Mr. Lovell’s family. Frank Lovell's Facebook profile picture. Frank Lovell, an outstanding defender of evolution and promoter of public understanding of science, died on January 26, 2023, from injuries suffered in a fall. He was 79 years old. He is survived by his wife Debbie and children Annie Lovell, Frank Lovell III, Alicia Lovell (Dennis Nalley) and Simon Lovell (Sneha Thapa) (1). Born in Ashland Kentucky, he served four years in the United States Army. He then studied physical organic chemistry at the University of Louisville and University of Kentucky, receiving a bachelor’s degree from the latter. A 30-year career with General Electric in Louisville followed. Frank’s anti-creationism efforts began in 1982 with letters to the editor; he estimated that he wrote a couple of dozen letters in the next couple of years (2). In 1983, I had a letter of my own published, critiquing a creationist op-ed. A couple of days later, I received a letter from Frank, praising my letter and including a copy of the letter he had written personally to the creationist. He invited me to join him in fighting creationism. This was the beginning of an extensive collaboration that would continue until I moved away from Louisville in 2006.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Funder of Super Bowl &quot;He Gets Us&quot; ad also funds many groups including AIG and the DI via dark money</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/Funder-of-Super-Bowl.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Funder of Super Bowl &quot;He Gets Us&quot; ad also funds many groups including AIG and the DI via dark money" /><published>2023-02-16T09:25:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-02-16T09:25:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/Funder-of-Super-Bowl</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/Funder-of-Super-Bowl.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Phelps_Creation_Museum_DSC03914_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Creation &amp;#34;Museum&amp;#34;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Entrance to the Creation &quot;Museum.&quot; &lt;small&gt;Photograph by Daniel Phelps, used by permission.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funder of the “He Gets Us” ad broadcast during the Super Bowl also funds many groups including Answers in Genesis and the Discovery Institute via dark money techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several investigators have recently looked into The Servant Foundation because they funded the “He Gets Us” Super Bowl advertisements for Jesus (for example &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.au.org/the-latest/articles/christian-nationalist-donors-super-bowl-jesus-ad/&quot;&gt;Americans United&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://skepchick.org/2023/02/whos-behind-those-jesus-ads-youre-gonna-see-during-the-big-game/&quot;&gt;Rebecca Watson&lt;/a&gt;, aka Skepchick). Both AU and Skepchick discovered that, in spite of the liberal-sounding nature of the Super Bowl advertising, the Servant Foundation also has donated to numerous fundamentalist Christian Nationalist hate groups. Apparently, the Servant Foundation is a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.irs.gov/charities-non-profits/charitable-organizations/donor-advised-funds&quot;&gt;donor-advised fund&lt;/a&gt;” and receives donations for a number of worthy causes as well as cringeworthy hateful groups. Because of loopholes in the tax laws, people can donate to the Servant Foundation and see that their money goes to their favorite extremist groups via a “donor-advised fund” without their identity being revealed; this is basically “dark-money.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazingly, The Servant Foundation, doing business as “&lt;a href=&quot;https://thesignatry.com/&quot;&gt;The Signatry&lt;/a&gt;,” presently has assets approaching $1 billion. I looked at their publicly available IRS Form 990’s for 2016 to 2020 and, besides a handful of small donations to worthy organizations, and many organizations of whom I am unaware, there were a number of donations to far-right, generally Christian Nationalist, organizations. I have mentioned below a number of them that are listed in the Form 990 from 4/1/20 to 3/31/21.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Answers in Genesis and the Discovery Institute have received monies from The Servant Foundation, presumably via a “donor-advised fund.” Since 2016, Answers in Genesis has received $19,349,691.00, and the Discovery Institute, $750,600.00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although AIG seems to have difficulty with the shrinking number of paid tickets at the Ark Encounter, they will never go broke because of donations, including these by The Servant Foundation’s donor-advised fund. So who is supplying this dark money to the creationists? Without donor transparency, this question may be impossible to answer. Kentucky media are shrinking and only rarely cover AIG and the Ark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supporting information below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Servant Foundation’s IRS Form 990’s are available via &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instrumentl.com/990-report/servant-foundation&quot;&gt; this website &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Servant Foundation doing business as The Signatry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Form 990, 4/1/20 and ending 3/31/21&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of the year assets $974,727,606.00
Form 990, Schedule I, Part II, Grants and Other Assistance to Domestic Organizations and Domestic Governments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers in Genesis: $10,552,200.00&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other groups that interested me and are listed as receiving donations (this is a far from a comprehensive list) include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Academy for Climate and Energy Analysis, Inc. Shawnee, Kansas, $5,500.00 (a tiny group run by a former TV weatherman that promotes anti-climate change disinformation. Seems mostly to be repeating Heartland Institute disinformation. https://aceanalysis.org/).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alliance Defending Freedom, $16,657,150.00 (far right fundamentalist organization in spite of the Orwellian name, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/alliance_defending_freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;American Center for Law and Justice, $44,636.00 (basically, Pat Robertson’s legal arm, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Center_for_Law_%26_Justice)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;American Family Association, $8,550.00 (a huge fundamentalist Christian Nationalist organization, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Family_Associatio).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creation Instruction Association, Inc., Juanita, Nebraska, $5,500.00 (a creationist organization that has a “Seismosaurus Mobile Museum” in an 18 wheeler truck. Lots of dinosaurs with humans dioramas, and also some real and replica fossils, https://www.creationinstruction.org/). A minor player, but still…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovery Institute, $250,500.00 (the leading “intelligent design” creationist organization https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Discovery_Institute. Yep, they are still out there).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edchoice Kentucky, Inc., Frankfort KY, $10,000.00 (a small organization here in Kentucky that advocates governmental support for charter and “non-public ” schools, https://edchoiceky.com/).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;God’s Not Dead Foundation doing business as Pure Flix, $15,000.00 (Pure Flix is partnered with Answers in Genesis so you can watch Ken Ham videos to your heart’s content if you join).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Institute for Creation Research, Dallas, TX, $11,000.00 (the granddaddy of creationist “science” organizations. Relatively tiny now that AiG is the biggest creationist ministry).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jordan B. Peterson Institute, Witchita, Kansas, $12,500.00 (Peterson has an inexplicable right wing young male anti-feminist following as a psychologist and amateur philosopher).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prager University Foundation, Owings Mills, Maryland, $220,750.00 (a “university.” Note that I use scare-quotes here, as actual universities are not based on a large collection of YouTube videos, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PragerU).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Form 990, 4/1/19 and ending 3/31/20&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of the year assets, $699,516,453.00
Form 990, Schedule I, Part II, Grants and Other Assistance to Domestic Organizations and Domestic Governments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers in Genesis, $7,764,000.00&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovery Institute, $250,000.00&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Form 990, 4/1/18 and ending 3/31/19&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of the year assets, $666,786,525.00
Form 990, Schedule I, Part II, Grants and Other Assistance to Domestic Organizations and Domestic Governments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers in Genesis, $1,025,575.00&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovery Institute, $250,100.00&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Form 990, 4/1/17 and ending 3/31/18&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of the year assets, $3,516,408.00
Form 990, Schedule I, Part II, Grants and Other Assistance to Domestic Organizations and Domestic Governments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers in Genesis, $0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovery Institute, $0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Form 990, 4/1/16 and ending 3/31/17&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of the year assets, $4,471,589.00
Form 990, Schedule I, Part II, Grants and Other Assistance to Domestic Organizations and Domestic Governments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers in Genesis, $7,921.00&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovery Institute, $0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing in older IRS Form 990’s that are available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Matt Young will be the principal moderator of this thread.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Entrance to the Creation &quot;Museum.&quot; Photograph by Daniel Phelps, used by permission. The funder of the “He Gets Us” ad broadcast during the Super Bowl also funds many groups including Answers in Genesis and the Discovery Institute via dark money techniques. Several investigators have recently looked into The Servant Foundation because they funded the “He Gets Us” Super Bowl advertisements for Jesus (for example Americans United and Rebecca Watson, aka Skepchick). Both AU and Skepchick discovered that, in spite of the liberal-sounding nature of the Super Bowl advertising, the Servant Foundation also has donated to numerous fundamentalist Christian Nationalist hate groups. Apparently, the Servant Foundation is a “donor-advised fund” and receives donations for a number of worthy causes as well as cringeworthy hateful groups. Because of loopholes in the tax laws, people can donate to the Servant Foundation and see that their money goes to their favorite extremist groups via a “donor-advised fund” without their identity being revealed; this is basically “dark-money.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Helicoverpa zea</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/helicoverpa-zea.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Helicoverpa zea" /><published>2023-02-13T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-02-13T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/helicoverpa-zea</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/helicoverpa-zea.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/P1000071_Moth_Helicoverpa_zea_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Corn earworm moth&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.butterfliesandmoths.org/species/Helicoverpa-zea?page=6&quot;&gt;Helicoverpa zea&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; corn earworm moth &amp;ndash; enjoying a sip from a &lt;a href=&quot;https://planttalk.colostate.edu/topics/trees-shrubs-vines/1741-rabbitbrush/&quot;&gt;rabbitbrush&lt;/a&gt; flower (&lt;i&gt;Chrysothamnus&lt;/i&gt; sp.), Walden Ponds, Boulder, Colorado, October, 2022.  I saw a zillion of these rather undistinguished looking creatures fluttering all over the rabbitbrush, so naturally I photographed some. They seem to be far more common in the eastern part of the United States, but there is an interesting concentration in Colorado between Fort Collins and Colorado Springs, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.butterfliesandmoths.org/species/Helicoverpa-zea?page=6&quot;&gt;Butterflies and Moths of North America&lt;/a&gt;, presumably because that is where all the people live. Something like 70 years ago, I learned that moths had furry antennas and butterflies had smooth antennas, so I first thought, against all odds, that these were butterflies (is the &quot;furry&quot; simply microscopic?). Fortunately, the Library of Congress asks (and answers), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.loc.gov/everyday-mysteries/zoology/item/how-can-you-tell-the-difference-between-a-butterfly-and-a-moth/&quot;&gt; How can you tell the difference between a butterfly and a moth?&lt;/a&gt; which notes several distinguishing features, not just one.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Helicoverpa zea &amp;ndash; corn earworm moth &amp;ndash; enjoying a sip from a rabbitbrush flower (Chrysothamnus sp.), Walden Ponds, Boulder, Colorado, October, 2022. I saw a zillion of these rather undistinguished looking creatures fluttering all over the rabbitbrush, so naturally I photographed some. They seem to be far more common in the eastern part of the United States, but there is an interesting concentration in Colorado between Fort Collins and Colorado Springs, according to Butterflies and Moths of North America, presumably because that is where all the people live. Something like 70 years ago, I learned that moths had furry antennas and butterflies had smooth antennas, so I first thought, against all odds, that these were butterflies (is the &quot;furry&quot; simply microscopic?). Fortunately, the Library of Congress asks (and answers), How can you tell the difference between a butterfly and a moth? which notes several distinguishing features, not just one.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creationism crawls back out of the woodwork</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/creationism-crawls-back.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creationism crawls back out of the woodwork" /><published>2023-02-10T09:22:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-02-10T09:22:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/creationism-crawls-back</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/creationism-crawls-back.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Creationist_Car_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Creationist car&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/f/f5/Creationist_car.jpg/&quot;&gt; Creationist car spotted on Broad Street in Athens, Georgia.&lt;/a&gt; Image by Amy Watts. &lt;small&gt;Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 2.0 Generic license.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recently learned of an article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edhat.com/news/why-creationism-may-come-back-to-our-schools&quot;&gt;Why Creationism May Come Back to Our Schools&lt;/a&gt;, by Eugenie Scott, the former director of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/&quot;&gt;National Center for Science Education&lt;/a&gt;. The occasion was a talk presented by Dr. Scott to the Humanist Society of Santa Barbara on February 1 and ably reported by Robert Bernstein for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edhat.com/&quot;&gt;Edhat&lt;/a&gt;, an online newspaper that covers Santa Barbara County, California.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may read Mr. Bernstein’s article for yourself; let it suffice to say that Dr. Scott reviews “many decades of cases” regarding the Establishment Clause and discusses why creationism generally fails. Then, she says, we come to the Kennedy case, wherein the Supreme Court overruled lower-court decisions and ruled that an assistant football coach, Joseph Kennedy, will be allowed to pray at the center of the football field with his students. The decision is troubling because the new right-wing Supreme Court has no trouble overruling previously established decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Jerry Coyne tells us, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2023/02/09/montana-considers-bill-that-allows-teaching-of-scientific-fcts-but-not-scientific-theories/&quot;&gt;Montana considers a bill that allows teaching of “scientific facts” but not “scientific theories”&lt;/a&gt;. Prof. Coyne is the proprietor of the popular blog &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com &quot;&gt;Why Evolution Is True&lt;/a&gt; and, as they say, has read the bill so you and I do not have to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bill in question is Montana Senate Bill 235, introduced by freshman Senator Dan Emrich. Prof. Coyne quotes the bill as saying&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHEREAS, [sic] the purpose of K-12 education is to educate children in the facts of our world to better prepare them for their future and further education in their chosen field of study, and to that end children must know the difference between scientific fact and scientific theory; and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WHEREAS, [sic] a scientific fact is observable and repeatable, and if it does not meet these criteria, it is a theory that is defined as speculation and is for higher education to explore, debate, and test to ultimately reach a scientific conclusion of fact or fiction. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prof. Coyne adds, ‘They later clarify: “As used in this section, ‘scientific fact’ means an indisputable and repeatable observation of a natural phenomenon.”’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very little in science can be considered an indisputable fact, so if this bill passes and becomes law, schools will not be allowed to teach, say, the theory of relativity, quantum theory, ideal gas theory, the germ theory of disease, or, for that matter, string theory or the theory of the leisure class. Or, what they are really after, the theory of evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, Sen. Emrich and his cosponsors are a trio of ignoramuses who do not have the foggiest idea what a scientific fact or a scientific theory is. They are very dangerous because, as Dr. Scott shows, they almost certainly have the Supreme Court on their side.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Creationist car spotted on Broad Street in Athens, Georgia. Image by Amy Watts. Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 2.0 Generic license. We recently learned of an article, Why Creationism May Come Back to Our Schools, by Eugenie Scott, the former director of the National Center for Science Education. The occasion was a talk presented by Dr. Scott to the Humanist Society of Santa Barbara on February 1 and ably reported by Robert Bernstein for Edhat, an online newspaper that covers Santa Barbara County, California. You may read Mr. Bernstein’s article for yourself; let it suffice to say that Dr. Scott reviews “many decades of cases” regarding the Establishment Clause and discusses why creationism generally fails. Then, she says, we come to the Kennedy case, wherein the Supreme Court overruled lower-court decisions and ruled that an assistant football coach, Joseph Kennedy, will be allowed to pray at the center of the football field with his students. The decision is troubling because the new right-wing Supreme Court has no trouble overruling previously established decisions. Meanwhile, Jerry Coyne tells us, Montana considers a bill that allows teaching of “scientific facts” but not “scientific theories”. Prof. Coyne is the proprietor of the popular blog Why Evolution Is True and, as they say, has read the bill so you and I do not have to.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ark attendance weak, at best</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/ark-attendance-week.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ark attendance weak, at best" /><published>2023-02-01T16:20:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-02-01T16:20:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/ark-attendance-week</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/ark-attendance-week.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Trollinger_Ark_Attendance_900.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Graph&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Actual Ark attendance vs. projected, based on the data of William Trollinger. The actual attendance in Year 1 seems to be an estimate. Actual attendance for the period March 2020 through February 2021 have been omitted owing to Covid. Actual attendance for the period January through June 2023 is an estimate based on the historical ratio of attendance during the first six months of the year to that of the last six months.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Trollinger, on the blog Righting America, presents what he calls a few facts about Ark Encounter attendance and deems that attendance to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/not-even-close-to-what-was-projected-a-few-facts-about-ark-encounter-attendance/&quot;&gt;Not Even Close to What Was Projected&lt;/a&gt;. Dr. Trollinger bases his conclusion on data acquired by the indomitable Dan Phelps, an occasional guest contributor here at PT. Mr. Phelps each month uses the Kentucky Open Records Act to ascertain the monies collected by the city of Williamstown from the safety fee of $0.50 added to each ticket. From these data it is easy to deduce the number of tickets sold and therefore the number of patrons in any given month, apart from a number of possibly fictitious season-pass holders who pass the ticket window without being assessed the safety fee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have graphed Dr. Trollinger’s data and show them as the frontispiece to this article. Two of the years, as noted, are estimates. Year 4 is actually a two-year period from July 2019 to June 2021, but with March 2020 through February 2021 omitted because of the Covid pandemic. The result does not seem out of line. Overall attendance, over the 6 years, is about 40 % of projected attendance and appears to have fallen somewhat since Year 3, as projected attendance rises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For that, as Dr. Trollinger notes, Williamstown issued $62 million in junk bonds and in effect forwent a significant sum in property taxes. For more details, see the original article.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Actual Ark attendance vs. projected, based on the data of William Trollinger. The actual attendance in Year 1 seems to be an estimate. Actual attendance for the period March 2020 through February 2021 have been omitted owing to Covid. Actual attendance for the period January through June 2023 is an estimate based on the historical ratio of attendance during the first six months of the year to that of the last six months. William Trollinger, on the blog Righting America, presents what he calls a few facts about Ark Encounter attendance and deems that attendance to be Not Even Close to What Was Projected. Dr. Trollinger bases his conclusion on data acquired by the indomitable Dan Phelps, an occasional guest contributor here at PT. Mr. Phelps each month uses the Kentucky Open Records Act to ascertain the monies collected by the city of Williamstown from the safety fee of $0.50 added to each ticket. From these data it is easy to deduce the number of tickets sold and therefore the number of patrons in any given month, apart from a number of possibly fictitious season-pass holders who pass the ticket window without being assessed the safety fee. I have graphed Dr. Trollinger’s data and show them as the frontispiece to this article. Two of the years, as noted, are estimates. Year 4 is actually a two-year period from July 2019 to June 2021, but with March 2020 through February 2021 omitted because of the Covid pandemic. The result does not seem out of line. Overall attendance, over the 6 years, is about 40 % of projected attendance and appears to have fallen somewhat since Year 3, as projected attendance rises. For that, as Dr. Trollinger notes, Williamstown issued $62 million in junk bonds and in effect forwent a significant sum in property taxes. For more details, see the original article.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cryptozoon occidentale</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/Cryptozoon-occidentale.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cryptozoon occidentale" /><published>2023-01-30T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-01-30T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/Cryptozoon-occidentale</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/Cryptozoon-occidentale.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;James Kocher&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Kocher_BeltStromCryptozoon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Stromatolite&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Cryptozoon occidentale&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stromatolite&quot;&gt;stromatolite&lt;/a&gt; colony, Snowslip Formation/Missoula Group from Essex, Montana.  Specimen is a vertical section cut on lapidary saw (i.e., perpendicular to bedding). Age = ~1.0 Ga; neoproterozoic. Width of picture is ~6 cm. See also &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp294D&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by James Kocher. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Cryptozoon occidentale &amp;ndash; stromatolite colony, Snowslip Formation/Missoula Group from Essex, Montana. Specimen is a vertical section cut on lapidary saw (i.e., perpendicular to bedding). Age = ~1.0 Ga; neoproterozoic. Width of picture is ~6 cm. See also here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Are cephalopods better designed than humans?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/cephalopods-better-designed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are cephalopods better designed than humans?" /><published>2023-01-23T08:42:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-01-23T08:42:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/cephalopods-better-designed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/cephalopods-better-designed.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Leopard_Tapetum_Keven_Law_Wikimedia_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reflections in eyes of leopard&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Amur leopard (not a cephalopod), showing retroreflection from tapetum. &lt;small&gt;Colchester Zoo, Monday, November 19, 2007. &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Amur_leopard_by_Keven_Law.jpg&quot;&gt;Photograph&lt;/a&gt; by Keven Law. Wikimedia Commons, CC BY-SA 2.0.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to the titular question depends on what you think they are designed for; hence, it seems to be a silly question. When it comes to the eyes, however, there is little doubt: human (and other vertebrate) retinas are in backward in that nerves, blood vessels, and other structures are piled on top of the photoreceptors and thus reduce sensitivity, if not resolution. Additionally, the nerves go out through a hole in the retina, which makes us susceptible to glaucoma. Cephalopod retinas, by contrast, face forward, with nothing covering the photoreceptors, and the nerves do not have to pass through a hole in the retina. Cephalopod eyes are thus clearly better designed than human eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I raise this question by way of introducing an article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://skepticalinquirer.org/2022/12/the-night-begins-to-shine-the-tapetum-lucidum-and-our-backward-retinas/&quot;&gt;The night begins to shine: The tapetum lucidum and our backward retinas&lt;/a&gt;, by Nathan H. Lents, in the January-February issue of &lt;i&gt;Skeptical Inquirer&lt;/i&gt;. The tapetum lucidum, or just tapetum, is a reflective membrane in the retinas of many nocturnal vertebrates and is located just behind the photoreceptors. Its purpose is presumedly to direct the light that the photoreceptors miss back into them and thereby increase the sensitivity. Interestingly, tapetums composed of many different materials appear to have evolved many different times in different creatures. Cephalopods have no tapetum, presumably because their retinas face forward, with the photoreceptors directly facing the light. Prof. Lents explains all this and more in great but easily understandable detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please forgive a physicist’s digression. I once lost a debate as to whether the retina is in backward or not. It is in backward. (In most anatomical drawings, however, the cones appear at least vaguely conical, with the open end facing the incoming light. Thus, the cones themselves are not exactly in backward.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At night, we are presumably dealing with rod (scotopic) vision, and the rods supposedly trap light due to total internal reflection. If that is so, then the law of refraction prohibits light traveling in the opposite direction (toward the light source) from getting into the rod. How then is the tapetum helpful?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot immediately find an answer to this question, so I will stick my neck out and suggest that the evanescent wave penetrates the rod and is absorbed by the dyes in the rod, similarly to frustrated total internal reflection. If that is so, then it is hard to see how the tapetum can be very effective, but I guess every little bit counts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/strong&gt;. Thanks to Nathan Lents for discovering what I can only call a silly mistake and to Steven Fliesler of the school of medicine of the University of Buffalo for interesting comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Amur leopard (not a cephalopod), showing retroreflection from tapetum. Colchester Zoo, Monday, November 19, 2007. Photograph by Keven Law. Wikimedia Commons, CC BY-SA 2.0. The answer to the titular question depends on what you think they are designed for; hence, it seems to be a silly question. When it comes to the eyes, however, there is little doubt: human (and other vertebrate) retinas are in backward in that nerves, blood vessels, and other structures are piled on top of the photoreceptors and thus reduce sensitivity, if not resolution. Additionally, the nerves go out through a hole in the retina, which makes us susceptible to glaucoma. Cephalopod retinas, by contrast, face forward, with nothing covering the photoreceptors, and the nerves do not have to pass through a hole in the retina. Cephalopod eyes are thus clearly better designed than human eyes. I raise this question by way of introducing an article, The night begins to shine: The tapetum lucidum and our backward retinas, by Nathan H. Lents, in the January-February issue of Skeptical Inquirer. The tapetum lucidum, or just tapetum, is a reflective membrane in the retinas of many nocturnal vertebrates and is located just behind the photoreceptors. Its purpose is presumedly to direct the light that the photoreceptors miss back into them and thereby increase the sensitivity. Interestingly, tapetums composed of many different materials appear to have evolved many different times in different creatures. Cephalopods have no tapetum, presumably because their retinas face forward, with the photoreceptors directly facing the light. Prof. Lents explains all this and more in great but easily understandable detail.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ken Ham Using Creation Museum for Kentucky Politics</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/ken-ham-using.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ken Ham Using Creation Museum for Kentucky Politics" /><published>2023-01-20T09:45:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-01-20T09:45:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/ken-ham-using</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/ken-ham-using.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Phelps_501c3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;IRS brochure&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;, January 28, 2023, 3:30 p.m., MST. A version of this post appeared in the Lexington (Kentucky) Herald-Leader under the head &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kentucky.com/opinion/op-ed/article271570602.html&quot;&gt;Creation Museum to host anti-abortion event with extremist pastor, Ky legislators | Opinion&lt;/a&gt;. Mark Looy replied under the head &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kentucky.com/opinion/letters-to-the-editor/article271724962.html &quot;&gt;Abortion clarification&lt;/a&gt;. You may see the text of his letter in &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/ken-ham-using.html#comment-6101095162&quot;&gt;Comment 6101095162&lt;/a&gt;. Mr. Phelps replies there that Mr. Looy’s reply “seems to concede what I said, but tries to obfuscate. He admits that the legislation would cause women that have abortions be charged with murder and that Pastor Jeff Durbin advocates the death penalty.”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ken Ham and Answers in Genesis (AiG), along with &lt;a href=&quot;https://metro.co.uk/2017/02/27/hipster-says-he-wants-to-execute-women-who-have-abortions-6475717/&quot;&gt;the extremist Jeff Durbin&lt;/a&gt; of Arizona’s Apologia Church, are hosting a political event for pastors at the Creation Museum to support &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5lyiv2zQr6k&quot;&gt;pending Kentucky anti-abortion legislation&lt;/a&gt;.  To my knowledge &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.legislature.ky.gov/record/23rs/index_headings.html&quot;&gt;this legislation has not yet been introduced&lt;/a&gt; as of January 18. The rally is also advertised on January 18, AiG’s weekly “Answers News”, near the end of the show (&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/AUkCdwY6LVs&quot;&gt;about 34 minutes in&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in March 2007, when the Creation Museum was about to open, AiG’s Mark Looy and Ken Ham penned a post to their website titled “&lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/world-religions/humanism/goose-stepping-to-zion/&quot;&gt;Goose-stepping to Zion&lt;/a&gt;.”    This essay claims AiG is “apolitical” and states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although Hedges insinuates that the creation movement (especially AiG, for he spends most of his chapter on us) is a major part of America’s religious right and its fascist tendencies, AiG is apolitical. It avoids the political arena. It’s not our job to change the culture—it’s our job to disseminate information, proclaim the gospel, and stand on the authority of God’s Word … and THEN see hearts changed for the Lord.&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;p&gt;Now, if these changed lives impact the culture, and if God blesses that, then we’re happy to see it. But we’re not going to be an activist ministry in the sense of legislating, litigating or lobbying key leaders to mandate change in society.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, policy on politicking has changed for AiG since 2007. Last October AiG had an “Answers for Pastors” meeting at the Ark Encounter featuring White Christian Nationalist Tony Perkins of the Family Research Council. I reported on this on the Panda’s Thumb &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/09/extreme-right-wing-Christian-nationalist.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this upcoming political rally for pastors supporting specific legislation is particularly disturbing, and not because it is about abortion. This event indicates Ham/AiG are becoming more overtly involved in Kentucky politics. Will Kentuckians see AiG become more involved in a multitude of political issues? Will AiG begin to endorse political candidates? AiG’s 501(c)(3) religious non-profit status may preclude such activities, but the IRS has generally been lax in its enforcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be interesting to see which state legislators, candidates for governor, and other politicians attend the Creation Museum rally. The separation of church and state in Kentucky looks weak at this writing. Meanwhile, AiG’s influence in Kentucky, political and otherwise, continues to grow.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Update, January 28, 2023, 3:30 p.m., MST. A version of this post appeared in the Lexington (Kentucky) Herald-Leader under the head Creation Museum to host anti-abortion event with extremist pastor, Ky legislators | Opinion. Mark Looy replied under the head Abortion clarification. You may see the text of his letter in Comment 6101095162. Mr. Phelps replies there that Mr. Looy’s reply “seems to concede what I said, but tries to obfuscate. He admits that the legislation would cause women that have abortions be charged with murder and that Pastor Jeff Durbin advocates the death penalty.” Ken Ham and Answers in Genesis (AiG), along with the extremist Jeff Durbin of Arizona’s Apologia Church, are hosting a political event for pastors at the Creation Museum to support pending Kentucky anti-abortion legislation. To my knowledge this legislation has not yet been introduced as of January 18. The rally is also advertised on January 18, AiG’s weekly “Answers News”, near the end of the show (about 34 minutes in). Back in March 2007, when the Creation Museum was about to open, AiG’s Mark Looy and Ken Ham penned a post to their website titled “Goose-stepping to Zion.” This essay claims AiG is “apolitical” and states:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Trioceros jacksonii</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/Trioceros-jacksonii.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trioceros jacksonii" /><published>2023-01-16T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-01-16T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/Trioceros%20jacksonii</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/01/Trioceros-jacksonii.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Mark Sturtevant&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photogrphy Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Sturtevant.Jacksons_Chameleon.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Chameleon&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Trioceros jacksonii&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; Jackson’s chameleon. Dr. Sturtevant writes, &quot;The Hawaiian islands harbor many unique species of plants and animals that have evolved there while in isolation. But of course humans have introduced many non-native species to the islands, and these foreigners come from around the world. This large chameleon was found along a forested path on Maui, and is one of many species of chameleons that thrive on the islands after having been introduced there through the pet trade and general human stupidity. This large chameleon is quite capable of swallowing baby birds that are in the nest, and so it is a threat to the native birds.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Mark Sturtevant. Photogrphy Contest, Honorable Mention. Trioceros jacksonii &amp;ndash; Jackson’s chameleon. Dr. Sturtevant writes, &quot;The Hawaiian islands harbor many unique species of plants and animals that have evolved there while in isolation. But of course humans have introduced many non-native species to the islands, and these foreigners come from around the world. This large chameleon was found along a forested path on Maui, and is one of many species of chameleons that thrive on the islands after having been introduced there through the pet trade and general human stupidity. This large chameleon is quite capable of swallowing baby birds that are in the nest, and so it is a threat to the native birds.&quot;</summary></entry></feed>