<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-14T04:01:42-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Is the NABT statement on teaching evolution flawed?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Is-the-NABT-statement-flawed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is the NABT statement on teaching evolution flawed?" /><published>2020-12-12T09:36:01-07:00</published><updated>2020-12-12T09:36:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Is-the-NABT-statement-flawed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Is-the-NABT-statement-flawed.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/SistineDarwinApe.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;SistineDarwinApe&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Copyright Michelangelo di Lodovico Buonarroti Simoni and anonymous&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This post consists of two statements reacting to the statement on teaching of evolution by National Association of Biology Teachers.  They are by Paul Braterman and Anj Petto.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Statement by Paul Braterman&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Biology teachers, especially in the US, often find themselves called upon to defend their teaching of evolution, on the grounds that it arbitrarily rejects the possibility of supernatural causes, and that since it is a theory it should not be taught as fact. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://nabt.org/Position-Statements-NABT-Position-Statement-on-Teaching-Evolution&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Position Statement from the National Association of Biology Teachers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is meant to address such concerns. In my opinion, it lamentably fails to do so, and indeed gives ammunition to the enemies of evolution science.
&lt;!--more--&gt;
Regarding supernatural causes, the Statement says that
&lt;blockquote&gt;
“[E]ducators should support science education by rejecting calls to account for the history of life or describe the mechanisms of evolution by invoking any non-natural or supernatural notions, whether under the banner of “creation science,” “scientific creationism,” “intelligent design,” or similar designations. Such notions are outside the scope of science, do not adhere to the shared scientific standards governing the collection and interpreting of evidence, and should not be presented as part of the science curriculum.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
In other words, according to the NABT, non-natural or supernatural notions regarding the history of life should be excluded from scientific discussion from the outset, without further examination, although they may be presented outside the context of science.
&lt;p&gt;
This is the worst of all possible worlds. It is philosophically inaccurate,&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; since “non-natural or supernatural notions” such as extra-sensory perception and the existence of ghosts, have been and should be within the domain of scientific inquiry. Indeed it is only as the result of such inquiry that we are able to state without circular argument that these notions are devoid of merit. Precisely the same is true of supernatural notions regarding the history of life, including specifically the notions of the separate creation of kinds (“creation science”), and of the intervention of a designer (“Intelligent Design”). Finally, it is not the role of NABT to rule about what may be presented outside the science curriculum, least of all to suggest that a notion that is unacceptable in the context of science may nonetheless be acceptable elsewhere.
As to why this is important, consider what Phillip Johnson, former Supreme Court clerk to Earl Warren, Professor of Law at UC Berkeley, and founder of the modern Intelligent Design movement, wrote about this specific topic in Defeating Darwin by Opening Minds:&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
“I agree with the common people [in seeing a role for God in the history of life]. If we are right, the consequences are very, very important. The ruling naturalists know that too, although they may deny it. That is why they are so determined to define words like evolution and science in such a way that naturalism is true by definition.” (pp 22-23)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
And again later (p 56):
&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Contemporary scientists… consider things supernatural to be outside of science. In other words, scientists start by assuming the naturalism is true, and they try to give purely natural explanations for everything, including our existence.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Notice how skilfully Johnson uses the NABT’s philosophical error to invoke anti-elitism and anti-intellectualism, and to suggest, as he repeatedly does in this book, that scientists accept evolution in the face of the evidence in order to justify atheism. I think it of the highest importance that we should not give the creationists a legitimate opening to do this. We can avoid doing so, while retaining what is of merit in this section of the Statement, by replacing the offending words with a short statement such as
“Non-naturalistic notions, such as &quot;Intelligent Design&quot;, have not proved fruitful, while separate creation is refuted by numerous lines of evidence&quot;
Relatedly, consider what NABT has to say regarding theories:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Scientific data overwhelmingly supports the theory of evolution. Scientific theories are supported by extensive evidence.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
The statement that “Scientific theories are supported by extensive evidence” is sometimes true, sometimes untrue, and claims to the contrary will correctly be seen as self-serving and based on circular reasoning. The study of evolution is a research program containing numerous theoretical and observational components, while common descent, which is what is really under discussion here, is not theory, but fact.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;footnotes&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
1] ABT is incorrectly imposing Intrinsic Methodological Naturalism on science as an a priori constraint, whereas it should be using Provisory Methodological Naturalism, in which naturalism emerges from the failure of the supernatural under scientific scrutiny. See How not to attack Intelligent Design Creationism: Philosophical misconceptions about Methodological Naturalism, Maarten Boudry, Stefaan Blancke, Johan Braeckman, Foundations of Science, 15(3), 227–244, 2010; draft publicly available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/maartenboudry/teksten-1/methodological-naturalism&quot;&gt;https://sites.google.com/site/maartenboudry/teksten-1/methodological-naturalism&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;
2] 2nd Edition, Intervarsity Press, 1997. The current NABT Statement differs in wording from the one that he is attacking, but not in ways that affect his argument.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I thank Joe Felsenstein and Maarten Boudry  for useful discussions.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Statement by Anj Petto&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The National Association on Biology Teachers (NABT) is one of several organizations that has released position statements over the last few decades on the centrality of evolution in the life sciences and its proper place in life sciences education. Let's frame the issues that NABT faced with its position statements using the A-B-T (And/But/Therefore) model for science communication of Filmmaker Randy Olsen.
&lt;p&gt;
Evolution is the foundation of the modern life sciences, &lt;b&gt;and&lt;/b&gt; no one can be “educated” in these disciplines unless the instruction is grounded in modern evolutionary science. &lt;b&gt;But&lt;/b&gt;, evolution education is considered “controversial” by some members of the general public; they object to its inclusion in the curriculum and they pressure teachers, administrators, political leaders, and community organizations to eliminate, weaken or challenge evolution education in public schools. Furthermore, all the efforts in science education reform in the United States since the late 1950s have had minimal success in convincing the public at large that evolution is real, is a valid scientific theory and research framework, explains the history and diversity of life on Earth, and applies to humans as well as to other organisms. &lt;b&gt;Therefore&lt;/b&gt;, professional organizations, such as NABT, issue policy statements and position papers to make clear their support for evolution education, its role in the scientific disciplines that its members teach, and the fundamental role that evolution serves in how we understand the history and diversity of life on Earth.
&lt;p&gt;
There is no fundamental disagreement within the sciences on the validity of evolutionary sciences (the AND). The problem, of course, is the public perception that there is such a disagreement, and that science education should include the objections to evolutionary science (the BUT). In other words, after close to 70 years of trying to improve the acceptance and understanding of evolution through science education reform, the nation is still sharply and almost equally divided between those who accept and those who reject evolution.
&lt;p&gt;
To address this problem (the THEREFORE), policy statements from national professional scientific or science education organizations have to publicize both the widespread scientific success of evolutionary science and the reluctance of close to half the general public to accept that this could be so. Of course, they need to affirm (and re-affirm) their support of and commitment to evolution education. At the same time, these organizations—especially science education organizations—must avoid making the situation worse for teachers and school personnel working in districts with strong and active religious communities. Many religious communities long ago made a peace with evolution consistent with their doctrines and practices (for example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/statements-religious-organizationse&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;https://ncse.ngo/statements-religious-organizations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). To force a choice between religious practice and acceptance of evolution runs the risk of alienating potential allies that science educators need to help overcome challenges in their districts.
&lt;p&gt;
In a series of revisions to its policy on teaching evolution, NABT (and other organizations) tried various ways of expressing that their intention is not to oppose religious belief per se among their students, but to focus on the natural laws and processes that produce the patterns of similarities and differences that we can observe in living organisms on the Earth in all the places and over all the time that life has occupied the planet; or, in a word: evolution.
&lt;p&gt;
Objections to evolutionary science are essentially unchanged since the 1950s. They promote the same arguments and objections to evolution rooted in the original “creation science” movement—evolution reserves no role for an omniscient creator spirit. The newer arguments appear to be different to the general public—for example, invoking an unnamed “intelligent agent” instead of naming a specific deity; showing mathematical formulae or alternative interpretation of geologic observations—and so policy statements need to keep up with the latest iterations.
&lt;p&gt;
Revisions in policy statements over time have addressed specific forms that objections to evolution have taken. Newer phrases and reworked arguments raise specific issues at specific points in time, and the policy statement has responded appropriately—if not always effectively—to those objections. We clearly haven't found the “one” policy statement that works: one that will convince communities that evolutionary science is solid and productive; that its track record of successful performance is why it should be included in the curriculum. But the “perfect” statement must always recognize the community context in which most evolution education is practiced; its wording must not alienate or exclude members of the community who would support evolution education by directly (and unnecessarily) challenging fundamental beliefs and values that are not in conflict with the principles of evolutionary science. It is threading scientific filament through the eye of a sociocultural needle.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman and Anj Petto</name></author><summary type="html">Copyright Michelangelo di Lodovico Buonarroti Simoni and anonymous This post consists of two statements reacting to the statement on teaching of evolution by National Association of Biology Teachers. They are by Paul Braterman and Anj Petto. Statement by Paul Braterman Biology teachers, especially in the US, often find themselves called upon to defend their teaching of evolution, on the grounds that it arbitrarily rejects the possibility of supernatural causes, and that since it is a theory it should not be taught as fact. The Position Statement from the National Association of Biology Teachers is meant to address such concerns. In my opinion, it lamentably fails to do so, and indeed gives ammunition to the enemies of evolution science.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Macrosiphini</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/macrosiphini.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Macrosiphini" /><published>2020-12-07T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-12-07T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/macrosiphini</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/macrosiphini.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/DSC03667_Aphid_Crop_600_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aphid&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;An aphid of the tribe &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugguide.net/node/view/359390/bgpage&quot;&gt;Macrosiphini&lt;/a&gt;, enjoying a tomato plant.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Natalie Hernandez in BugGuide identified the aphid as Macrosiphini, a “tribe” of aphids. She adds, “Tough to ID it further from this angle, the shape and texture of the head between the antennae (dorsal view) separates some of the similar genera. Reticulations on the siphunculi are important too but tough to see in photos, and this one isn’t helping by breaking the siphunculus that is in view.” The &lt;a href=&quot;http://aphid.aphidnet.org/siphunculus.php&quot;&gt;siphunculus&lt;/a&gt; is a small tube for emitting pheromones; I have not the foggiest idea where the siphunculus is in this picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Sturtevant, who provided many helpful tips on macrophotography, wrote me,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Aphids are weird. Late in the season like this they will likely start laying eggs soon to overwinter. But during the main part of the season they give live birth – regularly pooping out a young-un, which is simply dropped behind the parent, facing in the same direction as the mother [see the video &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hEoo-6InDA8&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;]. Furthermore, unless they are tended by ants, which tickle them for nectar and make them move, most aphids in a colony will all be facing the same direction. I think the reason for that is because what I just mentioned: They are born facing the same direction as their parent, and there they pretty much just sit. They grow, and soon start pooping out their own youngsters, until you have a dense colony, all facing the same direction which is the direction they were born (!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While this is happening, if you look closely at a “big” one you can often see pairs of red dots inside the abdomen. Those are the compound eyes of their unborn young.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And other weird things: These live births are done by parthenogenesis, so the babies are clones of the mothers. Aphids are all female for most of the season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And then there is another weird thing. Their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/news/photosynthesis-like-process-found-in-insects-1.11214&quot;&gt;bright colors&lt;/a&gt; (green, yellow, red, depending on the species) are apparently from genes lifted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nsf.gov/news/news_summ.jsp?cntn_id=116842&quot;&gt;fungi&lt;/a&gt; who-knows-how-long ago. This seems a case of gene transfer from fungi to animals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And then there are all the parasites and predators they get. You can sit for hours watching a large aphid colony and see lots of drama. Live births, and various forms of horrible death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">An aphid of the tribe Macrosiphini, enjoying a tomato plant. Natalie Hernandez in BugGuide identified the aphid as Macrosiphini, a “tribe” of aphids. She adds, “Tough to ID it further from this angle, the shape and texture of the head between the antennae (dorsal view) separates some of the similar genera. Reticulations on the siphunculi are important too but tough to see in photos, and this one isn’t helping by breaking the siphunculus that is in view.” The siphunculus is a small tube for emitting pheromones; I have not the foggiest idea where the siphunculus is in this picture. Mark Sturtevant, who provided many helpful tips on macrophotography, wrote me,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Are there any new ID arguments?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Any-new-arguments.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are there any new ID arguments?" /><published>2020-12-01T20:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-12-01T20:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Any-new-arguments</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Any-new-arguments.html">&lt;p&gt;In a discussion of the future of arguments with creationists and/or ID advocates, someone said there were no new arguments from them.  Here is my response, from an email.  It is mostly about the sort of ID arguments that I have paid most attention to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There have been attempts to come up with new versions of Dembski's arguments, from the Marks-Ewert-Holloway &quot;Design Inference&quot; axis.  But they are all somewhat vague and cannot be made explicit without it becoming clear how weak the arguments are.  Marks and Dembski have had an argument that on average &quot;evolutionary searches&quot; do no better than random guessing.  But they could do that only by including among the &quot;evolutionary&quot; searches as many that actively tried to get a bad result as there were ones that tried to get a good result.  Holloway and others also put forward arguments that Algorithmic Specified Complexity that is high because things are unusually non-complex (huh?) would be very rare among all possible bitstrings.  But they left it unclear why evolution should in some sense be trying to achieve that, and they made no argument about what natural selection would do with that measure.  There is also some rigorous math from George Monta&amp;ntilde;ez of that group on how to unify a whole bunch of measures of specified complexity -- without ever exploring whether any of them help make an argument against the effectiveness of evolutionary processes.  There are also works by Marks and co. on &quot;active information&quot;, which is, however, information that can be put into the genome by natural selection, so not at all a refutation of its involvement.
&lt;p&gt;
So ...
&lt;!--more--&gt;
they're trying, and doing lots of very mathy things, and these can get cited by creationists and other ID advocates as powerful mathy disproofs of the effectiveness of evolutionary processes, as long as no one really looks inside the argument to see what it actually shows.  And so far they have not dotted the i's and crossed the t's in any way that actually argues against natural selection being able to result in adaptation.
&lt;p&gt;
For posts here at PT on the Dembski/Marks/Ewert &quot;evolutionary algorithms&quot; argument, and on the relevance of the ASC measure of (non-)complexity see &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2015/03/fitness-surface.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/12/Is-Algorithmic-Specified-Complexity-Useless-for-Analyzing-Evolution.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;
There's also &lt;a href=&quot;https://discourse.peacefulscience.org/t/intelligent-design-1-0-2-0-3-0-and-beyond/12588&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;a recent discussion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at Josh Swamidass's site Peaceful Science of a video in which Stephen Meyer and Douglas Axe present &quot;ID 3.0&quot;. Many of the commenters conclude that it is vaporware.  I must have missed 2.0 as well.
&lt;p&gt;
What do people see out there that would qualify as a new, and possibly even valid, ID argument?  
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">In a discussion of the future of arguments with creationists and/or ID advocates, someone said there were no new arguments from them. Here is my response, from an email. It is mostly about the sort of ID arguments that I have paid most attention to. There have been attempts to come up with new versions of Dembski's arguments, from the Marks-Ewert-Holloway &quot;Design Inference&quot; axis.  But they are all somewhat vague and cannot be made explicit without it becoming clear how weak the arguments are.  Marks and Dembski have had an argument that on average &quot;evolutionary searches&quot; do no better than random guessing.  But they could do that only by including among the &quot;evolutionary&quot; searches as many that actively tried to get a bad result as there were ones that tried to get a good result.  Holloway and others also put forward arguments that Algorithmic Specified Complexity that is high because things are unusually non-complex (huh?) would be very rare among all possible bitstrings.  But they left it unclear why evolution should in some sense be trying to achieve that, and they made no argument about what natural selection would do with that measure.  There is also some rigorous math from George Monta&amp;ntilde;ez of that group on how to unify a whole bunch of measures of specified complexity -- without ever exploring whether any of them help make an argument against the effectiveness of evolutionary processes.  There are also works by Marks and co. on &quot;active information&quot;, which is, however, information that can be put into the genome by natural selection, so not at all a refutation of its involvement. So ...</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Penumbral eclipse of moon</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/penumbral-eclipse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Penumbral eclipse of moon" /><published>2020-11-30T10:08:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-11-30T10:08:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/penumbral-eclipse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/penumbral-eclipse.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/DSC03929_Penumbral_Eclipse_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot; Penumbral eclipse&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Penumbral eclipse of the moon, 2:40 a. m., MST, November 30, 2020.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeanddate.com/eclipse/lunar/2020-november-30&quot;&gt;penumbral eclipse&lt;/a&gt; of the moon last night. During a penumbral eclipse, the moon enters the penumbra of the Earth’s shadow, rather than the umbra, or the deep shadow. Unless I am mistaken, if you were in the penumbra, on the moon, you would see a partial eclipse of the sun. At any rate, the penumbral eclipse was supposed to last from 12:32 a. m. to 4:53 and peak at 2:42, Mountain Standard Time, this morning. I went out with my trusty digital camera and a 210-millimeter lens at about 12:30 and 1:30, but I could see nothing, and the photographs revealed nothing. At 2:40, however, I exposed the photograph above. Although I adjusted the exposure using Affinity software, the image is not doctored in any way. You can see a darkening of the limb in the upper-right corner. Once I saw the photograph in the camera, I could see the limb darkening with the naked eye, but evidently my retina was overexposed slightly, because I had to squint to see it. Given my lack of success at 1:30, I forwent the opportunity to take a picture at 3:30 and retired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had the good fortune to see a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2017/08/total-eclipse.html&quot;&gt;total eclipse of the sun&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/01/total-eclipse-moon.html&quot;&gt;total eclipse of the moon&lt;/a&gt; not very long ago. Unfortunately, the penumbral eclipse, though mildly interesting in principle, could not hold a candle to either of those.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Penumbral eclipse of the moon, 2:40 a. m., MST, November 30, 2020. There was a penumbral eclipse of the moon last night. During a penumbral eclipse, the moon enters the penumbra of the Earth’s shadow, rather than the umbra, or the deep shadow. Unless I am mistaken, if you were in the penumbra, on the moon, you would see a partial eclipse of the sun. At any rate, the penumbral eclipse was supposed to last from 12:32 a. m. to 4:53 and peak at 2:42, Mountain Standard Time, this morning. I went out with my trusty digital camera and a 210-millimeter lens at about 12:30 and 1:30, but I could see nothing, and the photographs revealed nothing. At 2:40, however, I exposed the photograph above. Although I adjusted the exposure using Affinity software, the image is not doctored in any way. You can see a darkening of the limb in the upper-right corner. Once I saw the photograph in the camera, I could see the limb darkening with the naked eye, but evidently my retina was overexposed slightly, because I had to squint to see it. Given my lack of success at 1:30, I forwent the opportunity to take a picture at 3:30 and retired. I had the good fortune to see a total eclipse of the sun and a total eclipse of the moon not very long ago. Unfortunately, the penumbral eclipse, though mildly interesting in principle, could not hold a candle to either of those.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Columba livia domestica</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/Columba_livia_domestica.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Columba livia domestica" /><published>2020-11-23T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-11-23T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/Columba_livia_domestica</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/Columba_livia_domestica.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Muharrem Gorkem&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Gorkem_DomesticPigeon1_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pigeon&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
The photographer writes, &quot;A domestic pigeon, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domestic_pigeon&quot;&gt;Columba livia domestica&lt;/a&gt;, on her evening tour just before my apartment.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Muharrem Gorkem. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. The photographer writes, &quot;A domestic pigeon, Columba livia domestica, on her evening tour just before my apartment.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What are the most important misconceptions about evolution?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/misconceptions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What are the most important misconceptions about evolution?" /><published>2020-11-22T00:01:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-11-22T00:01:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/misconceptions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/misconceptions.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/TeheranGraffitoPaulKellerA.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;caption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Street art from Teheran, 2007.  Photo by Paul Keller&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Misconceptions about evolution abound, but rather too little is said about them.  I’d like to open a discussion here, in the comments.  In the slightly longer run, we could have a series of articles about them; I’d be happy to post these on behalf of their authors.  But first, it would help to have a discussion of what are
the most important, and most misleading, misconceptions about evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another good source of information on this is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.talkorigins.org/origins/faqs-evolution.html&quot;&gt;Talk Origins Archive&lt;/a&gt; which has quite a few excellent articles.  The most widely-cited is probably Doug Theobald’s outstanding “29+ Evidences of Macroevolution”.  Without detracting from the great service that the TOA is providing, it has been less actively updated lately.  So having some more discussions here seems like a good idea.  Perhaps we can compile a master list of misconceptions.  Let’s discuss.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Street art from Teheran, 2007. Photo by Paul Keller Misconceptions about evolution abound, but rather too little is said about them. I’d like to open a discussion here, in the comments. In the slightly longer run, we could have a series of articles about them; I’d be happy to post these on behalf of their authors. But first, it would help to have a discussion of what are the most important, and most misleading, misconceptions about evolution. Another good source of information on this is the Talk Origins Archive which has quite a few excellent articles. The most widely-cited is probably Doug Theobald’s outstanding “29+ Evidences of Macroevolution”. Without detracting from the great service that the TOA is providing, it has been less actively updated lately. So having some more discussions here seems like a good idea. Perhaps we can compile a master list of misconceptions. Let’s discuss.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Counterexample to Mark Champneys’ argument about natural selection: more technical details</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/counterexample-to-mark-champneys-details.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Counterexample to Mark Champneys’ argument about natural selection: more technical details" /><published>2020-11-14T01:17:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-11-14T01:17:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/counterexample-to-mark-champneys-details</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/counterexample-to-mark-champneys-details.html">&lt;p&gt;This post will supply some more technical details of my counterexample to
Mark Champneys’ arguments that approach of physical and biological systems
to equilibrium prevents natural selection from being effective.  The counterexample is explained in &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/10/does-approach-toward-higher-probability.html&quot;&gt;my previous post&lt;/a&gt;.  Below I
provide the relevant equations and some simulation results showing what
the effect of genetic drift will be.  To avoid taking up too much space on the
site’s front page, I will put most of that content “below the fold” …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Population genetics theory&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The model had a very large (effectively infinite) population of haploid organisms, for which we are following 100 sites in their DNA.  Mutation is symmetrical among all
four possible nucleotides at rate  &lt;em&gt;u&lt;/em&gt;, with each mutational event equally likely
to result in each of the other 3 possible bases.  We are following the frequency
of the C allele at each site.  It has fitness a fraction &lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt; greater than the three other nucleotides, which have fitness &lt;em&gt;1&lt;/em&gt;.  So the fitness of C is &lt;em&gt;1+s&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each generation starts by producing a large number of offspring, with mutation
happening at that time.  So if the fraction of all copies of the site that have C is
&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;, after mutation a fraction &lt;em&gt;u&lt;/em&gt; of those have changed to another base, and
a fraction &lt;em&gt;u/3&lt;/em&gt; of the non-C bases have changed and become C.  Thus the
frequency of allele C is then &lt;em&gt;p’&lt;/em&gt;, where&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p’ =  p(1-u) + (u/3)(1-p)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then these individuals undergo natural selection.  &lt;em&gt;(1-p’)&lt;/em&gt; of the copies are
non-C bases, and &lt;em&gt;p’&lt;/em&gt; of the copies are C.  As these have fitnesses &lt;em&gt;1&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;1+s&lt;/em&gt;,
their numbers after selection will be proportional to  &lt;em&gt;(1-p’)&lt;/em&gt;  and  &lt;em&gt;p’(1+s)&lt;/em&gt;,
so that the fraction of copies that are C will then become&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p’(1+s) / ((1-p’) + p’(1+s)),&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p’(1+s) / (1 + p’ s).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applying these two formulas in that order, we get after a full generation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(p(1-u) + (u/3)(1-p)) (1+s) / (1 + (p(1-u) + (u/3)(1-p)) s )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we have reached the equilibrium gene frequency, this is again &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;, so
that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p  =  (p(1-u) + (u/3)(1-p) )(1+s) / (1 + (p(1-u) + (u/3)(1-p)) s ).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multiplying through by the denominator and collecting terms, after some struggle
we end up with the quadratic equation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;s(1-(4/3)u) p^2  +  p( (4u/3) - s + (5/3)us)  - (u/3)(1+s)  = 0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solving this for  &lt;em&gt;u = 0.0001&lt;/em&gt; and  &lt;em&gt;s = 0&lt;/em&gt;, we get  &lt;em&gt;p = 1/4&lt;/em&gt;, the obvious answer from
the symmetry of the mutational model.  When &lt;em&gt;s = 0.005&lt;/em&gt;, the equation becomes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;0.004999333 p^2 - 0.00486583333 p - 0.0000335  =  0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;whose positive root is the equilibrium frequency,  &lt;em&gt;p = 0.980133157&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simulations showing the effect of genetic drift&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the 100 sites are far enough apart to have noticeable levels of recombination
between them, and if their fitnesses combine multiplicatively, then each site can be regarded as evolving independently.  If the population size is not infinite but, say, 20,000 then we can use a single-locus genetic simulation program such as the teaching program PopG produced by my laboratory.  It is a Java application that can be downloaded from the site  &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution.gs.washington.edu/popg/popg.html&quot;&gt;https://evolution.gs.washington.edu/popg/popg.html&lt;/a&gt; at our webserver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program is for a diploid population, but by making the diploid population size be
10,000 and making the fitnesses of the genotypes be powers of &lt;em&gt;(1+s)&lt;/em&gt;, it will give the same results as a haploid population twice the size and with fitnesses &lt;em&gt;(1+s) ; 1&lt;/em&gt;.  So I ran the program with 5 independent populations and 10,000 diploid individuals per population, and fitnesses of &lt;em&gt;AA&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Aa&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;aa&lt;/em&gt; of  &lt;em&gt;1.010025 : 1.005 : 1&lt;/em&gt;, and this is equivalent to having &lt;em&gt;20,000&lt;/em&gt; haploid individuals with fitnesses &lt;em&gt;1.005 : 1&lt;/em&gt; for &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
We have mutation rate from &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; to non-&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; of 0.0001 and from non-&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; of one-third that value,
&lt;em&gt;0.000033333&lt;/em&gt;.  Note that in these cases allele A stands in for the selectively favored base, C.
The figure below shows two runs, each with 5 populations, which is equivalent to following 5 sites:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/champneys3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see the mutational equilibrium in the absence of natural selection on the left,
and the effect of selection with mutation in the figure on the right.  The smooth blue
curve shows what would have happened without genetic drift.  With a larger population
the individual sites would have remained closer to the smooth blue curves.
The 50 individual sites will vary in gene frequency, as these 5 do,  The result will
be distributions a bit wider than the original  binomial distributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Without genetic drift&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a very large population, where we can ignore genetic drift, each site has the
frequency of the C allele change.  At any generation, all 100 sites will have equal
gene frequencies.  Thus the distribution of the numbers of C’s in the haploid
genomes will follow the binomial distribution, with 100 trials, each with a probability
of C that is 1/4 (if there is no natural selection) or each with a probability of C
that is 0.980133157.  The state of the population will be a binomial distribution of
the number of C’s,  and this distribution will either approach an average of 25 C’s or an average of 98.0133157 C’s, depending on whether there is not or is natural selection.  Like an idealized gas, the individuals will vary randomly, but the distribution of their properties will be a distribution that changes deterministically, from generation to generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like gas in a container that is evenly distributed when there is no gravity, but collects at the bottom of the container if the whole thing is placed in a strong gravitational field, the population approaches an equilibrium which is different whether there is or is not natural selection.  And that simple fact disproves the statements Mark Champneys made in his video about movement towards equilibrium preventing natural selection from having any long-term effect.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">This post will supply some more technical details of my counterexample to Mark Champneys’ arguments that approach of physical and biological systems to equilibrium prevents natural selection from being effective. The counterexample is explained in my previous post. Below I provide the relevant equations and some simulation results showing what the effect of genetic drift will be. To avoid taking up too much space on the site’s front page, I will put most of that content “below the fold” …</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Less than optimistic view of Pfizer vaccine</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/Pfizer-vaccine.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Less than optimistic view of Pfizer vaccine" /><published>2020-11-11T11:11:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-11-11T11:11:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/Pfizer-vaccine</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/Pfizer-vaccine.html">&lt;p&gt;I heard an interview with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laurie_Garrett&quot;&gt;Laurie Garrett&lt;/a&gt; last night on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.democracynow.org/&quot;&gt;Democracy Now&lt;/a&gt;. Ms. Garrett, a distinguished science journalist and the author of the apparently prescient 1995 book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Coming-Plague-Emerging-Diseases-Balance/dp/0140250913&quot;&gt;The Coming Plague: Newly Emerging Diseases in a World out of Balance&lt;/a&gt;, is not quite as optimistic as the stock market regarding Pfizer’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pfizer.com/news/press-release/press-release-detail/pfizer-and-biontech-announce-vaccine-candidate-against&quot;&gt;recent announcement&lt;/a&gt; of a potentially successful coronavirus vaccine. So I looked up Ms. Garrett’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://foreignpolicy.com/2020/11/10/the-vaccine-news-is-good-heres-the-bad-news/&quot;&gt;recent article in &lt;em&gt;Foreign Policy&lt;/em&gt; magazine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms. Garrett seems generally pessimistic, because cases are surging, the United States has roughly one-fifth of known cases worldwide, and possibly one-third (!) of the population will probably refuse a vaccine, once one is available. Though optimistic that President-Elect Biden has appointed a Covid task force, she also notes that the present lame-duck administration will be in charge for more than two months and the presidential scientific advisor, Scott Atlas, advocates “what amounts to a do-nothing approach to Covid-19 control” (as we noted &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/are-creationists-dictating.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Ms. Garrett foresees a “mass exodus” of health officials from the government this fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about the vaccine? Ms. Garrett says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But let’s be clear about what this Pfizer study shows so far: For 90 percent of the volunteers who got the vaccine (as opposed to a placebo), SARS-CoV-2 infection did not occur for a study period of seven days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Seven days&lt;/em&gt;. Nothing more is known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If that protection turns out to be durable for, say, a full year, the Pfizer vaccine might be deemed a spectacular success. But nobody is going to wait a year to find out. The moment the FDA approves the product, Pfizer says in its press release, “we expect to produce globally up to 50 million vaccine doses in 2020 and up to 1.3 billion doses in 2021.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vaccine, however, is made of messenger RNA and as such “is unlike any vaccine ever used, for any disease.” It requires storage at a temperature of -103 °F (or -75 °C in God’s units) – well below typical refrigeration temperatures, and there is apparently a shortage of dry ice (-78 °C).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://cspinet.org/news/beyond-the-curve/causes-for-hope&quot;&gt;generally positive article&lt;/a&gt; praising President-Elect Biden’s Covid-19 task force and also his plan to ensure, among other things, that “public health decisions are made by public health professionals,” Peter Lurie of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cspinet.org/&quot;&gt;Center for Science in the Public Interest&lt;/a&gt; observes that the claimed 90 % is well beyond the minimum requirement of the FDA. He wants to know, however,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How many cases were in the treated and placebo groups? How serious were the cases? How many people have been followed in the trial and for how long? How big is the vaccine’s safety database and what does it show?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and, in particular, he notes that Pfizer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;pointedly declined support from Operation Warp Speed, [and] may not be subject to the same constraints upon pricing that those who signed up for the program might feel obligated to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I heard an interview with Laurie Garrett last night on Democracy Now. Ms. Garrett, a distinguished science journalist and the author of the apparently prescient 1995 book, The Coming Plague: Newly Emerging Diseases in a World out of Balance, is not quite as optimistic as the stock market regarding Pfizer’s recent announcement of a potentially successful coronavirus vaccine. So I looked up Ms. Garrett’s recent article in Foreign Policy magazine. Ms. Garrett seems generally pessimistic, because cases are surging, the United States has roughly one-fifth of known cases worldwide, and possibly one-third (!) of the population will probably refuse a vaccine, once one is available. Though optimistic that President-Elect Biden has appointed a Covid task force, she also notes that the present lame-duck administration will be in charge for more than two months and the presidential scientific advisor, Scott Atlas, advocates “what amounts to a do-nothing approach to Covid-19 control” (as we noted here). Ms. Garrett foresees a “mass exodus” of health officials from the government this fall. What about the vaccine? Ms. Garrett says,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pyronia tithonus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/Pyronia-tithonus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pyronia tithonus" /><published>2020-11-09T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-11-09T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/Pyronia-tithonus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/Pyronia-tithonus.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Marilyn Susek&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photogaphy Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Susek_Gatekeeper-Butterfly.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Butterfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ukbutterflies.co.uk/species.php?species=tithonus&quot;&gt;Pyronia tithonus&lt;/a&gt;, gatekeeper butterfly. The photographer writes, &quot;This photograph was taken at my garden in Rotherham, S. Yorkshire, UK. I noticed that the under wing of this gatekeeper is not the same as other photos of gatekeeper butterflies. It is sitting on an Echinacea.&quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Marilyn Susek. Photogaphy Contest, Honorable Mention. Pyronia tithonus, gatekeeper butterfly. The photographer writes, &quot;This photograph was taken at my garden in Rotherham, S. Yorkshire, UK. I noticed that the under wing of this gatekeeper is not the same as other photos of gatekeeper butterflies. It is sitting on an Echinacea.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Are creationists dictating Covid policy?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/are-creationists-dictating.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are creationists dictating Covid policy?" /><published>2020-11-04T10:24:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-11-04T10:24:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/are-creationists-dictating</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/11/are-creationists-dictating.html">&lt;p&gt;Are creationists dictating Covid policy? We just received an article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rightwingwatch.org/post/exclusive-far-right-creationists-are-setting-trumps-virus-response/&quot;&gt;Far-Right Creationists Are Setting Trump’s Virus Response&lt;/a&gt;, by Matthew Sheffield, which suggests precisely that. Mr. Sheffield’s article is posted in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rightwingwatch.org/&quot;&gt;Right Wing Watch&lt;/a&gt;, a “project” of the progressive organization People For the American Way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Sheffield begins by noting that Mark Meadows, Mr. Trump’s chief of staff, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/2020/10/25/politics/mark-meadows-controlling-coronavirus-pandemic-cnntv/index.html&quot;&gt;told Jake Tapper of CNN&lt;/a&gt;, “We are not going to control the pandemic … because it’s a contagious virus” (does he think we could control it better if it were a non-contagious virus?). Mr. Meadows may or may not be a creationist, but he is certainly a fellow traveler: At one time, he &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/news/news-desk/mark-meadows-and-the-undisclosed-dinosaur-property&quot;&gt;purchased a piece of property&lt;/a&gt; on which an &lt;em&gt;Allosaurus&lt;/em&gt; specimen had been discovered (supposedly by some home-schooled children). He then sold the property to Answers in Genesis, arguably in order to keep the fossils under the control of young-earth creationists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Vice-President, Mike Pence, heads the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_House_Coronavirus_Task_Force&quot;&gt;White House Coronavirus Task Force&lt;/a&gt;. On August 8, 2016, Mr. Sheffield reminds us, Mr. Pence said, in a somewhat rambling &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.c-span.org/video/?c4617037/user-clip-mike-pence-evolution&quot;&gt;speech on the floor of the House&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I believe that God created the known universe, the earth, and everything in it, including man. And I also believe that some day scientists will come to see that only the theory of intelligent design provides [an] even remotely rational explanation for the known universe, but until that day comes and [sic] I have no fear of science. I believe that the more we study the science, the more the truths of faith will become apparent. I just would humbly ask, as new theories of evolution find their ways into the newspapers and into the textbooks, let us demand that educators around America teach evolution not as fact but as theory. And an interesting theory to boot.
But let’s also bring into the minds of all of our children all of the theories about the unknowable that some bright day in the future, through science and perhaps through faith, we will find the truth from whence we come[.] [Lightly edited from a user clip, not recorded by C-Span.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be hard to argue that Mr. Pence was not a creationist, though conceivably not a young-earth creationist. In the statement above, contrary to Mr. Sheffield, he did not claim “that science is too changeable to be trusted, and that schools should also teach that humans were ‘created’ by God in their current form,” though he certainly mentioned all the old creationist shibboleths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://profiles.stanford.edu/scott-atlas&quot;&gt;Scott Atlas&lt;/a&gt;, the White House’s advisor on Covid-19, appears to have been a fairly prolific neuroradiologist before he joined the Hoover Institution, a right-wing think tank. Mr. Sheffield is impressed by the fact that Dr. Atlas is in turn impressed by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the COVID-19 mitigation proposals of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Gilder&quot;&gt;George Gilder&lt;/a&gt;, co-founder of the Discovery Institute, a Seattle-based think tank that specializes in promoting supply-side economics, climate science denial, and “intelligent design,” a spit-polished version of creationism which focuses more on attacking “Darwinism” than promoting biblical fundamentalism. According to Atlas, Gilder’s recommendation to “defer as much as possible to the principles of freedom” was “right on target.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Sheffield details how Mr. Gilder “has also applied his particular blend of junk economics and junk science” elsewhere, but I want to concentrate on Dr. Atlas. Dr. Atlas is not a virologist, an infectious-disease specialist, or an epidemiologist. Nevertheless, he has been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/09/02/us/politics/trump-scott-atlas-coronavirus.html&quot;&gt;advising the White House&lt;/a&gt; to let the virus run its course and rely on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-02948-4&quot;&gt;herd immunity&lt;/a&gt;, while protecting “vulnerable populations.” As far as I can determine, no true experts, not least Anthony Fauci, Deborah Birx, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/stanford-colleagues-warn-dr-scott-atlas-fosters-falsehoods/story&quot;&gt;78 of his former colleagues&lt;/a&gt; at Stanford Medical School agree with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he is he a creationist? Neither the &lt;em&gt;Times&lt;/em&gt; article nor his Wikipedia entry hints that he is a creationist of any kind, let alone a young-earth creationist, which I think is what we mean when we use the term unadorned. At most, Mr. Sheffield has established, in his case, a kind of guilt by association, and the association is mostly with Mr. Gilder and the Discovery Institute, not Mr. Meadows and Mr. Pence. Even so, it seems to me that a creationist is not necessarily wrong about everything else, nor is every so-called libertarian necessarily in favor of inaptly applying a political position, such as “the principles of freedom,” to a medical problem, such as Covid-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, Mr. Meadows and Mr. Pence may be creationists, depending on your definition. But if Mr. Sheffield is trying to connect Dr. Atlas to creationism, broadly construed, it seems to me that he is on the wrong track: the connection is both tenuous and irrelevant to Dr. Atlas’s position on Covid-19. I think that Dr. Atlas is wrong because he is wrong, and not because he has colleagues who are creationists. And I think I will leave it at that.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Are creationists dictating Covid policy? We just received an article, Far-Right Creationists Are Setting Trump’s Virus Response, by Matthew Sheffield, which suggests precisely that. Mr. Sheffield’s article is posted in Right Wing Watch, a “project” of the progressive organization People For the American Way. Mr. Sheffield begins by noting that Mark Meadows, Mr. Trump’s chief of staff, told Jake Tapper of CNN, “We are not going to control the pandemic … because it’s a contagious virus” (does he think we could control it better if it were a non-contagious virus?). Mr. Meadows may or may not be a creationist, but he is certainly a fellow traveler: At one time, he purchased a piece of property on which an Allosaurus specimen had been discovered (supposedly by some home-schooled children). He then sold the property to Answers in Genesis, arguably in order to keep the fossils under the control of young-earth creationists. The Vice-President, Mike Pence, heads the White House Coronavirus Task Force. On August 8, 2016, Mr. Sheffield reminds us, Mr. Pence said, in a somewhat rambling speech on the floor of the House,</summary></entry></feed>