<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-10-25T00:46:32-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Interaction between science and religion</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/interaction-between-science-religion.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interaction between science and religion" /><published>2021-10-24T16:15:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-10-24T16:15:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/interaction-between-science-religion</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/interaction-between-science-religion.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Sinai_Synapses_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cover&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;Detail from the cover of the &lt;i&gt;Electronic Journal for Research
in Science &amp;amp; Mathematics Education&lt;/i&gt;, Vol. 25, no. 3, Fall, 2021.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If I had not been familiar with &lt;a href=&quot;https://sinaiandsynapses.org/&quot;&gt;Sinai and Synapses&lt;/a&gt;,* I might have dismissed this &lt;a href=&quot;https://ejrsme.icrsme.com/issue/view/1643/222&quot;&gt;special issue&lt;/a&gt; of an obscure journal as yet another attempt to use science to rationalize religious beliefs. It is nothing of the kind. The entire issue consists of essays by Fellows who have been supported over the years by the Sinai and Synapses organization, about which I have said a few words below, in an Endnote. The Fellows are experts in their fields and mostly faculty at secular universities. All of them, I am certain, know what they are talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The front matter contains helpful synopses of all the papers. Sometimes, I admit, the synopsis was all I wanted. I learned, however, that a second-century CE rabbi, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judah_ha-Nasi&quot;&gt;Judah ha-Nasi&lt;/a&gt;, had noted that “pestilence” often transferred from pigs to humans, so Rabbi Judah recommended fasting whenever pigs suffered pestilence. I wondered why on earth such an influential rabbi would care one whit about pigs, so I naturally turned first to the article, “Zoonotic pandemics and Judaism’s early-modern turn to science,” by Jonathan Crane of Emory University. I was relieved to find that Rabbi Judah did not raise pigs, but he had nevertheless noted the similarity between pigs’ organs and humans’. More strikingly, he recognized that diseases could be contagious and could be transferred from pigs to humans. Rabbi Crane introduces us to later Talmudic scholars who, in addition to citing earlier scholars and relying on their expertise, adduced their own evidence and required confirmation. Specifically, medieval Jewish scholars such as Maimonides accepted the scientific knowledge of their day, and the early modern period found Jews embracing “exogenous knowledge as well as the emerging means to discover and develop it.” Rabbi Crane continues, “To be precise, scientific method and evidence matter when it comes to physical issues like medicine and public health.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do I find this article important? Because if the ultra-Orthodox &lt;i&gt;Charedim&lt;/i&gt;, in both the United States and Israel, can be convinced that the sages accepted and indeed embraced the medical knowledge of their times and even understood zoonotic diseases, then we may have hope of getting them vaccinated and otherwise contributing to the battle against Covid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The need to convince people about scientific realities is not limited to the ultra-Orthodox. I next read the article, “Communicating with skeptical audiences,” by Matthew Groves. Mr. Groves is a high school science teacher and a faith educator who lives in rural Appalachia. His article primarily concerns convincing evangelicals of the reality of climate change. The data, as he says, are clear, “so how can people remain unconvinced?” He learned (slowly, I infer) to employ “the communication skills [he] developed as a teacher and a pastor and have found significant successes with audiences of all ages, denominations, and acceptance levels of climate science.” In short, language matters or, perhaps more precisely, terminology matters, and he has learned to strictly avoid technical terms and scientific jargon. The bottom line, to me, was somewhere in the middle of the article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;To get around [the vocabulary problem], oftentimes I completely avoid using these terms [climate change vs. global warming]. I often finish a full hour Sunday School class without using either, but end up in a place that’s much closer to where I want our conversation to culminate. We spend time talking about humanity’s relationship with God, each other, and nature, and therein I’ve been able to spark much more interesting conversations, which are fundamentally tied to climate change, than if I had started with throwing in those words initially and triggered someone’s sensitivities. If we can arrive at the conversations we want without tripping people up, all the better! This isn’t being dishonest, it’s just smarter communication. In my own work, if I walk into a church and trigger every audience member by leading with the climate-related issues that are sticking points for this community, no one will listen to me. This is true regardless of how central those tangential topics really are to solving the climate crisis – like its intersections with race, economics, gender, etc. When I plan my lessons, I think to myself: “&lt;i&gt;Here are the 8 words that will stop half of the audience from listening to me. How can I cover these concepts without saying those words?&lt;/i&gt;” [Italics in original.]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Mr. Groves notes that people may be “alarmed, concerned, cautious, disengaged,
doubtful, [or] dismissive,” and his job is to move them up the ladder one rung at a time, not all in one jump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I read the articles by Rabbi Crane and Mr. Groves, I began to wonder, in order to get through to religious conservatives, do you have to be one? Perhaps not, but it helps an awful lot to know how to sing the appropriate song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last article I have read, so far, at least, is “Overlapping magisteria: Motivated cognition and the places where science and religion mingle,” by Jonathan Morgan of the University of Colorado, Colorado Springs. Prof. Morgan introduces Stephen Jay Gould’s concept of Non-Overlapping Magisteria, or Noma. Prof. Morgan argues that, if the magisteria do not overlap, then at a minimum they encroach on each other’s properties (a claim that I made myself &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B079332NDB&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). The article is fairly dense and concentrates on areas where science may encroach on religion, as opposed to religion encroaching on science, which he says has been amply covered elsewhere. I will discuss only a very small part of it. The author devotes several paragraphs to free will, mostly demonstrating that a belief in free will may have practical consequences. Studying the consequences of believing in free will is not the same as asking whether we have it or not, but the author criticizes the studies for using science as a sort of default condition. I cannot disagree, though, that those of us who claim that we do or do not actually have free will may be leaving the domain of science and entering religion or philosophy, even as we think we are doing science. Are we engaging in motivated reasoning? Probably. Is it a problem? I will let Dr. Morgan explain:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;…when
science communicators venture onto metaphysical grounds, they risk threatening broad swaths of the
public who hold different theological views. …[W]hen people were presented with a highly credentialed scientist who was advocating for a position with which they disagreed, they were significantly less likely to rank that scientist as an expert. In other words, they did not dismiss the argument, they dismissed the source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When science communicators are representing capital “S” Science while staking out
metaphysical disagreements with religious worldviews, they risk undermining a broader sense of trust
in the expertise of science. This is risky because there are plenty of other issues around which scientists
are making well-founded inferences that people may still dislike–evolution, climate change, and
vaccinations are among the most well studied. We make it more difficult for public buy-in on these
contentious issues when science communicators are also making threatening incursions onto terrain
where they cannot actually stand on solid empirical ground.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I think we can infer that the best people to talk to groups like vaccination, global warming, or evolution deniers are members of those groups or at least people who understand them implicitly. Then, to return to Mr. Groves’s categories, we work them up the ladder one rung at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will eventually read more of the articles and will comment only if I think they are important enough. In the meantime, any readers who want to read one or more of the contributions are invited to discuss them in the Comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*A word about &lt;a href=&quot;https://sinaiandsynapses.org/our-mission-and-methods/ &quot;&gt;Sinai and Synapses&lt;/a&gt;. I think it is fair to say that it is a religious organization that is interested in scientific inquiry. It has been “incubated” by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.clal.org/&quot;&gt;Clal – The National Jewish Center for Learning and Leadership&lt;/a&gt; and provides education and seminars. I have listened to a few interviews presided over by Geoffrey Mitelman and attended two or three sessions of &lt;a href=&quot;http://sinaiandsynapses.org/scientists-in-synagogues/&quot;&gt;Scientists in Synagogues&lt;/a&gt; and found them at least mildly interesting. Scientists in Synagogues is partly funded by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.templeton.org/&quot;&gt;Templeton&lt;/a&gt;. I do not think Sinai and Synapses has any hidden agenda such as trying to mount a scientific defense of religion. And they have an exceedingly clever logo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Sinai_And_Synapses_Logo_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Logo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may find more about them on their website, above.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Detail from the cover of the Electronic Journal for Research in Science &amp;amp; Mathematics Education, Vol. 25, no. 3, Fall, 2021. If I had not been familiar with Sinai and Synapses,* I might have dismissed this special issue of an obscure journal as yet another attempt to use science to rationalize religious beliefs. It is nothing of the kind. The entire issue consists of essays by Fellows who have been supported over the years by the Sinai and Synapses organization, about which I have said a few words below, in an Endnote. The Fellows are experts in their fields and mostly faculty at secular universities. All of them, I am certain, know what they are talking about. The front matter contains helpful synopses of all the papers. Sometimes, I admit, the synopsis was all I wanted. I learned, however, that a second-century CE rabbi, Judah ha-Nasi, had noted that “pestilence” often transferred from pigs to humans, so Rabbi Judah recommended fasting whenever pigs suffered pestilence. I wondered why on earth such an influential rabbi would care one whit about pigs, so I naturally turned first to the article, “Zoonotic pandemics and Judaism’s early-modern turn to science,” by Jonathan Crane of Emory University. I was relieved to find that Rabbi Judah did not raise pigs, but he had nevertheless noted the similarity between pigs’ organs and humans’. More strikingly, he recognized that diseases could be contagious and could be transferred from pigs to humans. Rabbi Crane introduces us to later Talmudic scholars who, in addition to citing earlier scholars and relying on their expertise, adduced their own evidence and required confirmation. Specifically, medieval Jewish scholars such as Maimonides accepted the scientific knowledge of their day, and the early modern period found Jews embracing “exogenous knowledge as well as the emerging means to discover and develop it.” Rabbi Crane continues, “To be precise, scientific method and evidence matter when it comes to physical issues like medicine and public health.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Advertising bot solves the problems of early hominid</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/Advertising-bot-solves-the-problems.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Advertising bot solves the problems of early hominid" /><published>2021-10-22T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-10-22T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/Advertising-bot-solves-the-problems</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/Advertising-bot-solves-the-problems.html">&lt;p&gt;I was looking at a post today at Uncommon Descent, wondering what strange interpretation they were going to make of this palaeoanthropology report from 
Smithsonian Magazine.
On my browser, in the middle of the post there was an ad.  I know that the UD site is not responsible for which ad gets put onto the page when I view it.  In this case a bot seems
to be responding to the word “footprint”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Screenshot20211022.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[UD post with ad]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The advertising bot appears to have decided that &lt;em&gt;Graecopithecus&lt;/em&gt; needed relief for sore feet.  It does not realize that 6 million years ago hominids did not have 
Amazon accounts.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">I was looking at a post today at Uncommon Descent, wondering what strange interpretation they were going to make of this palaeoanthropology report from Smithsonian Magazine. On my browser, in the middle of the post there was an ad. I know that the UD site is not responsible for which ad gets put onto the page when I view it. In this case a bot seems to be responding to the word “footprint”. The advertising bot appears to have decided that Graecopithecus needed relief for sore feet. It does not realize that 6 million years ago hominids did not have Amazon accounts.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">There are no risk-free choices: interview with Paul Offit</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/offit-no-risk-free-choices.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="There are no risk-free choices: interview with Paul Offit" /><published>2021-10-11T12:58:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-10-11T12:58:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/offit-no-risk-free-choices</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/offit-no-risk-free-choices.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Offit_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently caught an &lt;a href=&quot;https://think.kera.org/2021/09/29/we-cant-have-medical-progress-without-risk/&quot;&gt;interview with Paul Offit&lt;/a&gt;, chief of the Division of Infectious Diseases and the director of the Vaccine Education Center at the Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia and a professor of vaccinology and pediatrics at the University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine. The interview, originally broadcast on KERA in Dallas, was moderated by Krys Boyd. Part of the purpose of the interview, obviously, was to sell his latest book, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/You-Bet-Your-Life-Transfusions/dp/1541620399&quot;&gt; You Bet Your Life&lt;/a&gt;: From Blood Transfusions to Mass Vaccination, the Long and Risky History of Medical Innovation&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get immediately to the point, Dr. Offit argues convincingly that there are no risk-free choices. If you choose not to be vaccinated, then you are choosing between the risk of contracting a deadly widespread disease (and, I might add, of infecting others) and the risk of suffering from a rare side effect. Why do people choose the common disease over the rare side effect? One reason, Dr. Offit claims, is that a sin of commission may be seen as a greater risk than a sin of omission, even if statistically it is not. Thus, you may feel guilt over a sin of commission but not over a sin of omission. Further, and equally regrettably, people see themselves and their children as invulnerable – “I am strong and healthy; it won’t happen to me” – and Dr. Offit attributes this kind of denialism to the unfortunate fact that the emotional centers evolved early, before what I shall call the thinking centers. He did not, according to my notes, discuss the political implications of refusing vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How safe are the Covid vaccines?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vaccine trials typically involve 20-30,000 individuals. These individuals are observed carefully for 2 months, because historically the side effects occur within 2 months. The real question is the duration of the efficacy, and that requires a longer study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does he recommend the vaccine for everyone who is authorized to receive it? Yes, but only because we are in a pandemic, so the benefit of vaccination far outweighs the risk. If we were not in a pandemic, then he would not advise releasing the vaccine before it was fully approved by the FDA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are the risks of waiting for full approval? Consider the polio vaccine. The vaccine was shown to be safe, potent, and effective. Yet during the trial 16 people died and 36 were paralyzed, of whom 34 were in the placebo group. Another way of looking at it, approximately 60 people were sacrificed in order to ensure the safety of the vaccine. Absent an epidemic like the polio epidemic, many fewer people would have suffered an adverse impact. We could, I presume, anticipate similar statistics if we wait for a Covid vaccine to be fully approved. You may hear additional anecdotes, including a discussion of the safety of the blood supply, in the full interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Offit also noted, and I cannot disagree, that the FDA failed us when (the arm of the FDA commisioner having been sufficiently twisted) it bowed to political pressure and approved hydroxychloroquine and convalescent plasma, even though they have been shown to be useless. In those cases, politics trumped science. We need the FDA, and I can only hope that its reputation has not been too badly damaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an aside, Dr. Offit considers the development of the Covid vaccines to be the greatest single medical accomplishment he has seen during his career: two safe, effective vaccines were developed a mere 11 months after the virus had been sequenced. Regarding safety, he stresses again that there are no risk-free choices, and in a fit of levity points out that even driving to the office to get the vaccine is not wholly safe.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I recently caught an interview with Paul Offit, chief of the Division of Infectious Diseases and the director of the Vaccine Education Center at the Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia and a professor of vaccinology and pediatrics at the University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine. The interview, originally broadcast on KERA in Dallas, was moderated by Krys Boyd. Part of the purpose of the interview, obviously, was to sell his latest book, You Bet Your Life: From Blood Transfusions to Mass Vaccination, the Long and Risky History of Medical Innovation. To get immediately to the point, Dr. Offit argues convincingly that there are no risk-free choices. If you choose not to be vaccinated, then you are choosing between the risk of contracting a deadly widespread disease (and, I might add, of infecting others) and the risk of suffering from a rare side effect. Why do people choose the common disease over the rare side effect? One reason, Dr. Offit claims, is that a sin of commission may be seen as a greater risk than a sin of omission, even if statistically it is not. Thus, you may feel guilt over a sin of commission but not over a sin of omission. Further, and equally regrettably, people see themselves and their children as invulnerable – “I am strong and healthy; it won’t happen to me” – and Dr. Offit attributes this kind of denialism to the unfortunate fact that the emotional centers evolved early, before what I shall call the thinking centers. He did not, according to my notes, discuss the political implications of refusing vaccination. How safe are the Covid vaccines?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Iris pseudacorus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/Iris-pseudacorus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Iris pseudacorus" /><published>2021-10-11T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-10-11T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/Iris-pseudacorus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/Iris-pseudacorus.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/IMG_188_Iris_Crop_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Yellow flag iris&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iris_pseudacorus&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Iris pseudacorus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; yellow flag iris, Cottonwood Lake, Boulder, Colorado, June, 2015. This plant is an aquatic iris. I took this snapshot in 2015 (and an earlier one in 2009) and did not give it much thought. The plant was not very widespread when I snapped the pictures, but last week I came across a sign warning that the area had been sprayed to control yellow flag iris, cattail, and teasel. Sure enough, the Colorado Department of Agriculture &lt;a href=&quot;https://ag.colorado.gov/conservation/noxious-weeds/noxious-weed-species-id/yellow-flag-iris&quot;&gt;considers yellow flag iris a noxious weed&lt;/a&gt;, though it is only on a watchlist and not regulated. I have no idea why cattail is being sprayed, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2013/02/dipsacus-fullon.html&quot;&gt;teasel&lt;/a&gt; is very invasive.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Iris pseudacorus &amp;ndash; yellow flag iris, Cottonwood Lake, Boulder, Colorado, June, 2015. This plant is an aquatic iris. I took this snapshot in 2015 (and an earlier one in 2009) and did not give it much thought. The plant was not very widespread when I snapped the pictures, but last week I came across a sign warning that the area had been sprayed to control yellow flag iris, cattail, and teasel. Sure enough, the Colorado Department of Agriculture considers yellow flag iris a noxious weed, though it is only on a watchlist and not regulated. I have no idea why cattail is being sprayed, but teasel is very invasive.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creationists and advocates of social justice unite to take down T.H. Huxley, a leader in educational inclusion</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creationists and advocates of social justice unite to take down T.H. Huxley, a leader in educational inclusion" /><published>2021-10-07T10:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-10-07T10:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;WWU’s Huxley College of the Environment may be renamed after a bizarre report uncritically plagiarising far-right creationist &amp;amp; conspiracist materials gets Thomas Henry Huxley exactly backwards on racism.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;From 2004-2007 Dr. Nick Matzke worked at the National Center for Science Education, including the &lt;u&gt;[Kitzmiller v. Dover(http://www.talkorigins.org/faqs/dover/kitzmiller_v_dover.html)&lt;/u&gt; court case that determined that teaching “intelligent design” in public schools was unconstitutional. He obtained his Ph.D. in Integrative Biology from the University of California, Berkeley, in 2013. He is now a Senior Lecturer in the School of Biological Sciences at the University of Auckland. This essay represents his personal scholarly views, not those of current or former employers.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Western Washington University’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://huxley.wwu.edu/&quot;&gt;Huxley College of the Environment&lt;/a&gt; was founded in 1969, the year of the Santa Barbara oil spill, when the Cuyahoga River caught on fire, and when Earth Day was proposed. It is now one of the oldest and most prestigious environmental colleges in the country. It was named for Thomas Henry Huxley (1825-1895), famed not only as “Darwin’s Bulldog” after the 1859 publication of the &lt;i&gt;Origin of Species&lt;/i&gt;, but also for his remarkable career, rising from a family too poor to pay for school to becoming a leading anatomist (proposing the kinship of humans with the great apes, and birds with dinosaurs), geologist, ethnologist, and philosopher (coiner of the word “agnostic,” foe of Social Darwinism). Above all he was a leading figure in making science a profession (rather than a hobby for priests and the landed gentry), and making a liberal science education available to all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite accomplishing more than most could ever dream for science and public science education, Huxley is now in the dock at WWU. The main charge is racism, with many at WWU calling for Huxley College to be renamed. WWU’s president commissioned a &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/research-and-resources&quot;&gt;Legacy Review Task Force&lt;/a&gt; which issued a &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/files/2021-07/LRTF%20Report%20and%20Recommendations_June%202021.pdf&quot;&gt;Report&lt;/a&gt; making the rather elliptical claim that Huxley’s “ethnological accomplishments were grounded in white supremacist values that dehumanize and harm many members of the Western community.” More directly, the Report indicts him for advocating polygenism (the idea that different human races are separate species) and “many negative generalizations on the basis of race.” Another charge was that Huxley’s “Huxley’s claims about the inexhaustibility of fisheries has contributed to the decline of the salmon runs that are central to Coast Salish cultures.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are the accusations correct? A large debate could be had about the substantial difficulties of fully understanding the views of historical figures, let alone judging them. But clearly universities should not ignore major relevant evidence, nor rely on badly biased and one-sided presentations of the evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea that Huxley claimed salmon stocks were inexhaustible – which gets Huxley’s actual view exactly backwards – stems from a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icr.org/article/huxley-error-led-cod-calamity/&quot;&gt;2009 Institute for Creation Research article&lt;/a&gt;. The false idea that Huxley was a polygenist traces to an &lt;a href=&quot;https://larouchepub.com/eiw/public/2015/eirv42n24-20150612/18-29_4224.pdf&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; from the conspiracist &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/national/longterm/cult/larouche/main.htm&quot;&gt;Lyndon LaRouche organization&lt;/a&gt;; the citation is present in the Task Force’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/files/2021-04/TH%20Huxley%20Research%20Document_%20_Why%20is%20TH%20Huxley%20problematic__.pdf&quot;&gt;notes&lt;/a&gt;, but the LaRouche citation was dropped from the Report, while the outrageous claim was kept. The notes and Report also cite &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.troy.edu/index.php/JSAHMS/article/view/256&quot;&gt;anti-Huxley material&lt;/a&gt; from a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discovery.org/p/flannery/&quot;&gt;Fellow of the Discovery Institute&lt;/a&gt;, the infamous Seattle home of “intelligent design” creationism, also known for advocating &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/41487865&quot;&gt;climate denialism&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2020/05/stephen-meyer-teach-the-coronavirus-controversy/&quot;&gt;Covid denialism&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discovery.org/p/rufo/&quot;&gt;anti-critical race theory&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/news/annals-of-inquiry/how-a-conservative-activist-invented-the-conflict-over-critical-race-theory&quot;&gt;hysteria&lt;/a&gt;. The other major source the Task Force relies on is historian Nicholaas Rupke, himself a former young-earth creationist, and now a lonely apostle for Richard Owen (1804-1892), Huxley’s bitter scientific rival, who tried to keep a place for divine intervention in evolution. The Task Force essentially ignored the positive &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/research-and-resources&quot;&gt;evaluations&lt;/a&gt; of Huxley provided by three other historians that WWU commissioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about the racism accusation? While admitting Huxley’s anti-slavery position, the Task Force says that “opposition to slavery and belief in the basic humanity of people of African descent was not uncommon, exceptional, or, in the context of Huxley’s many negative generalizations on the basis of race, laudable.” The cited “negative generalizations” come entirely from Huxley’s 1865 essay “&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathcs.clarku.edu/huxley/CE3/B&amp;amp;W.html&quot;&gt;Emancipation—Black and White&lt;/a&gt;,” which has some cringeworthy passages, although made while endorsing “equal natural rights” of Black people and arguing to “give women the same civil and political rights as men,” some 53 years before British women attained the vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Huxley’s anti-racist activities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creationists have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icr.org/article/evolution-modern-racism/&quot;&gt;quote-mined this essay for decades&lt;/a&gt;, shorn of context, to portray Huxley as racist. The Legacy Review Task Force does the same. But relying on a single source for Huxley’s views is hazardous. Huxley’s style was “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Politics-literature-modern-Britain-George/dp/0874719879&quot;&gt;vigorously paradoxical&lt;/a&gt;” and he loved to use hyperbole and superficial self-contradiction to make his points, which were often about separating factual claims from value claims. In addition, his public statements on race were actively evolving in the 1860s. A proper historical review would at least consider the major episodes. Three important episodes give a much clearer view on where Huxley stood on race: his battle with the leading scientific racist of the day, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/j.ctt1pprf8.19&quot;&gt;James Hunt&lt;/a&gt;; his participation in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oxforddnb.com/view/10.1093/ref:odnb/9780198614128.001.0001/odnb-9780198614128-e-42293&quot;&gt;Jamaica Committee&lt;/a&gt;; and Huxley’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://mathcs.clarku.edu/huxley/guide18.html&quot;&gt;1867 Birmingham lectures&lt;/a&gt; on race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;T.H. Huxley vs. James Hunt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to historian &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Colour-Class-Victorians-Attitudes-Mid-Nineteenth-dp-0718511611/dp/0718511611/&quot;&gt;Douglas Lorimer&lt;/a&gt;, in 1863, James Hunt broke away from the older Ethnological Society of London to form the Anthropological Society, in part so that Hunt could promote “the racist speculations of Robert Knox.” Knox was “the outstanding British advocate of…revived polygenesis and of the place of race in determining man’s past […Knox’s 1850] &lt;i&gt;The Races of Man&lt;/i&gt;, [was] the fullest statement of his racist theory.” The Anthropological Society received donations from a Confederate agent who “apparently viewed the Society as a useful outlet for pro-Southern propaganda, for he included his donations to the anthropologists in his Secret Service Accounts for the Richmond Government.” Hunt “became the leading British exponent of scientific racism in the 1860s.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Huxley was a leading critic of Hunt. Lorimer says, “Huxley severely criticized Hunt for his paper, ‘On the Negro’s Place in Nature’”.  (Hunt’s title was a dig at Huxley’s 1863 book &lt;i&gt;Man’s Place in Nature&lt;/i&gt;, which apparently offended Hunt with its monogenism and lack of racist vitriol. Hunt’s paper was largely a collection of quotes of older authorities “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/j.ctt1pprf8.19&quot;&gt;carefully&lt;/a&gt; select[ing] authorities to represent the most negative scientific expressions of racial evaluation available.”) According to Lorimer, Huxley “ridiculed, in particular, the comparison between the Negro and the ape. In Huxley’s view, Hunt’s study of the Negro was ‘the most remarkable result of a modification of anatomical structure I had ever heard of. And the faculty for evolving nonsense displayed by its author…. I forbear to characterize, because the only appropriate phraseology would not be for me to utter or for you to hear.’” Huxley worried the Anthropological Society could do “a good deal of harm if it went wrong,” and advised colleagues to avoid “the quacks who are at the head of the ‘Anthropological Society’.” Huxley was “thoroughly disgusted” with the split-off Anthropological Society, and he resigned his membership, calling the Society a “nest of imposters.” Hunt, for his part, accused Huxley of “negromania” and printed in 1868 that Huxley was “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/4331106&quot;&gt;our most deadly, and sometimes even our most bitter, foe&lt;/a&gt;.” After Hunt died in 1869, Huxley and others in 1871 engineered a merger of the Ethnological and Anthropological societies into the Anthropological Institute of Great Britain and Ireland, fulfilling Hunt’s earlier worry that Huxley would “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/2799027&quot;&gt;crush us&lt;/a&gt;.” In 1873, some of Hunt’s followers again split off so they could “study the laws of race”, forming the London Anthropological Society, which only lasted for two years.  Those who condemn Huxley as a racist should consider what history of science and evolutionary biology would have looked like if someone of Huxley’s talents and prestige had promoted the views of James Hunt, instead of opposing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Huxley on the Jamaica Committee&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huxley not only opposed Britain’s leading scientific racist, he engaged in political activism. In late 1865, in the wake of the Civil War, the British colonial governor of Jamaica, Edward Eyre, killed hundreds of Black protestors who were marching for justice, land reform, and enfranchisement. A massive multiyear controversy broke out in Britain over the carnage. But the government refused to prosecute Eyre, so the Jamaica Committee, led by philosopher, parliamentarian, Radical, and feminist John Stuart Mill, decided to privately prosecute Eyre for murder. Mill was joined by Huxley, himself a Radical, along with most other prominent evolutionists, including Charles Darwin, Alfred Russel Wallace, Charles Lyell, and Herbert Spencer, and about 800 others. It would take rose-coloured glasses to pretend that the Jamaica Committee’s actions were popular. The Eyre Defense Fund was supported by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/43244890&quot;&gt;many leading lights&lt;/a&gt; of British society, including Thomas Carlyle (who was a major intellectual influence on Huxley), Alfred Lord Tennyson, Charles Dickens, John Tyndall, 40 generals, 26 admirals, 400 clergy and 6 bishops, 71 peers and 20 MPs, and 30,000 others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The link between being an evolutionist and having progressive views on race was noticed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/25611713&quot;&gt;racists of the day&lt;/a&gt;, for example when the &lt;i&gt;Pall Mall Gazette&lt;/i&gt; said, “It would be curious also to know how far Sir Charles Lyell’s and Mr. Huxley’s peculiar views on the development of species have influenced them in bestowing on the negro that sympathetic recognition which they are willing to extend even to the ape as ‘a man and a brother’.” James Hunt, for his part, wrote that “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B002RI9S8I/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;btkr=1&quot;&gt;ignorant, prejudiced Stupid&lt;/a&gt; and bigoted Humbugs of the Jamaica Committee who were hunting to the gallows…the brave Heroic Man who had saved Jamaica”, and Governor Eyre was explored as a replacement for Hunt when he resigned as leader of the Anthropological Society. In 1867, Hunt gave a particularly nasty address to his Society, targeting Huxley &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/j.ctt1pprf8.19&quot;&gt;yet again&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Even scientific men were sometimes afflicted with the disorder [of negromania]. He heard, only on passing through London, that a very eminent anatomist had had another attack, and actually gone and joined the Jamaica committee (laughter). This was Professor Huxley; and it was said that he intended to propose that they should prosecute M. du Chaillu for shooting gorillas (laughter).&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Huxley’s 1867 Birmingham lecture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is true that early in these debates, Huxley sometimes disclaimed support for egalitarianism, although as we have seen above, he had a longstanding &lt;a href=&quot;https://shareok.org/handle/11244/14408&quot;&gt;rhetorical strategy&lt;/a&gt; of separating claimed facts and values. However, his statements seem to shift later in the 1860s, probably because of a combination of his continuing anatomical and evolutionary work, his battles with James Hunt, and the changing political context after slavery was outlawed and radicals moved to obtaining the vote for disenfranchised groups like American Blacks or British working-class Whites (battles fought and won in 1867-1868). In October 1867, Huxley gave a lecture to the Birmingham and Midland Institute. This was a region populated by his people, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.british-history.ac.uk/vch/warks/vol7/pp223-245&quot;&gt;working class&lt;/a&gt; artisans who were not granted the vote until 1868 (for men) and 1918 (women); they saw &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/25611713&quot;&gt;common cause with nonwhites&lt;/a&gt; in the colonies who were also being oppressed by the British ruling classes. In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.gale.com/apps/doc/BA3201120082/BNCN?u=learn&amp;amp;sid=bookmark-BNCN&amp;amp;xid=8e5a703f&quot;&gt;lecture&lt;/a&gt;, Huxley strongly denied polygenism, noting that all races could interbreed successfully, saying, “no sound argument had been brought forward on the side of the distinct origination of the modifications of mankind.” He also denied the idea that any extant races were intermediate with apes, stating “there was no shade of justification for the assertion that any existing modification of mankind now known was to be considered as an intermediate form between man and the animals next below him in the scale of the fauna of the world.” He also states clearly that all existing races (Huxley prefers the word “&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathcs.clarku.edu/huxley/guide18.html&quot;&gt;modifications&lt;/a&gt;”) are closer to each other than any are to the recently-discovered Neanderthal, which itself is vastly more similar to modern humans than it is to apes. This explodes the WWU Legacy Review Task Force’s claim, stemming from Rupke, that there was a “Huxley’s Rule” stating that Africans were intermediate between whites and apes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this lecture, Huxley even challenged the very idea that “so-called higher” and “lower” races were meaningful categories. Undermining the idea that Africans are closer to apes, Huxley notes that “beyond everything”, human hair varies across the races, “[b]ut the apes were all straight-haired, like the respectable assemblage in that lecture theatre, and in that respect the white people were a great deal more like the lower animals than the negro was.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huxley also pillories Hunt’s absurd claim that Black people had projecting heels, a common enough topic for Huxley that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Wentworth_Higginson&quot;&gt;Thomas Wentworth Higginson&lt;/a&gt;, an American militant abolitionist who helped arm John Brown’s slave rebellion and who led the Union’s first Black regiment through 2 years of combat duty, specifically &lt;a href=&quot;https://nla.gov.au/nla.obj-895212518/view&quot;&gt;wrote Huxley&lt;/a&gt; in June 1867 to confirm that his soldiers wore the same boots as White soldiers. And anyway, says Huxley in his lecture, if the absurd claim were true, it would be more evidence that Whites were more apelike, as apes have short heels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turning to cultural attributes, Huxley points out how the technology and organization of societies is historically and culturally contingent, rather than some innate feature of races, noting that the Romans thought Britons and Germans were barbarians, but now these were technological leaders, and the Roman Empire was gone. He concludes by denying that “any of those differences observed among mankind were such as to justify the higher races in dealing with the lower differently from the manner in which the higher races thought themselves justified in dealing with each other.” By an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/3014371&quot;&gt;1870 lecture&lt;/a&gt; on geographic distribution of humans, Huxley abandons the usage of the terms “race,” “higher”, and “lower” (despite these terms still being utterly conventional at the time); by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/018467a0&quot;&gt;1878&lt;/a&gt; he emphasizes “social conditions which exercise an enormous influence” on the economic and political status of races. (Huxley is here commenting on Irish – Celts – towards whom there was a &lt;a href=&quot;https://victorianweb.org/history/race/Racism.html&quot;&gt;tremendous amount of racism in the Victorian era&lt;/a&gt;; Huxley opposed this consistently, again fighting James Hunt, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/3826928&quot;&gt;writing&lt;/a&gt; “the arguments about the differences between Anglo-Saxons and Celts are a mere sham and delusion.”)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Radicals and Race in 1865&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have seen the dangers in considering Huxley’s 1865 essay in isolation from Huxley’s other anti-racist activities. Yet another danger is ignoring historical context. To search for context, we have to consider the political issues of the day; because Huxley was staunchly antislavery and a political Radical, we should look to other antislavery Radicals. The U.S. Civil War was ending in 1865, and the Radicals were striving to solidify the Union’s victory with lawmaking achievements. Huxley’s 1865 statements should be compared to the 1865 comments of Thaddeus Stevens, the U.S. Congressman and Radical Republican. As surprising as it might be to modern readers, in the 1860s the Republicans were the “left-wing” party, insofar as modern categories are meaningful in the 1800s, and the Radical Republicans were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g7spJRHAnUU&amp;amp;t=2234s&quot;&gt;the most extreme&lt;/a&gt;, championing not just the abolition of slavery (13th Amendment) but, after Lincoln’s assassination, giving Black people equal rights and the vote (the 14th and 15th Amendments), impeaching Democrat Andrew Johnson (who opposed all of these measures), and leading the Radical Reconstruction, which included military occupation of the South, suppression of the KKK, the election of hundreds of Black state legislators, and redistribution of land confiscated from secessionists to Black people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thaddeus Stevens was one of the leaders of the Radical Republicans. For his efforts, he was hated by racist Southerners for generations, for example when pilloried as Austin Stoneman in the infamous 1915 movie &lt;i&gt;The Birth of a Nation&lt;/i&gt;, which inspired the second rise of the KKK. Given all of this, we might expect Stevens, of anyone, to have views acceptable to modern ears. But what did Stevens actually say in 1865?  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Final-Freedom-Abolition-Thirteenth-Historical-ebook-dp-B00174LWPA/dp/B00174LWPA/&quot;&gt;He said&lt;/a&gt;, “I never held to that doctrine of negro equality…not equality in all things – simply before the laws, nothing else.” Another historian &lt;a href=&quot;https://housedivided.dickinson.edu/sites/blogdivided/2013/02/22/how-the-lincoln-movie-reconstructed-thaddeus-stevens/&quot;&gt;calls this&lt;/a&gt; “part of a concerted radical strategy during this period to avoid inflammatory questions about racial equality” in order to accomplish the most important goal, passage of amendments and legislation.  (The episode was dramatized, perhaps &lt;a href=&quot;https://housedivided.dickinson.edu/sites/blogdivided/2013/02/22/how-the-lincoln-movie-reconstructed-thaddeus-stevens/&quot;&gt;overly so&lt;/a&gt;, in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/results?search_query=tommy+lee+jones+lincoln&quot;&gt;a famous Tommy Lee Jones scene&lt;/a&gt; in the 2012 Spielberg movie &lt;i&gt;Lincoln&lt;/i&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judging historical figures is therefore not so simple as mining historical material for sentence fragments that sound bad to modern ears, and evaluating them as if they were 2020s posts on Twitter. Returning to Huxley, several points deserve consideration. Throughout his career Huxley made a point to distinguish claims about facts from claims about values, often using his “vigorously paradoxical” style to dramatize the distinction. For example, in &lt;a href=&quot;https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=uc1.b000787429&amp;amp;view=1up&amp;amp;format=plaintext&amp;amp;seq=272&quot;&gt;1854&lt;/a&gt;, Huxley wrote something more “offensive” (out of context) than anything he said in 1865: “Grant that the negro is a distinct species, or even a metamorphosed orang…”  However, Huxley never actually believed either of these positions; his point was that it didn’t matter for the ethical argument. He went on to say “the most complete demonstration of the specific diversity of the types of mankind [i.e. polygenism, the racist position that different human races are different species] will nowise constrain science to spread her ægis over their [slaveholders’] atrocities,” and “Ethnology had better perish as a science than be swamped” by Southern sympathizers arguing for polygenism to support slavery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirty-nine years later, in his famous 1893 essay &lt;a href=&quot;https://mathcs.clarku.edu/huxley/CE9/E-E.html&quot;&gt;Evolution and Ethics&lt;/a&gt;, Huxley, as strong an evolutionist as any, affirmed that humans were subject to Darwin’s process of natural selection. But he departed radically from the “social Darwinism” and eugenics which were increasingly popular in the late 1800s, writing, “what we call goodness or virtue – involves a course of conduct which, in all respects, is &lt;i&gt;opposed&lt;/i&gt; to that which leads to success in the cosmic struggle for existence… the ethical progress of society depends, not on imitating the cosmic process, still less in running away from it, but in &lt;i&gt;combating&lt;/i&gt; it” (emphasis added). Again and again, Huxley makes his ethical points by saying that, even if his opponents’ claimed facts are admitted, they do not support the value judgments made. Modern readers are, of course, free to disagree with Huxley’s rhetorical strategy, but they should at least acknowledge that it exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other errors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the above information is easily accessible with a little scholarly due diligence, and these episodes are referenced in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mathcs.clarku.edu/huxley/guide18.html&quot;&gt;online Huxley File&lt;/a&gt;; yet none of it appears in the Task Force Report, despite nearly a year of controversy at WWU. While this shockingly poor form for an official report that is supposed to provide authoritative guidance for university decision making, it is perhaps not surprising, considering that the makeup of the Task Force failed to include any evolutionary biologists or historians of evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other Task Force errors flow from the lack of scientific input. Misunderstandings of the relevant science and history are rife. For example, the Task Force Report attempted to make the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2012/02/continuous-geog.html&quot;&gt;accurate statement&lt;/a&gt; that in humans, within-group genetic variance exceeds between-group variance, but the Report text actually states the opposite. The Report says that “Genetic scientists have since disproved the notions of a ‘Black gene’ or ‘White gene’ and have disproven the idea that intragroup difference exceeds intergroup difference—establishing that race is a social, not biological, system.” But the word “gene” was not coined until the early 1900s, and Huxley died in 1895. “Gene” was not part of the conceptual framework of Huxley or any other evolutionists in the 1800s, who had to work with vaguer notions of heredity. The concept of a “Black gene” and “White gene” therefore could not have even been raised in the 1800s, and in fact was probably never a view held by any scientist. In fact, part of the difficulty in accurately understanding Victorian-era comments on “race” is that cultural and biological inheritance &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-1-349-24950-3_7&quot;&gt;were very blurred in this era&lt;/a&gt;. After all, Darwin and others believed in the inheritance of acquired characteristics through use and disuse, and this opens up the possibility that cultural change could rapidly cause biological change. Taking the primarily 20th-century concept of “race” as genetic categorization, and uncritically reading it back into Victorian discussions of race, commits the historian’s fallacy of anachronism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the Task Force sidetracks into an irrelevant attack on Julian Huxley, grandson of T.H. Huxley (another grandson was Aldous Huxley, author of &lt;i&gt;Brave New World&lt;/i&gt;; their brother, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Huxley&quot;&gt;Sir Andrew Huxley&lt;/a&gt;, merely &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/medicine/1963/huxley/facts/&quot;&gt;won a Nobel Prize&lt;/a&gt;, and is the third most famous Huxley grandson). Julian was invited to speak at Huxley College (he declined due to advanced age). The Report notes Julian’s eugenics advocacy, but makes the absurd claim that this “suggests that the racist pseudoscience of ‘better breeding’ was seen as a legitimate aspect of [T.H.] Huxley’s legacy even after eugenics had been widely critiqued as unethical and potentially genocidal.”  This is made up out of whole cloth. Julian Huxley was a famous zoologist and popular science writer in his own right, one of the leaders of the “Modern Synthesis” in twentieth-century evolutionary biology. Julian’s legacy cannot be described as a racist eugenicist. He was actually known as a “reform” eugenicist, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/144521a0&quot;&gt;group known&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.nz/books/edition/Beyond_the_Laboratory/IzGtDwAAQBAJ?hl=en&amp;amp;gbpv=1&amp;amp;dq=%22A+Call+to+Scientists%22+Huxley+Haldane&amp;amp;pg=PA175&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&quot;&gt;strongly&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.nz/books?id=-c8aSO-gnwMC&amp;amp;q=exploitation+race+concept#v=snippet&amp;amp;q=exploitation%20race%20concept&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;and&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/jhered/article-abstract/30/9/371/791396&quot;&gt;publicly&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.nz/books/edition/Beyond_the_Laboratory/IzGtDwAAQBAJ?hl=en&amp;amp;gbpv=1&amp;amp;dq=%22A+Call+to+Scientists%22+Huxley+Haldane&amp;amp;pg=PA175&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&quot;&gt;opposing&lt;/a&gt; the Nazis &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/138988a0&quot;&gt;and their&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/134229a0&quot;&gt;racist&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/137635a0&quot;&gt;eugenics&lt;/a&gt; in the 1930s, well before World War 2. As a result this group did not associate their relatively restrained and anti-racist eugenic views with the Nazis after the war. On anti-racism, Julian Huxley was actually probably the most important anti-racist biologist of the mid-20th century. He coauthored the 1935 &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.nz/books/edition/We_Europeans/_4YYAQAAMAAJ&quot;&gt;We Europeans: A Survey of ‘Racial’ Problems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.nz/books?id=-c8aSO-gnwMC&amp;amp;vq=letter&amp;amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s&quot;&gt;historians&lt;/a&gt; “a popular and influential anti-racist statement,” “[a]mong the most important of this genre which helped undermine the scientific basis for racism.” Julian was also the founding director of UNESCO in 1946, and helped draft UNESCO’s famous anti-racism declarations in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.unesco.org/courier/july-august-1950&quot;&gt;1950&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000073351_eng&quot;&gt;1952&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://search.credoreference.com/content/entry/fofe/huxley_julian_s/0?institutionId=181&quot;&gt;Encyclopedia of Evolution&lt;/a&gt; says, “largely due to his efforts, the UNESCO statement on race reported that race was a cultural, not a scientific, concept, and that any attempts to find scientific evidence of the superiority of one race over another were invalid.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;T.H. Huxley and Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion in Science&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all the Task Force Report’s scholarly flaws, the most concerning is its claim that “Huxley contributed to upholding values that have made education less inclusive.” The reality is that Huxley promoted &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/621619&quot;&gt;scientific education&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.nz/books?id=hggzbROi9NcC&amp;amp;q=committee+of+ladies#v=snippet&amp;amp;q=committee%20of%20ladies&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;women&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://embryo.asu.edu/pages/thomas-henry-huxley-1825-1895&quot;&gt;working class&lt;/a&gt;. For example, in 1868 Huxley “&lt;a href=&quot;https://embryo.asu.edu/pages/thomas-henry-huxley-1825-1895&quot;&gt;inaugurated and became head&lt;/a&gt; of the South London Working Men’s College, which, along with its educational opportunities for working class men, held evening classes for women and kindergarten classes for the children of working class families.” His famous lectures ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/43410826&quot;&gt;On a piece of chalk&lt;/a&gt;’ and ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.nz/books?id=jJTzDwAAQBAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA16&amp;amp;lpg=PA16&amp;amp;dq=T+H+Huxley,+%22learned+from+a+piece+of+coal%22&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=Zy6l24aXSa&amp;amp;sig=ACfU3U0Q0ZK_v4F6LoClpkGKS0KAXhhN-w&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwj9kN3ksNjyAhXdzjgGHeZvBXYQ6AF6BAgCEAM#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=T%20H%20Huxley%2C%20%22learned%20from%20a%20piece%20of%20coal%22&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;What is to be learned from a piece of coal&lt;/a&gt;’ were designed in this period, serving as the basis for his 1877 book &lt;i&gt;Physiography&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/621619&quot;&gt;which&lt;/a&gt; “defined for a generation the way in which the earth’s physical features were studied in Britain; it defined also the nature of school education”, and “was the first thoroughly scientific presentation of elementary ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.nz/books?id=hggzbROi9NcC&amp;amp;dq=was+the+first+thoroughly+scientific+presentation+of+elementary+%27environmental+studies&amp;amp;q=environmental+studies#v=snippet&amp;amp;q=environmental%20studies&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;environmental studies&lt;/a&gt;‘”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1869, at the request of a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.nz/books?id=hggzbROi9NcC&amp;amp;q=committee+of+ladies#v=snippet&amp;amp;q=committee%20of%20ladies&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;committee of ladies&lt;/a&gt; ” he gave a course of 12 science lectures, with notes, to an audience of 300 women. He supported “Emily Davies in the establishment of Girton College for female university education, as he later did Maria Grey with her Girls’ Public Day School Company and her Bishopsgate Training College for Women,” opened his classes to women, hired a woman as a Physiology demonstrator, and backed the founding of London School of Medicine for Women. He said, “I am at a loss to understand on what grounds of justice or public policy a career which is open to the weakest and most foolish of the male sex should be forcibly closed to women of vigour and capacity”. Huxley was instrumental in addressing “the greatest need of all, a system of schooling for the children of the ordinary people, [which] had always been held up by the conflicting interests of the competing religious sects.” He gave another course of a dozen lectures to schoolchildren to illustrate his approach basing science education on local observation and applied common sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1869 Huxley &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.nz/books?id=hggzbROi9NcC&amp;amp;q=committee+of+ladies#v=snippet&amp;amp;q=committee%20of%20ladies&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;ran for and won&lt;/a&gt; a position on the newly-established London School Board, and chaired the “all-important Scheme of Education Committee,” which established “the pattern of infant, junior and senior schools which spread right across the land and lasted until the Act of 1944”, mandated standards for hygiene, restricted corporal punishment, and protected teachers’ authority from political interference. The inclusion of practical lab exercises in biology and earth science classes can be traced to his influence. This work included 170 committee meetings and extensive travel; in 1871 Huxley suffered “total collapse” and required extensive convalescence. Late in life he wrote, “I am glad to think that, after all these years, I can look back upon that period of my life as perhaps the part of it least wasted.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is WWU shooting its anti-racism goals in the foot?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bellinghamherald.com/news/local/news-columns-blogs/article22220466.html&quot;&gt;2014 retrospective&lt;/a&gt; on the key founder of Huxley College of the Environment, Jerry Flora, the &lt;i&gt;Bellingham Herald&lt;/i&gt; explored origins of the name. Flora chose the name “Huxley” in the 1960s because he feared that the new environmental college “might stress ‘green’ consciousness over tested truth. ‘I wanted science, man,’ he recalled. ‘I wanted hard science.’” T.H. Huxley, as we have seen, was a leader in science and science education, spanning biological and earth sciences, a leader in distinguishing claimed facts and values, an important ethical thinker, a leader in promoting inclusion in science, and a leading opponent of the most prominent scientific racist of his day, the latter because Huxley’s science indicated the unity of the human species, and advocated for the common ancestry of humans with apes without claiming different races were transitional forms. Confronted with Huxley’s actual record, we should all ask ourselves: What have I done lately?  Can any reader say they have accomplished as much as T.H. Huxley? The names put on buildings and institutions are often arbitrary – the product of donor money or historical accidents. There ought to be a little space in the world for naming institutions after inspirational figures who changed the world for the better, even though such figures, as humans, are never perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Legacy Review Task Force, unfortunately, has so far failed to do its due diligence on Huxley’s legacy. The many flaws in the Task Force Report on Huxley show that moral outrage against racism and social injustice, while laudable, does not by itself supply reliable facts upon which to base decisions. The facts need to be determined by careful research, particularly in the case of historical figures with a record of activities and accomplishments so massive that even assembling a decent survey of them is challenging. Racial equality and equity, social justice, and diversity and inclusion are all crucial goals for any modern university, but by relying on badly flawed depictions of Huxley, WWU may end up shooting itself in the foot with respect to these goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does it serve justice to treat T.H. Huxley as if he were James Hunt or Governor Eyre, when he actually was their vehement opponent?  Removing Huxley’s name from the College would in fact be removing the name of a pioneer for educational inclusion, a key figure in scientifically establishing that all humans are one species, and undermining the concept of biological “race.” Doing so while relying on propaganda deriving from fundamentalist creationists and other right-wing provocateurs would be falling into the exact trap arranged by these provocateurs: namely, to drive a wedge between science and the causes of social and racial justice. Helping to drive this wedge deeper cannot help increase diversity, equity, and inclusion in science. Imagine creationists, for the next several decades, going to legislatures and state school boards with a line like: “Evolution is a racist theory. After all, Western Washington University acknowledged this when they removed the name ‘Huxley’ from their College of the Environment.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, there are wider implications for the credibility of academic institutions if renamings are premised on inaccurate, poorly-researched historical claims. First, far more important than the name of any university entity is the basic purpose of universities, namely, to promote truth and good scholarship. Renaming a building by accepting warmed-over creationist propaganda would only spread the propaganda further. Creationists would surely use a victory at the university level to push their evolution-is-racist material, which is &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/charles-darwin/racism/&quot;&gt;voluminous&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/?s=racism+Huxley&quot;&gt;and&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icr.org/home/submitsearch?f_search_type=icr&amp;amp;f_keyword_all=racism&amp;amp;module=home&amp;amp;action=submitsearch&amp;amp;search=AdvancedSearch&amp;amp;section=0&amp;amp;f_constraint=both&amp;amp;f_context_all=any&amp;amp;f_context_exact=any&amp;amp;f_context_any=any&amp;amp;f_context_without=any&amp;amp;op=&quot;&gt;pre-prepared&lt;/a&gt;, into the public schools. Second, establishing such a precedent could very easily backfire against social justice goals. Consider that the initial demand to the administration &lt;a href=&quot;https://as.wwu.edu/gov/board/&quot;&gt;submitted&lt;/a&gt; by WWU’s Black Student Organizations was to “Rename Huxley College, and rename campus buildings to honor important figures in Black History.” Surely it is worthwhile and important to memorialize important figures in Black History by naming buildings after them. But renaming Huxley College based on sloppy history derived from tendentiously selective portrayals of Huxley, assembled by his worst enemies, would create a precedent that could easily be turned against any other historical figure. All people are complex, and no historical figure who is memorialized for significant achievements that improved society will be unassailable if absolute perfection according to modern lights is the standard. This is particularly so if depictions by those motivated to portray them in an unfavorable light are adopted uncritically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As most references are online and hyperlinked, I list only a few particularly useful offline references.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorimer, Douglas A. (1978). &lt;i&gt;Colour, Class and the Victorians: English attitudes to the Negro in the mid-nineteenth century&lt;/i&gt;. New York: Holmes &amp;amp; Meier Publishers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watson, George (1977). “Race and the Socialists.” Chapter 8 of &lt;i&gt;Politics and Literature in Modern Britain&lt;/i&gt;. London: The Macmillan Press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;This article was originally posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://osf.io/4smwv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and is reproduced at the request of the author. Matt Young will be the principal moderator. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Matzke</name></author><summary type="html">WWU’s Huxley College of the Environment may be renamed after a bizarre report uncritically plagiarising far-right creationist &amp;amp; conspiracist materials gets Thomas Henry Huxley exactly backwards on racism. From 2004-2007 Dr. Nick Matzke worked at the National Center for Science Education, including the [Kitzmiller v. Dover(http://www.talkorigins.org/faqs/dover/kitzmiller_v_dover.html) court case that determined that teaching “intelligent design” in public schools was unconstitutional. He obtained his Ph.D. in Integrative Biology from the University of California, Berkeley, in 2013. He is now a Senior Lecturer in the School of Biological Sciences at the University of Auckland. This essay represents his personal scholarly views, not those of current or former employers. Western Washington University’s Huxley College of the Environment was founded in 1969, the year of the Santa Barbara oil spill, when the Cuyahoga River caught on fire, and when Earth Day was proposed. It is now one of the oldest and most prestigious environmental colleges in the country. It was named for Thomas Henry Huxley (1825-1895), famed not only as “Darwin’s Bulldog” after the 1859 publication of the Origin of Species, but also for his remarkable career, rising from a family too poor to pay for school to becoming a leading anatomist (proposing the kinship of humans with the great apes, and birds with dinosaurs), geologist, ethnologist, and philosopher (coiner of the word “agnostic,” foe of Social Darwinism). Above all he was a leading figure in making science a profession (rather than a hobby for priests and the landed gentry), and making a liberal science education available to all. Despite accomplishing more than most could ever dream for science and public science education, Huxley is now in the dock at WWU. The main charge is racism, with many at WWU calling for Huxley College to be renamed. WWU’s president commissioned a Legacy Review Task Force which issued a Report making the rather elliptical claim that Huxley’s “ethnological accomplishments were grounded in white supremacist values that dehumanize and harm many members of the Western community.” More directly, the Report indicts him for advocating polygenism (the idea that different human races are separate species) and “many negative generalizations on the basis of race.” Another charge was that Huxley’s “Huxley’s claims about the inexhaustibility of fisheries has contributed to the decline of the salmon runs that are central to Coast Salish cultures.” Are the accusations correct? A large debate could be had about the substantial difficulties of fully understanding the views of historical figures, let alone judging them. But clearly universities should not ignore major relevant evidence, nor rely on badly biased and one-sided presentations of the evidence.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tall el-Hammam: an airburst of gullibility</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/tall-el-hammam-gullibility.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tall el-Hammam: an airburst of gullibility" /><published>2021-10-05T14:49:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-10-05T14:49:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/tall-el-hammam-gullibility</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/tall-el-hammam-gullibility.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Braterman_figure-3-Detail-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Detail of photograph&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;Enlargement of detail &lt;a href=&quot;https://scienceintegritydigest.com/2021/10/01/blast-in-the-past-image-concerns-in-paper-about-comet-that-might-have-destroyed-tall-el-hammam/&quot;&gt;from Elisabeth Bik’s blog&lt;/a&gt;, one of several illustrations showing apparently duplicated areas within the key figures of the paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-021-97778-3&quot;&gt;A Tunguska sized airburst destroyed Tall el-Hammam …&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Note added 14 October 2021, 6:40 p.m. MDT: Professor Braterman has published an expanded version of this article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://paulbraterman.wordpress.com/2021/10/14/tall-el-hammam-an-airburst-of-gullibility-it-gets-worse/&quot;&gt;Tall el-Hammam; an airburst of gullibility; it gets worse&lt;/a&gt;, in the blog Primate’s Progress.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shared the excitement when I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-021-97778-3&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; that “in ~ 1650 BCE (~ 3600 years ago), a cosmic airburst destroyed Tall el-Hammam, a Middle-Bronze-Age city in the southern Jordan Valley northeast of the Dead Sea,” and that this event could have given rise to the biblical account of the destruction of Sodom and Gomorrah. Somewhat to my surprise, Ken Ham of &lt;i&gt;Answers in Genesis&lt;/i&gt; did not. I now think that Ken’s conclusion [1] was right and I was wrong.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I suspect many of the journalists and interested readers who swooped on this story, I failed at first to notice that the paper was not, despite the link, an article in &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt; but in &lt;i&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/i&gt;. This is one of the stable of second-line journals closely linked to &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt; being published by Springer, now controlled by the publishing giant Hotlzbrinck, and profiting from &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt;’s reputation for excellence. I was only vaguely aware of the authors’ long history of invoking airbursts, took the many kinds of evidence listed at face value, and did not even blink at the claim that “[a]n airburst-related influx of salt (~ 4 wt.%) produced hypersalinity,” a process for which I can envisage no credible mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors have since described this work to a much larger audience in &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/a-giant-space-rock-demolished-an-ancient-middle-eastern-city-and-everyone-in-it-possibly-inspiring-the-biblical-story-of-sodom-167678&quot;&gt;The Conversation&lt;/a&gt;, where they &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-020-60867-w&quot;&gt;repeat their claim&lt;/a&gt;, also published in &lt;i&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/i&gt;, of a similar catastrophe at Abu Hureyra in what is now Syria, around 10,800 BCE, assert that “it almost certainly won’t be the last time a human city meets this fate,” claim that such events “pose a severe modern-day hazard,” and advise that “unless orbiting or ground-based telescopes detect these rogue objects, the world may have no warning, just like the people of Tall el-Hammam.” The Abu Hureya paper also repeats &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Younger_Dryas_impact_hypothesis&quot;&gt;a litany of earlier claims&lt;/a&gt; that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Younger_Dryas&quot;&gt;Younger Dryas&lt;/a&gt;, a period of severe cold in the northern hemisphere from around 12,900 to 11,700  years Before Present [Present is fixed at 1950 CE], was caused by a  series of impacts with cometary debris, spread over at least four continents. These claims have been severely disputed; see papers listed below.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prominent among the critics is my friend &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Boslough&quot;&gt;Mark Boslough&lt;/a&gt;, an expert on such cataclysmic events who even has an asteroid named after him. He tells me that he is tired of repeated rebuttal of what he considers to be obviously false claims, and of seeing his own theoretical analysis of the effect of airbursts invoked as an explanation of claims completely inconsistent with such a process, or perhaps any credible process. For this reason, rather than publishing yet another counterblast that will be ignored, he has taken to describing the controversy, extending over many years, on Twitter (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MarkBoslough/status/1440097126856282113&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MarkBoslough/status/1440378973309968391&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and subsequent threads).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are numerous reasons for concern about the Tall el-Hammam paper in particular.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper tells us, “The project is under the aegis of the School of Archaeology, Veritas International University, Santa Ana, CA, and the College of Archaeology, Trinity Southwest University, Albuquerque, NM, under the auspices of the Department of Antiquities of the Hashemite Kingdom of Jordan.” &lt;a href=&quot;https://viu.ves.edu/doctrinal-statement/&quot;&gt;Veritas International University believes in&lt;/a&gt; “the full historicity and comprehensibility of the biblical record.” It is accredited by the Transnational Association of Christian Colleges and Schools (TRACS), which I have written about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.3quarksdaily.com/3quarksdaily/2013/11/credit-where-none-is-due-creationist-colleges-and-courses-i-am-browsing-school-science-textbooks-pub.html&quot;&gt;elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;. Trinity Southwest University, which now operates from an office in a strip mall in Albuquerque, was formerly in Tulsa, Oklahoma, under the name Southwest Biblical Seminary, and rejects any government accreditation whatsoever as intrusive violation of the separation of Church and State. While the traditional site of Sodom is in Israel (and within the pre-1967 boundaries), Tall el-Hammam is in Jordan.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The corresponding author is Allen West, who has been publishing prolifically in this area since 2005 (&lt;a href=&quot;https://escholarship.org/uc/item/6434d1px&quot;&gt;Evidence for the Extinction of Mammoths by an Extraterrestrial Impact Event&lt;/a&gt;) and in 2006 co-authored a book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.uk/books?hl=en&amp;amp;lr=&amp;amp;id=d1ooDwAAQBAJ&amp;amp;oi=fnd&amp;amp;pg=PT14&amp;amp;dq=%22Allen+West%22&amp;amp;ots=9QLiSjyrE3&amp;amp;sig=6pEWeeRLpuPRJeGozdWInxrMUsw#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=%22Allen%20West%22&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;The Cycle of Cosmic Catastrophes: How a Stone-Age Comet Changed the Course of World Culture&lt;/a&gt;, which claims  that the debris of a shattered comet was responsible for  “a cosmic chain of events [that] began 41,000 years ago and culminated in a major global  catastrophe  28,000 years later.” These events include everything from the extinction of the mammoths to the landform of the Carolina Bays to the legend of Atlantis to a purported “mysterious layer of black sediment” found spanning North America to the Younger Dryas discussed in the Abu Hureya paper.  West has no academic qualifications or affiliations and gives his address as Comet Research Group (CRG), Prescott, Arizona (several of the other authors are also members of this group, &lt;a href=&quot;https://scienceintegritydigest.com/2021/10/01/blast-in-the-past-image-concerns-in-paper-about-comet-that-might-have-destroyed-tall-el-hammam/&quot;&gt;which is linked&lt;/a&gt; to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.authortalk.audio/&quot;&gt;Rising Light Group&lt;/a&gt;, a 501(c)3, tax-exempt charitable organization with a clear Christian and biblical agenda, registered in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.authortalk.audio/501-c3.html&quot;&gt;Allen West’s name&lt;/a&gt;. As &lt;a href=&quot;https://psmag.com/environment/comet-claim-comes-crashing-to-earth-31180&quot;&gt;detailed by Pacific Standard Magazine&lt;/a&gt;, discussing how thing stood regarding CRG’s work in 2017, there have been calls for a formal inquiry, and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; University of Wyoming archaeologist &lt;a href=&quot;http://uwacadweb.uwyo.edu/SUROVELL/&quot;&gt;Todd Surovell&lt;/a&gt; and his colleagues couldn’t find increased magnetic spherules representing cosmic debris at seven &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pnas.org/content/106/43/18155.abstract?sid=49d79c32-625b-4cdd-bbb2-3ff3254f8a46&quot;&gt;Clovis sites&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.geology.siu.edu/people/pinter/index.html&quot;&gt;Nicholas Pinter&lt;/a&gt; and his colleagues at Southern Illinois University Carbondale argue the carbon spherules are organic residue of fungus or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.agu.org/pubs/crossref/2010/2010GL043345.shtml&quot;&gt;arthropod excrement&lt;/a&gt;. And &lt;a href=&quot;http://physics.wustl.edu/people/daulton_tyrone-l&quot;&gt;Tyrone Daulton&lt;/a&gt; of Washington University in St. Louis and his colleagues reported that supposed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pnas.org/content/107/37/16043&quot;&gt;nanodiamonds formed by the impact were misidentified&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numerous other concerns specific to the present work &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubpeer.com/publications/37B87CAC48DE4BC98AD40E00330143&quot;&gt;have been presented&lt;/a&gt; at PubPeer, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://scienceintegritydigest.com/2021/10/01/blast-in-the-past-image-concerns-in-paper-about-comet-that-might-have-destroyed-tall-el-hammam/&quot;&gt;very detailed concerns&lt;/a&gt; have been raised by Elisabeth Bik in her blog, Science Integrity Digest, where she presents evidence that images in the paper had been manipulated.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, in an acrimonious exchange with me in the Comments section of &lt;i&gt;The Conversation&lt;/i&gt;, Wells pointed out,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Our group included, among many others: Dr. James Kennett, emeritus professor at UCSB, specializing in stratigraphy, micropaleontology, paleobiology. He is a member of the National Academy of Sciences, which recognizes the contributions of just 0.1% of all scientists. Dr. Ted Bunch, former NASA section chief and a world-leading meteoriticist. Dr. Robert Hermes, retired from Los Alamos National Labs, world-recognized expert in trinitite or atomic glass. Dr. Wendy Wolbach, chemistry professor who discovered high-temperature soot at the K-Pg boundary.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I replied with a listing of some papers that I have examined criticising West’s own earlier work regarding airbursts, including sampling techniques and claimed evidence for very high temperatures:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Scott AC, Hardiman M, Pinter N, Anderson RS, Daulton TL, Ejarque A, Finch P, Carter-champion A (2017). &lt;a href=&quot;https://researchportal.port.ac.uk/portal/en/publications/interpreting-palaeofire-evidence-from-fluvial-sediments(f8638df6-4a41-4fa7-b26f-c337e91253b1).html&quot;&gt; Interpreting palaeofire evidence from fluvial sediments: a case study from Santa Rosa Island, California, with implications for the Younger Dryas Impact Hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;. Journal of Quaternary Science. 32 (1): 35–47. doi:10.1002/jqs.2914.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;*Boslough M, Harris AW, Chapman C, Morrison D (November 2013). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3831451&quot;&gt;Younger Dryas impact model confuses comet facts, defies airburst physics&lt;/a&gt;. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America. 110 (45): E4170. doi:10.1073/pnas.1313495110. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;*Boslough M (April 2013). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3645552&quot;&gt;Faulty protocols yield contaminated samples, unconfirmed results&lt;/a&gt;. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America. 110 (18): E1651. doi:10.1073/pnas.1220567110. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Van Hoesel A, Hoek WZ, Pennock GM, Drury MR (2014). The Younger Dryas impact hypothesis: a critical review. Quaternary Science Reviews. 83: 95–114. doi:10.1016/j.quascirev.2013.10.033.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;*Meltzer DJ, Holliday VT, Cannon MD, Miller DS (May 2014). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4040610&quot;&gt;Chronological evidence fails to support claim of an isochronous widespread layer of cosmic impact indicators dated to 12,800 years ago&lt;/a&gt;. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America. 111 (21): E2162-71. doi:10.1073/pnas.1401150111. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;*Holliday VT (December 2015). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4679064&quot;&gt;Problematic dating of claimed Younger Dryas boundary impact proxies&lt;/a&gt;. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America. 112 (49): E6721. doi:10.1073/pnas.1518945112. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thy P, Willcox G, Barfod GH, Fuller DQ (2015). Anthropogenic origin of siliceous scoria droplets from Pleistocene and Holocene archaeological sites in northern Syria. Journal of Archaeological Science. 54: 193–209. doi:10.1016/j.jas.2014.11.027. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;*Van der Hammen T, Van Geel B (2016). &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1017%2FS0016774600023416&quot;&gt; Charcoal in soils of the Allerød-Younger Dryas transition were the result of natural fires and not necessarily the effect of an extra-terrestrial impact&lt;/a&gt;. Netherlands Journal of Geosciences. 87 (4): 359–361. doi:10.1016/j.jas.2014.11.027&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, however, in defence of the Younger Dryas impact theory, *Sweatman MB (2021). The Younger Dryas Impact hypothesis: Review of the impact evidence. Earth-Science Reviews. 218: 103677. doi:10.1016/j.earscirev.2021.103677. I thank Christopher R. Moore, one of the authors of the paper I am criticising, for drawing my attention to this review.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Freely accessible via doi; for other papers, doi gives access to abstracts but not full text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://retractionwatch.com/2021/10/01/criticism-engulfs-paper-claiming-an-asteroid-destroyed-biblical-sodom-and-gomorrah/#more-123196&quot;&gt;Retraction Watch&lt;/a&gt; has drawn attention to the criticisms that the paper has attracted, and Richard White, the chief editor of &lt;i&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/i&gt;, says that he is aware of the concerns that have been raised, and considering them carefully.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We await his decision with interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] Though not his reasoning, Ken’s argument is based on his Ussher-style &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/bible-timeline/how-does-mans-history-fit-with-the-biblical-timeline/&quot;&gt;biblical timeline&lt;/a&gt;, which places the call of Abraham at 1922 BCE, whereas the destruction of Tall el-Hammam is dated to ~ 1650 BCE. For what it’s worth (not much, I know), this disagreement would disappear if we use, instead, the traditional Jewish date of 3760 BCE for the Creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Paul Braterman is Emeritus Professor of Chemistry at the University of North Texas and honorary senior Research Fellow in Chemistry at the University of Glasgow, as well as a science writer. He has written for PT before, most recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/12/Is-the-NABT-statement-flawed.html&quot;&gt;Is the NABT statement on teaching evolution flawed?&lt;/a&gt;  and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/aig-climate-change-vaccination.html&quot;&gt; Answers in Genesis, climate change, and vaccination&lt;/a&gt;.  Matt Young will be the primary moderator of this thread.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman</name></author><summary type="html">Enlargement of detail from Elisabeth Bik’s blog, one of several illustrations showing apparently duplicated areas within the key figures of the paper A Tunguska sized airburst destroyed Tall el-Hammam …. Note added 14 October 2021, 6:40 p.m. MDT: Professor Braterman has published an expanded version of this article, Tall el-Hammam; an airburst of gullibility; it gets worse, in the blog Primate’s Progress. I shared the excitement when I read here that “in ~ 1650 BCE (~ 3600 years ago), a cosmic airburst destroyed Tall el-Hammam, a Middle-Bronze-Age city in the southern Jordan Valley northeast of the Dead Sea,” and that this event could have given rise to the biblical account of the destruction of Sodom and Gomorrah. Somewhat to my surprise, Ken Ham of Answers in Genesis did not. I now think that Ken’s conclusion [1] was right and I was wrong. Like I suspect many of the journalists and interested readers who swooped on this story, I failed at first to notice that the paper was not, despite the link, an article in Nature but in Scientific Reports. This is one of the stable of second-line journals closely linked to Nature being published by Springer, now controlled by the publishing giant Hotlzbrinck, and profiting from Nature’s reputation for excellence. I was only vaguely aware of the authors’ long history of invoking airbursts, took the many kinds of evidence listed at face value, and did not even blink at the claim that “[a]n airburst-related influx of salt (~ 4 wt.%) produced hypersalinity,” a process for which I can envisage no credible mechanism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Return of the God of the Gaps</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/return-god-gaps.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Return of the God of the Gaps" /><published>2021-10-01T09:02:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-10-01T09:02:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/return-god-gaps</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/10/return-god-gaps.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Meyer_God_Hypothesis_Cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot; &quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt; &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not read Stephen Meyer’s new book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B07G122JJN/&quot;&gt;Return of the God Hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;, subtitled “Three Scientific Discoveries That Reveal the Mind Behind the Universe,” and possibly will not. I had not been aware that the God hypothesis had ever gone away, and 700-odd pages of what looks like old hat seems perhaps a bit excessive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, what may look to some like an unlikely source, the right-wing blog &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ricochet_(website)&quot;&gt;Ricochet&lt;/a&gt;, may have saved me the trouble: They recently ran a splendid “&lt;a href=&quot;https://ricochet.com/1059644/stephen-meyers-return-of-the-god-hypothesis/&quot;&gt;critique&lt;/a&gt;” of the book by &lt;a href=&quot;https://poddtoppen.se/podcast/1535406429/clearer-thinking-with-spencer-greenberg/liberalism-and-conservatism-with-cassandra-xia-and-hank-racette&quot;&gt;Henry Racette&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Mr. Racette, the book stands on three pillars:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The universe had a beginning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The universe is fine-tuned for life.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The genetic code is evidence of an intelligent designer. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Racette considers the fine-tuning argument to be the strongest of the three. Nevertheless, he ultimately dismisses it and wisely invokes the God of the Gaps before concluding,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Meyer has written a book that could have been written at any time during our long quest for understanding. The details would change, the sophistication would vary, but the product would be similar: a man standing on the edge of the unknown surveys the wisest men around him and concludes that, since they have no wholly satisfactory answers, one or another god is the most plausible explanation.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I shall have no need to read this book, since Mr. Racette has done so for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgment.&lt;/strong&gt; I am indebted to several colleagues, who provided some links and a brief discussion of Mr. Racette’s review.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I have not read Stephen Meyer’s new book, Return of the God Hypothesis, subtitled “Three Scientific Discoveries That Reveal the Mind Behind the Universe,” and possibly will not. I had not been aware that the God hypothesis had ever gone away, and 700-odd pages of what looks like old hat seems perhaps a bit excessive. Fortunately, what may look to some like an unlikely source, the right-wing blog Ricochet, may have saved me the trouble: They recently ran a splendid “critique” of the book by Henry Racette. According to Mr. Racette, the book stands on three pillars:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bubo virginianus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/bubo-virginianus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bubo virginianus" /><published>2021-09-27T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-27T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/bubo-virginianus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/bubo-virginianus.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;David Young&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/IMG_2840_David_Owl_Crop_2_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Great horned owl&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_horned_owl&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Bubo virginianus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; great horned owl that flew into the back yard one day, Boulder, Colorado, September, 2021.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by David Young. Bubo virginianus &amp;ndash; great horned owl that flew into the back yard one day, Boulder, Colorado, September, 2021.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Apex predator was vegetarian: AIG</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/apex-predator-vegetarian.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Apex predator was vegetarian: AIG" /><published>2021-09-23T09:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-23T09:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/apex-predator-vegetarian</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/apex-predator-vegetarian.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Carcharodontosaurus_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dinosaur&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Carcharodontosaurus.png&quot;&gt;Carcharodontosaurus reconstruction.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt; Credit: Fred Wierum. Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 4.0 International license.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Guest post by &lt;strong&gt;Dan Phelps&lt;/strong&gt;, to whom we are indebted for unearthing this whopper from Answers in Genesis:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, creationists are misrepresenting a recent dinosaur discovery. This time it is a large carcharodontosaur from Uzbekistan that was recently described in a paper, &lt;a href=&quot;https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rsos.210923&quot;&gt;A new carcharodontosaurian theropod dinosaur occupies apex predator niche in the early Late Cretaceous of Uzbekistan&lt;/a&gt;, by Kohei Tanaka and colleagues from the universities of Tsukuba, Hokkaido, and Calgary.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On today’s “Answers News,” an online news video by Answers in Genesis, their employees (including Ken Ham’s son-in-law, Bodie Hodge) discuss this dinosaur. The discussion can be found from about 9 minutes, 30 seconds to about 14 minutes in &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/4Jhf2eKXwAc&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; YouTube video.  As is par for the course, they ignore the actual publication and rely instead on popular press discussions such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.deseret.com/u-s-world/2021/9/9/22664700/tyrannosaurus-rex-ulughbegsaurus-uzbekistanensis-bigger-dinosaur&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; . They also add their bizarre creationist interpretations and claim the fossil was buried in Noah’s Flood. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even more ridiculously, they suggest the theropod dinosaur – the apex predator! – may have been a vegetarian. This would be amusing except that AIG is misinforming children and adults via such broadcasts as above, the Creation “Museum,” and their Kentucky-taxpayer–subsidized “Ark Encounter.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Carcharodontosaurus reconstruction. Credit: Fred Wierum. Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 4.0 International license. Guest post by Dan Phelps, to whom we are indebted for unearthing this whopper from Answers in Genesis: Once again, creationists are misrepresenting a recent dinosaur discovery. This time it is a large carcharodontosaur from Uzbekistan that was recently described in a paper, A new carcharodontosaurian theropod dinosaur occupies apex predator niche in the early Late Cretaceous of Uzbekistan, by Kohei Tanaka and colleagues from the universities of Tsukuba, Hokkaido, and Calgary. On today’s “Answers News,” an online news video by Answers in Genesis, their employees (including Ken Ham’s son-in-law, Bodie Hodge) discuss this dinosaur. The discussion can be found from about 9 minutes, 30 seconds to about 14 minutes in this YouTube video. As is par for the course, they ignore the actual publication and rely instead on popular press discussions such as this one . They also add their bizarre creationist interpretations and claim the fossil was buried in Noah’s Flood. Even more ridiculously, they suggest the theropod dinosaur – the apex predator! – may have been a vegetarian. This would be amusing except that AIG is misinforming children and adults via such broadcasts as above, the Creation “Museum,” and their Kentucky-taxpayer–subsidized “Ark Encounter.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Will the name of Huxley College be changed on a pretext?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/thhuxley-3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Will the name of Huxley College be changed on a pretext?" /><published>2021-09-17T13:24:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-17T13:24:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/thhuxley-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/thhuxley-3.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/WWU_Viking.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Viking mascot&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western_Washington_Vikings&quot;&gt;Western Washington University mascot&lt;/a&gt;. You may see their Viking ship &lt;a href=&quot;https://designsystem.wwu.edu/athletics-branding-and-spirit-marks&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, toward the bottom. &lt;small&gt;Credit: Wikipedia. Fair Use.&lt;/small&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Board of Trustees of Huxley College met the day before yesterday, September 17, &lt;a href=&quot;https://trustees.wwu.edu/files/00%20BOT%20Sept%202021%20Work%20Session%20Agenda%20-%20FINAL.pdf&quot;&gt;solely to discuss renaming the college &lt;/a&gt;. According to a source whom I prefer to leave anonymous,*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;[T]he consensus seems to be to drop the Huxley name. They acknowledge that there was lots of information submitted both in support of and opposed to dropping the Huxley name. They acknowledge that Huxley did lots of great stuff both as a scientist and as a strong abolitionist and a defender of universal human rights, and in expanding educational opportunities for a diverse audience. However, they were troubled by some of the bigoted and sexist language that Huxley made at times. They also point out that Huxley had no real links to the Pacific Northwest or North America. Fair point. It sounds like they just don’t have the stomach to deal with the blowback of rejecting the &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/files/2021-07/LRTF%20Report%20and%20Recommendations_June%202021.pdf&quot;&gt;Legacy Review Task Force&lt;/a&gt;. No decision but it seems clear where they want to go.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

They then went on the discuss &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/files/2021-02/WWU%20Building%20Names%20Report%20Sept%202020.pdf&quot;&gt;Mathes and Haggard&lt;/a&gt; [two dormitories]. They are not inclined to reject these two, in spite of the majority recommendation of the Task Force to do so, and made comments along the line that “you should judge people based on the standards and language used in their time, not by modern standards.” Interesting that they are not inclined to use the same standard for Huxley. They want to judge him based on modern standards.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is curious that they only now discovered that Huxley had no direct connection to their area. If I wanted to be suspicious, I might suspect that they plan to change the name of the college on a pretext.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another source thought it was&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;[a] very sad and embarrassing spectacle all around.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

It started well enough, with written comments from the student board member who couldn’t be there. His comments were read/summarized by the chair. He expressed concern with the Task Force report and the impact it would have on the academic reputation of the university. He also seemed concerned with a “purity” test that was being applied to Huxley.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

From there I couldn’t tell which Board member was speaking, so I’ll just refer to them generically in the order in which they spoke.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

The first Board member obviously felt uncomfortable with the racism claims in the Task Force report and sought to distance the Board from them by suggesting a wholly different reason for changing the name: that Huxley had no real historic connection to WWU. On that principle alone she said she was prepared to dename the college.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

President Randhawa supported this, saying the key principle should be a direct connection to the university. Huxley's contributions pro and con are moot if relationship to the university is the main criterion.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

It was all downhill from there.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

The next board member said that denaming would have a de minimis impact on T.H. Huxley’s reputation because WWU is a regional university, so it wasn’t as if an organization with a national or international reputation made such a name change. He said there was a high cost in defending the name with little return. He accused Huxley of being an early eugenicist, and claimed that he had no connection to public education institutions like Huxley College. He called Huxley’s reputation “controversial.”&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

The next board member recognized that she was talking from an emotional perspective. She repeated the creationist trope that Huxley advocated a hierarchical theory of race and, because of that, going to a school named after him reminded her of the harm caused by going to a high school in Baltimore named after Roger B. Taney, the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court who wrote the Dred Scott decision. So in short, she compared Huxley’s legacy to Taney's.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Sensing the overwhelming sentiment, the Board chair than suggested that they needed to start thinking through how they were going to communicate the thought process behind their decision.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Another Board member asked if they need more input, more process. The chair restated this, asking if they needed to rehear the case? The response overall from several board members was no, there was plenty of opportunity for input.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

One Board member suggested voting at the October meeting. The president suggested it would be better to do so at the December meeting, or it will look like it was all worked out in advance. Several others concurred and suggested that the October meeting focus on communicating the rationale for the denaming.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

So in summary, they totally bought the creationist narrative in the Task Force report. I was embarrassed for them, for WWU, and for my own association with WWU.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another source observed that, when a committee was appointed,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;usually the decision on the path forward had already been made.  We were part of the required process.  But I do think all that work did make a difference.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Universities in Washington are essentially non-regulatory State Agencies and therefore policy making political bodies.  The process here is clearly political, and the members of the Board are political appointees.  It does now appear that at least some of the members of the Board are realizing the significance of the misinformation presented by the Huxley section of the report.  Without our efforts [I think he refers to comments submitted to the task force and the article &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seattletimes.com/opinion/reconsider-cancel-culture-target-at-wwu/&quot;&gt;Reconsider cancel-culture target at WWU&lt;/a&gt; in the Seattle Times, and maybe even the earlier articles in PT] the motion to change the name would have been presented and passed at yesterday’s and certainly by October’s Board meeting.  [At least we have gotten their attention, and] the Board and the President are now looking for ways to remove the name of Huxley from the college without claiming social injustice or racism.  The Seattle Times piece stated that there may be other reasons for removing Huxley as the name of the college, but that the racist and injustice charges were not true. Perhaps that is where they are thinking of going now.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps amusingly, the Task Force also discussed changing the name of the Viking Union, which I assume is the student union. The Viking is also the mascot of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western_Washington_Vikings&quot;&gt;University’s sports teams&lt;/a&gt;. Footnote 49 in their report tells you more than you want to know about the choice of the Viking mascot. If nothing else, the Task Force seems concerned that “Vikings have been romanticized by white supremacist groups as icons of conquest,” and white supremacists have been active on campus. One final source said that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;they seemed pretty resigned to the idea that that name would eventually change also.  There was some comment along the lines that any group of people has probably done something awful to someone else at some point, probably true.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* I have cited several sources and I have tacit permission to quote them, but I have left them anonymous to protect them from any possible retaliation. I have lightly edited their comments, for example, by replacing initialisms with full spellings when appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Western Washington University mascot. You may see their Viking ship here, toward the bottom. Credit: Wikipedia. Fair Use. The Board of Trustees of Huxley College met the day before yesterday, September 17, solely to discuss renaming the college . According to a source whom I prefer to leave anonymous,* [T]he consensus seems to be to drop the Huxley name. They acknowledge that there was lots of information submitted both in support of and opposed to dropping the Huxley name. They acknowledge that Huxley did lots of great stuff both as a scientist and as a strong abolitionist and a defender of universal human rights, and in expanding educational opportunities for a diverse audience. However, they were troubled by some of the bigoted and sexist language that Huxley made at times. They also point out that Huxley had no real links to the Pacific Northwest or North America. Fair point. It sounds like they just don’t have the stomach to deal with the blowback of rejecting the Legacy Review Task Force. No decision but it seems clear where they want to go. They then went on the discuss Mathes and Haggard [two dormitories]. They are not inclined to reject these two, in spite of the majority recommendation of the Task Force to do so, and made comments along the line that “you should judge people based on the standards and language used in their time, not by modern standards.” Interesting that they are not inclined to use the same standard for Huxley. They want to judge him based on modern standards. It is curious that they only now discovered that Huxley had no direct connection to their area. If I wanted to be suspicious, I might suspect that they plan to change the name of the college on a pretext. Another source thought it was</summary></entry></feed>