<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-09-07T13:37:17-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Evaluating Alan Kleinman’s arguments</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/evaluating-alan-kleinmans-arguments.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evaluating Alan Kleinman’s arguments" /><published>2021-09-06T18:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-06T18:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/evaluating-alan-kleinmans-arguments</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/evaluating-alan-kleinmans-arguments.html">&lt;p&gt;Alan Kleinman has been commenting on various threads here at PT, in ways that repeatedly argue that he has done
the first correct probabilistic analysis of “DNA evolutionary adaptation” and “competition”, and that call for
evolutionary biologists to provide an analysis of the Lenski and Kishony experiments in bacterial evolution.  He
also argues that we have not provided a correct analysis of bacterial antibiotic resistence or of the evolution
of drug resistance in cancer.  This thread is intended to allow discussion of these assertions, without disrupting discussions of other topics at PT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me explain.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kleinman has published 7 papers on modeling evolutionary processes.  I have provided links to PDFs of these, when I encountered ones that might be free:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kleinman, A.  2014.  The basic science and mathematics of random mutation and natural
 selection &lt;em&gt;Statistics in Medicine&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;33 (29):&lt;/strong&gt; 5074–5080 &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1002/sim.6307&quot;&gt;(PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kleinman, A. 2015.  Random recombination and evolution of drug resistance. &lt;em&gt;Statistics in Medicine&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;34 (11):&lt;/strong&gt; 1977–1980.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kleinman, A.  2016.  The mathematics of random mutation and natural selection for multiple simultaneous selection
 pressures and the evolution of antimicrobial drug resistance. &lt;em&gt;Statistics in Medicine&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;35 (29):&lt;/strong&gt; 5391-5400&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kleinman, A. 2018a.  Random mutation and natural selection in competitive and 
noncompetitive environments.  &lt;em&gt;Biomedical Journal of Scientific &amp;amp; Technical Research&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;9 (1):&lt;/strong&gt; 6903–6906. &lt;a href=&quot;https://biomedres.us/volume9-issue1.php&quot;&gt;(PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kleinman, A. 2018b. Malaria and other infectious diseases, Suppression of the evolution
 of drug resistance. &lt;em&gt;Biomedical Journal of Scientific &amp;amp; Technical Research&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;12 (2):&lt;/strong&gt; 9083-9085. &lt;a href=&quot;https://biomedres.us/fulltexts/BJSTR.MS.ID.002219.php&quot;&gt;(PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kleinman, A. 2019. Fixation and adaptation in the Lenski E. coli Long Term Evolution Experiment. &lt;em&gt;Biomedical Journal of Scientific &amp;amp; Technical Research&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;20 (1):&lt;/strong&gt; 14754–14760. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Alan-Kleinman/publication/335243441_Fixation_and_Adaptation_in_the_Lenski_E_coli_Long_Term_Evolution_Experiment/links/5d5ae99d4585152102521f7f/Fixation-and-Adaptation-in-the-Lenski-E-coli-Long-Term-Evolution-Experiment.pdf&quot;&gt;(PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kleinman, A. M. 2020.  Drug resistance, An enemy of targeted cancer therapies. &lt;em&gt;Annals of Clinical and Medical Case Reports&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;4 (9):&lt;/strong&gt; 1–4.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has also brought his argument up repeatedly at Peaceful Science and at 
Panda&quot;s Thumb,
usually in the middle of threads devoted to other issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic calculation he does is to consider a haploid clonally-reproducing organism such
a bacterial culture, one which has no recombination.  He develops a formula for the
probability that the clone has beneficial mutations occuring at &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; sites, where the
first such mutation has &lt;em&gt;nGA&lt;/em&gt; generations to occur, the second has &lt;em&gt;nGB&lt;/em&gt; generations to
occur, and so on.  Note that an important feature of his model is that he considers,
not the time in generations but the number of cells that have ever arisen in the clone.
So with a probability &lt;em&gt;mu PA&lt;/em&gt; for each new cell that
it has a beneficial mutation, it takes about &lt;em&gt;1/(mu PA)&lt;/em&gt; cells before there is a
reasonable probability of seeing the beneficial mutation once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mystery (to me, anyway) is where selection is in all this.  We are computing
probabilities that, when a given number of cells has arisen, we have had
beneficial mutation at all of the &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; sites.  Once one has occurred, there seems to
be no futher mutation at that site.  Why?   This calculation is supposed to show
us the fundamental mathematical theory of mutation &lt;em&gt;and selection&lt;/em&gt;, but aside from
waiting until a mutation labelled “beneficial” occurs, there is no further
effect of selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same theory is also used in most of his other papers (an exception being the paper
on recombination which I will get back to later).  He has an idiosyncratic terminology.
As far as I can tell it involves calling the occurrence of beneficial mutations by
mutation “DNA adaptive evolution” while he calls their subsequent changes of gene
frequency in the population “competition”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some questions arise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kleinman sees two processes at work: “competition” which is survival of the fittest, and “DNA evolutionary adaptation” which is
changes of genotypes by mutation, either deleterious or beneficial.  Is this terminology helpful?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;His equations are all about how many organisms (or cells) need to have arisen to get a given probability that a beneficial
allele will arise by mutation.  The theory uses the stochastic process of mutation. How does natural selection affect
this?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;His treatment of recombination between genotypes with two or more loci assumes that offspring of a cross between a haploid
Ab genotype and a haploid  aB  genotype will all be  AB.  Is that true?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He seems to think that he is the first to give a correct mathematical theory of
mutation and natural selection.  Was he?  For example, his first paper has the
rather astonishingly grand title “The basic science and mathematics of random mutation and
natural selection”. Would RA Fisher
(1922) or JBS Haldane (1924) have agreed?  I think he is off by 97-99 years.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is he really the first to apply the mathematics of population genetics theory to evolution or drug resistance in cancer, or to
success of multidrug therapies for diseases?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I must be misunderstanding how his theory works, and I hope that this thread will explain his theory to me.
After all, if it is the fundamental mathematical theory of my own field, then it is surely important to know.
By doing the discussion here, we can avoid being so rudely interrupted by the folks in the previous threads who were trying to discuss arguments
other than Kleinman&quot;s.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Alan Kleinman has been commenting on various threads here at PT, in ways that repeatedly argue that he has done the first correct probabilistic analysis of “DNA evolutionary adaptation” and “competition”, and that call for evolutionary biologists to provide an analysis of the Lenski and Kishony experiments in bacterial evolution. He also argues that we have not provided a correct analysis of bacterial antibiotic resistence or of the evolution of drug resistance in cancer. This thread is intended to allow discussion of these assertions, without disrupting discussions of other topics at PT. Let me explain.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dendrocygna viduata</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/Dendrocygna-viduata.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dendrocygna viduata" /><published>2021-09-06T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-06T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/Dendrocygna-viduata</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/09/Dendrocygna-viduata.html">&lt;p&gt;Whistling ducks, by &lt;strong&gt;John Harshman&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Harshman_whistling_duck.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Whistling duck&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whistling_duck&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Dendrocygna viduata&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – white-faced whistling ducks, Botswana. The photographer writes, &quot;Here is a trio of white-faced whistling ducks. It’s not a particularly scientifically informative shot, but it’s one of my all-time favorite photos. Whistling ducks, on the other hand, are interesting from a number of perspectives. They’re the sister group of all other Anatidae, and they’re a very old genus: genetic divergence within &lt;i&gt;Dendrocygna&lt;/i&gt; is approximately equal to that within the rest of Anatidae. And yet they all look pretty much alike, so we have a fine example of morphological stasis. That may also be the reason that white-faced whistling ducks, with fairly sedentary habits, are nevertheless found in both Africa and South America with no recognized subspecific variation. (Fulvous whistling ducks &lt;i&gt;D. bicolor&lt;/i&gt; are worse: they’re found in North and South America, Africa, and India, still with no subspecies.)&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Whistling ducks, by John Harshman. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Dendrocygna viduata – white-faced whistling ducks, Botswana. The photographer writes, &quot;Here is a trio of white-faced whistling ducks. It’s not a particularly scientifically informative shot, but it’s one of my all-time favorite photos. Whistling ducks, on the other hand, are interesting from a number of perspectives. They’re the sister group of all other Anatidae, and they’re a very old genus: genetic divergence within Dendrocygna is approximately equal to that within the rest of Anatidae. And yet they all look pretty much alike, so we have a fine example of morphological stasis. That may also be the reason that white-faced whistling ducks, with fairly sedentary habits, are nevertheless found in both Africa and South America with no recognized subspecific variation. (Fulvous whistling ducks D. bicolor are worse: they’re found in North and South America, Africa, and India, still with no subspecies.)&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Euphydryas colon</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Euphydryas-colon.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Euphydryas colon" /><published>2021-08-30T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-30T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Euphydryas-colon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Euphydryas-colon.html">&lt;p&gt;Snowberry checkerspot butterfly, by &lt;strong&gt;Malcom Schongalla&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Schongalla_Euphydryas_colon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Snowberry checkerspot butterfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.butterfliesoforegon.com/euphydryas-colon&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt; Euphydryas colon&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – snowberry checkerspot butterfly, Hillscreek, Oregon, June, 2021.  The photographer writes, &quot;Some references list this as a subspecies of &lt;i&gt;Euphydryas chalcedona&lt;/i&gt; (chalcedon or variable checkerspot).  I am not a butterfly expert and this is my best attempt at identification.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Snowberry checkerspot butterfly, by Malcom Schongalla. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Euphydryas colon – snowberry checkerspot butterfly, Hillscreek, Oregon, June, 2021. The photographer writes, &quot;Some references list this as a subspecies of Euphydryas chalcedona (chalcedon or variable checkerspot). I am not a butterfly expert and this is my best attempt at identification.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Phyciodes batesii</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Phyciodes-batesii.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Phyciodes batesii" /><published>2021-08-23T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-23T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Phyciodes-batesii</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Phyciodes-batesii.html">&lt;p&gt;Tawny crescent butterfly, by &lt;strong&gt;Seanna Watson&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Watson_Seanna_Phyciodes_batesii.jpg&quot; alt=&quot; Tawny crescent butterfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbif.gc.ca/eng/species-bank/butterflies-of-canada/tawny-crescent/?id=1370403265789&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Phyciodes batesii&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – tawny crescent, Neys Provincial Park, Ontario.
&lt;/figcaption&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Tawny crescent butterfly, by Seanna Watson. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Phyciodes batesii – tawny crescent, Neys Provincial Park, Ontario.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Answers in Genesis, climate change, and vaccination</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/aig-climate-change-vaccination.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Answers in Genesis, climate change, and vaccination" /><published>2021-08-22T12:38:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-22T12:38:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/aig-climate-change-vaccination</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/aig-climate-change-vaccination.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Great_Unmasked.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Audience&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/aigkenham/status/1425040762052427776?s=21&quot;&gt;Forty days &amp;amp; nights of gospel music at the Ark&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; The Great Unmasked.&lt;/div&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was dismayed last Thursday to see &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/science/conservatives-have-difficult-relationship-science/&quot;&gt;the following paragraph&lt;/a&gt; posted by AiG under Ken Ham’s byline:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/many-conservatives-have-a-difficult-relationship-with-science-we-wanted-to-find-out-why-165499&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; [in &lt;i&gt;The Conversation&lt;/i&gt;], the author uses the term &lt;i&gt;science&lt;/i&gt; to refer to the so-called “scientific consensus” regarding things such as climate change alarmism, vaccinations, evolution, and a lack of “human exceptionalism.” But what the author is failing to recognize is the difference between observational and historical science. In other words, this author has a “difficult relationship with science” because the author doesn’t understand the word &lt;i&gt;science&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some time, Answers in Genesis has &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/environmental-science/ice-cores-secret-understanding-earths-climate/&quot;&gt;minimized the importance of human-made climate change&lt;/a&gt;, as have &lt;a href=&quot;https://creation.com/climate-change&quot;&gt;Creation Ministries International&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2020/04/tyson-and-cosmos-sound-the-climate-alarm-again/&quot;&gt;Discovery Institute&lt;/a&gt;, and this position of necessity involves denying the authority of a declared scientific consensus. However, Answers in Genesis has hitherto accepted the value of vaccines, and in two recent related articles, &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/human-body/wise-blood-overcoming-in-disease-immunity-part-1/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/human-body/wise-blood-antibodies-principle-overcoming-disease-part-2/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, gives a detailed scientific account of how vaccines work, and praises their effectiveness in the context of the complexity of the immune system, which of course for AiG is evidence for creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/many-conservatives-have-a-difficult-relationship-with-science-we-wanted-to-find-out-why-165499&quot;&gt;article in &lt;i&gt;The Conversation&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, cited above, reports that “[p]eople with a libertarian or conservative worldview are more likely to reject climate change and evolution and &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0250123&quot;&gt;are less likely to be vaccinated against COVID-19&lt;/a&gt;,” and in the US context relates such rejection of science and an exaggerated view of human exceptionalism, to religiosity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The historical versus observation nonsense is familiar, as are the attacks on scientific consensus and on concern about climate change, and our models of climate change do indeed involve the “historical science” that uses ice cores and other techniques to map climate change throughout the Ice Ages and beyond. But including “vaccinations” in the areas of scientific consensus apparently to be rejected is alarming. The study of vaccine effectiveness is very much part of current observational science, and we can see no good reason for Answers in Genesis to be turning against it, even on their own terms.
What we must fear is that AiG may be about to fall in line with other creationist institutions ranging from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gty.org/library/blog/B200723&quot;&gt;Grace Community Church&lt;/a&gt; to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2020/08/in-fauci-we-trust-c-s-lewis-foresaw-scientific-authoritarianism/&quot;&gt;Discovery Institute&lt;/a&gt; in minimizing the severity of an epidemic that is known to have killed 644,840 people in the US and 4,442,332 worldwide (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/&quot;&gt;as of August 22&lt;/a&gt;). AiG was from the outset &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/coronavirus/coronavirus-biblical-practical/&quot;&gt;ambivalent about masks&lt;/a&gt;, and even jokingly (or blasphemously) telling its readers &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2020/11/28/therefore-tell-you-do-not-be-anxious-about-covid/&quot;&gt;not to be anxious about COVID&lt;/a&gt; just as Jesus told his disciples (Matthew 6:25-34) not to worry about the necessities of life. Despite a rash of articles in March and April of last year, arguing that the mutations giving rise to COVID were not really examples of evolution, AiG has published nothing of significance on the subject since that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does not bode well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Dan Phelps for simultaneously alerting us to the AIG post and also for unearthing the photograph. Matt Young will be the primary moderator of this thread.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman</name></author><summary type="html">Forty days &amp;amp; nights of gospel music at the Ark &amp;ndash; The Great Unmasked. I was dismayed last Thursday to see the following paragraph posted by AiG under Ken Ham’s byline: In the article [in The Conversation], the author uses the term science to refer to the so-called “scientific consensus” regarding things such as climate change alarmism, vaccinations, evolution, and a lack of “human exceptionalism.” But what the author is failing to recognize is the difference between observational and historical science. In other words, this author has a “difficult relationship with science” because the author doesn’t understand the word science.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">All theories in science involving randomness are invalid</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/randomness-is-not.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All theories in science involving randomness are invalid" /><published>2021-08-20T20:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-20T20:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/randomness-is-not</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/randomness-is-not.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Diffusion640px.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Diffusion, modeled by random movement of molecules.  By Jaap Pol,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diffusion#/media/File:Diffusion.svg&quot;&gt;from Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/&quot;&gt;its license&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contemporary theories of evolution involve mutation as the ultimate source of
variability, and model it as having a distribution of directions which is independent
of the needs of the organism. It is natural selection that provides the
directionality of evolutionary change.  There can hardly be any assertion in
the theory that is more disliked by creationists and ID advocates.  Now they
have found a way to oppose this view: argue that randomness cannot be part
of the explanation of any phenomenon that we claim to have explained
scientifically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alas, there is an unfortunate side effect of this position: many scientific
theories have to be tossed out if we accept it.  Let me explain …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general principle was stated by Eric Holloway, in a post &lt;a href=&quot;https://mindmatters.ai/2021/08/randomness-is-not-a-scientific-explanation/&quot;&gt;“Randomness is
not a Scientific Explanation”&lt;/a&gt; on the Discovery
Institute’s site “Mind Matters” on 9 August 2021.  Mind Matters, a blog
of the DI’s Walter Bradley Center for Natural and Artificial Intelligence,
is devoted
to making profound arguments as to why artificial intelligence will forever
remain unintelligent, because only supernatural forces can create an
intelligent system.  The article was of course immediately &lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/at-mind-matters-news-randomness-is-not-a-scientific-explanation/&quot;&gt;greeted with enthusiasm&lt;/a&gt;
at Uncommon Descent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mindmatters.ai/2021/08/randomness-is-not-a-scientific-explanation/&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is Holloway’s argument:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is common in the sciences to claim aspects of our universe are random:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;In evolution, mutations are random.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;In quantum physics, the wave collapse is random.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;In biology, much of the genome is random.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;In business theory, organizational ecologists state new ideas are random.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;There is a general idea that everything new has its origins in randomness.
This is because within our current philosophy of science, the two fundamental
causes in our universe boil down to randomness and necessity. Since necessity
never creates anything new, then by process of elimination the source of
newness must be randomness. Similar to how the ancient Greeks believed the
universe originated from chaos.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Here’s  the irony of the view that whatever is unique in our universe is
random: We can never know if anything is truly random. This is because
randomness is unprovable, which was proven by three different computer
scientists: Ray Solomonoff, Andrey Kolmogorov, and Gregory Chaitin.
The only thing we can know is that something is not random. Hence, we can
never know that something originated from randomness.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;What does this result mean for science? It means that randomness can never be
a scientific explanation, since we can never know that something is random. At
best, saying something is random is shorthand for “we don’t know”.
So, when scientists state the origin of something in our universe is random,
they do not know the origin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that takes care of it, doesn’t it?  Instead of modeling the mutational
process as random, in order to be part of a scientific theory, we must
describe the actual causes of mutation so as to be able to predict individual
mutations.  Right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, not so fast.  Are there other models used in science that involve
random events?  Yes, definitely.  Here are a few I can think of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Random times of decay of radioactive atoms.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Random movements of molecules when they diffuse in solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brownian motion of particles in gases or liquids.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The movement of molecules in a gas, and the distribution of velocities
that results.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Random segregation of chromosomes in meiosis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Random changes of gene frequency in a population (random genetic drift).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rolls of dice, spins of roulette wheels, or fall of cards in gambling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those are just the ones I can think of, I’m sure there are many more.  If
Holloway’s argument is accepted, all of these successful scientific theories
will need to be discarded  Maybe even probability theory.  The Discovery Institute has just carried out
the greatest revolution in scientific explanation ever. Or tried to, anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that none of these theories actually asserts that the universe is
fundamentally stochastic, or fundamentally deterministic.  It just has
phenomena in it that are well-modeled by models involving randomness, which
is a much more limited assertion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone wants to argue that the argument applies to its original intended
target but not to any of the phenomena on the above list, I would be
interested to hear that.  Though I may be profoundly skeptical of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, does Holloway’s argument work?  Has science been revolutionized?  Any
discussion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I wish to thank the Discovery Institute for making a science blogger’s life easy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Diffusion, modeled by random movement of molecules. By Jaap Pol, from Wikimedia Commons, see its license, Contemporary theories of evolution involve mutation as the ultimate source of variability, and model it as having a distribution of directions which is independent of the needs of the organism. It is natural selection that provides the directionality of evolutionary change. There can hardly be any assertion in the theory that is more disliked by creationists and ID advocates. Now they have found a way to oppose this view: argue that randomness cannot be part of the explanation of any phenomenon that we claim to have explained scientifically. Alas, there is an unfortunate side effect of this position: many scientific theories have to be tossed out if we accept it. Let me explain …</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Denaming the Huxley College of the Environment, Part 3</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/thhuxley-3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Denaming the Huxley College of the Environment, Part 3" /><published>2021-08-20T08:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-20T08:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/thhuxley-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/thhuxley-3.html">&lt;p&gt;This morning, a group of faculty from Western Washington University submitted  their response to the University’s Legacy Review Task Force Report, regarding renaming the Huxley College of the Environment. We reported on the controversy &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/thhuxley-2.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find the group’s response &lt;a href=&quot;https://huxley.wwu.edu/response-legacy-review-task-force-report&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Note that they describe it as a “living document” that will be updated periodically as more contributions are submitted and vetted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today at 8:50 a.m. PDT, two of the coauthors, Steve Hollenhorst and Wayne Landis, made public comments at the Board of Trustees meeting, introducing them to the response document and briefly summarizing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may find documentation for the meeting &lt;a href=&quot;https://trustees.wwu.edu/meeting-materials&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The meeting itself was audiocast &lt;a href=&quot;https://wp.wwu.edu/live/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. We will provide a URL when the archived file is made available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edited 12:45 p.m. MDT.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">This morning, a group of faculty from Western Washington University submitted their response to the University’s Legacy Review Task Force Report, regarding renaming the Huxley College of the Environment. We reported on the controversy here. You can find the group’s response here. Note that they describe it as a “living document” that will be updated periodically as more contributions are submitted and vetted. Today at 8:50 a.m. PDT, two of the coauthors, Steve Hollenhorst and Wayne Landis, made public comments at the Board of Trustees meeting, introducing them to the response document and briefly summarizing it. You may find documentation for the meeting here. The meeting itself was audiocast here. We will provide a URL when the archived file is made available. Edited 12:45 p.m. MDT.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sarracenia sp.</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Sarracenia-sp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sarracenia sp." /><published>2021-08-16T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-16T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Sarracenia-sp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Sarracenia-sp.html">&lt;p&gt;Pitcher plant, by &lt;strong&gt;C. Joseph Long&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Long_pitcher_plant.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pitcher plant&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarracenia&quot;&gt; &lt;i&gt;Sarracenia&lt;/i&gt; sp. &lt;/a&gt; – pitcher plant, Green Swamp, west of Wilmington, N. C. (not the Green Swamp west of Orlando).  The photographer writes, &quot;This is a Nature Conservancy site which is typical nitrogen-poor lowland where plants that can find their own protein are favored.  There are also Venus flytraps in the near vicinity and, reportedly, sundews.  Recommended as an easily accessible example of this type of environment.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Pitcher plant, by C. Joseph Long. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Sarracenia sp. – pitcher plant, Green Swamp, west of Wilmington, N. C. (not the Green Swamp west of Orlando). The photographer writes, &quot;This is a Nature Conservancy site which is typical nitrogen-poor lowland where plants that can find their own protein are favored. There are also Venus flytraps in the near vicinity and, reportedly, sundews. Recommended as an easily accessible example of this type of environment.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Denaming the Huxley College of the Environment, Part 2</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/thhuxley-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Denaming the Huxley College of the Environment, Part 2" /><published>2021-08-09T13:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-09T13:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/thhuxley-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/thhuxley-2.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Huxley1882.png&quot; alt=&quot;T.H. Huxley&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Thomas Henry Huxley. &lt;a href=&quot;https://wellcomecollection.org/works/bdcm4asr&quot;&gt;Reproduction of drawing by T. B. Wirgman, 1882&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;small&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan to rename Huxley College of the Environment at Western Washington University may be gathering steam. As we noted in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/05/canceling-huxley&quot;&gt;earlier article&lt;/a&gt;, this plan seems to be an exercise in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Presentism_(literary_and_historical_analysis)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;presentism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by which we mean applying the moral and ethical standards of today to historical figures as if they were aware of them. Less delicately, you might say that presentism is using (or misusing) the moral and ethical standards of today to condemn historical figures and dismiss their achievements. (Indeed, according to the Report cited below, “Some Task Force members questioned how ethical and consensual Huxley’s ethnological methodologies were and evaluated them as failing to meet the University’s contemporary standards for academic integrity [p. 5].” This is presentism at its worst.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earlier PT article cited above gives the background to the current controversy. Since that article was published, however, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/files/2021-07/LRTF%20Report%20and%20Recommendations_June%202021.pdf&quot;&gt;Legacy Review Task Force sent its report&lt;/a&gt; to the president, Sabah Randhawa. The “Recommendation Regarding Huxley College of the Environment” is Section 2.1 of the report and occupies pp. 5-13. The president’s cover letter, which we obtained from a faculty member, is noncommittal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Summary section of the report says of Huxley,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;First, the Task Force unanimously recommends that the Board of Trustees remove T.H. Huxley’s name from the College the Environment. T.H. Huxley accomplished a great deal as a scholar during his lifetime. Unfortunately, his ethnological accomplishments were grounded in white supremacist values that dehumanize and harm many members of the Western community. The Task Force concluded that his legacy conflicts with the university’s current mission.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The President of WWU has made statements by historians of science and others concerning Huxley’s work and views available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://president.wwu.edu/research-and-resources&quot;&gt;a resources webpage&lt;/a&gt;.  We call attention to the contrast between the views of Nicolaas Rupke and
Paul White; and also to the article in WWU’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://asreview.org/2021/01/22/thomas-huxley-once-respected-now-rejected/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;AS Review&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which objected to using Huxley’s name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A group of faculty at Huxley, with help from several of us on the outside, are organizing to oppose the name change. One such faculty member has asked us, in effect, to crowd-source their response. We also are open to hearing that we should not oppose the name change, particularly if you can say why.  Thus, the following questions, which you may respond to in the comments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Does the report propagate untruths about Huxley?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most English intellectual figures of Huxley's time probably favored what today we would call racism, imperialism, sexism, and oppression of working people. Although slavery was abolished in England in 1833, the British elite nevertheless supported the Confederacy during the American Civil War. Did Huxley, who was an abolitionist and an important and fervent advocate of making education available to all, favor or oppose these evils? Was he unusual in that regard? Was he involved in efforts to oppose them?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does the Huxley section of the report accept creationist myths about the relationship between evolutionary biology and racism? Specifically, what are those myths? How do they relate to Huxley?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can anyone point out additional materials or resources that should be taken into account?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is there any major intellectual figure from the 1800's or even the 1900's whose activities or views are so 
pure that it is acceptable to name something after them?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whereas a name is only symbolic, we consider the matter to be of some importance, if only because we do not want to give in to demands based on unfounded allegations, or allegations that dismiss all the positive achievements associated with an important individual. If an influential scholar such as Huxley can be condemned, who is next? Are we going to develop a “fatal flaw” theory of history, where having one transgression makes it wrong to note their other major accomplishments? Washington enslaved people; should Western Washington University have “Washington” in its name?  If we are impressed by someone’s scientific work, by saying that do we automatically attempt to cover up unpleasant facts about their other views? Let us hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein and Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Thomas Henry Huxley. Reproduction of drawing by T. B. Wirgman, 1882. Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license. The plan to rename Huxley College of the Environment at Western Washington University may be gathering steam. As we noted in our earlier article, this plan seems to be an exercise in presentism, by which we mean applying the moral and ethical standards of today to historical figures as if they were aware of them. Less delicately, you might say that presentism is using (or misusing) the moral and ethical standards of today to condemn historical figures and dismiss their achievements. (Indeed, according to the Report cited below, “Some Task Force members questioned how ethical and consensual Huxley’s ethnological methodologies were and evaluated them as failing to meet the University’s contemporary standards for academic integrity [p. 5].” This is presentism at its worst.) The earlier PT article cited above gives the background to the current controversy. Since that article was published, however, the Legacy Review Task Force sent its report to the president, Sabah Randhawa. The “Recommendation Regarding Huxley College of the Environment” is Section 2.1 of the report and occupies pp. 5-13. The president’s cover letter, which we obtained from a faculty member, is noncommittal. The Summary section of the report says of Huxley,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Psittacula krameri</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Psittacula-krameri.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Psittacula krameri" /><published>2021-08-09T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-09T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Psittacula-krameri</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/08/Psittacula-krameri.html">&lt;p&gt;Ring necked parakeet, by &lt;strong&gt;Philip Abrams&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Abrams_Psittacula_krameri.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Parakeet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rspb.org.uk/birds-and-wildlife/wildlife-guides/bird-a-z/ring-necked-parakeet&quot;&gt; &lt;i&gt;Psittacula krameria&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, ring necked parakeet, photographed 27 June 2021, at the Royal Hospital, Chelsea, London SW3, United Kingdom. The photographer writes, &quot;Although they are not indigenous, there are estimated to be some 8600 breeding pairs in the UK, mostly in and around London. They are very noisy, and, often, quite tame and trusting! More info from the Royal Society for Protection of Birds (link, above).&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Ring necked parakeet, by Philip Abrams. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Psittacula krameria, ring necked parakeet, photographed 27 June 2021, at the Royal Hospital, Chelsea, London SW3, United Kingdom. The photographer writes, &quot;Although they are not indigenous, there are estimated to be some 8600 breeding pairs in the UK, mostly in and around London. They are very noisy, and, often, quite tame and trusting! More info from the Royal Society for Protection of Birds (link, above).&quot;</summary></entry></feed>