<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-09-25T00:24:56-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Worst. Book about the Scopes Trial. Ever!</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/worst-book-about.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Worst. Book about the Scopes Trial. Ever!" /><published>2024-09-19T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-19T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/worst-book-about</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/worst-book-about.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Branch_Worst_Book_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bryan being questioned by Darrow&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;William Jennings Bryan (left, seated) being questioned by Clarence Darrow at the Scopes Trial in Dayton, Tennessee. &lt;small&gt;Image from the Smithsonian Archives via &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Tennessee_v._John_T._Scopes_Trial-_Outdoor_proceedings_on_July_20,_1925,_showing_William_Jennings_Bryan_and_Clarence_Darrow._(2_of_4_photos)_(2898243103)_crop.jpg&quot;&gt; Wikimedia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Reprinted with permission from &lt;/i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/worst-book-about-the-scopes-trial-ever/&quot;&gt;Worst. Book about the Scopes Trial. Ever!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;, published on September 10, 2024, by &lt;/i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;Righting America&quot;&gt;Righting America&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;, a forum for scholarly conversation about Christianity, culture, and politics in the US.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Glenn Branch is deputy director of the National Center for Science Education, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as &lt;/i&gt;Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher&lt;i&gt;, and the &lt;/i&gt;Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics&lt;i&gt;, and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of &lt;/i&gt;Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools&lt;i&gt; (2006). He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the summer of 1925, a young teacher, John T. Scopes, was on trial in Dayton, Tennessee, for violating a recently enacted state law, the Butler Act, which forbade educators in the state&amp;rsquo;s public schools to &amp;ldquo;teach any theory that denies the truth of the Divine Creation of man as taught in the Bible, and to teach instead that man has descended from a lower order of animals.&amp;rdquo; The Scopes trial was instantly a national sensation, partly thanks to the participation of two national figures &amp;mdash; William Jennings Bryan on the prosecution team and Clarence Darrow on the defense team &amp;mdash; and the reportage of a third, the brilliant but mordant journalist H. L. Mencken. With its hundredth anniversary just around the corner, the Scopes trial is understandably attracting attention again, with recent treatments including Randy Moore&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomsbury.com/in/scopes-monkey-trial-9798216184171/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Scopes &amp;ldquo;Monkey Trial&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2022), Gregg Jarrett&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/The-Trial-of-the-Century/Gregg-Jarrett/9781982198572&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Trial of the Century&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2023), and Brenda Wineapple&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/648098/keeping-the-faith-by-brenda-wineapple/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Keeping the Faith&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2024). These are all more or less readable and accurate guides to the context, personalities, conduct, aftermath, and significance of the trial. And then, in contrast, there is Jerry Bergman&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://wipfandstock.com/9798385200887/the-other-side-of-the-scopes-monkey-trial/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Other Side of the Scopes Monkey Trial&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2023).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the thesis of &lt;em&gt;The Other Side of the Scopes Monkey Trial&lt;/em&gt;? According to its subtitle, &lt;em&gt;At Its Heart the Trial was about Racism,&lt;/em&gt; while within the text, Bergman awkwardly declaims, &amp;ldquo;The trial was about human evolution, and more about &lt;em&gt;racism and eugenics&lt;/em&gt; than religion and evolution&amp;rdquo; (p. 5, emphasis in original). Later, a section complaining that commentators on the trial ignore the racism and eugenics of both classroom textbooks and the American scientific community of the 1920s is entitled &amp;ldquo;Denying the Core of the Scopes Trial&amp;rdquo;; in the following chapter, Bergman writes, &amp;ldquo;That the teaching of eugenics was at issue in the Scopes Trial was obvious to those who understood what eugenics is all about is clear&amp;rdquo; (p. 61); and the chapter after that is entitled &amp;ldquo;The Scopes Trial: A Struggle Against Eugenics and Racism.&amp;rdquo; And in the final chapter, Bergman concludes, &amp;ldquo;The racism and eugenics that was central in the Scopes Trial has been ignored, even though it is a well-documented part of the record&amp;rdquo; (p. 195). Thus, although there is a certain perplexing vacillation between racism and eugenics, the book&amp;rsquo;s thesis appears to be that the Scopes trial was about these issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a glaring obstacle to the thesis, which in fact Bergman briefly acknowledges: that &amp;ldquo;in the entire Scopes court &lt;a href=&quot;https://profjoecain.net/scopes-monkey-trial-1925-complete-trial-transcripts/&quot;&gt;transcript&lt;/a&gt; the topic of eugenics and racism was avoided&amp;rdquo; (p. 81, link added). He then clutches at a counterfactual straw, suggesting that if Bryan, a prominent Democrat, had been a Republican, then he might have focused &amp;ldquo;on the racism and eugenics core of the Hunter textbook [&lt;em&gt;A Civic Biology&lt;/em&gt;, from which Scopes taught]&amp;rdquo; (p. 81). But as matters stand, the Scopes trial was clearly not about racism and eugenics. It is equally clear that a number of the participants in and observers of the Scopes trial held various attitudes toward racism and eugenics, which were matters of public controversy in the 1920s &amp;mdash; but there would be no point in writing a book to document the fact. Is there a thesis in the neighborhood that is neither clearly false nor clearly trivial? Perhaps that the attitudes toward racism and eugenics of the participants in and the observers of the trial significantly and substantially influenced the conduct of and the public understanding of the trial? That suggestion threads the needle, but it would require meticulously collected and judiciously assessed evidence to make the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No attempt to make such a case is visible in &lt;em&gt;The Other Side of the Scopes Monkey Trial&lt;/em&gt;, and meticulous collection and judicious assessment of evidence are likewise absent. Instead, there is hagiographizing, conspiracy theorizing, and mudslinging. For example, amid Bergman&amp;rsquo;s fulsome praise for Bryan, there is no mention of what his biographer Michael Kazin described in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/90625/a-godly-hero-by-michael-kazin/9780307424358/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Godly Hero&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2006) as &amp;ldquo;Bryan&amp;rsquo;s habit of ignoring the &amp;lsquo;race problem&amp;rsquo; or minimizing it with fatuous rationales,&amp;rdquo; which culminated with his last political &lt;a href=&quot;https://newrepublic.com/article/183009/craziest-convention-american-history&quot;&gt;success&lt;/a&gt;: convincing the 1924 Democratic National Convention not to adopt a party platform plank condemning the Ku Klux Klan by name. Bergman alleges that the leaders of the American Civil Liberties Union, which coordinated Scopes&amp;rsquo;s defense, &amp;ldquo;no doubt openly, or covertly, agreed to ignore the most important part of the Scopes case, namely its racism&amp;rdquo; (p. 74), a claim for which there is no rationale evident except for the need to protect his thesis come what may. Chapter 10, the longest chapter of the book, is a sustained attempt at assassinating the moral character of Mencken &amp;mdash; who, to be sure, was not exactly a paragon on matters of race, gender, and religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even independently of the fact that it consists entirely of a string of decontextualized quotations from Mencken&amp;rsquo;s voluminous oeuvre with Bergman&amp;rsquo;s perfunctory and sometimes bizarre comments on them, intended to portray Mencken as,&lt;em&gt; inter alia&lt;/em&gt;, a vicious racist, eugenicist, and bigot, chapter 10 is deeply problematic. The problem is that Bergman&amp;rsquo;s discussion is conspicuously similar to Vincent Torley&amp;rsquo;s 2012 blog post &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.angelfire.com/linux/vjtorley/mencken.html&quot;&gt;H. L. Mencken: Is this your hero, New Atheists?&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; &amp;mdash; not only in the selection and order of the quotations but also in the language used to summarize and criticize them. For example, Torley asks, with respect to a whimsical suggestion of Mencken&amp;rsquo;s that God should have used platinum rather than carbon as a basis for life, &amp;ldquo;But has Mencken even thought for a moment about how a platinum organism would eat, excrete, reproduce and for that matter, evolve?&amp;rdquo; while Bergman declares, &amp;ldquo;Mencken had obviously not thought about how platinum-based organisms could possibly eat, grow, excrete and, for that matter, evolve&amp;rdquo; (p. 161). Bergman cites Torley&amp;rsquo;s blog post only once (p. 128, n. 15), regrettably not in a way that adequately acknowledges his apparent debt to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bergman&amp;rsquo;s scholarly practices are otherwise troubling. He often cites subpar scholarship, including from his fellow creationists, without any evident discernment. He repeatedly interpolates unwarranted text of his own into verbatim quotations, including in a passage from Martin Gilbert&amp;rsquo;s history of the twentieth century (p. 9), a letter from Leonard Darwin &amp;mdash; a son of Charles Darwin, writing on behalf of the Eugenics Education Society &amp;mdash; to Scopes (p. 61), and a passage from Edward J. Larson&amp;rsquo;s book about the trial (p. 195). Similarly, he claims that &amp;ldquo;a survey of AAAS members found that close to 99 percent are functional atheists, meaning that they live their lives as if there is no God&amp;rdquo;: he is evidently referring to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/science/2015/07/23/an-elaboration-of-aaas-scientists-views/&quot;&gt;Pew Research Center&lt;/a&gt; survey in 2014 that found that close to 99 percent of members of the American Association for the Advancement of Science accept that humans have evolved over time: the &amp;ldquo;functional atheism&amp;rdquo; claim is a confabulation. He wrongly claims that the pistol-packing pastor J. Frank Norris came to Dayton, Tennessee, during the Scopes trial, citing &amp;ldquo;Larson, &amp;lsquo;Classroom Controversy,&amp;rsquo; 54&amp;rdquo;: the article in question begins on p. 63 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.press.jhu.edu/books/title/9326/pandas-black-box&quot;&gt;The Panda&amp;rsquo;s Black Box&lt;/a&gt; (2007) and Norris is not mentioned in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A particularly interesting error is not entirely Bergman&amp;rsquo;s fault. Relying on James Gilbert&amp;rsquo;s account in &lt;a href=&quot;https://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/R/bo3615369.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Redeeming Culture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (1997), he claims that Bryan argued to the West Virginia legislature in 1923 that evolution is precluded by the second law of thermodynamics. (He then proceeds to endorse the argument, unaware or uncaring that it is scientifically &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution-outreach.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1007/s12052-009-0195-3&quot;&gt;bankrupt&lt;/a&gt;.) That would be strange if true, not only because Bryan fails to use the argument in his most famous antievolution writings, such as &lt;em&gt;In His Image &lt;/em&gt;(1922) and his planned closing address in the Scopes trial, but also because the argument seems to have gained currency only with the work of two British creationists, Robert E. D. Clark and E. H. Betts, in the 1940s. (The wrinkle that the second law is the objective correlative of the Fall would later be introduced in &lt;em&gt;The Genesis Flood&lt;/em&gt; [1961], by John C. Whitcomb and Henry M. Morris.) But it is not true. And it would not have been difficult for Bergman to locate Bryan&amp;rsquo;s speech, reprinted as the second part of &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/OrthodoxChristianityVersusModernism&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Orthodox Christanity versus Modernism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (1923), and there to find that the closest Bryan approaches the second law of thermodynamics is invoking the distinct phenomenon of radioactive decay. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bergman repeatedly, and correctly, emphasizes that the Butler Act, under which Scopes was prosecuted, only concerned the teaching of human evolution. He accordingly devotes chapter 9 to a discussion of human evolution. The result is inaccurate and incompetent. He claims that the scientific evidence for human evolution presented at the Scopes trial consisted of &amp;ldquo;Nebraska Man, Piltdown Man, Java Man, and Neanderthal Man fossils&amp;rdquo; (p. 106), and devotes most of the chapter to &amp;ldquo;Nebraska Man,&amp;rdquo; repeating whole sentences and paragraphs in the process. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&quot;https://magazine.atavist.com/curious-case-of-nebraska-man-william-jennings-bryan-scopes-trial-evolution-creationism/&quot;&gt;Nebraska Man&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; was known only from what proved to be a fossil peccary tooth &amp;mdash; not, pace Bergman, a fossil pig tooth &amp;mdash; and was not presented at the Scopes trial, although it might have been if Henry Fairfield Osborn, the president of the American Museum of Natural History and the chief promoter of the fossil, had testified. Perhaps exhausted by his Nebraskan efforts, Bergman dismisses &amp;ldquo;Java Man&amp;rdquo; as &amp;ldquo;another race of humans called &lt;em&gt;Homo erectus&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; (p. 118) &amp;mdash; not exactly a devastating rejoinder &amp;mdash; and fails to rehearse the standard, long-ago-refuted, creationist complaints about &amp;ldquo;Piltdown Man&amp;rdquo; (a never tremendously convincing hoax) and Neanderthals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all of Bergman&amp;rsquo;s myriad errors are tendentious. Stephen Jay Gould is misquoted as referring to the &amp;ldquo;populace&amp;rdquo; rather than the &amp;ldquo;populist&amp;rdquo; thinking of Bryan (p. 26); the anthropologist Ruth Benedict is rechristened Ruth Bennet (p. 37); the polling organization Gallup departs at a gallop (p. 55). Bergman reports that &amp;ldquo;the Supreme Court refused to hear the Scopes appeal&amp;rdquo; (p. 103): if he&amp;rsquo;s thinking of the Tennessee Supreme Court, he&amp;rsquo;s wrong because the court indeed heard the appeal, overturning the verdict, while if he&amp;rsquo;s thinking of the United States Supreme Court, he&amp;rsquo;s wrong because the case was not appealed to it. Two paragraphs of chapter 12, which contains only six paragraphs, rely on the conclusions of &amp;ldquo;Georgianna,&amp;rdquo; with no full name or bibliographical information provided. (&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.proquest.com/openview/c8cd810026d7c7700ecda2d5ae839f8d/1?pq-origsite=gscholar&amp;amp;cbl=18750&amp;amp;diss=y&quot;&gt;The Moral Majority and Fundamentalism: Plausibility and Dissonance&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;rdquo; Sharon Linzey Georgianna&amp;rsquo;s 1984 dissertation at Indiana University, was presumably intended.) The sole appendix presents the text of a Tennessee law: not the Butler Act, but House Bill 368/Senate Bill 893 of 2012, nicknamed &amp;ldquo;the monkey bill&amp;rdquo; and codified as &lt;a href=&quot;https://law.justia.com/codes/tennessee/2021/title-49/chapter-6/part-10/section-49-6-1030/&quot;&gt;Tennessee Code 49-6-1030&lt;/a&gt;. No explanation is offered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early in &lt;em&gt;The Other Side of the Scopes Monkey Trial&lt;/em&gt;, Bergman writes, &amp;ldquo;The present work is an attempt to fill in this important gap&amp;rdquo; (p. 7). Characteristically, there is no explicit description of a gap in the preceding text, but he appears to mean that there&amp;rsquo;s a lack of discussions of the trial sympathetic to the prosecution, which overlooks any number of works, including Marvin Olasky and John Perry&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Monkey Business&lt;/em&gt; (2005), which appears in Bergman&amp;rsquo;s bibliography. A shoddy and biased apologia for creationism, &lt;em&gt;Monkey Business&lt;/em&gt; is nevertheless head and shoulders over &lt;em&gt;The Other Side of the Scopes Monkey Trial&lt;/em&gt;: not nearly so badly conceived, researched, organized, written, and edited. After offering his description of &amp;ldquo;the present work,&amp;rdquo; Bergman continues, &amp;ldquo;and it is up to readers to determine how successful this tome was&amp;rdquo; (p. 7) &amp;mdash; for all the world as if readers are unaware of their prerogatives. Only readers who are already relatively familiar with the trial are guaranteed to recognize the abject failure of the book, unfortunately; despite the crudity and incompetence of what can only be described as Bergman&amp;rsquo;s propaganda, there is a risk that the uninformed and the gullible will be misled.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Glenn Branch</name></author><summary type="html">William Jennings Bryan (left, seated) being questioned by Clarence Darrow at the Scopes Trial in Dayton, Tennessee. Image from the Smithsonian Archives via Wikimedia. Reprinted with permission from Worst. Book about the Scopes Trial. Ever!, published on September 10, 2024, by Righting America, a forum for scholarly conversation about Christianity, culture, and politics in the US. Glenn Branch is deputy director of the National Center for Science Education, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher, and the Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics, and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools (2006). He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers. In the summer of 1925, a young teacher, John T. Scopes, was on trial in Dayton, Tennessee, for violating a recently enacted state law, the Butler Act, which forbade educators in the state&amp;rsquo;s public schools to &amp;ldquo;teach any theory that denies the truth of the Divine Creation of man as taught in the Bible, and to teach instead that man has descended from a lower order of animals.&amp;rdquo; The Scopes trial was instantly a national sensation, partly thanks to the participation of two national figures &amp;mdash; William Jennings Bryan on the prosecution team and Clarence Darrow on the defense team &amp;mdash; and the reportage of a third, the brilliant but mordant journalist H. L. Mencken. With its hundredth anniversary just around the corner, the Scopes trial is understandably attracting attention again, with recent treatments including Randy Moore&amp;rsquo;s The Scopes &amp;ldquo;Monkey Trial&amp;rdquo; (2022), Gregg Jarrett&amp;rsquo;s The Trial of the Century (2023), and Brenda Wineapple&amp;rsquo;s Keeping the Faith (2024). These are all more or less readable and accurate guides to the context, personalities, conduct, aftermath, and significance of the trial. And then, in contrast, there is Jerry Bergman&amp;rsquo;s The Other Side of the Scopes Monkey Trial (2023). What is the thesis of The Other Side of the Scopes Monkey Trial? According to its subtitle, At Its Heart the Trial was about Racism, while within the text, Bergman awkwardly declaims, &amp;ldquo;The trial was about human evolution, and more about racism and eugenics than religion and evolution&amp;rdquo; (p. 5, emphasis in original). Later, a section complaining that commentators on the trial ignore the racism and eugenics of both classroom textbooks and the American scientific community of the 1920s is entitled &amp;ldquo;Denying the Core of the Scopes Trial&amp;rdquo;; in the following chapter, Bergman writes, &amp;ldquo;That the teaching of eugenics was at issue in the Scopes Trial was obvious to those who understood what eugenics is all about is clear&amp;rdquo; (p. 61); and the chapter after that is entitled &amp;ldquo;The Scopes Trial: A Struggle Against Eugenics and Racism.&amp;rdquo; And in the final chapter, Bergman concludes, &amp;ldquo;The racism and eugenics that was central in the Scopes Trial has been ignored, even though it is a well-documented part of the record&amp;rdquo; (p. 195). Thus, although there is a certain perplexing vacillation between racism and eugenics, the book&amp;rsquo;s thesis appears to be that the Scopes trial was about these issues.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Partial lunar eclipse</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/partial-lunar-eclipse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Partial lunar eclipse" /><published>2024-09-18T09:26:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-18T09:26:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/partial-lunar-eclipse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/partial-lunar-eclipse.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/DSC05907_Partial_Eclipse.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Partial eclipse&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeanddate.com/eclipse/in/usa/boulder?iso=20240918&quot;&gt;Partial lunar eclipse&lt;/a&gt; as seen from Boulder, Colorado, approximately 8:40 local time, yesterday. Also a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.space.com/harvest-moon-supermoon-lunar-eclipse-september-photos&quot;&gt;supermoon&lt;/a&gt;, but it was hard to tell with the naked eye. Not the best display ever, yet for some reason eclipses fascinate.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post, click below.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Partial lunar eclipse as seen from Boulder, Colorado, approximately 8:40 local time, yesterday. Also a supermoon, but it was hard to tell with the naked eye. Not the best display ever, yet for some reason eclipses fascinate. To see comments on this post, click below.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Araneus gemmoides</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/araneus-gemmoides.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Araneus gemmoides" /><published>2024-09-16T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-16T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/araneus-gemmoides</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/araneus-gemmoides.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;David Young&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spider courtesy of &lt;strong&gt;Alex Young&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Cat_Faced_Orb_Weaver_MG_1184_600.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Spider&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Araneus_gemmoides&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Araneus gemmoides&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; female cat-faced orb weaver. The abdomen is over 1&amp;nbsp;cm long. The photograph is upside down to emphasize the &quot;ears&quot; and the &quot;eyes.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

The underside of the spider is displayed below the fold.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Cat_Faced_Orb_Weaver_MG_1178_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spider&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by David Young. Spider courtesy of Alex Young. Araneus gemmoides &amp;ndash; female cat-faced orb weaver. The abdomen is over 1&amp;nbsp;cm long. The photograph is upside down to emphasize the &quot;ears&quot; and the &quot;eyes.&quot; The underside of the spider is displayed below the fold.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Artificial selection is not Intelligent Design</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/artificial.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Artificial selection is not Intelligent Design" /><published>2024-09-15T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-15T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/artificial</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/artificial.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/636px-Wm19342a.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[a nice image of fancy pigeons]&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;by Karl Wagner, from a major German encyclopedia, &lt;em&gt;Meyers Großes Konversations-Lexikon, Volume 19&lt;/em&gt;, published in 1909 in Leipzig.  From Wikimedia, figure in public domain.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When evolutionary biologists argue with creationists or 
advocates of Intelligent Design about the effectiveness 
of natural selection, the biologists often use the example of 
artificial selection.  And almost invariably, the 
ID advocate or creationist tries for a “gotcha” by 
saying “but artificial selection is an example of 
intelligent design, and is nothing like natural 
selection!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re going to go into why this is not a “gotcha” 
but is a mistaken analogy on their part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial selection is a very old practice, dating 
back to inadvertent selection when wild animals were 
domesticated, with the wildest ones being eaten or chased 
away, or they successfully escaped.  With the start of 
agriculture, farmers often bred from their best animals 
(or plants).   Charles Darwin paid close attention to 
the ways animals had been changed by breeding, both for 
food production or as pets.  He was particularly attentive 
to the results of pigeon breeding. “Natural selection” was named 
in analogy to artificial selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-much-design-is-in-design&quot;&gt;How much design is in Design?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saying that artificial selection is Intelligent Design is 
wrong because plant and animal breeders, until very recently, 
had no detailed understanding of the genomes of their 
organisms or how to make detailed changes in the genomes to 
affect the phenotype.  All they could do was to choose who 
to breed from, based on their phenotype (such as the amount 
of beef produced).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 20th century this got more sophisticated, but was still 
not Intelligent Design.  Real statisticians got involved, and 
selection was based on numerical indices computed from multiple 
characters.  I remember visiting a poultry breeding operation 
and hearing how they measured 10 characters, including not 
just the production characters but such important traits as 
susceptibility to viral disease.  This was in the 1970s, and 
they had a modest mainframe computer in their offices, with 
databases of traits.  It was the natural outcome of work in 
the 1930s and 1940s by quantitative-genetics-inspired animal 
breeders at such centers as Iowa State University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they did not know the detailed genetics of these traits. 
The selection still depended on observing the traits and not 
directly knowing any of the genetics, or much about the 
developmental biology of the traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on-to-intelligent-design&quot;&gt;On to Intelligent Design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the 2010s animal and plant breeding was entering a new 
era, though with difficulty.  In 2014 I was invited to give 
a talk (on natural selection) in Vancouver BC, at the 10th World 
Congress of Genetics Applied to Livestock Production.  I was 
talking about the mathematics of natural selection.  It was 
apparent from the muted audience response that this was now of lesser 
interest to people working on livestock production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead the hot topic of the Congress was QTLs – “quantitive trait 
loci” – how could they find individual genes whose alleles 
affected the production traits and disease resistance traits. 
If these could be found, they could be used by screening potential 
parents of the next generation, and maybe even by genetically 
engineering their genotypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that lots of effort is now going on towards 
entering this new era of genomics should be enough to make it clear 
that even thousands of years of animal and plant breeding, 
with lots of human intelligence applied, is not the same as 
Intelligent Design.   So the success of that history of breeding does 
say a lot about it as exemplifying the power of selection, 
without genetic engineering or even understanding the effects 
of changes in genotypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-comparable-example&quot;&gt;A comparable example&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It occurs to me that another similar flawed critique is 
when creationists and ID advocates argue that the success 
of Genetic Algorithms in solving engineering problems is 
irrelevant, because that is an example of Intelligent 
Design.  It isn’t, if the algorithm has random mutations, 
random recombinations, and random mating, with fitnesses based 
on the final phenotypes rather than on detailed knowledge 
of how they were achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In ID books such as Robert Marks, William Dembski, and 
Winston Ewert’s “Introduction to Evolutionary Informatics” there 
is a great effort to show that in simulations of 
natural selection, they only succeed because the design 
information is built in.  For example, in Richard Dawkins’s 
famous teaching example of the “Weasel”, the target phrase 
is part of the program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet in other cases, such as Dave Thomas’s genetic algorithm 
for a Traveling Salesman problem (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2006/07/target-target-w-1.html&quot;&gt;his 2006 post here at 
Panda’s Thumb&lt;/a&gt;
) no particular solution is built in.  All Marks, Dembski and 
Ewert could do was point to places where some fine-tuning of 
the algorithm had been made to make it more successful, but 
this is not the same as building in the answer to the particular 
problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So neither the success of animal and plant breeding, nor 
the success of genetic algorithms, can be sensibly attributed 
to Intelligent Design of the answers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">by Karl Wagner, from a major German encyclopedia, Meyers Großes Konversations-Lexikon, Volume 19, published in 1909 in Leipzig. From Wikimedia, figure in public domain. &amp;nbsp; When evolutionary biologists argue with creationists or advocates of Intelligent Design about the effectiveness of natural selection, the biologists often use the example of artificial selection. And almost invariably, the ID advocate or creationist tries for a “gotcha” by saying “but artificial selection is an example of intelligent design, and is nothing like natural selection!” We’re going to go into why this is not a “gotcha” but is a mistaken analogy on their part. Artificial selection is a very old practice, dating back to inadvertent selection when wild animals were domesticated, with the wildest ones being eaten or chased away, or they successfully escaped. With the start of agriculture, farmers often bred from their best animals (or plants). Charles Darwin paid close attention to the ways animals had been changed by breeding, both for food production or as pets. He was particularly attentive to the results of pigeon breeding. “Natural selection” was named in analogy to artificial selection.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NASA astronaut promotes Ark in space</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/nasa-astronaut-promotes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NASA astronaut promotes Ark in space" /><published>2024-09-08T13:50:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-08T13:50:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/nasa-astronaut-promotes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/nasa-astronaut-promotes.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Phelps_Ham_Astronaut_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ark Encounter swag in space&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Screenshot showing AIG products worn by astronaut Barry Wilmore in the International Space Station. &lt;small&gt;Source: AIG. Fair use.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronaut Barry “Butch” Wilmore is an ardent supporter of Answers in Genesis. Captain Wilmore is stuck, possibly until next year, on the International Space Station (ISS) because of concerns with the safety of the Boeing Starliner capsule. Apparently, Ken Ham will get tons of publicity from support by astronaut Wilmore, who can be seen wearing an Ark Encounter T-shirt and hat in the photo. Captain Wilmore has also taken separate photos of two different Ark baseball caps on the ISS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Ham is already hawking “as seen in space” merchandise promoting the Ark &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2024/08/30/as-seen-in-space/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. He writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;These “as seen in space” items are available on our online store or at the attractions.&lt;/strong&gt; It’s a fun way to promote the Ark and talk about a man who is bold in his witness for Jesus Christ and the truth of God’s Word from the very first verse, even while working as an astronaut with NASA.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost to send a payload to the ISS is about $10,000/lb, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/humans-in-space/commercial-and-marketing-pricing-policy/&quot;&gt;according to NASA&lt;/a&gt;. Moreover, it was probably much more expensive to send anything on the ill-fated Boeing Starliner. If the T-shirt weighs about 5 or 6 oz and the two caps combined weigh a similar amount, then the cost of getting them into orbit was around $8,000. Although NASA allows astronauts to have personal items, both NASA and the International Space Station have explicit guidelines for advertising.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/nasa-brand-center/advertising-guidelines/&quot;&gt;NASA’s guidelines&lt;/a&gt; appear to explicitly forbid Wilmore’s advertising for Answers in Genesis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Advertising and Marketing on the International Space Station &lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Commercials and other marketing filming/activity on the International Space Station authorized by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.nasa.gov/sites/default/files/atoms/files/s1701746119060610280_1.pdf&quot;&gt; NASA Interim Directive (NID) on Use of International Space Station (ISS) for Commercial and Marketing Activities&lt;/a&gt; are additionally subject to the following guidelines: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; NASA support in filming/capturing commercials or other marketing videos, which will occur behind the scenes, shall not be used to indicate or imply that NASA approves or endorses the requesting entity or its products, services, or enterprises. No commercials or promotional materials filmed on ISS may imply such approval or endorsement, nor may NASA stock images or footage be used in a way that does so. … &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.law.cornell.edu/cfr/text/14/1214.403&quot;&gt;rules for the ISS crew&lt;/a&gt; state:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; ISS crewmembers shall refrain from any use of the position of ISS crewmember that is motivated, or has the appearance of being motivated, by private gain, including financial gain, for himself or herself or other persons or entities. …&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Wilmore certainly gives the appearance of promoting the for-profit Ark Encounter and the non-profit Answers in Genesis ministry at US taxpayer expense. Ken Ham will probably make a lot of money off the shirt and cap sales. I predict that NASA and the ISS will ignore this apparent violation of their own rules to avoid negative publicity and pushback from AIG’s supporters. Mr. Ham and AIG once again triumph in getting a benefit from the taxpayer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Screenshot showing AIG products worn by astronaut Barry Wilmore in the International Space Station. Source: AIG. Fair use. Astronaut Barry “Butch” Wilmore is an ardent supporter of Answers in Genesis. Captain Wilmore is stuck, possibly until next year, on the International Space Station (ISS) because of concerns with the safety of the Boeing Starliner capsule. Apparently, Ken Ham will get tons of publicity from support by astronaut Wilmore, who can be seen wearing an Ark Encounter T-shirt and hat in the photo. Captain Wilmore has also taken separate photos of two different Ark baseball caps on the ISS. Mr. Ham is already hawking “as seen in space” merchandise promoting the Ark here. He writes: These “as seen in space” items are available on our online store or at the attractions. It’s a fun way to promote the Ark and talk about a man who is bold in his witness for Jesus Christ and the truth of God’s Word from the very first verse, even while working as an astronaut with NASA.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hexagonaria</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/hexagonaria.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hexagonaria" /><published>2024-09-02T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-02T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/hexagonaria</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/hexagonaria.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;James Kocher&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Photo Contest_JamesKocher_Hexagonaria.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hexagonaria&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hexagonaria&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Hexagonaria davidsoni&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; in-situ Upper Devonian fossilized coral, Middle/Upper Devonian Callaway Limestone, ~350 Ma, Dry Fork Creek, Mark Twain National Forest (Cedar Creek Section), Callaway County, MO. The northern red oak (&lt;i&gt;Quercus rubra&lt;/i&gt;) leaf is for scale. See also &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lakeneosho.org/MissouriFossils/Publication.html&quot;&gt;Missouri Fossils&lt;/a&gt;, by Bruce L. Stinchcomb.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by James Kocher. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Hexagonaria davidsoni &amp;ndash; in-situ Upper Devonian fossilized coral, Middle/Upper Devonian Callaway Limestone, ~350 Ma, Dry Fork Creek, Mark Twain National Forest (Cedar Creek Section), Callaway County, MO. The northern red oak (Quercus rubra) leaf is for scale. See also Missouri Fossils, by Bruce L. Stinchcomb.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dan Phelps lecture on Kentucky Fossils</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/dan-phelps-lecture.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dan Phelps lecture on Kentucky Fossils" /><published>2024-09-01T12:25:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-01T12:25:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/dan-phelps-lecture</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/09/dan-phelps-lecture.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Phelps_Edrioasteroid.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dan Phelps showing a slide&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Slightly underexposed Dan Phelps showing a slide of his &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edrioasteroidea&quot;&gt;favorite fossil&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Fans of Dan Phelps may be interested in his lecture on Kentucky Fossils as part of the Frankfort (Kentucky) Heritage Lecture Series. You may see the lecture, which was delivered on August 27 and is about 90 min long, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=x2sfqhPodQQ&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
According to the Lecture Series notes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This presentation [was] an overview of the various types of fossils found in Kentucky, discussing specimens from the Late Ordovician (450 million years ago) to the Pleistocene (ending about 12,000 years ago). There will be numerous fossil specimens on display before and after the talk. The public is encouraged to bring in local fossils for identification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniel J. Phelps is a native of Lexington and a retired environmental geologist with degrees from the University of Kentucky. Besides his environmental work, he has been employed as a petroleum and coal geologist. Additionally, Dan has taught part-time in Kentucky’s Community College system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Slightly underexposed Dan Phelps showing a slide of his favorite fossil. Fans of Dan Phelps may be interested in his lecture on Kentucky Fossils as part of the Frankfort (Kentucky) Heritage Lecture Series. You may see the lecture, which was delivered on August 27 and is about 90 min long, here. According to the Lecture Series notes, This presentation [was] an overview of the various types of fossils found in Kentucky, discussing specimens from the Late Ordovician (450 million years ago) to the Pleistocene (ending about 12,000 years ago). There will be numerous fossil specimens on display before and after the talk. The public is encouraged to bring in local fossils for identification. Daniel J. Phelps is a native of Lexington and a retired environmental geologist with degrees from the University of Kentucky. Besides his environmental work, he has been employed as a petroleum and coal geologist. Additionally, Dan has taught part-time in Kentucky’s Community College system. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creationist astronomer calculates age of the Flood from Utah arch collapse</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/creationist-astronomer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creationist astronomer calculates age of the Flood from Utah arch collapse" /><published>2024-08-24T08:50:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-08-24T08:50:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/creationist-astronomer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/creationist-astronomer.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Van_Den_Bos_Arch_Detail_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Delicate Arch&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;An arch that has not collapsed: Delicate Arch in Utah. &lt;small&gt;Detail of photograph by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/person-in-black-jacket-and-blue-denim-jeans-sitting-on-brown-rock-formation-during-daytime-uDKqTcWDc6U&quot;&gt;Mike van den Bos&lt;/a&gt; on Unsplash.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/geology/how-long-have-arches-been-around/&quot;&gt;How Long Have Arches Been Around?&lt;/a&gt;, by &lt;i&gt;Dr&lt;/i&gt;. Danny Faulkner, describes creationist “research” into geomorphology. It is laughably bad, even for creationists. Natural arches and bridges are aesthetically interesting, but are only a tiny part of some geomorphology studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this piece, Dr. Faulkner* extrapolates backward to “show” that arches in Arches National Park, Utah, have formed since Noah’s Flood, about 4,500 years ago. He claims this timeframe because of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Biblical literalism. Employees of Answers in Genesis must sign a &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/about/faith/&quot;&gt;Statement of Faith&lt;/a&gt; that posits that the earth and universe are 6,000 years old, and that most geology is a result of Noah’s Flood, approximately 4,500 years ago. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;An exponential rate of arch collapse.  Faulkner states he doesn’t use a linear decline in numbers of arches because no arches would remain after 4,500 years. No consideration is given to the possibility of much longer time scales, or changes in climate and erosion rates. Change in regional climates over time is ignored, possibly because the young earth creationists at AIG cram the nearly 2 million years of Pleistocene glacial maxima into a single ice age of only 200 years after the Flood. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conveniently, AiG uses this denial of the Pleistocene to also ignore evidence for past climate changes and the evidence scientists use to support anthropogenic climate change in the present. Faulkner has invented his model by assuming that an exponential model is the best for arch collapse, and then he fits things assuming the rate is 43 arches in 29 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, his scholarship is abysmally shoddy. Conceivably, it would be possible to make a plot of cumulative arches lost vs. time. This would be a more accurate method for modeling. However, Faulkner just assumes the loss rate was constant (a cumulative arches-vs.-time chart would show the accuracy of that assumption).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also seems to assume that the collapse of arches in Utah is related solely to the minerals cementing the sandstone that the arches are formed from. He doesn’t document any effort to examine records to see if any collapses were associated with long term climate changes, intense storms, seismic events, vandalism, and innumerable other possible causes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faulkner also assumes a uniform rate of arch formation. He then uses his model and that assumption to show that, in his view, there would have been an implausible number of arches if the Earth were as old as earth scientists claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All his equations are a smoke screen, an appeal to look like scientific research when religious apologetics is what is actually being presented. In short, this is a parody of how science is actually done. The 4,500 year time frame and the Flood are required by AIG’s  peculiar version of a “Biblical Worldview,” which is more than a bit of a science stopper and a weird excuse to start with creationist conclusions and work backwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Faulkner oddly discusses Kentucky arches in Red River Gorge in addition to Arches National Park, but cannot do a similar calculation for the Kentucky arches, as arch collapse here in Kentucky has not been documented. The reported observations in Kentucky are another smoke screen in the article, basically a non sequitur. The discovery/documentation rate of arches in Kentucky has no bearing on their rate of formation or collapse (and the same holds for Utah).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Faulkner’s apparent assumption of the evolution of arches from formation to collapse is naive. Surely, the height, span, and dimensions of the suspended material are factors to consider. Not all arches are formed in the same fashion: some are formed by wind or water erosion; some by collapse. Not all arches are in the same topographic position: some are isolated and exposed on points; some are parallel to cliff faces. The relationship to and importance of natural fracturing differs among arches. If Dr. Faulkner considered these factors, he didn’t document his efforts. Our assumption is that he was unaware of these complications or deliberately chose to ignore them (and didn’t document why he did so).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nonscientific method used by Answers in Genesis “researchers” results in the publication of materials that don’t reflect reality very well; yet AiG’s conclusions are held by millions of our fellow citizens. Faulkner’s piece is a &lt;i&gt;dazzle-them-with-sciency-sounding-stuff faux research that confirms AIG and their audience’s preexisting biases&lt;/i&gt;. The public deserves better. It should be part of our job as earth scientists to do a better job of explaining science to the public&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Faulkner’s Ph.D. is in astronomy; he works as a researcher for Answers in Genesis. He has some family ties to the region and occasionally has led paid AIG creationist hiking tours of Red River Gorge and its arches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix&lt;/strong&gt;. If you are interested in Kentucky geology, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uky.edu/KGS/geoky/fieldtrip/2005%20NaturalBridge%20red%20river%20gorge%20guide.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uky.edu/KGS/geoky/fieldtrip/2010%20Guidebook%20natural%20bridge%20guidebook.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; are field guides to the Red River Gorge area written by geologists (and you can use these guidebooks to visit the public sites for free!). The Kentucky Geological Survey has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://kgs.uky.edu/arches/&quot;&gt;project and map service&lt;/a&gt; dedicated to Kentucky arches for the hiking public. (Arches on private land are generally excluded from this database.)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps and Brandon Nuttall</name></author><summary type="html">An arch that has not collapsed: Delicate Arch in Utah. Detail of photograph by Mike van den Bos on Unsplash. This article, How Long Have Arches Been Around?, by Dr. Danny Faulkner, describes creationist “research” into geomorphology. It is laughably bad, even for creationists. Natural arches and bridges are aesthetically interesting, but are only a tiny part of some geomorphology studies. In this piece, Dr. Faulkner* extrapolates backward to “show” that arches in Arches National Park, Utah, have formed since Noah’s Flood, about 4,500 years ago. He claims this timeframe because of Biblical literalism. Employees of Answers in Genesis must sign a Statement of Faith that posits that the earth and universe are 6,000 years old, and that most geology is a result of Noah’s Flood, approximately 4,500 years ago. An exponential rate of arch collapse. Faulkner states he doesn’t use a linear decline in numbers of arches because no arches would remain after 4,500 years. No consideration is given to the possibility of much longer time scales, or changes in climate and erosion rates. Change in regional climates over time is ignored, possibly because the young earth creationists at AIG cram the nearly 2 million years of Pleistocene glacial maxima into a single ice age of only 200 years after the Flood.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Buteo lineatus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/buteo-lineatus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buteo lineatus" /><published>2024-08-19T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-08-19T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/buteo-lineatus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/buteo-lineatus.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Ole Lundin&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Lundin_Buteo_lineatus.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Red-shouldered hawk&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.audubon.org/field-guide/bird/red-shouldered-hawk&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Buteo lineatus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; red-shouldered hawk, observed in back yard, Durham, NC, December, 2014. Mr. Lundin writes, &quot;I like this one for the angle of view (slightly downward), and the background coloration that matches the hawk's coloration. This hawk was undoubtedly preying on the colony of rabbits inhabiting the brush in my back yard.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Ole Lundin. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Buteo lineatus &amp;ndash; red-shouldered hawk, observed in back yard, Durham, NC, December, 2014. Mr. Lundin writes, &quot;I like this one for the angle of view (slightly downward), and the background coloration that matches the hawk's coloration. This hawk was undoubtedly preying on the colony of rabbits inhabiting the brush in my back yard.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tax-exempt AIG attacks Presidential candidate, may be reported to IRS</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/heres-what-people-need.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tax-exempt AIG attacks Presidential candidate, may be reported to IRS" /><published>2024-08-14T18:07:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-08-14T18:07:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/heres-what-people-need</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/08/heres-what-people-need.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Ham_Video_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ken Ham on his video&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Ken Ham on YouTube assuring us that a fertilized egg is a human being.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The original title of this article, borrowed (as you may infer) from Ken Ham, was &quot;Here's What People NEED To Know about Ken Ham.&quot; That title now seems too cute and did not seem to give the article much traction, so we have taken the unusual step of changing it to the present, more descriptive title. The URL remains the same. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ken Ham, on a YouTube video entitled “&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/1aGZoJCdCpo?si=8iLpBwawPiOYOYbE&quot;&gt;Here’s What People NEED to Realize about Kamala Harris&lt;/a&gt;” and specifically credited to Answers in Genesis, explicitly attacks Vice President and presidential candidate Kamala Harris for her views on abortion and other matters. The video received around 150,000 views in a day or so. AIG writes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;In this short video, Ken Ham speaks on the recent political ideologies of Kamala, sharing his perspective on them as a Bible-believing Christian.&quot; [Note how he infantilizes her by using her first name only.]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our colleague Dan Phelps, who sent us this link, asks, “How is AIG, a ministry, still tax exempt?” He notes that AIG’s shell company, Ark Encounter, gets $1.825 million per year in sales tax rebates from Kentucky Tourism and is advertised for free by the taxpayer-supported “Kentucky Faith Trail.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Phelps suggests that you can complain to the IRS using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/f13909.pdf&quot;&gt;Form 13909, Tax-Exempt Organization Complaint (Referral)&lt;/a&gt;. It is not clear whether the IRS will take any action, but a few complaints cannot hurt. AIG’s street address is Answers in Genesis, 2800 Bullittsburg Church Rd., Petersburg, KY 41080, and their EIN, or Employer Identification Number, is 33-0596423.  You need to send a cover letter along with the form, but both may be e-mailed to the address at the bottom of page 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IRS form asks you for “Who/What/Where/When/How you learned about and obtained the information in this report.” I do not know precisely what approach to take, beyond that Mr. Ham runs a tax-exempt religious organization, which he considers a ministry, and in this video he is implicitly campaigning against Kamala Harris. Perhaps this line of reasoning can be fleshed out in the comments to this post. The URL of the video is https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1aGZoJCdCpo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you have the illusion that Mr. Ham is not electioneering, I can assure you that his minions think otherwise. Consider, for example, these (admittedly cherry-picked) comments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;We have had four years of warning. It’s time to vote her OUT!&quot; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Thanks Ken for being bold enough to say the truth about this election. Glory be to God in the Highest!&quot; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;I can barely stand to listen to her. God help us all if she gets to be president.&quot; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &quot;It’s time the we Christians vote politicians like this out of office and keep them out of our political arena..&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;I pray EVERY Christian goes out and votes this November. Pray and Vote. We cannot tolerate this evil any longer. Thank you AIG for making things so clear.&quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A majority of the comments merely pray for our lost souls and whatnot, but comments such as these clearly show that many, if not most, listeners recognize Mr. Ham’s true intention.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Ken Ham on YouTube assuring us that a fertilized egg is a human being. The original title of this article, borrowed (as you may infer) from Ken Ham, was &quot;Here's What People NEED To Know about Ken Ham.&quot; That title now seems too cute and did not seem to give the article much traction, so we have taken the unusual step of changing it to the present, more descriptive title. The URL remains the same. Ken Ham, on a YouTube video entitled “Here’s What People NEED to Realize about Kamala Harris” and specifically credited to Answers in Genesis, explicitly attacks Vice President and presidential candidate Kamala Harris for her views on abortion and other matters. The video received around 150,000 views in a day or so. AIG writes, &quot;In this short video, Ken Ham speaks on the recent political ideologies of Kamala, sharing his perspective on them as a Bible-believing Christian.&quot; [Note how he infantilizes her by using her first name only.] Our colleague Dan Phelps, who sent us this link, asks, “How is AIG, a ministry, still tax exempt?” He notes that AIG’s shell company, Ark Encounter, gets $1.825 million per year in sales tax rebates from Kentucky Tourism and is advertised for free by the taxpayer-supported “Kentucky Faith Trail.” Mr. Phelps suggests that you can complain to the IRS using Form 13909, Tax-Exempt Organization Complaint (Referral). It is not clear whether the IRS will take any action, but a few complaints cannot hurt. AIG’s street address is Answers in Genesis, 2800 Bullittsburg Church Rd., Petersburg, KY 41080, and their EIN, or Employer Identification Number, is 33-0596423. You need to send a cover letter along with the form, but both may be e-mailed to the address at the bottom of page 1. The IRS form asks you for “Who/What/Where/When/How you learned about and obtained the information in this report.” I do not know precisely what approach to take, beyond that Mr. Ham runs a tax-exempt religious organization, which he considers a ministry, and in this video he is implicitly campaigning against Kamala Harris. Perhaps this line of reasoning can be fleshed out in the comments to this post. The URL of the video is https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1aGZoJCdCpo. In case you have the illusion that Mr. Ham is not electioneering, I can assure you that his minions think otherwise. Consider, for example, these (admittedly cherry-picked) comments:</summary></entry></feed>