<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-03-22T11:38:54-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Understanding Evolution: Book Review</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/understanding-evolution.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding Evolution: Book Review" /><published>2021-03-17T13:29:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-03-17T13:29:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/understanding-evolution</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/understanding-evolution.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Kampourakis_Cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book is entitled &lt;em&gt;Understanding Evolution&lt;/em&gt;, but it is perhaps as much about &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; understanding &lt;em&gt;of&lt;/em&gt; evolution and why some people do not understand it or refuse to understand it. In this essay, I concentrate  on “the understanding of,” or what I might call the meta-evolution parts of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the second edition of the book; &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2014/04/now-book-on-und.html&quot;&gt;John Wilkins reviewed the first on PT&lt;/a&gt; in 2014. It is a short book, well under 200 pages and 8 chapters, counting the unnumbered Concluding Remarks. The book is generally easy to read, with one exception that I shall note below. The early chapters especially have a lot of useful figures, mostly well annotated and well captioned. Many of them suffer from being in black and white, and look like they were originally prepared in color but never seriously adapted to black and white. The book ends with a useful summary of common misconceptions about evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to categorize this book. The first three chapters concern the public acceptance of evolution, religious resistance to accepting evolution, and conceptual obstacles to understanding evolution. The fourth chapter gives a detailed example of Darwin’s “conceptual change,” in order to provide a description of someone gradually coming to accept evolution, as Darwin progressed from natural theology to natural selection. I was relieved that he showed a picture of Darwin more or less in his prime, rather than the somewhat conventional picture of an elderly man with a big white beard. I worry, though, that he may give too much attention to Darwin; creationists can mislead people into thinking that Darwin is our messiah and that evolutionary biology is a religion that has not shown any progress since 1859. Nothing, of course, could be farther from the truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next two chapters describe common ancestry and evolutionary processes. Though neither chapter is particularly difficult, they were in some ways written for biologists or biology students; this layperson could easily keep track of homologies and homoplasies, but began to slow down on apomorphies, plesiomorphies, synapomorphies, and symplesiomorphies. On the other hand, simple examples, such as the evolution of the name Nathan or the gradual transmutation of a pizza shop into a cookie shop, suggest that the book was written for laypersons, or at least for scientists in other disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final (numbered) chapter concerns the nature of science and includes a certain amount of philosophy of science, some of which was familiar, some not. The chapter demonstrates what Dr. Kampourakis calls the virtues of evolutionary theory, which include not only internal consistency, but also consistency with other theories such as physics and chemistry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book says a great deal about creationism and the reasons people resist evolution. In chapter 1, after critiquing the way the Gallup and Pew polls asked their questions, Dr. Kampourakis turns to religious resistance to evolution. In particular, after informing us of the truism that not all religious people are creationists, he plots a graph (Figure 1.9) showing that people who are &lt;i&gt;unsure&lt;/i&gt; about evolution are more or less equally distributed among countries that are “more religious” and “less religious.” This conclusion is partly in contrast to the conventional wisdom that acceptance of evolution correlates negatively with religious belief (Figure 1.7). Here, despite an earlier, broader definition of creationism, and for the purpose of this discussion, Dr. Kampourakis limits “creationist” to mean anyone who thinks that humans were created in their present form within the last 10,000 years (page 10); doing so may classify some Biblical literalists (&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/03/be-very-very-careful.html&quot;&gt;Gerald Schroeder&lt;/a&gt; comes to mind) among theistic evolutionists, and may skew some of his results in one direction or the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second chapter, Dr. Kampourakis engages in a little epistemology. He makes a clear distinction between what you believe and what you know; I would add to that what you feel. He writes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What matters for science is to have strong empirical grounding for our beliefs. Beyond this, one should believe what one wants.…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is in my view where the problem of religious resistance to the acceptance of evolution lies, at least in part. People do not easily distinguish between what they know and what they believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly many people confuse knowledge with belief, but I cannot agree that you should or even may believe whatever you want. I think, rather, that it is appropriate to think scientifically, so to speak, about even your nonrational beliefs. In particular, we do not &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; there is a god. We can adduce some evidence in favor of a god, but none of it, to my mind, is dispositive. When we say we believe in God, therefore, we really mean we &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; there is a god (seemingly inconsistent capitalization deliberate). Whether God interfered in any way with evolution is even more problematic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Kampourakis concludes that people’s skepticism or uncertainty about evolution is not directly related to their religion or lack of religion. Rather, he says that we are bound by our intuitions and, among other things, conflate living organisms with human artifacts. Especially, we think that parts of organisms, if not organisms themselves, must have been provided for a purpose (wings are for flying). We thus see teleology where none exists. (That, of course, depends on how good your intuition is.) For this reason, Dr. Kampourakis warns against using the metaphor of design in biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Dr. Kampourakis argues that we tend toward essentialism or, more precisely, psychological essentialism (as opposed to philosophical). In other words, we perceive that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[c]ertain categories are real rather than human constructions, and they possess an underlying essence, which is responsible for why category members are the way they are and share so many properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, as a creationist might put it, “It is still a monkey!” Such thinking makes us resist the idea that one species can transmute into another, because the presumably fixed essences would have to change. In addition, essentialism may make us unaware of the very significant variation within a single species; this variation is often what drives evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a person who has occasionally been accused of scientism (a red herring if ever there was one!), I greatly appreciated the final chapter on the nature of science. In addition to a good introduction to the philosophy of science, Dr. Kampourakis introduces us to the limits of scientific thinking and concludes that some topics, such as the existence or nonexistence of God, are beyond the reach of science. I am inclined to agree with him, but I think that we can apply scientific thinking to the question, as discussed above. A discussion of theodicy may or may not have been appropriate here; the word appears only once, in the chapter on religious resistance, and is defined incorrectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read the book on a Kindle Paperwhite. The figures were extremely difficult, and I had to view many of them on a computer. I thought surely that the figures in the print edition would be in color, but the Look Inside feature on Amazon showed only black and white. The graphs were intelligible, though mostly the font was too small. Many were bar graphs with two or more data sets. Some, in particular, Figure 1.9, mentioned above, may have been better as conventional line graphs, showing data points connected by line segments. Figures such as Figure 6.1, adaptation vs. exaptation, or 6.3, selection &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; vs. selection &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt;, while excellent figures, simply do not work well in black and white, especially with gray backgrounds. Those, among others, should have been revised so as to display better contrast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have only briefly touched upon some of the contents of this fine book. For more, I am afraid that you will have to acquire the book for yourselves.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Deanna Young and Glenn Branch read this review and made a very significant number of helpful comments.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">This book is entitled Understanding Evolution, but it is perhaps as much about the understanding of evolution and why some people do not understand it or refuse to understand it. In this essay, I concentrate on “the understanding of,” or what I might call the meta-evolution parts of the book. This is the second edition of the book; John Wilkins reviewed the first on PT in 2014. It is a short book, well under 200 pages and 8 chapters, counting the unnumbered Concluding Remarks. The book is generally easy to read, with one exception that I shall note below. The early chapters especially have a lot of useful figures, mostly well annotated and well captioned. Many of them suffer from being in black and white, and look like they were originally prepared in color but never seriously adapted to black and white. The book ends with a useful summary of common misconceptions about evolution.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">House Resolution Concerning Pi Day</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/house-resolution.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="House Resolution Concerning Pi Day" /><published>2021-03-15T20:15:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-03-15T20:15:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/house-resolution</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/house-resolution.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Pi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;100 digits of pi&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;center&gt;3.1415926535897932384626433832795028841971693993751058209&lt;br /&gt;
  749445923078164062862089986280348253421170679, etc.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, March 14, was Pi Day, and I learned today that several representatives introduced a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.congress.gov/117/bills/hres221/BILLS-117hres221ih.pdf&quot;&gt;RESOLUTION Expressing support for designation of March 14, 2021, as “National Pi Day”&lt;/a&gt;. I thought it was a good resolution, and it concluded,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Whereas Pi can be approximated as 3.14, and thus March 14, 2021, is an appropriate day for &quot;National Pi Day&quot;: Now, therefore, be it &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;i&gt;Resolved&lt;/i&gt;, That the House of Representatives— &lt;br /&gt;

(1) supports the designation of a &quot;Pi Day&quot; and its celebration around the world; &lt;br /&gt;

(2) recognizes the continuing importance of the National Science Foundation’s math and science education programs; &lt;br /&gt;

and (3) encourages schools and educators to observe the day with appropriate activities that teach students about Pi and engage them about the study of mathematics.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bill was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.congress.gov/bill/117th-congress/house-resolution/221/all-info&quot;&gt;introduced on March 11&lt;/a&gt;, which gave them 3 days to pass it. Guess where the bill is now….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… In committee.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">3.1415926535897932384626433832795028841971693993751058209 749445923078164062862089986280348253421170679, etc. Yesterday, March 14, was Pi Day, and I learned today that several representatives introduced a RESOLUTION Expressing support for designation of March 14, 2021, as “National Pi Day”. I thought it was a good resolution, and it concluded, Whereas Pi can be approximated as 3.14, and thus March 14, 2021, is an appropriate day for &quot;National Pi Day&quot;: Now, therefore, be it Resolved, That the House of Representatives— (1) supports the designation of a &quot;Pi Day&quot; and its celebration around the world; (2) recognizes the continuing importance of the National Science Foundation’s math and science education programs; and (3) encourages schools and educators to observe the day with appropriate activities that teach students about Pi and engage them about the study of mathematics. The bill was introduced on March 11, which gave them 3 days to pass it. Guess where the bill is now….</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ardea herodias and ardea alba</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/ardea-herodias-alba.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ardea herodias and ardea alba" /><published>2021-03-15T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-03-15T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/ardea-herodias-alba</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/ardea-herodias-alba.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Paul Burnett&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Burnett.Heron.Egret.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Heron and egret&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_blue_heron&quot;&gt;Ardea herodias&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_egret&quot;&gt;Ardea alba&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; great blue heron and great egret, studiously ignoring each other, San Francisco Bay, off Crown Beach, Alameda, California.
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Paul Burnett. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Ardea herodias and Ardea alba &amp;ndash; great blue heron and great egret, studiously ignoring each other, San Francisco Bay, off Crown Beach, Alameda, California.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creationism, accreditation, and the rules of evidence</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/creationism-accreditation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creationism, accreditation, and the rules of evidence" /><published>2021-03-08T08:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-03-08T08:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/creationism-accreditation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/creationism-accreditation.html">&lt;p&gt;Last month I argued  that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.snopes.com/news/2021/02/04/why-creationism-bears-all-the-hallmarks-of-a-conspiracy-theory/&quot;&gt;present-day creationism is a conspiracy theory&lt;/a&gt;, that like other conspiracy theories, it has its own rules of evidence, and that one underlying driver for this conspiracy theory is a struggle for power. Two recent developments give substance to my claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, regarding the rules of evidence. We are familiar with the creationist claim that ancient-earth geology and the related studies such as the fossil record are mere historical sciences, based on unproven and unprovable assumptions about unrepeatable past events, whereas the scientific method requires reproducibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The errors here are obvious. The observations must, circumstances permitting, be reproducible, but the past event inferred need not be. For example, recent DNA evidence established that the father of the Archbishop of Canterbury was not the person named on his birth certificate. We can test this conclusion, to the highest scientific standards, by repeating the DNA test, but there is no need to beget additional Archbishops to prove our point. We do indeed assume, with Hutton, that the present is the key to the past, but this assumption is itself the result of repeated observation. We can see rain splashes in billion-year-old mudstone and rounded pebbles in ancient riverbeds. The resemblance between past and present is not, as creationists claim, an input into interpretation but an outcome of observation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this month the world’s most noted creationist organisation has gone even further.  In a piece titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/apologetics/critical-thinking/thinking-critically-ape-man-messages/&quot;&gt;Thinking Critically About “Ape-Man” Messages&lt;/a&gt;, Patricia Engler of Answers in Genesis tells us “how to sort through such claims with biblical, critical thinking.” Her recommended procedure is dramatically effective: “The first way to detect a lie is by comparing it to the truth, with the ultimate standard for truth being God’s Word.” Unsurprisingly, this leads her to conclude, “Hominid claims fail this test.” The first test for truth, she tells us, is correspondence with AiG’s views. Whatever does not correspond to these views is not true. The insulation from criticism is perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted find out more about Ms Engler, but Answers in Genesis tells us &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/bios/patricia-engler/&quot;&gt;tantalizingly little&lt;/a&gt;. We are told that after 12 years homeschooling, she completed a BSc with distinction at a liberal arts college, where “she studied intensely evolutionary courses to learn firsthand how Christian students can navigate secular education without compromising their biblical worldview,” but we are not told the subject matter of her BSc nor the identity of the college where she acquired these navigational skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the role of power in creationism, we have an example this week, when the Transnational Association of Christian Colleges and Schools (Tracs) will have the status of its accreditations reviewed by the Council for Higher Education Accreditation. Joshua Swamidass has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/a-compromise-on-creationism-11614901537&quot;&gt;discussed the issues concerned in the Wall Street Journal&lt;/a&gt;, and Panda’s Thumb has covered Dr. Swamidass’s article &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/should-colleges-that-teach.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I discuss Tracs as an instrument of power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to be accredited by Tracs, an institution must, &lt;a href=&quot;https://tracs.org/resources/&quot;&gt;as their website makes plain&lt;/a&gt; submit a Faith Statement which&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;should identify it as part of the evangelical protestant tradition in higher education. It is to be written so as to conform to the historic creeds and statements of Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As to what those historic creeds and statements may be, they would seem to require compatibility with at least the spirit of Tracs’s own &lt;a href=&quot;https://tracs.org/statement-of-faith/&quot;&gt;Statement of Faith&lt;/a&gt;, which concludes with the following statements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Biblical Creation&lt;/strong&gt;. Special creation of the existing space-time universe and all its basic systems and kinds of organisms in the six literal days of the creation week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Satan&lt;/strong&gt;. The existence of a personal, malevolent being called Satan who acts as tempter and accuser, for whom the place of eternal punishment was prepared, where all who die outside of Christ shall be confined in conscious torment for eternity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Readers may remember that Charles Darwin, in his Autobiography, expressed his repugnance towards the “damnable doctrine” of punishment of unbelievers, and that his widow wished to suppress his remarks on the grounds that &lt;a href=&quot;http://darwin-online.org.uk/content/frameset?itemID=F1497&amp;amp;viewtype=side&amp;amp;pageseq=89&quot;&gt;surely nobody really believed anything of the sort any more&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My present concern, however, is not with the content of this Statement of Faith, but with Tracs’s enforcement of it. Since its inception, Christianity has given rise to endless differences of doctrine and interpretation. Yet Tracs claims the right to determine which particular doctrines and interpretations an institution must adhere to, and which historic creeds and statements it must accept, before it will recognize that institution as Christian. Power indeed!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman</name></author><summary type="html">Last month I argued that present-day creationism is a conspiracy theory, that like other conspiracy theories, it has its own rules of evidence, and that one underlying driver for this conspiracy theory is a struggle for power. Two recent developments give substance to my claim. Firstly, regarding the rules of evidence. We are familiar with the creationist claim that ancient-earth geology and the related studies such as the fossil record are mere historical sciences, based on unproven and unprovable assumptions about unrepeatable past events, whereas the scientific method requires reproducibility. The errors here are obvious. The observations must, circumstances permitting, be reproducible, but the past event inferred need not be. For example, recent DNA evidence established that the father of the Archbishop of Canterbury was not the person named on his birth certificate. We can test this conclusion, to the highest scientific standards, by repeating the DNA test, but there is no need to beget additional Archbishops to prove our point. We do indeed assume, with Hutton, that the present is the key to the past, but this assumption is itself the result of repeated observation. We can see rain splashes in billion-year-old mudstone and rounded pebbles in ancient riverbeds. The resemblance between past and present is not, as creationists claim, an input into interpretation but an outcome of observation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Should colleges that teach creationism be accredited?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/should-colleges-that-teach.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Should colleges that teach creationism be accredited?" /><published>2021-03-05T14:45:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-03-05T14:45:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/should-colleges-that%20teach</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/should-colleges-that-teach.html">&lt;p&gt;Should sectarian religious colleges that teach creationism be accredited? Our colleague, Joshua Swamidass, writing in the Wall Street Journal, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/a-compromise-on-creationism-11614901537&quot;&gt;answers with a qualified yes&lt;/a&gt;. Specifically, the issue involves an accrediting agency known as Transnational Association of Christian Colleges and Schools, or Tracs. Tracs was established in the 1970’s to provide accreditation for colleges and universities that taught young-earth creationism and six literal days of creation, rather than modern science. Eventually, Tracs was recognized by the Council for Higher Education Accreditation, or CHEA, which is in essence an umbrella agency that accredits accrediting agencies. The recognition of Tracs by CHEA is up for renewal this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But should Tracs colleges be accredited? Should Tracs be recognized? Dr. Swamidass thinks so but would require stringent conditions. To oversimplify his position, he thinks that colleges should be allowed to teach creationism, but if Tracs is to accredit them, then they must agree to teach modern science as well. He writes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As a matter of academic freedom, scientists should tolerate institutions that teach creation science. But deviations from national norms in a science curriculum need to be prominently disclosed, tracked and reported. In practice, that means transcripts that clearly state which courses and degrees include creation science. Credit from courses that include creation science should not be used toward science degrees. Nor should they be eligible for transfer to secular institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Swamidass notes that the “public arena” is pluralistic and concludes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… Avoiding conflict by unconditionally renewing Tracs’ membership is an unacceptable approach. But we need a more constructive solution than simply excluding those with whom we disagree—even if they seem obviously wrong, as creationists do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The best solution is to respect Tracs institutions’ unique character while holding them to high academic standards. Insisting on policies of transparency and academic freedom might even lay the groundwork for change in future generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix&lt;/strong&gt;. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chea.org/node/80121&quot;&gt;CHEA Committee on Recognition meets virtually March 8-10&lt;/a&gt;. You may register for meetings at 9:00 a.m. EST on March 9 and 10 &lt;a href=&quot;https://us02web.zoom.us/meeting/register/tZYrfuusrz0oHtZlo3yk9oJ-4fMgNGn_xQ3F&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I understand that they will discuss Tracs the morning of March 10 and make a recommendation to the full board, which will decide the matter in October. They no longer accept new comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Should sectarian religious colleges that teach creationism be accredited? Our colleague, Joshua Swamidass, writing in the Wall Street Journal, answers with a qualified yes. Specifically, the issue involves an accrediting agency known as Transnational Association of Christian Colleges and Schools, or Tracs. Tracs was established in the 1970’s to provide accreditation for colleges and universities that taught young-earth creationism and six literal days of creation, rather than modern science. Eventually, Tracs was recognized by the Council for Higher Education Accreditation, or CHEA, which is in essence an umbrella agency that accredits accrediting agencies. The recognition of Tracs by CHEA is up for renewal this year. But should Tracs colleges be accredited? Should Tracs be recognized? Dr. Swamidass thinks so but would require stringent conditions. To oversimplify his position, he thinks that colleges should be allowed to teach creationism, but if Tracs is to accredit them, then they must agree to teach modern science as well. He writes, As a matter of academic freedom, scientists should tolerate institutions that teach creation science. But deviations from national norms in a science curriculum need to be prominently disclosed, tracked and reported. In practice, that means transcripts that clearly state which courses and degrees include creation science. Credit from courses that include creation science should not be used toward science degrees. Nor should they be eligible for transfer to secular institutions.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pink sky</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/pink-sky.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pink sky" /><published>2021-03-01T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-03-01T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/pink-sky</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/pink-sky.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Vivian Dullien&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Vivian_Pink_Sky_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pink sky&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;center&gt;Pink sky, February 20, 2021, approximately 7 a.m., Boulder, Colorado.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The photographer was facing west, a short time, possibly as much as an hour, after sunrise. The mountain is illuminated by direct sunlight, but you can see the shadow of the mountain on which Dr. Dullien is perched. The top of the mountain looks reddish, in part because the rocks are red and probably in part because the sun is reddish early in the morning. In the shadow, the mountain is bluish because, well, because shadows are bluish because they are illuminated by scattered light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why is the sky pink? The photograph of the mountain is sharp, so there is no aerosol to the west. I was stumped. For an answer, I checked in with Stephen Corfidi of the NOAA/NWS Storm Prediction Center in Norman, Oklahoma. I discovered Dr. Corfidi through his splendid post, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spc.noaa.gov/publications/corfidi/sunset/&quot;&gt;The Colors of Sunset and Twilight&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without going into detail, Dr. Corfidi thinks that the pink sky in the west is essentially a reflection of the red sky in the east, by the aerosols in the west. That is, the aerosols in the west are scattering (reflecting) some of the red light back eastward. The scattered light may be pink rather than red or red-orange if there are scatterers in the lower atmosphere, but that explanation gets a little messy. I am also going to guess that some blue sky resulting from direct sunlight peeks through and shifts the spectrum slightly to the blue, as well as possibly reducing the saturation of the back-scattered light.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Vivian Dullien. Pink sky, February 20, 2021, approximately 7 a.m., Boulder, Colorado. The photographer was facing west, a short time, possibly as much as an hour, after sunrise. The mountain is illuminated by direct sunlight, but you can see the shadow of the mountain on which Dr. Dullien is perched. The top of the mountain looks reddish, in part because the rocks are red and probably in part because the sun is reddish early in the morning. In the shadow, the mountain is bluish because, well, because shadows are bluish because they are illuminated by scattered light. But why is the sky pink? The photograph of the mountain is sharp, so there is no aerosol to the west. I was stumped. For an answer, I checked in with Stephen Corfidi of the NOAA/NWS Storm Prediction Center in Norman, Oklahoma. I discovered Dr. Corfidi through his splendid post, The Colors of Sunset and Twilight. Without going into detail, Dr. Corfidi thinks that the pink sky in the west is essentially a reflection of the red sky in the east, by the aerosols in the west. That is, the aerosols in the west are scattering (reflecting) some of the red light back eastward. The scattered light may be pink rather than red or red-orange if there are scatterers in the lower atmosphere, but that explanation gets a little messy. I am also going to guess that some blue sky resulting from direct sunlight peeks through and shifts the spectrum slightly to the blue, as well as possibly reducing the saturation of the back-scattered light.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Behe Meets the Peaceful Science Forum</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/behe-meets-peaceful.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Behe Meets the Peaceful Science Forum" /><published>2021-03-01T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-03-01T10:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/behe-meets-peaceful</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/03/behe-meets-peaceful.html">&lt;p&gt;Today Nathan H. Lents authored an &lt;a href=&quot;https://skepticalinquirer.org/2021/03/behe-bias-and-bears-oh-my/&quot;&gt;article in the &lt;em&gt;Skeptical Inquirer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, telling the story of how we responded to Michael Behe’s last book. Specifically, in February of 2019, Michael Behe published the third book in his trilogy critiquing evolutionary science, &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/363/6427/590&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Darwin Devolves&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this book, Dr. Behe argues that adaptive evolution proceeds almost entirely by degrading or damaging genes. Even when evolution increases the fitness of organisms, it does so by destroying information in the genome, so evolution is a self-limited process that cannot explain the diversity of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The month before his book was published, in January of 2019, Richard Lenski, Nathan Lents, and I published &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/363/6427/590&quot;&gt;an 800-word review that was critical of &lt;em&gt;Darwin Devolves&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; together in &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We expected a reaction from the Discovery Institute (DI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There certainly was a strong reaction. In the ensuing weeks, the DI published &lt;a href=&quot;https://discourse.peacefulscience.org/t/darwin-devolves-the-end-of-evolution/4270&quot;&gt;over seventeen articles&lt;/a&gt;. In just days, they flooded search engine results with thousands and thousands of words written in response to us. These articles were written by Michael Behe himself and other scientists associated with intelligent design (ID).* Some articles were unsigned without identifying any authors by name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sort of “squid ink” response to criticism is surely unorthodox, but do not underestimate its effectiveness. It performs a particular public theater, one that benefits the DI in its quest to promote ID. The cloud of articles attracts attention. The DI and Behe can claim to have “responded” to all the criticism directed at them. Most non-scientists cannot follow the details or assess the quality of the responses. Some might interpret the exchange as a legitimate debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This theater is normally where it ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facing this ink cloud, most scientists just do not have the time or platform to respond. Most scientists find the flurry of articles off-putting, but the public might see evolutionary scientists abandoning a scientific debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this &lt;em&gt;particular&lt;/em&gt; case, however, Dr. Lents and I anticipated what was coming. We were prepared. We did not have millions of dollars of funding and a team of staff.  But we did have the &lt;a href=&quot;https://discourse.peacefulscience.org&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Peaceful Science&lt;/em&gt; forum&lt;/a&gt;. That forum made all the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The forum is fairly small, with only 50 or so active participants each day, but it is closely watched by several people in the origins debate. It is also an open forum, where anyone can join the conversation, adding information, expertise, and questions. As an open forum, it is also chaotic and unpredictable, not fully under our control. Still, it proved to be an effective platform, turning the tables on the DI’s typical public theater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DI had a turnaround time of days, but the forum had a far quicker turnaround, in minutes at best and hours at worst. Many of our contributors are scientists, and that became important. Quick analysis and rebuttal of DI articles was possible, at the moment when the public was watching, and these rebuttals did not depend on just the three co-authors of the &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DI did technically respond to our review in &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;. On the forum, several of us explained in detail why their responses were not “responsive” and why they did not convince us. That response disrupted the story DI wanted to tell. In that way, we interrupted their theater and told a better story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is all true, but it doesn’t quite capture the beautiful experience we shared together on the forum. Here we were, a group of scientists with demanding day jobs, participating in several discussion threads and dissecting the science of polar bear evolution together. None of us had closely studied polar bear evolution before, and we may never have done so if not for &lt;em&gt;Darwin Devolves&lt;/em&gt;. So, on the forum, we held an &lt;em&gt;impromptu&lt;/em&gt; journal club on polar bear evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We began with the specific paper that Behe referenced in his book, but went beyond, doing some of our work with genomic data from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/&quot;&gt;National Center for Biotechnology Information&lt;/a&gt;. Each of us commented on each other’s contributions in real time, taking questions from the non-scientist readers as we went. There were doubts and disagreements, different expertise brought to bear, and even some messy discussion. The general public was able to look behind the curtain to see how scientists think through and work on questions like these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one afternoon and evening, about eight of us did the homework that Behe should have done on polar bear genomics. This wasn’t just a discussion, we were doing science, &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; science, the same way we would tackle our own research questions, while the public looked on and asked questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This stands as a stark contrast to the DI. They did not and do not transparently reveal deliberations or disagreement. Instead, they present a united front, never publicly contradicting or criticizing each other. That is not how science actually works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we dug in more and more, a plant biologist, Arthur Hunt, recognized several serious problems with Michael Behe’s analysis of polar bear genetics in his first chapter. What began as a forum post by Dr. Hunt was quickly upgraded to a full-fledged &lt;a href=&quot;https://discourse.peacefulscience.org/t/lents-and-hunt-behe-and-the-polar-bears-fat/4473&quot;&gt;blog post co-authored by Drs. Hunt and Lents&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Behe responded with a blog post of his own, in which he called us “incompetent.” Surprising all of us, though, he doubled down by presenting data from the polar bear paper in a very misleading way. Just as important, his discussion revealed fundamental misunderstanding of the algorithms used to predict the function of mutations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This exchange was really important for several reasons. It certainly made it very clear exactly where Dr. Behe’s reasoning had gone wrong in a prominent example in his book. He could have conceded this example, without necessarily destroying his whole argument. But he doubled down instead. If a scientist can’t correct &lt;a href=&quot;https://discourse.peacefulscience.org/t/three-misrepresentations-on-darwin-devolves-back-cover/5237&quot;&gt;ancillary mistakes&lt;/a&gt;, why would anyone trust him to correct more important errors?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visible on the forum are several entertaining subplots within the larger story, far too much to cover here. The twists and turns were wild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were more blog posts, of course, including a few from &lt;a href=&quot;https://telliamedrevisited.wordpress.com/2019/02/22/on-damaged-genes-and-polar-bears/&quot;&gt;Richard Lenski&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://peacefulscience.org/fair-hearing-behe/&quot;&gt;me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The never-ending debate over ID can tax anyone’s patience and often seems pedantic. But the quick back and forth of a forum was different. With other scientists to help us along, responding to the DI felt more like play than pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DI still uses this same strategy, so we will not be the last to face the cloud of ink. Next time you are caught in the cloud, come join us at &lt;em&gt;Peaceful Science&lt;/em&gt;. Together we might succeed turning the theater around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are lucky, we might even get to explore some interesting science together. It was polar bear evolution this time, but next time? I cannot wait to find out.  Whatever comes, I’m sure that we will have far more success tackling it together than alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;i&gt;On March 8th, this article was updated to correct an editing error, replacing a reference to “ID creationism” with a reference to “ID” alone.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joshua Swamidass</name></author><summary type="html">Today Nathan H. Lents authored an article in the Skeptical Inquirer, telling the story of how we responded to Michael Behe’s last book. Specifically, in February of 2019, Michael Behe published the third book in his trilogy critiquing evolutionary science, Darwin Devolves. In this book, Dr. Behe argues that adaptive evolution proceeds almost entirely by degrading or damaging genes. Even when evolution increases the fitness of organisms, it does so by destroying information in the genome, so evolution is a self-limited process that cannot explain the diversity of life. The month before his book was published, in January of 2019, Richard Lenski, Nathan Lents, and I published an 800-word review that was critical of Darwin Devolves together in Science. We expected a reaction from the Discovery Institute (DI).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Grant County Loses to Ark Park – Again</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/grant-county-loses.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grant County Loses to Ark Park – Again" /><published>2021-02-21T10:35:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-02-21T10:35:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/grant-county-loses</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/grant-county-loses.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Ark_Bow.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bow of Ark&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;small&gt;Photo courtesy of Dan Phelps.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By Dan Phelps&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt; Posted with permission. Mr. Phelps sent this note to us by way of an e-mail.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is very old news, but I just learned of the resolution of the lawsuit Grant County Board of Education v. Ark Encounter. Unsurprisingly, the Grant County News (a very pro-Ark newspaper) did not cover the outcome of this case, although the paper had covered the initial lawsuit. The Louisville Courier-Journal also did a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.courier-journal.com/story/news/local/northeast/2019/08/27/ark-encounter-kentucky-pva-sued-for-undervalued-property/2128604001/&quot;&gt;story on the initial lawsuit&lt;/a&gt; on August 27, 2019. I discussed the situation with many people back in 2019, but was unaware of the final result until now, since it was unreported outside legal databases. The final decision (summarized briefly below) was not given until July 29, 2020, and was not widely reported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the school board lost the lawsuit in 2020, the following is moot, but shows yet another way the Ark has shortchanged the locals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of the lawsuit, Grant County education is, remarkably, going to be funded by taxes on the Ark at &lt;i&gt;less than 50 % of what the Ark itself claims it is worth&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2017/07/when-is-a-for-profit.html&quot;&gt;AiG/Crosswater Canyon&lt;/a&gt; claim the Ark is worth well more than $100 million on their Form 990’s submitted to the IRS. The &amp;gt;$100 million amount makes AiG/Ark look better when borrowing money from financial institutions. However, the local Property Value Administrators evaluate the Ark at only $48 million for taxes (and, further, the Ark does not pay the full property tax amount because of an agreement/incentive given them before the Ark was built). Thus the financially strapped local schools do not receive as much tax money as they would if the PVA had evaluated the Ark at what AiG says it is worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lexology.com/library/detail.aspx?g=c6699337-99ef-4799-8c91-885c952c39b4&quot;&gt;Grant County Board of Education v. Ark Encounter&lt;/a&gt;, LLC, No. 19-CI-00204 (Grant Cir. Ct. July 29, 2020, affirming, File No. K18-S-15, Final Order No. K-25927 (KCC May 31, 2019) – Property Tax – Standing to Appeal Assessment&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; 
The Board of Education (BOE) attempted to appeal PVA’s tax assessment of Ark Encounter property assessed at $48 million, alleging a value of $130 million. The KCC [Kentucky Circuit Court] dismissed the BOE’s appeal for lack of standing under the statute since the BOE was not a taxpayer or an aggrieved party, while also noting that historically this has never been done. On appeal to the Grant County Circuit Court, the parties entered an Agreed Order affirming the Final Order of the KCC.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photo courtesy of Dan Phelps. By Dan Phelps. Posted with permission. Mr. Phelps sent this note to us by way of an e-mail. This is very old news, but I just learned of the resolution of the lawsuit Grant County Board of Education v. Ark Encounter. Unsurprisingly, the Grant County News (a very pro-Ark newspaper) did not cover the outcome of this case, although the paper had covered the initial lawsuit. The Louisville Courier-Journal also did a story on the initial lawsuit on August 27, 2019. I discussed the situation with many people back in 2019, but was unaware of the final result until now, since it was unreported outside legal databases. The final decision (summarized briefly below) was not given until July 29, 2020, and was not widely reported. Since the school board lost the lawsuit in 2020, the following is moot, but shows yet another way the Ark has shortchanged the locals.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Was the origin of cave paintings in the stratosphere?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/origin-of-cave-paintings.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Was the origin of cave paintings in the stratosphere?" /><published>2021-02-20T08:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-02-20T08:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/origin-of-cave-paintings</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/origin-of-cave-paintings.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/Red_Hands_Cave001_Wikimedia_600.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Aboriginal hand stencils, Red Hands Cave, Blue Mountains NP, NSW, Australia. &lt;small&gt;Sardaka, own work (Kodachrome slide scanned at 6400). Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 4.0 International.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A team from the University of New South Wales in Australia has discovered a very ancient and well-preserved log that they used to &lt;a href=&quot;https://phys.org/news/2021-02-ancient-relic-earth-history-years.html&quot;&gt;date the last reversal of the earth’s magnetic field very precisely to 42 ka (thousand years) ago&lt;/a&gt;. Using climate modelling and whatnot, they calculated a detailed timescale and deduced that the magnetic-field reversal – known as the Laschamps Excursion – coincided with high solar activity and may have caused glaciation in North America and a relatively sudden change in the climate in Australia, which may in turn have led to the extinction of the Neanderthals and some early modern human cultures, and of megafaunas in Australia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the field reversal occurred 42 millennia ago, the team dubbed it the Adams Event, in honor of Douglas Adams, who wrote in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Hitchhiker%27s_Guide_to_the_Galaxy&quot;&gt;Hitchhiker’s Guide to the Galaxy&lt;/a&gt; that the answer to life, the universe, and everything is 42.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very briefly, the team used the trunk of an ancient &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agathis_australis&quot;&gt; kauri tree&lt;/a&gt;, which had been well preserved in a bog, carbon-dated each ring, and correlated the results with other, existing data. As &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/371/6531/766.full&quot;&gt;described in a news article in Science&lt;/a&gt;, they applied a climate model and, very briefly, deduced that the excess high-energy radiation from the sun depleted the ozone layer and caused high-altitude cooling, which in turn altered the wind patterns and thus the climate near the surface. The change of climate caused the extinctions noted above. (You may find the technical article &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/371/6531/811&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I read portions of it, but not surprisingly I found that it was not just Greek to me, but technical Greek to me.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What caught my eye, however, was the claim that the field reversal somehow brought about the origin of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cave_painting&quot;&gt;cave paintings&lt;/a&gt; in Eurasia. In brief, the argument is that the high UV levels caused by the destruction of the ozone layer forced people into caves. Indeed, they argue that the handprints signal that the red ochre used for the paintings may also have been used as sunscreen. Well, IANAX[pert], but Wikipedia claims that a red hand stencil was made by a Neanderthal 64 ka ago. Their dates for modern humans are indeed in their range of 42 ka ago, or less. Still, it is hard to conceive that humans did not discover caves until they got severely sunburned, and I am at least partly sympathetic with those who told &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; that the study may be too speculative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Vivian Dullien directed my attention to the phys.org article. Nothing in this brief report is her fault.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Aboriginal hand stencils, Red Hands Cave, Blue Mountains NP, NSW, Australia. Sardaka, own work (Kodachrome slide scanned at 6400). Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 4.0 International. A team from the University of New South Wales in Australia has discovered a very ancient and well-preserved log that they used to date the last reversal of the earth’s magnetic field very precisely to 42 ka (thousand years) ago. Using climate modelling and whatnot, they calculated a detailed timescale and deduced that the magnetic-field reversal – known as the Laschamps Excursion – coincided with high solar activity and may have caused glaciation in North America and a relatively sudden change in the climate in Australia, which may in turn have led to the extinction of the Neanderthals and some early modern human cultures, and of megafaunas in Australia. Because the field reversal occurred 42 millennia ago, the team dubbed it the Adams Event, in honor of Douglas Adams, who wrote in Hitchhiker’s Guide to the Galaxy that the answer to life, the universe, and everything is 42.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Report: Are jellyfish so dumb that their evolution needed help?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/Are-jellyfish-so-dumb.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Report: Are jellyfish so dumb that their evolution needed help?" /><published>2021-02-19T12:01:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-02-19T12:01:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/Are-jellyfish-so-dumb</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/Are-jellyfish-so-dumb.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2021/AureliaEkranoplan.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;The moon jelly &lt;em&gt;Aurelia aurita&lt;/em&gt; and a Russian Soviet-era Ekranoplan ground-effect craft, the A-90 Orlyonok.  Both images courtesy of Wikimedia Commons under the Creative Commons license.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Posts labeled “Report:” will discuss material posted on other sites, particularly ones that contain silly arguments&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting report in this paper:&lt;br /&gt;
Gemmell, Brad J., Kevin T. Du Clos, Sean P. Colin, Kelly R. Sutherland and John H. Costello.  2021. The most efficient metazoan swimmer creates a ‘virtual wall’ to enhance performance.  Proceedings of the Royal Society B (Biological Sciences)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2020.2494&quot;&gt;http://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2020.2494&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
argues that jellyfish use a subtle fluid dynamic effect, the ‘ground effect’, to swim efficiently.  The suthors used sophisticated monitoring techniques to measure the movement of water, as well as computationally intensive calculation methods of fluid dynamics.  They found that when the body of the common Moon Jelly &lt;em&gt;Aurelia aurita&lt;/em&gt; contracts, it creates two vortices, each like a smoke ring, but rotating in opposite directions.  Together they function as a ‘virtual wall’ against which water is pushed.  The result is extraordinarily efficient swimming.  The paper is open access and may be read at the link above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ground effect has been known in fluid dynamics since the 1920s, when pilots reported that their planes flew more efficiently when close to the ground, an effect due to the air beneath the wings being compressed by being squeezed between the wings and the ground.  A number of countries have tested vehicles used the ground effect to “fly” just above the surface of the ocean.  The most active development program was the models of “ekranoplans” produced in Soviet-era Russia in the 1970s and 1980s, one of which you will see above.  The model shown there was also capable of a limited amount of actual flight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as astonishing as jellyfish are, and as surprising as ground-effect vehicles are,
they have inspired an actual flight of fancy.  This was by the ever-astonishing
Denyse O’Leary, who writes for the ID advocacy blog Uncommon Descent.  Her
argument needs to be quoted – you would not believe me if I summarized it …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O’Leary, who writes for Uncommon Descent as “News”, is an expert at invective.  A common trope of her reports is that science is wrong, a position that she backs up with frequent reports on fudged data, failures of peer review, and failure of further work to confirm initial reports.  This time, for a change, she is merely implying that scientists have failed to notice a dramatic implication of some work – that the feature could not be explained by ordinary evolutionary mechanisms but must imply that there was Intelligent Design.
After citing a report on jellyfish and ground effect and indicating that the original paper is open access, she simply says &lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/jellyfish-enhance-their-skills-by-building-a-virtual-wall/&quot;&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Either jellyfish are smarter than we think or there is design in nature.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is astonishing – I am glad I am not a coffee drinker because I would have had to replace my computer after reading it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are only two comments on that post.  True to the form of UD commenters, who are the ultimate ID cheering section, one from commenter Mahuna says&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; ....
OK, clearly some INDIVIDUAL jellyfish did NOT invent this technique on a slow afternoon and then TEACH it to his bros. It is MUCH more likely, since ALL jellyfish know how to do this, that the skill was INSTALLED way back when the Designer was messing around with the pre-production prototypes. ....
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;while commenter Querius says “Yes, indeed!”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently ID advocates, or at least these ones, cannot understand how natural selection could favor an adaptation that makes use of a sophisticated concept of physics or engineering &lt;em&gt;unless the organism understands the physics&lt;/em&gt;.  I suppose that the fact that trees use capillary action to bring water from the roots up to the leaves must also be evidence for ID, since trees scarcely understand the relevant physics.  Years ago, I saw an ID advocate argue that it was hard to explain how the colors of some birds could come from diffraction of light &lt;em&gt;since birds do not understand the concept of diffraction&lt;/em&gt;.  (I wish I had kept a link to that quote).  Likewise all the adaptations of single-celled protists must be the result of Design, since protists understand so little chemistry and physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s facepalm time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A slightly off-topic aside:&lt;/em&gt; The ‘flight’ of ground-effect vehicles is related to the way hovercraft move across water.  I’ve experienced that myself.  In 1983 I crossed the English Channel on the hovercraft ferry from Boulogne, France to Dover, England.  The craft rested on pillars rising from a concrete pad which was at the top end of a smooth, sloping beach.  After we boarded it on a gangway and seated ourselves in rows of airline-style seats, the engines started up.  The fans that blew air down inside the skirt of the craft made it rise up a few feet, and it started to slide down the beach, just barely touching the sand.  It came to the water and started out across it, driven by the propellers mounted above the craft.  That was the fun part.  Unfortunately the motion of the hovercraft consisted of riding up the front of a wave, and then slamming down once past it.  This kicked up a lot of spray, which rose in a cloud around the craft, coating the windows so that one could not see much.  It also leaked in at one place in the plexiglas canopy.  The result was an uncomfortable ride, though it did get to Dover in only about an hour.  At the Dover end it drove up onto the beach, riding above it as it did on the water, until it settled onto its supports there.  There is still one hovercraft ferry service in England, between Southsea in Portsmouth and the Isle of Wight.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">The moon jelly Aurelia aurita and a Russian Soviet-era Ekranoplan ground-effect craft, the A-90 Orlyonok. Both images courtesy of Wikimedia Commons under the Creative Commons license. Posts labeled “Report:” will discuss material posted on other sites, particularly ones that contain silly arguments An interesting report in this paper: Gemmell, Brad J., Kevin T. Du Clos, Sean P. Colin, Kelly R. Sutherland and John H. Costello. 2021. The most efficient metazoan swimmer creates a ‘virtual wall’ to enhance performance. Proceedings of the Royal Society B (Biological Sciences) http://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2020.2494 argues that jellyfish use a subtle fluid dynamic effect, the ‘ground effect’, to swim efficiently. The suthors used sophisticated monitoring techniques to measure the movement of water, as well as computationally intensive calculation methods of fluid dynamics. They found that when the body of the common Moon Jelly Aurelia aurita contracts, it creates two vortices, each like a smoke ring, but rotating in opposite directions. Together they function as a ‘virtual wall’ against which water is pushed. The result is extraordinarily efficient swimming. The paper is open access and may be read at the link above. The ground effect has been known in fluid dynamics since the 1920s, when pilots reported that their planes flew more efficiently when close to the ground, an effect due to the air beneath the wings being compressed by being squeezed between the wings and the ground. A number of countries have tested vehicles used the ground effect to “fly” just above the surface of the ocean. The most active development program was the models of “ekranoplans” produced in Soviet-era Russia in the 1970s and 1980s, one of which you will see above. The model shown there was also capable of a limited amount of actual flight. But as astonishing as jellyfish are, and as surprising as ground-effect vehicles are, they have inspired an actual flight of fancy. This was by the ever-astonishing Denyse O’Leary, who writes for the ID advocacy blog Uncommon Descent. Her argument needs to be quoted – you would not believe me if I summarized it …</summary></entry></feed>