<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-11-07T11:33:52-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Science leads to stock photo entertainment</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/stockphotos.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science leads to stock photo entertainment" /><published>2022-11-01T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-11-01T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/stockphotos</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/stockphotos.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/chickenspace.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stock science images&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Left: &quot;Talk to us, Dr. Chicken!&quot; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Right: Showing us where outer space is.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent meme widely spread on the internet shows Worst Science Stock Photos.  It seems to have originated with Dr. Kit Chapman of the University of Falmouth, U.K., who posted candidates for worst on his 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ChemistryKit/status/1580308605416325120?cxt=HHwWgICq1biTse4rAAAA&quot;&gt;Twitter account&lt;/a&gt; and conducted a vote.  The two above were among these (the left one was #2 in the voting).  They are 
shown because they are my favorites.  #1 was an image showing a model holding a soldering iron by its hot tip and soldering on the wrong side of a circuit board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also further comments on Reddit, which you can find by searching for “Reddit worst science stock photos”.  To see discussion 
here at PT, click on the title of this post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Left: &quot;Talk to us, Dr. Chicken!&quot; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Right: Showing us where outer space is. &amp;nbsp; A recent meme widely spread on the internet shows Worst Science Stock Photos. It seems to have originated with Dr. Kit Chapman of the University of Falmouth, U.K., who posted candidates for worst on his Twitter account and conducted a vote. The two above were among these (the left one was #2 in the voting). They are shown because they are my favorites. #1 was an image showing a model holding a soldering iron by its hot tip and soldering on the wrong side of a circuit board. There are also further comments on Reddit, which you can find by searching for “Reddit worst science stock photos”. To see discussion here at PT, click on the title of this post.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Phymata pennsylvanica</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/Phymata-pennsylvanica.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Phymata pennsylvanica" /><published>2022-10-24T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-24T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/Phymata-pennsylvanica</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/Phymata-pennsylvanica.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Mark Sturtevant&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Sturtevant.1.Ambush_Bugs.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ambush bug&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insectidentification.org/insect-description.asp?identification=Ambush-Bug&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Phymata pennsylvanica&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; ambush bugs. The photographer writes, &quot;Ambush bugs are well camouflaged insects that lie in wait on flowers. A visiting insect will be grabbed, and the proboscis of this insect will be used to kill and feed upon the prey. In this case, the female of the mating pair has taken a digger bee (&lt;i&gt;Anthophora&lt;/i&gt; sp.). Clearly, ambush bugs are not concerned about taking stinging insects!
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Mark Sturtevant. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Phymata pennsylvanica &amp;ndash; ambush bugs. The photographer writes, &quot;Ambush bugs are well camouflaged insects that lie in wait on flowers. A visiting insect will be grabbed, and the proboscis of this insect will be used to kill and feed upon the prey. In this case, the female of the mating pair has taken a digger bee (Anthophora sp.). Clearly, ambush bugs are not concerned about taking stinging insects!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PBS to rebroadcast “We Believe in Dinosaurs” in December</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/PBS-to-rebroadcast.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PBS to rebroadcast “We Believe in Dinosaurs” in December" /><published>2022-10-19T15:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-19T15:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/PBS-to-rebroadcast</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/PBS-to-rebroadcast.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Allosaurus_SDNHM_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Allosaurus&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Allosaurus at the San Diego Museum of Natural History. &lt;small&gt;Wikimedia. Photograph by user Sheep81. Public domain.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Daniel Phelps was featured in the full-length documentary film &lt;/i&gt;We Believe in Dinosaurs&lt;i&gt;, which we reported on &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/04/reviews-of-documentary.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The film was later slightly shortened to accommodate a 1-hour television program; that version was &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/11/we-believe-on-PBS.html&quot;&gt;broadcast February 17, 2020&lt;/a&gt;. Below is what we received from Mr. Phelps.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was recently forwarded the message below from ITVS Avis, the producer of the documentary. It looks as if PBS will again air the documentary “We Believe in Dinosaurs” on the PBS show “Independent Lens” on December 19 and make the show available for free streaming until mid-January.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is wonderful news. The documentary deserved more local and national coverage than it received when it first aired right before the CoVid pandemic hit in 2020. I hope recipients of this message will publicize the film and review it in appropriate publications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an edited version of the message:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am reaching out to you today to let you know that we are bringing back your film, &lt;i&gt;We Believe in Dinosaurs&lt;/i&gt;, on the Public Television Broadcast &amp;amp; the PBS Video Application. The scheduled TV air date &amp;amp; the Streaming window are as follows.&lt;/p&gt; 
  &lt;p&gt;·  TV Air Date: 10/9C, 12/19/2022&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;·  Free Online streaming: 12/19/2022 - 01/15/2023 (28 days)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Viewing Instructions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the streaming window, to watch &lt;i&gt;We Believe in Dinosaurs&lt;/i&gt; on your computer, go to pbs.org/believeindinosaurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To watch the film on a TV, phone, or tablet, you'll need to download the PBS Video app. On a TV, that means downloading the app in Roku, Apple TV, or your smart TV interface. Once you're in the PBS Video app, look for the &lt;i&gt;Independent Lens&lt;/i&gt; tile (or search for &lt;i&gt;We Believe in Dinosaurs&lt;/i&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
 
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social Media Info&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
·  Independent Lens' handle: @independentlens&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Allosaurus at the San Diego Museum of Natural History. Wikimedia. Photograph by user Sheep81. Public domain. Daniel Phelps was featured in the full-length documentary film We Believe in Dinosaurs, which we reported on here. The film was later slightly shortened to accommodate a 1-hour television program; that version was broadcast February 17, 2020. Below is what we received from Mr. Phelps. I was recently forwarded the message below from ITVS Avis, the producer of the documentary. It looks as if PBS will again air the documentary “We Believe in Dinosaurs” on the PBS show “Independent Lens” on December 19 and make the show available for free streaming until mid-January. This is wonderful news. The documentary deserved more local and national coverage than it received when it first aired right before the CoVid pandemic hit in 2020. I hope recipients of this message will publicize the film and review it in appropriate publications. Here is an edited version of the message:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How jellyfish prove Intelligent Design (according to ID advocates)</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/those-divinely-inspired-jellyfish.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How jellyfish prove Intelligent Design (according to ID advocates)" /><published>2022-10-18T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-18T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/those-divinely-inspired-jellyfish</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/those-divinely-inspired-jellyfish.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Aurelia_aurita.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Moon Jellyfish&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;The Moon Jellyfish, &lt;em&gt;Aurelia aurita&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br /&gt; Photo by Luc Viatour.&lt;br /&gt; From Wikimedia Commons.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On October 6, The Discovery Institute’s ID site “Evolution News and Science Today:” reprised
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2022/10/secrets-that-give-sea-lions-and-jellyfish-their-edge-as-swimmers/&quot;&gt;(here)&lt;/a&gt;
a 2015 post by David Coppege.  A few days later, at the site Uncommon Descent, their regular
poster “caspian”, whom they identify as physicist Dr. Eric Hedin, noted that post and quoted
much of its content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2015 post was based on two interesting reports in The Conversation.  One, by Megan Leftwich of George Washington University, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/scientists-at-work-cracking-sea-lions-high-thrust-low-wake-swimming-technique-45295&quot;&gt;described her lab’s work on the efficiency with which sea lions swim&lt;/a&gt;.  The other, &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/jellyfish-are-the-most-energy-efficient-swimmers-new-metric-confirms-26729&quot;&gt;by Akshat Rathi, who interviewed Neelesh Patankar of Northwestern University and John Dabiri of Caltech&lt;/a&gt; reports studies that show that jellyfish are unusually efficient in their use of energy in swimming, because they can recover some of the energy they exert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reports in The Conversation are interesting reports on very effective adaptations.  But they do not contain 
any discussion of Intelligent Design.  Here our heroes David Coppege and Dr. Eric Hedin come to the rescue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re used to seeing sites like Evolution News and Uncommon Descent present reports on 
particularly impressive adaptations, with the implication that such a good adaptation
must surely be the result of Design Intervention and could not have been brought about by 
ordinary evolutionary forces such as natural selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This handwaving is not for David Coppege, who has a degree in physics, or Eric Hedin, who
took his doctorate in that field at my own university.  Coppege makes the argument 
more specific:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If the world’s best human designers are attempting to build machines to mimic what these animals “naturally do,” it’s a reasonable inference that sea lions and jellyfish originated from an intelligent cause — one with superior knowledge of propulsion, fluid mechanics, and optimization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Hedin does not add anything to this, but quotes Coppege’s report extensively and approvingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen an Argument From Jellyfish and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/Are-jellyfish-so-dumb.html&quot;&gt;commented on it here before&lt;/a&gt;.  That post reported on one from Uncommon Descent in 
2021, by Dr. Hedin’s colleague Denyse O’Leary, the previous most frequent poster
at that site.  She cited a more recent report of how jellyfish conserve energy while 
swimming.  She had a somewhat different
take on why this supported Intelligent Design:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Either jellyfish are smarter than we think or there is design in nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there we have two fascinating takes on why an excellent adaptation strongly indicates Design Intervention: because natural selection could not do something that works better than what human engineers can design, or because jellyfish are too dumb to know how to design themselves.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">The Moon Jellyfish, Aurelia aurita. Photo by Luc Viatour. From Wikimedia Commons. &amp;nbsp; On October 6, The Discovery Institute’s ID site “Evolution News and Science Today:” reprised (here) a 2015 post by David Coppege. A few days later, at the site Uncommon Descent, their regular poster “caspian”, whom they identify as physicist Dr. Eric Hedin, noted that post and quoted much of its content. The 2015 post was based on two interesting reports in The Conversation. One, by Megan Leftwich of George Washington University, described her lab’s work on the efficiency with which sea lions swim. The other, by Akshat Rathi, who interviewed Neelesh Patankar of Northwestern University and John Dabiri of Caltech reports studies that show that jellyfish are unusually efficient in their use of energy in swimming, because they can recover some of the energy they exert. The reports in The Conversation are interesting reports on very effective adaptations. But they do not contain any discussion of Intelligent Design. Here our heroes David Coppege and Dr. Eric Hedin come to the rescue.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Danaus plexippus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/danaus-plexippus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Danaus plexippus" /><published>2022-10-10T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-10T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/danaus-plexippus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/danaus-plexippus.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Revelle Hamilton&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Revelle_Monarch_Larvae_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Monarch larvae&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monarch_butterfly&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Danaus plexippus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; monarch butterfly larvae.  The photographer writes, &quot;The next generation of monarchs. I saw 5 on the milkweed this AM. I bought plants originally but this spring the seeds from the plants germinated &amp;amp; I have little milkweeds in various places.  I am picking off some of the pods and placing them in places I hope they will come up next year.&quot; We hope so too!
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Revelle Hamilton. Danaus plexippus &amp;ndash; monarch butterfly larvae. The photographer writes, &quot;The next generation of monarchs. I saw 5 on the milkweed this AM. I bought plants originally but this spring the seeds from the plants germinated &amp;amp; I have little milkweeds in various places. I am picking off some of the pods and placing them in places I hope they will come up next year.&quot; We hope so too!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creationism and climate - birth of a new pseudoscience</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/creationclimate.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creationism and climate - birth of a new pseudoscience" /><published>2022-10-04T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-04T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/creationclimate</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/creationclimate.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/iceage.png&quot; alt=&quot;Creationist timeline&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A young-earth creationist timeline &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/bible-timeline/how-does-mans-history-fit-with-the-biblical-timeline/&quot;&gt;from AnswerInGenesis in 2006&lt;/a&gt;.  Where is
the Ice Age?  Copyright 2022, Answers In Genesis. Used here under Fair Use.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are all too familiar with creationist life science (theory of kinds) and creationist Earth science (Flood geology). As I explain in &lt;a href=&quot;https://3quarksdaily.com/3quarksdaily/2022/10/creationism-in-the-service-of-climate-change-denial.html&quot;&gt;an article at 3 Quarks Daily&lt;/a&gt;, recent decades have seen the emergence of a creationist climate science, which is a direct attack on the “secular” climate science of climate change. Creationist climate science rejects, as it must, the palaeoclimatology that helped establish the existence of positive climate feedbacks, and from this draws the inference that our present concern about human effects on climate is unbiblical, unscientific, and exaggerated. This fits in directly with the agendas of the organisations opposing fossil fuel restraint, and even involves some of the same people. We need to pay attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creationists cannot avoid accepting a single Ice Age, which they have to regard as more recent than Noah’s Flood. So with great imagination they have devised theories that make the Ice Age an actual consequence of the Flood, and in the process they come to believe that their own theories are biblical. They can then call into play the entire creationist rhetorical apparatus, invoking arguments about biblical versus secular, God’s word versus man’s word, and a conspiracy of secular scientists deliberately hoodwinking the public by ignoring the biblical evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is this secular science that lies behind our models of the climatic effects of human activity. In particular, the ability of the Milankovitch cycles to cause such large changes in Ice Age climate shows the existence of positive feedbacks, as further confirmed by detailed ice core studies. The creationists, whom we must not to dismiss as ignorant or ill informed, are well aware of this, and draw the implication that the appeal to positive feedbacks is an artefact of the secularist viewpoint, and should be rejected. They argue from this that current concerns about where the climate is going are misplaced. As I show in my 3QD article, all this is explicitly spelt out in the creationist literature, which links directly to the Cornwall Alliance’s climate change denial literature. This is no accident. The director of the Cornwall Alliance is an active contributor to Answers in Genesis, and the right wing political philosopher Jay W. Richards, who over at the Discovery Institute pours scorn on evolution science and global warming concerns alike, is a senior research fellow at the Heritage Foundation, and a former adviser to Cornwall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all these reasons, I regard creationist climate science as a much more pressing threat than the usual annoying creationist nonsense. How should we respond?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/milankovitch.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Milankovitch cycles and climate&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;420,000 years of ice core data from Vostok, Antarctica, research station. Current period is at left. From bottom to top: insolation at 65°N due to Milankovitch cycles (connected to 18O); 18O isotope of oxygen; levels of methane (CH4); relative temperature; levels of carbon dioxide (CO2). From Wikimedia Commons, public domain&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman</name></author><summary type="html">A young-earth creationist timeline from AnswerInGenesis in 2006. Where is the Ice Age? Copyright 2022, Answers In Genesis. Used here under Fair Use. We are all too familiar with creationist life science (theory of kinds) and creationist Earth science (Flood geology). As I explain in an article at 3 Quarks Daily, recent decades have seen the emergence of a creationist climate science, which is a direct attack on the “secular” climate science of climate change. Creationist climate science rejects, as it must, the palaeoclimatology that helped establish the existence of positive climate feedbacks, and from this draws the inference that our present concern about human effects on climate is unbiblical, unscientific, and exaggerated. This fits in directly with the agendas of the organisations opposing fossil fuel restraint, and even involves some of the same people. We need to pay attention.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Neuroterus numismalis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/09/neuroterus-numismalis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Neuroterus numismalis" /><published>2022-09-26T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-09-26T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/09/neuroterus-numismalis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/09/neuroterus-numismalis.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Sarah Boosey&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Sookie_Silk_Button_Gall_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Silk button galls&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Silk button galls &amp;ndash; eggs laid by &lt;a href=&quot;https://guatemala.inaturalist.org/taxa/127758-Neuroterus-numismalis&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Neuroterus numismalis&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or silk-button gall wasp. These gall wasps exhibit sexual and asexual reproduction in successive generations, as detailed in the article cited. The silk buttons, so called bacause they look like they are wrapped in silk thread, are deposited by females in the &lt;i&gt;agamic&lt;/i&gt;, or asexual, generation.  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Sarah Boosey. Silk button galls &amp;ndash; eggs laid by Neuroterus numismalis, or silk-button gall wasp. These gall wasps exhibit sexual and asexual reproduction in successive generations, as detailed in the article cited. The silk buttons, so called bacause they look like they are wrapped in silk thread, are deposited by females in the agamic, or asexual, generation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">YEC astronomers appropriate findings of JWST</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/09/yec-astronomers-jwst.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="YEC astronomers appropriate findings of JWST" /><published>2022-09-16T13:18:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-09-16T13:18:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/09/yec-astronomers-jwst</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/09/yec-astronomers-jwst.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Phelps_Yec_Astronomers_JWST_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Screenshot of an inane cartoon that the author considers insulting to scientists in particular and intelligent people in general. Note how it conflates cosmology or cosmogony with evolution.&lt;small&gt;Fair use.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young Earth Creationist (YEC) astronomers have declared victory for creationism because of the findings of the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST). Our favorite YEC astronomers have finally discussed the JWST at length. On Wednesday, September 14, 2022, on Facebook Dr. Danny Faulkner and Rob Webb of AiG, and Dr. Jason Lisle (formerly of AiG, now at the Biblical Science Institute) discuss the early findings of the JWST for &lt;a href=&quot;https://fb.watch/fymizG2T2H/&quot;&gt;a full excruciating hour&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faulkner and Lisle have PhDs in astronomy. Rob Webb recently was hired by AiG as a preacher/scientist and has experience in aerospace engineering, helping design several different spacecraft (hence his AiG nickname “Rocket Rob”).  Their “discussion” consists mostly of self-congratulation and sundry claims that every new finding supports Young Earth Creationism including having light from galaxies billions of light years away getting to Earth in a mere 6,000 years (a miracle!). Their self congratulations are based on the fact that astronomers are revising their ideas about how quickly galaxies and heavy elements formed in the early universe because of new data from JWST findings. This motley crew seems to be gloating that other astronomers are – gasp! – doing science. Much of the rest of the video is preaching/scripture quoting and, at about 23 minutes in, claiming a nefarious conspiracy of morally questionable “secular astronomers” based on their “worldview.” Most astronomers I know are upright citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About 32 minutes in, Drs. Lisle and Faulkner joke about dead Democrats voting in Chicago, and Dr. Lisle claims “dead people vote Left.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Dr. Faulkner’s esteemed scientific opinion God created life only on earth, not elsewhere (~36 minutes in). However, he intones, this only includes “physical life like us; I’m not talking about spirit beings like angels and demons, and so forth.” (Is this video from the 13th century?) Then, after a discussion of exoplanets, Dr. Faulkner also tells us that God will destroy stars and galaxies when he creates a “new heavens and a new Earth” (~39 minutes). Golly wow! Thankfully, Dr. Faulkner goes on to rebuff an online questioner who asks about the flat earth, giving Biblical and scientific reasons the ancient Bible-based cosmology is wrong. Dr. Faulkner has even written a thick tome about the subject (for sale at the Creation Museum and Ark Park, as well as online). The three gentlemen then discuss flat earth theory and the psychology of the cultish behavior behind it for a bit. They appear oblivious to the irony, that, in spite of their education, they are promoting a 6,000 year old universe and Earth. When they agreed that it is a “psychological issue,” I stopped the video for a few minutes out of necessity. I couldn’t decide to laugh or cry, so I took a bathroom break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Near the end (~53 minutes) Dr. Lisle bemoans that mainstream science is ignoring his claim that he predicted the findings of the JWST. He goes on to claim that science itself wouldn’t be possible if the Bible weren’t true. Lisle then posts the inane cartoon in the frontispiece (my screenshot) insulting scientists and intelligent people as well as confusing evolution and cosmology/cosmogony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video ends with mentions of books for sale and touts the Creation Museum planetarium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Based on an e-mail provided by Mr. Phelps, lightly edited, and reproduced with permission. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Screenshot of an inane cartoon that the author considers insulting to scientists in particular and intelligent people in general. Note how it conflates cosmology or cosmogony with evolution.Fair use. Young Earth Creationist (YEC) astronomers have declared victory for creationism because of the findings of the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST). Our favorite YEC astronomers have finally discussed the JWST at length. On Wednesday, September 14, 2022, on Facebook Dr. Danny Faulkner and Rob Webb of AiG, and Dr. Jason Lisle (formerly of AiG, now at the Biblical Science Institute) discuss the early findings of the JWST for a full excruciating hour. Faulkner and Lisle have PhDs in astronomy. Rob Webb recently was hired by AiG as a preacher/scientist and has experience in aerospace engineering, helping design several different spacecraft (hence his AiG nickname “Rocket Rob”). Their “discussion” consists mostly of self-congratulation and sundry claims that every new finding supports Young Earth Creationism including having light from galaxies billions of light years away getting to Earth in a mere 6,000 years (a miracle!). Their self congratulations are based on the fact that astronomers are revising their ideas about how quickly galaxies and heavy elements formed in the early universe because of new data from JWST findings. This motley crew seems to be gloating that other astronomers are – gasp! – doing science. Much of the rest of the video is preaching/scripture quoting and, at about 23 minutes in, claiming a nefarious conspiracy of morally questionable “secular astronomers” based on their “worldview.” Most astronomers I know are upright citizens.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A wrong analysis of information in evolution</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/09/badinformation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A wrong analysis of information in evolution" /><published>2022-09-12T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-09-12T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/09/badinformation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/09/badinformation.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Dandelions.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dandelions image&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Dandelions at Nerstrand Big Woods State Park, Minnesota (c) 2018 Tony Webster, from Wikimedia&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a simple example of how natural selection can put functional information
into a population of organisms, I like to point to dandelions growing in
my yard.  They take energy from the sun and grow.  If there are two different
genotypes, one of which processes that solar energy more efficiently, the
frequency of that genotype will increase as it grows more than the other one,
competes better, and produces more seeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When we consider a scale of fitness, or a scale of energy-processing efficiency,
this process of natural selection shifts the distribution of genotypes so
that more and more of the dandelions have higher efficiency of energy
processing.  It does not take much calculating to see that the population 
then has increased functional information.  The information does not come mysteriously
from nowhere: energy is flowing from the sun into the plants, and ultimately 
heat is lost to the environment. All of which is a net increase in entropy. 
Evolution is simply slowing down this overall increase, not reversing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This would seem to be an elementary example.  But at the ID-advocacy website
Uncommon Descent, their regular post author Dr. Eric Hedin gets examples like
this wrong.  In a recent post &lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/natural-sources-of-information/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Natural sources of information?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  he quotes his own book &quot;Canceled Science: What Some Atheists Don't Want You to See&quot;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In systems which are far from thermodynamic equilibrium, differences or gradients in various thermodynamic variables may exist within the system and between the system and the environment. It has sometimes been mistakenly assumed that these gradients could generate the information found in living systems.[i] However, while thermodynamic gradients may produce complexity, they do not generate information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is particularly surprising since Dr. Hedin is trained as an experimental
plasma physicist, actually at my own university.  He obviously got a solid grounding in thermodynamics and information theory.  But somehow he has failed to
apply that correctly to evolving organisms.  Let's look more closely at
his discussion ...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the excerpt he quoted, Eric Hedin gives examples of natural processes 
that tend to degrade information.  For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our sun is a low-entropy source of thermal energy that the Earth receives via electromagnetic radiation. This thermal energy is useful energy in the thermodynamic sense because it can be used to do work. The same is true of energy released by gravitational potential energy being converted into kinetic energy or heat. Waterfalls and solar collectors can produce energy for useful work, but they are sterile with respect to generating information.
In fact, sources of natural energy (sunlight, fire, earthquakes, hurricanes, etc.) universally destroy complex specified information, and never create it. What will happen to a painting if left outside in the elements? What happens to a note tossed into a mulch pile? They degrade by the actions of nature, until all traces of information disappear. Or consider an unfortunate opossum killed on a country road. Will its internal, complex biochemistry increase or decrease with time due to the effects of natural forces? We all know the answer. If not eaten by scavengers, it eventually turns to a pile of dirt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These examples are fine, but they do not consider what happens when there are biological organisms 
present, such as my dandelions.  They can take sunlight, air and water, and make more dandelions,
which would seem to contradict the generalization that Dr. Hedin just made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He would probably answer that I have skipped over a part of his post where he addressed the 
case where there is a &quot;design template&quot;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Decreasing thermodynamic entropy can only be leveraged into information if a design template and the mechanism to employ it already exist. In this case, the desired information is not being created by the action of the low-entropy energy source; it is merely being transferred from the template to an output product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For an individual clone of dandelions, he would be asserting that when the number of dandelions of 
that genotype increases, that this is no gain of information.  But if the information is &quot;transferred&quot; 
to the offspring, this can happen multiple times, if the parent produces lots of seeds. Which is an 
odd way of bookkeeping the amount of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Things get even worse for his argument when we consider the information that gets put into the genome 
when natural selection favors one genotype over the other.  That is the case I started with.  Choosing 
one genotype out of a mixture, as the predominant genotype on my lawn, is a fundamental operation in 
information theory.  And if that genotype is the better one on a scale of specification or function, 
that is an increase of functional information in the population of genotypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Is that information coming from a &quot;template&quot;?  No.  Each genotype might (or might not) be considered
as one of Hedin's templates.  But where is the super-template that says which clone of dandelions will
ultimately predominate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Someone might point to William Dembski and Robert Marks's concept of &quot;active information&quot;, which 
seems to describe information existing in the fitness landscape, the table of fitnesses of all possible 
genotypes.  But that concept, whether sensible or not, is bookkeeping information that is transferred 
by natural processes, such as mutation and natural selection, into the population of genotypes.  It 
therefore already violates Hedin's generalization, so it cannot be used to rescue it.  Hedin's 
sweeping statements are contradicted by the natural processes of reproduction, and the process 
of natural selection which flows from them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Dandelions at Nerstrand Big Woods State Park, Minnesota (c) 2018 Tony Webster, from Wikimedia As a simple example of how natural selection can put functional information into a population of organisms, I like to point to dandelions growing in my yard. They take energy from the sun and grow. If there are two different genotypes, one of which processes that solar energy more efficiently, the frequency of that genotype will increase as it grows more than the other one, competes better, and produces more seeds. When we consider a scale of fitness, or a scale of energy-processing efficiency, this process of natural selection shifts the distribution of genotypes so that more and more of the dandelions have higher efficiency of energy processing. It does not take much calculating to see that the population then has increased functional information. The information does not come mysteriously from nowhere: energy is flowing from the sun into the plants, and ultimately heat is lost to the environment. All of which is a net increase in entropy. Evolution is simply slowing down this overall increase, not reversing it. This would seem to be an elementary example. But at the ID-advocacy website Uncommon Descent, their regular post author Dr. Eric Hedin gets examples like this wrong. In a recent post Natural sources of information? he quotes his own book &quot;Canceled Science: What Some Atheists Don't Want You to See&quot;: In systems which are far from thermodynamic equilibrium, differences or gradients in various thermodynamic variables may exist within the system and between the system and the environment. It has sometimes been mistakenly assumed that these gradients could generate the information found in living systems.[i] However, while thermodynamic gradients may produce complexity, they do not generate information. This is particularly surprising since Dr. Hedin is trained as an experimental plasma physicist, actually at my own university. He obviously got a solid grounding in thermodynamics and information theory. But somehow he has failed to apply that correctly to evolving organisms. Let's look more closely at his discussion ...</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lovell telescope</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/09/lovell-telescope.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lovell telescope" /><published>2022-09-12T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-09-12T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/09/lovell-telescope</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/09/lovell-telescope.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Marilyn Susek&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Susek.Lovell_Telescope.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lovell Telescope&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lovell_Telescope&quot;&gt;Lovell Telescope&lt;/a&gt; at Jodrell Bank Observatory, near Goostrey, Cheshire, England. Photograph taken while with the Sheffield Astronomical Society trip to Jodrell Bank. When it was built, the Lovell Telescope was the largest steerable radio telescope in the world.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Marilyn Susek. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Lovell Telescope at Jodrell Bank Observatory, near Goostrey, Cheshire, England. Photograph taken while with the Sheffield Astronomical Society trip to Jodrell Bank. When it was built, the Lovell Telescope was the largest steerable radio telescope in the world.</summary></entry></feed>