<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-11-29T08:07:02-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Amanda Townley new director at NCSE</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/amanda-townley-new-director.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amanda Townley new director at NCSE" /><published>2023-11-28T13:35:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-11-28T13:35:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/amanda-townley-new-director</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/amanda-townley-new-director.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Amanda_Townley_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Amanda Townley&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Amanda Townley, incoming director of the National Center for Science Education. &lt;small&gt;Copyright by Amanda Townley. Used with permission.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amanda Townley is set to become the third director of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/&quot;&gt;National Center for Science Education&lt;/a&gt;, succeeding present director Ann Reid and the “legendary” founder Eugenie Scott, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/article/brought-creationist-home-scientist-fights-evolution&quot;&gt;an article&lt;/a&gt; by Jeffrey Mervis, posted today by the magazine &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;. Dr. Townley, currently a professor of education at Georgia Southern University, is also &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.georgiasouthern.edu/my/2023/01/25/amanda-townley-ph-d-elected-president-of-national-association-of-biology-teachers/&quot;&gt;President of the National Association of Biology Teachers&lt;/a&gt;. She will assume responsibility for a staff of 11 and an annual budget of $1.5 million in December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Townley told &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; that she had been brought up in a home that embraced young-earth creationism. When the biology teacher skipped the chapter on evolution, young Amanda took it upon herself to read that chapter and thought it made a lot of sense. She decided to become an evolutionary biologist and to teach evolutionary biology. Ultimately, she helped to develop a teaching strategy known as &lt;i&gt;cultural and religious sensitivity&lt;/i&gt;, which “allows teachers and students to address their conflicting views before delving into the subject matter,” in the words of Mr. Mervis. Briefly, the teacher respects students’ views, and students are taught that their beliefs do not preclude accepting evolution. You may read more detail in the &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt; article and in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/ncse-names-amanda-l-townley-next-executive-director&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; by NCSE Director of Communications Paul Oh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Amanda Townley, incoming director of the National Center for Science Education. Copyright by Amanda Townley. Used with permission. Amanda Townley is set to become the third director of the National Center for Science Education, succeeding present director Ann Reid and the “legendary” founder Eugenie Scott, according to an article by Jeffrey Mervis, posted today by the magazine Science. Dr. Townley, currently a professor of education at Georgia Southern University, is also President of the National Association of Biology Teachers. She will assume responsibility for a staff of 11 and an annual budget of $1.5 million in December. Dr. Townley told Science that she had been brought up in a home that embraced young-earth creationism. When the biology teacher skipped the chapter on evolution, young Amanda took it upon herself to read that chapter and thought it made a lot of sense. She decided to become an evolutionary biologist and to teach evolutionary biology. Ultimately, she helped to develop a teaching strategy known as cultural and religious sensitivity, which “allows teachers and students to address their conflicting views before delving into the subject matter,” in the words of Mr. Mervis. Briefly, the teacher respects students’ views, and students are taught that their beliefs do not preclude accepting evolution. You may read more detail in the Science article and in an article by NCSE Director of Communications Paul Oh. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Geococcyx californianus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/Geococcyx-californianus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Geococcyx californianus" /><published>2023-11-27T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-11-27T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/Geococcyx-californianus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/Geococcyx-californianus.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Mark Lee&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Lee_Greater_Roadrunner.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Greater roadrunner&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Greater_Roadrunner/overview&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Geococcyx californianus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; greater roadrunner.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Mark Lee. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Geococcyx californianus &amp;ndash; greater roadrunner. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Edition of Dembski's Design Inference</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/new-edition-design-inference.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Edition of Dembski's Design Inference" /><published>2023-11-19T09:15:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-11-19T09:15:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/new-edition-design-inference</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/new-edition-design-inference.html">&lt;p&gt;Last year, I published a book called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Failures-Mathematical-Anti-Evolutionism-Jason-Rosenhouse/dp/1108820441&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Failures of Mathematical Anti-Evolutionism&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with Cambridge University Press.  As the title suggests, I analyze all of the major mathematical arguments put forth by creationists and intelligent design (ID) proponents and find them all to be very poor.  Inevitably, I devote a fair amount of space to William Dembski’s arguments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I naturally raised an eyebrow upon hearing that Dembski has now released a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Design-Inference-Eliminating-through-Probabilities/dp/1637120346&quot;&gt; revised and expanded edition&lt;/a&gt; of his 1998 book &lt;i&gt;The Design Inference&lt;/i&gt;, now coauthored with Winston Ewert.  I wondered if he would have anything worthwhile to say in response to my book, and it was gratifying to see that my name shows up numerous times in the index.  I will look forward to seeing what he has to say, once I have acquired a copy of the book.  However, Dembski has &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2023/11/an-argument-from-ignorance/&quot;&gt;posted an excerpt&lt;/a&gt; from the book’s Introduction, and I was delighted to see that, perhaps inadvertently, he has simply conceded two of the main points I raised against his ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recall that Dembski’s catchphrase is “complex, specified information.”  Roughly, this means that if something has a low probability of arising by chance and instantiates an independently describable pattern, then intelligent design is implicated at some point in its causal history.  In my book, I argued that, to the extent that he intends to apply this to biological structures, he has no hope of establishing either complexity or specificity.  We have nothing like the information we need to carry out a meaningful probability calculation, and we have no background information relevant to distinguishing design-suggesting patterns from those we simply impose on nature (like seeing a dragon in a fluffy, cumulus cloud).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More specifically, I noted that when Dembski calculates the probability of something like a flagellum, he explicitly assumes that an “irreducibly complex” (IC) system cannot evolve by gradual means.  This means his argument is completely parasitic on Michael Behe’s claims about IC systems: If those claims are correct, then they are all by themselves a strong argument against evolution.  A probability calculation adds nothing.  But since those claims are completely wrong, no calculation based on them will have any meaning.  For specification, I noted that Dembski presents an elaborate mathematical apparatus, complete with notation, jargon, and Greek letters, which is meant to allow us to distinguish real patterns from artificial ones.  But then he never uses that machinery for anything, but instead just says that biological structures are obviously specified by their function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that set-up, here is Dembski from his Introduction:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Tacitly in the first edition of &lt;i&gt;The Design Inference&lt;/i&gt; and explicitly in its sequel, &lt;i&gt;No Free Lunch&lt;/i&gt;, I argued that natural selection and random variation could not create the sort of complexity we see in living things.  My approach in applying the design inference to biology was to piggyback on the work of design biologists Douglas Axe and Michael Behe.  They had identified certain subcellular systems . . . that proved highly resistant to Darwinian explanations.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Precisely my point!  “Piggyback” is a more polite term than “parasitic,” but my term is more accurate.  It is the claims made by Behe and Axe that are doing all the work in the argument that evolution as currently understood is seriously deficient.  Dembski’s calculations are irrelevant, in addition to being incorrect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing from the last quote, Dembski writes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Our joint task was to put plausible numbers to these systems so that even factoring in Darwinian natural selection, the probability of those systems arising was exceedingly small.  Note that the specification of these systems, as in their exhibiting the right sort of a pattern for a design inference, was never in question.  The issue was always whether the probabilities were small enough.  
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dembski’s calculations do not, in even the slightest way, “factor in” Darwinian natural selection.  Instead, they use certain claims made by Behe and Axe to justify ignoring natural selection altogether.  Once again, it is those claims, and not Dembski’s pointless calculations, that are doing all the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, note how dismissive he is of establishing “specificity” in his idiosyncratic sense.  This, again, was precisely my point.  Dembski and his supporters tell the world he has a mathematically rigorous way of distinguishing real patterns from artificial ones.  But that mathematical machinery plays no role at all in his actual argument that the flagellum, say, is specified.  Apparently, to specify a flagellum it is sufficient to say, “Kinda looks like an outboard motor.”  Nothing rigorous about it.  And since biologists argue that natural selection crafts functional systems as a matter of course, I would say the question of specificity is very much in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this excerpt is representative of the rest of the book, then I do not think his critics have anything to worry about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me finish with an extended analogy.  Suppose someone tells you they drew five cards from a shuffled deck and that all were the same suit.  He asks you to work out the probability of that happening.  No problem, that is a basic calculation.  But then he gives you a plot twist.  He tells you that his deck has millions of cards and dozens of suits, and that he will not be any more specific than that.  At this point you laugh and say you need more information to find the probability, thinking that you had just stated the obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now an ID proponent charges into the room.  He says, “Of course you can work out the probability.  Just assume there are exactly one million cards and forty suits, with the same number of cards in each suit.”  He then scribbles down elaborate calculations involving factorials and binomial coefficients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astonished that anyone would seriously put forth such a thing, you reply that his calculation is silly since it is based on entirely arbitrary assumptions.  But he just ignores you and says, “And not only is this improbable, but it’s also specified!  I mean, seriously, five cards of the same suit.  What an obvious pattern!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point you are face-palming and rolling your eyes.  You point out that since we know nothing about the distribution of suits in this deck, we have no idea if it is remarkable to get five cards of the same suit.  You say, “For all we know one suit is so overrepresented in the deck that getting five of the same suit is close to inevitable.”  Again, you are surprised you need to point this out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the ID proponent is undaunted.  He shouts, “You’re just a dogmatic, anti-religious tool of the scientific mafia.”  Then he runs out of the room and writes books telling the world about how he has revolutionized mathematics, biology, and philosophy.  His sycophants start calling him the Isaac Newton of information theory.  Meanwhile, you are left wondering what just happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End scene.  I think that captures the frustration scientists feel when addressing ID proponents.  Except that there is one point where my analogy does not go far enough: In the analogy, the assumptions underlying the calculation were merely unjustified.  In Dembski’s writing, the assumptions are plainly false.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dembski packs an astonishing amount of error into such a short excerpt, and there is much more to comment on than what I have presented here.  But we will save that for another day.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jason Rosenhouse</name></author><summary type="html">Last year, I published a book called The Failures of Mathematical Anti-Evolutionism with Cambridge University Press. As the title suggests, I analyze all of the major mathematical arguments put forth by creationists and intelligent design (ID) proponents and find them all to be very poor. Inevitably, I devote a fair amount of space to William Dembski’s arguments. So I naturally raised an eyebrow upon hearing that Dembski has now released a revised and expanded edition of his 1998 book The Design Inference, now coauthored with Winston Ewert. I wondered if he would have anything worthwhile to say in response to my book, and it was gratifying to see that my name shows up numerous times in the index. I will look forward to seeing what he has to say, once I have acquired a copy of the book. However, Dembski has posted an excerpt from the book’s Introduction, and I was delighted to see that, perhaps inadvertently, he has simply conceded two of the main points I raised against his ideas.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pterocomma sp.</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/pterocomma-sp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pterocomma sp." /><published>2023-11-13T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-11-13T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/pterocomma-sp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/pterocomma-sp.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/P1010941_aphid_pterocomma_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aphid&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aphid&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Pterocomma&lt;/i&gt; sp.&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; one of the few aphids that survived a light frost and also the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/harmonia-axyridis.html&quot;&gt;lady-beetle larva&lt;/a&gt; shown two weeks ago. (Thanks once again to the experts at &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugguide.net/node/view/15740&quot;&gt;Bugguide&lt;/a&gt; for the identification.)
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Pterocomma sp. &amp;ndash; one of the few aphids that survived a light frost and also the lady-beetle larva shown two weeks ago. (Thanks once again to the experts at Bugguide for the identification.) To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Martyn Iles Is Now Executive CEO of Answers in Genesis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/Martyn-Iles-Is-Executive.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Martyn Iles Is Now Executive CEO of Answers in Genesis" /><published>2023-11-10T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-11-10T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/Martyn-Iles-Is-Executive</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/Martyn-Iles-Is-Executive.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Screenshot 2023-11-10_Iles_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Martyn Iles&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Martyn Iles. &lt;small&gt;Fair Use&lt;/small&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Martyn Iles, who first joined Answers in Genesis in May of this year, is now Executive CEO. Iles announced this development on his own Facebook page with, the next day, an identical emailing from Answers in Genesis to its supporters, and an article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://vision.org.au/faith/martyn-iles-answers-in-genesis-ceo/&quot;&gt;Martin Iles: Answers in Genesis CEO&lt;/a&gt;, in Vision Christian Media, by Tony Davenport. The article is mainly devoted to Iles’s own statement, with a flattering headshot and minimal mention of Ken Ham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iles’s ascendance is very bad news indeed, not only because he is a formidable figure, but also because he is explicitly far more political than Ham ever revealed himself to be. On January 21, 2021, two weeks after the Capitol riot, Iles, who was still at that time managing director of the politically explicit Australian Christian Lobby, posted,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Donald Trump's term in the White House ends today, so I thought I'd share this crucial highlight of his presidency... Thanks President Trump, from an Aussie who still likes you and is happy to admit it. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This highlight consists of Trump making pugnacious gestures to an applauding crowd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, in a podcast, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/BrBgSjAC7kE&quot;&gt;The truth of it&lt;/a&gt;, Episode 55, shortly after the November, 2020 election, Iles noted the narrow margins in some states, drawing attention to lawsuits, and claimed that suspicion of fraud was reasonable:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;There's a radical strand [of people on the left]… Do you really think that they wouldn't—they wouldn’t have a little tamper with a vote to stop a man who they believe is literally Hitler?… Of course, they would. … I mean, forgive me for thinking that someone who sets fire to a church wouldn't mess with 10,000 ballots. Of course, they would. Of course, they would.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Here, Iles is presumably trying to link the election result to nebulous allegations of damage by un-named rioters.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Iles’s statement announcing his appointment, quoted in Davenport’s article, he mentions two new concerns:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Just as scientific naturalism has threatened the faith of so many, post-modernism and new critical theories threaten the faith of a new generation.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find the reference to &lt;i&gt;new&lt;/i&gt; critical theories interesting. Churches have been dealing with textual criticism of the Bible for over a century, so I suspect that he is referring to critical theories of society, such as Critical Race Theory. As Governor DeSantis’s policies in Florida show, criticism of CRT is now used to attack any teaching that questions conservative dogma, much as 70 years ago such questioning was condemned as Communism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Postmodernism was a bit of a surprise, but Mike Johnson has also attacked postmodernism, in his &lt;a href=&quot;https://3quarksdaily.com/3quarksdaily/2023/10/learning-about-darwin-causes-mass-shootings-according-to-mike-johnson.html&quot;&gt;2017 Shreveport Christian Center speech&lt;/a&gt;.There he referred to postmodernism, which he described as a $10 word that he needed to explain to his audience, as among the results of studying Darwin, because it elevates individual opinion over the one and only Truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have yet to see how Answers in Genesis will evolve under its new management, and how it will affect long-standing members of the AIG team, such as Ham’s son-in-law Bodie Hodge, who has been with Answers in Genesis for 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following is the text of the announcement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a great honour to announce I have been elevated to the position of Executive CEO by the board of Answers in Genesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fear not – Ken Ham is still the Founding CEO. We are leading together for the next season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an arrangement designed to set Answers in Genesis up for the future. It means our feet are firmly planted on our foundations whilst we adapt to a new era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The culture is changing, fast. The next generation is different. Digital technology is disrupting our existence.
Just as scientific naturalism has threatened the faith of so many, postmodernism and new critical theories threaten the faith of a new generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But God’s word is a word for every generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the gospel is God’s answer to every generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will adapt to that which is new, holding fast to that which is timeless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please pray for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Unless the Lord builds the house, those that labour build it in vain.” (Ps 127:1)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. And… Both Ken and I will be in Australia together in March 2024. Do not miss it!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman</name></author><summary type="html">Martyn Iles. Fair Use. Martyn Iles, who first joined Answers in Genesis in May of this year, is now Executive CEO. Iles announced this development on his own Facebook page with, the next day, an identical emailing from Answers in Genesis to its supporters, and an article, Martin Iles: Answers in Genesis CEO, in Vision Christian Media, by Tony Davenport. The article is mainly devoted to Iles’s own statement, with a flattering headshot and minimal mention of Ken Ham. Iles’s ascendance is very bad news indeed, not only because he is a formidable figure, but also because he is explicitly far more political than Ham ever revealed himself to be. On January 21, 2021, two weeks after the Capitol riot, Iles, who was still at that time managing director of the politically explicit Australian Christian Lobby, posted,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Harmonia axyridis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/harmonia-axyridis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Harmonia axyridis" /><published>2023-10-30T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-30T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/harmonia-axyridis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/harmonia-axyridis.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/P1010906_Lady_Beetle_Harmonia_axyridis_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lady beetle larva&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;This ferocious looking creature may resemble an Asian lady beetle, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harmonia_axyridis&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Harmonia axyridis&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, eating an aphid, but it is in fact an Internet Avenger eating a troll. They will be out in force tomorrow night, October 31, the eve of All Hallows Day. Trolls are hereby warned not to go online tomorrow and at all costs stay away from bridges.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click here:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">This ferocious looking creature may resemble an Asian lady beetle, Harmonia axyridis, eating an aphid, but it is in fact an Internet Avenger eating a troll. They will be out in force tomorrow night, October 31, the eve of All Hallows Day. Trolls are hereby warned not to go online tomorrow and at all costs stay away from bridges. To see comments on this post click here:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dan Phelps reminds Ken Ham of some important tax benefits</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/dan-phelps-reminds-ken-ham.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dan Phelps reminds Ken Ham of some important tax benefits" /><published>2023-10-29T09:45:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-29T09:45:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/dan-phelps-reminds-ken-ham</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/dan-phelps-reminds-ken-ham.html">&lt;p&gt;Our indefatigable colleague Dan Phelps seems to have caught Ken Ham in a, um, mild prevarication and corrects the record here. In particular, Mr. Phelps read an October 27 tweet (or a twX or whatever they are called now) in which Mr. Ham proclaimed,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;At @AiG we have stated so many times before that the Ark was funded 100% by private funding. Let me say it again, the @ArkEncounter project and the @CreationMuseum were both funded 100% from private funding. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Phelps notes that the Ark receives a sales tax rebate of $1.825 million every year. Perhaps, he says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; Ham could always decide not to cash the check and return it to the Commonwealth of Kentucky if he wishes to keep claiming lack of government support. However, even if he returned the sales tax rebate money, he would still be getting or has received all sorts of other money and benefits from state, county, and city sources. These include and have included: &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;City of Williamstown sold Ark 98 acres of land for $1. &lt;/li&gt;



&lt;li&gt;City also gave AIG $175,000 in cash. &lt;/li&gt;



&lt;li&gt;City reduced property tax on Ark. &lt;/li&gt;



&lt;li&gt;City issued $62 million in unsecured junk bonds for Ark construction. &lt;/li&gt;



&lt;li&gt;75% of Ark Encounter's property taxes will go to repaying bonds instead of to local government. &lt;/li&gt;



&lt;li&gt;Employees of Ark Encounter must pay 2% of wages to Ark bond debt (for next 30 years). &lt;/li&gt;



&lt;li&gt;State transportation cabinet spent $11 million to upgrade Interstate 75 exits in anticipation of huge traffic increase that did not occur. &lt;/li&gt;



&lt;li&gt;AIG claims Ark is worth $130 million on 990 forms to Federal government and potentially when getting loans. Grant County property tax valuation (which supports local schools) assesses Ark value at $48 million.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire tweet (or whatever) is reproduced below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Ham_Tweet_1_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tweet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Ham_Tweet_2_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tweet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Curiously, a headline in an unspecified newspaper proclaimed that Representative Mike Johnson, the Speaker of the House of the moment, had once funded a Noah’s Ark theme park. Mr. Ham categorizes this claim as a lie. Whether or not it is a lie or merely an error, Mr. Phelps notes that on this point only, Mr. Ham is correct. Interestingly, though, Mr. Johnson once successfully represented the Ark in a suit against the Commonwealth of Kentucky. He published &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kentucky.com/opinion/letters-to-the-editor/article44504949.html&quot;&gt;this diatribe&lt;/a&gt; against Mr. Phelps under the head, “Ark Park unfairly damned.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Our indefatigable colleague Dan Phelps seems to have caught Ken Ham in a, um, mild prevarication and corrects the record here. In particular, Mr. Phelps read an October 27 tweet (or a twX or whatever they are called now) in which Mr. Ham proclaimed, At @AiG we have stated so many times before that the Ark was funded 100% by private funding. Let me say it again, the @ArkEncounter project and the @CreationMuseum were both funded 100% from private funding. Mr. Phelps notes that the Ark receives a sales tax rebate of $1.825 million every year. Perhaps, he says, Ham could always decide not to cash the check and return it to the Commonwealth of Kentucky if he wishes to keep claiming lack of government support. However, even if he returned the sales tax rebate money, he would still be getting or has received all sorts of other money and benefits from state, county, and city sources. These include and have included:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Do we have free will? No</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/do-we-have-free-will.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do we have free will? No" /><published>2023-10-24T11:35:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-24T11:35:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/do-we-have-free-will</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/do-we-have-free-will.html">&lt;p&gt;Jerry Coyne ran an &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2023/10/22/robert-sapolsky-gets-interviewed-about-his-new-book-on-free-will-and-determinism/&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; the other day on the question of free will. The occasion was the publication of Robert Sapolsky’s book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Determined-Science-Life-without-Free-ebook/dp/B0BSKQ5ZDM/&quot;&gt;Determined: A Science of Life without Free Will&lt;/a&gt;. Sapolsky, in turn, was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2023/10/16/science/free-will-sapolsky.html&quot;&gt;interviewed&lt;/a&gt; by Hope Reese in &lt;i&gt;The New York Times&lt;/i&gt;. The online title, incidentally, was “Robert Sapolsky doesn’t believe in free will. (But feel free to disagree.)”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coyne, Sapolsky, and I are what are called “hard determinists”: we think that “all our actions are determined by the laws of physics.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not know what all the fuss is about; any physicist could have told them that. Indeed, I said it myself in a 2001 book on science and religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book was &lt;i&gt;No Sense of Obligation: Science and Religion in an Impersonal Universe&lt;/i&gt;. It suffered from two main problems: (1) It was 5 or 10 years ahead of its time, and (2) it was not shrill enough and too sympathetic to religion. I have long ago given up the idea of becoming rich on it, and you may read it &lt;a href=&quot;https://people.mines.edu/mmyoung/wp-content/uploads/sites/99/2019/01/Young_No_Sense_of_Obligation.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the point: In that book, I argued that humans were biological creatures and therefore governed by the laws of physics. Those laws are deterministic (we will get back to that in a minute), so everything we do, think, or decide is determined by those laws. We may think we have free will; we certainly have to act as if we have free will; but in fact we have no such thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now before you get your knickers in a twist, none of the foregoing implies, for example, that we should not punish criminals. The pain they may inflict is real, and we may have to separate them from society until (or unless) they reform. I suggest, however, that their lack of free will suggests that we should be rehabilitating rather than punishing criminals. But that discussion is a little off-task here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I wrote &lt;i&gt;NSO&lt;/i&gt;, I assumed that quantum mechanics was itself purely deterministic and that some day we would discover an underlying, deterministic theory. It simply seemed unreasonable that, for example, an atomic nucleus would decide all on its own to emit an alpha particle, rather than being caused to do so by some external agency. It still seems unreasonable to me, but it may not be right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does quantum mechanics then come to our rescue and somehow grant free will? No. First, so many molecules are involved in, say, neurotransmission that their action may be considered completely classical and therefore completely deterministic. Even so, the occasional quantum fluctuation would not so much grant free will as it would make our decisions somewhat random, a condition that I think proponents of free will would not particularly care for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quantum randomness may have been critically important to the evolution of the early universe. If we ran the “experiment” again, we might, for all I know, end up with a very different universe, one that does not even include us. That said, quantum randomness has very little effect on our daily lives, unless you count, for example, cancers induced by radioactive decay or cosmic radiation. Thus, as Sapolsky would argue, everything we think, say, and do is wholly and unequivocally determined by our detailed histories (except, as I have noted, for the occasional quantum fluctuation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I conclude, then, that we have no free will in any sense. I do not understand why some people consider that threatening; it simply is the way it is. We feel as if we have free will, we act as if we have free will, and we are treated as if we have free will. Free will is thus a useful fiction, but in reality it is only a fiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will undoubtedly read Sapolsky’s book when I get a chance. I think, though, that I will end with a complaint, one that I have made before: The Kindle edition of this book, which I may lease but not own, costs $18.99. The hardcover costs $23.28, and the paperback $12.95. Thus, I am expected to spend $6.04 for the convenience of leasing the Kindle edition, rather than owning the paperback edition. I was not going to write this paragraph, but I had no choice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Jerry Coyne ran an article the other day on the question of free will. The occasion was the publication of Robert Sapolsky’s book, Determined: A Science of Life without Free Will. Sapolsky, in turn, was interviewed by Hope Reese in The New York Times. The online title, incidentally, was “Robert Sapolsky doesn’t believe in free will. (But feel free to disagree.)” Coyne, Sapolsky, and I are what are called “hard determinists”: we think that “all our actions are determined by the laws of physics.” I do not know what all the fuss is about; any physicist could have told them that. Indeed, I said it myself in a 2001 book on science and religion.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Darren Naish takes on ornithologist Alan Feduccia</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/naish-takes-on-feduccia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Darren Naish takes on ornithologist Alan Feduccia" /><published>2023-10-22T09:28:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-22T09:28:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/naish-takes-on-feduccia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/naish-takes-on-feduccia.html">&lt;p&gt;Paleontologist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darren_Naish&quot;&gt;Darren Naish&lt;/a&gt; recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://tetzoo.com/blog/2023/10/2/alan-feduccia-romancing-the-birds-and-dinosaurs&quot;&gt;reviewed &lt;i&gt;Romancing the Birds and Dinosaurs&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by the contrarian ornithologist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_Feduccia&quot;&gt;Alan Feduccia&lt;/a&gt;.  Prof. Feduccia, an emeritus professor at the University of North Carolina, has for years denied the conventional wisdom that birds are descended from Mesozoic dinosaurs. According to my colleague Martin Neukamm,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;[&quot;Romancing&quot;] is like an all-out attack on the mainstream of evolutionary research; it even advanced to a kind of edification reading for creationism.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Naish, an author and consultant, describes himself as “associated” with the University of Southampton (UK), the BBC’s Natural History Unit, and the National Maritime Museum, Falmouth. His review, shall we say, was not entirely favorable. Here is one of the (admittedly more extreme) paragraphs that caught my eye:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;... But try as I might to think of the author as a wise sage and friend of the reader, the fact is that &lt;i&gt;RTBAD&lt;/i&gt; is cartoonishly overloaded with bias and dirty tricks. Whataboutism, intellectual dishonesty, erroneous repetition, strawmanning and naïve falsification appear throughout as the author aims to diminish positions he dislikes, the most vehement of his arguments representing nothing more than personal incredulity.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Neukamm and his colleague Andreas Beyer were allowed to translate the review into German, and you may find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ag-evolutionsbiologie.net/html/2023/feduccia-romancing-birds-and-dinosaurs.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Our thanks to Mr. Neukamm for the tip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click here:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Paleontologist Darren Naish recently reviewed Romancing the Birds and Dinosaurs by the contrarian ornithologist Alan Feduccia. Prof. Feduccia, an emeritus professor at the University of North Carolina, has for years denied the conventional wisdom that birds are descended from Mesozoic dinosaurs. According to my colleague Martin Neukamm, [&quot;Romancing&quot;] is like an all-out attack on the mainstream of evolutionary research; it even advanced to a kind of edification reading for creationism. Dr. Naish, an author and consultant, describes himself as “associated” with the University of Southampton (UK), the BBC’s Natural History Unit, and the National Maritime Museum, Falmouth. His review, shall we say, was not entirely favorable. Here is one of the (admittedly more extreme) paragraphs that caught my eye: ... But try as I might to think of the author as a wise sage and friend of the reader, the fact is that RTBAD is cartoonishly overloaded with bias and dirty tricks. Whataboutism, intellectual dishonesty, erroneous repetition, strawmanning and naïve falsification appear throughout as the author aims to diminish positions he dislikes, the most vehement of his arguments representing nothing more than personal incredulity. Mr. Neukamm and his colleague Andreas Beyer were allowed to translate the review into German, and you may find it here. Our thanks to Mr. Neukamm for the tip. To see comments on this post click here:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Deadly Rise of Anti-Science: book by Peter Hotez</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/deadly-rise-anti-science.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Deadly Rise of Anti-Science: book by Peter Hotez" /><published>2023-10-20T07:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-20T07:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/deadly-rise-anti-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/10/deadly-rise-anti-science.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Hotez_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Hotez and his team have developed inexpensive vaccines and distributed them to the Third World through a nonprofit organization. No good deed goes unpunished, and as he describes in the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Deadly-Rise-Anti-science-Scientists-Warning-ebook/dp/B0BWSLNSVY&quot;&gt;The Deadly Rise of Anti-Science&lt;/a&gt;, he was therefore vilified by the anti-vaccination faction. Anti-vaxxers, as they are often called, have gained so much influence that so far 200,000 Americans have died of Covid because they refused the vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anti-vaxxers have had enough influence that we now see occasional outbreaks of measles, a disease that once had been virtually eliminated. I remember the polio epidemic of the 1940’s and -50’s, and I am very much afraid that mandatory vaccinations for students in public schools may be on the way out. Indeed, Dr. Hotez notes that preliminary data show declines in childhood immunization in conservative states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Hotez sees the anti-vaxxers as part of a right-wing conspiracy to undermine not just vaccination but science in general. You may consider it overstatement, but he compares the anti-vaccination, anti-science movement to similar movements in Stalinist Russia and Nazi Germany. He is sufficiently concerned that he suggests courses in science communication for graduate students. Additionally, he suggests something like a Southern Poverty Law Center to protect scientists and academics, but the proposal is too vague to merit much discussion here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At any rate, the problem has become political, not scientific. Virtually no reputable scientists doubt the value of vaccines (nor accept the efficacy of &lt;a href=&quot;https://scdhec.gov/covid19/dangers-using-hydroxychloroquine-ivermectin-preventing-or-treating-covid-19&quot;&gt;hydrochloroquine or ivermectin&lt;/a&gt;). Nevertheless, a significant amount of money from right-wing sources is spreading disinformation about vaccination, just as they have about climate change and evolution. Russia has also apparently developed a program of vaccine disinformation aimed at the United States. Vaccine denialism is also spreading worldwide. Dr. Hotez claims that far-right and extremist groups “play hardball.” I think he is mistaken: they play snowball with rocks concealed inside their snowballs. No one, he says, is coming to our rescue; we have to take care of ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one time, Dr. Hotez went public and appeared in television interviews, including on Fox News, in an attempt, as he put it, to reach across the aisle. When he was subsequently attacked by the right wing, most ominously white supremacists and anti-Semites, he checked in with the climate-change expert Michael Mann and found that the attack by climate-change deniers paralleled the attack by anti-vaxxers. Climate scientists now have a system for responding to the attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anti-science faction is already sufficiently in control in, say, Florida that the governor there gets his advice from “contrarians and so-called experts from far-right think tanks.” In this vein, you may read a nice section on Trofim Lysenko and the influence he had in the Soviet Union under Stalin. The brain drain from Nazi Germany may also be relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book makes a case for vaccination and also notes that the number and distribution of those who succumbed to the Covid virus (and therefore did not vote) could have been enough to tip the last presidential election in favor of Pres. Biden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In time, Dr. Hotez says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;[he] came to believe the tremendous loss in human life from the COVID-19 immunization refusal was not an accident but an orchestrated product of a networked political ecosystem of anti-science extremism.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, he notes, you cannot defeat this kind of anti-science extremism with facts and data; emotional appeals can be far more compelling (see also my article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/how-to-talk-science-denier.html&quot;&gt;How to Talk to a Science Denier&lt;/a&gt;, by Lee McIntyre). The government, for its part, hoped the extremists would run out of gas and “die a quiet death.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Hotez is a professor of Tropical Medicine at Baylor College of Medicine in Houston and has an appointment at the Texas Children’s Hospital. He was introduced to the anti-science world when he published a book, &lt;i&gt;Vaccines Did Not Cause Rachel’s [his daughter’s] Autism&lt;/i&gt;, and was attacked by the anti-vaxx crowd, which believes otherwise, partly as a result of a thoroughly discredited study. He worked hard to develop the Covid vaccine and supply it to the Third World. He was nominated for the Nobel Peace Prize, as he reminds us more than once, but I had the impression that it was his own colleagues who nominated him. The book, while good and useful, sometimes has a little more personal narrative than I might have wanted and appears just a wee bit self-serving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Hotez_Customer_Reviews_10_18.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Graph of reviews&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Histogram of reviews on Amazon as of October 18, 2023.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you were wondering, the book gets a sizeable number of one-star reviews on Amazon (see the figure). Some of the reviewers have read the book; some have not. I imagine it is a quasi-orchestrated attempt to denigrate the work, as happened previously with respect to the film, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/We_Believe_in_Dinosaurs&quot;&gt;We Believe in Dinosaurs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told myself I would not exactly review the book, but I cannot help noticing mistakes like these: pedal for peddle, diffuse for defuse. Additionally, I was somewhat put off by the use of first names – Tony instead of Fauci or Dr. Fauci – which had the effect, probably unintentional, of showing how the author is on first-name terms with several VIP’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[open rant]And finally, I am the author or co-author of 5 published books, so I am the last person who would begrudge a publisher or an author their due. Yet I was very put off when I found that the Kindle edition cost $21.34, whereas the hardback (there is no paperback) cost &lt;strike&gt;$24.95&lt;/strike&gt; $22.46, or $1.12 more than the Kindle – and I do not even get to own the Kindle edition! Surely, the marginal cost of manufacturing the hardback book is well over $1.12. So I confess that, in a fit of pique, I borrowed the Kindle edition from a library. It seems to me that a Kindle book, which I technically lease but do not purchase, has virtually no marginal cost and ought to cost less than a paperback, yet their prices are slowly inching up.[end rant]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Peter Hotez and his team have developed inexpensive vaccines and distributed them to the Third World through a nonprofit organization. No good deed goes unpunished, and as he describes in the book The Deadly Rise of Anti-Science, he was therefore vilified by the anti-vaccination faction. Anti-vaxxers, as they are often called, have gained so much influence that so far 200,000 Americans have died of Covid because they refused the vaccine. Anti-vaxxers have had enough influence that we now see occasional outbreaks of measles, a disease that once had been virtually eliminated. I remember the polio epidemic of the 1940’s and -50’s, and I am very much afraid that mandatory vaccinations for students in public schools may be on the way out. Indeed, Dr. Hotez notes that preliminary data show declines in childhood immunization in conservative states. Dr. Hotez sees the anti-vaxxers as part of a right-wing conspiracy to undermine not just vaccination but science in general. You may consider it overstatement, but he compares the anti-vaccination, anti-science movement to similar movements in Stalinist Russia and Nazi Germany. He is sufficiently concerned that he suggests courses in science communication for graduate students. Additionally, he suggests something like a Southern Poverty Law Center to protect scientists and academics, but the proposal is too vague to merit much discussion here.</summary></entry></feed>