<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-11-17T16:29:13-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Science, hypotheses, and intelligent design</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell8.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science, hypotheses, and intelligent design" /><published>2022-11-16T13:15:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-11-16T13:15:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell8</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell8.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is an additional post by Lars Johan Erkell made on September 8, 2021 in Swedish at the Biolog(g) site after the seven posts 
of his “Breakthrough for Intelligent Design?” series were made.  He has requested that we post it here after 
the second post in that series, to explain his position in that post on what can be considered legitimate 
science.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A central point in the discussion I have with Ola Hössjer in the posts entitled &quot;Breakthrough for
intelligent design?&quot; concerns the limits for what can be considered legitimate science. Since my
responses to his comments on this matter are too long for the comments section, I have made a
separate post on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The central question is how to formulate a hypothesis, that is, a suggested explanation for a
phenomenon. Hypotheses are not formulated in an arbitrary way; you don't just grab something out
of the air. A hypothesis should be based on prior knowledge. It should also be falsifiable, which
means that it must be possible to show that it is incorrect. The scientific work then consists of testing
the hypothesis. Whether it proves to be true or false, something new has been learned. The
important thing here is that the hypothesis is formulated in such a way that it can be tested in
practice with a clear-cut result. If you cannot do that, you cannot learn anything new. And if you
cannot test your hypotheses, you cannot root your theories in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, just because a hypothesis is falsifiable does not mean that it is scientific. For example, &quot;the
Moon is a cheese&quot; is a falsifiable (and falsified) hypothesis. But pure nonsense. If we want to give it a
scientific touch, we can formulate it as a classical syllogism:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Premise 1: The Moon is yellow, round and has craters&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Premise 2: A cut cheese is yellow, round and has pits that look like craters&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conclusion: The Moon is a cheese&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This conclusion is not just grabbed out of thin air; it is based on an analogy. But it is still nonsense.
My point here is that just because a hypothesis is falsifiable, or is expressed in a formally correct
manner, that does not mean it is plausible or even makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example of a falsifiable hypothesis that is scientifically acceptable, let us take a classic: Darwin's
hypothesis of the common descent of life forms. It implies, among other implications, that older
forms must lie below younger forms in the fossil record. In other words, a fossil of a reliably
identified and reliably dated rabbit (or any other modern mammal) may not be found in Cambrian
deposits, i.e. from a time long before the first mammals emerged. Despite millions of fossils being
unearthed, nothing has yet been found to disprove Darwin's hypothesis. Still, in principle it could
happen, and that would be a fundamental blow to the theory of evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can hear ID proponents argue that ID can also make falsifiable hypotheses. Stephen Meyer
devotes an entire appendix to discussing the matter in his 2009 book &lt;em&gt;Signature in the Cell&lt;/em&gt;. He writes
on page 482: &quot;… the theory of intelligent design makes predictions about the kind of features we are
likely to find in living systems if they were in fact intelligently designed&quot;. What is important here is
the wording &quot;we are likely to find&quot; - ID's predictions are thus based on what one might vaguely
expect to find. Not on what one &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; find or on what one &lt;em&gt;must not&lt;/em&gt; find, i.e. not on any compelling
predictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that one cannot clearly falsify an ID hypothesis. As an example, let us take an ID-inspired
hypothesis that Meyer puts forward: &quot;The functional sequences of amino acids within amino 
acid-sequence space should be extremely rare rather than common&quot;. He argues that of all possible
combinations of the amino acids that make up proteins, there should be very few combinations that
result in functional protein structures. The first problem is that Meyer does not give a clear limit for
what would be extremely rare and what would not, so the question is impossible to decide in
practice - &quot;extremely rare&quot; can be interpreted in very different ways. The second, and bigger,
problem is that there is no logical connection to a designer - how do we know that the designer
decided that there must be only a few working combinations? We don't. So even if we could confirm
the hypothesis, it would not tell us anything about whether proteins were designed or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ID hypothesis is clearly not about proving ID, but about ruling out an evolutionary explanation. If
it could be shown that there were extremely few working combinations of amino acids, this would be
seen as an argument against the theory of evolution (which, by the way, it is not). In other words,
Meyer tries to demonstrate &quot;non-evolution&quot; and sees this as a sign of design. This is a classic fallacy -
the fact that one explanation does not hold up does not mean that another explanation must be
correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meyer in his appendix has a list of twelve &quot;ID-inspired&quot; predictions of which the above example was
the last one. The other eleven suffer from the same weaknesses. Some of them are pure arguments
against evolutionary processes and have nothing to do with design. Others assume that the designer
is working with a particular type of design which you then want to identify. But you cannot know
what type of design the designer uses, so what you are actually testing is the idea you have about
how the designer should work. Without actual knowledge of the designer, it is impossible to know
how to formulate precise hypotheses. Everything becomes pure conjecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example of empirical work based on a hypothetical designer, consider a study of the impact of
intercessory prayer on the recovery of patients who have undergone a particular type of heart
surgery.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; This is a large study with 1800 patients, carried out according to all the rules of the art. The
end result was that no significant effect of prayer was seen. Does this mean that prayer has been
shown not to work? Not at all. The results only show that intercession does not work with the
particular experimental design chosen. Perhaps it would have worked with other patients, other
experimental groups, other control groups, other prayer rituals, other people praying? We don't
know. Since we have no concrete knowledge of the designer, we do not know how the experiment
should be set up to show with certainty the effect of intercessory prayer. We can guess endlessly.
This is not how good hypothesis testing is done - that requires precise, testable hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us leave the hypotheses and move on to what is required of a scientific explanation. Explaining
something means clearly demonstrating the causes of some phenomenon; you connect cause and
effect. You also have to show how the cause leads to the observed phenomenon. A good
explanation, then, involves linking a phenomenon to a known cause through a known mechanism.
Darwin's theory of evolution is a good example. His idea of common descent was quickly accepted by
his contemporaries; it was so obvious that it explained the patterns of nature well. But with natural
selection it was not so. Darwin could not explain the mechanisms of heredity, which was a
prerequisite for understanding natural selection. That is why not many people fully accepted his
theory. However, by the turn of the 20th century, the mechanisms of genetics were starting to be
elucidated, so now the process of evolution was being understood. But it was still not clear exactly
how evolution happened. It wasn't until population genetics had developed sufficiently in the 1930s
and 40s that the theory became widely accepted. By then, the whole chain was clear: known causes
(heredity and variation) caused a known phenomenon (evolution) through a known mechanism
(natural selection).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we can understand the entire causal chain. We can understand it at the molecular level as well
as at the population level. We know the molecules and processes that cause evolution. We can
observe and measure them, which allows us to have an evidence-based discussion about the
importance of different factors, and how well different models fit reality. That is how it should be
with a good scientific explanation. It also allows us to formulate and test new hypotheses based on
the knowledge we already have - for example, can cooperation and helpfulness be explained in
evolutionary terms? It turns out that it can. The theory of inclusive fitness provides a robust
evolutionary explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare this to an ID explanation of how a complex biological structure would arise. The cause, the
designer, is unknown, and so are the mechanisms by which the design would be implemented. Thus,
we cannot assess how plausible the ID explanation is, or how it compares to other explanations. An
explanation based on unknown causes and unknown mechanisms is, strictly speaking, no explanation
at all - it doesn't make us any wiser. It provides no concrete knowledge. It has no explanatory value.
Nor does it provide a reliable basis for further hypotheses. If you are already firmly convinced that
there is a designer, it may work as a religiously based explanation, but it is scientifically uninteresting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fuzziness of ID explanations is characteristic. It is also reflected in the lack of precision in the
concepts used. For example, &quot;complex specified information&quot; is not defined in a way that makes it
measurable or practically useful. Similarly, it is impossible to clearly determine whether a structure is
irreducibly complex or not - distinct criteria are lacking. It is obviously impossible to conduct
meaningful research with such fuzzy concepts. Yet ID proponents refer to these concepts as if they
were clear, meaningful and established. But they are definitely not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conclusion is clear: ID cannot provide the kind of mechanistic explanations that are the basis of a
scientific theory. Thus ID cannot compete with established science, and can never be a scientific
alternative. On the other hand, ID could be a complementary explanation on another level: one is
free to imagine a governing intelligence behind all the mysteries of existence, while science provides
the mechanistic explanations of how the world actually works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reference:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Benson, H., et al: Study of the Therapeutic Effects of Intercessory Prayer (STEP) in cardiac bypass
patients. &lt;em&gt;American Heart Journal&lt;/em&gt; (2006) 151, pp. 934-42
https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16569567&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lars Johan Erkell</name></author><summary type="html">This is an additional post by Lars Johan Erkell made on September 8, 2021 in Swedish at the Biolog(g) site after the seven posts of his “Breakthrough for Intelligent Design?” series were made. He has requested that we post it here after the second post in that series, to explain his position in that post on what can be considered legitimate science. &amp;nbsp; A central point in the discussion I have with Ola Hössjer in the posts entitled &quot;Breakthrough for intelligent design?&quot; concerns the limits for what can be considered legitimate science. Since my responses to his comments on this matter are too long for the comments section, I have made a separate post on the subject. The central question is how to formulate a hypothesis, that is, a suggested explanation for a phenomenon. Hypotheses are not formulated in an arbitrary way; you don't just grab something out of the air. A hypothesis should be based on prior knowledge. It should also be falsifiable, which means that it must be possible to show that it is incorrect. The scientific work then consists of testing the hypothesis. Whether it proves to be true or false, something new has been learned. The important thing here is that the hypothesis is formulated in such a way that it can be tested in practice with a clear-cut result. If you cannot do that, you cannot learn anything new. And if you cannot test your hypotheses, you cannot root your theories in the real world. However, just because a hypothesis is falsifiable does not mean that it is scientific. For example, &quot;the Moon is a cheese&quot; is a falsifiable (and falsified) hypothesis. But pure nonsense. If we want to give it a scientific touch, we can formulate it as a classical syllogism: Premise 1: The Moon is yellow, round and has craters Premise 2: A cut cheese is yellow, round and has pits that look like craters Conclusion: The Moon is a cheese This conclusion is not just grabbed out of thin air; it is based on an analogy. But it is still nonsense. My point here is that just because a hypothesis is falsifiable, or is expressed in a formally correct manner, that does not mean it is plausible or even makes sense.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breakthrough for Intelligent Design? (Part 2)</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breakthrough for Intelligent Design? (Part 2)" /><published>2022-11-16T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-11-16T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell2.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Biologg_Banner_900.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Biolog(g) banner&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The text is a pun in Swedish: &quot;Logg&quot; means something like a ship´s log or a logbook. A blog is &quot;blogg&quot;. 
So &quot;Biolog(g)&quot; is a biologist´s log or blog.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is part 2 of a series of 7 posts by Lars Johan Erkell, with comments on each by Ola Hössjer and a reply by Erkell.  An eighth post by Erkell is near this one, put here because he refers to it. Part 1 will be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PandasThumb/pandasthumb.github.io/edit/source/_posts/2022/2022-11-09-erkell1.md&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;breakthrough-for-intelligent-design-part-2&quot;&gt;Breakthrough for Intelligent design? (Part 2)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;November 13, 2020&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Lars Johan Erkell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you calculate design?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What stands out about Thorvaldsen and Hössjer’s work, and what makes me write these blog posts, is that they raise the question of how one could demonstrate fine-tuning and design using scientific methods. In any case, how one could imagine doing so; it doesn’t get more concrete than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thorvaldsen and Hössjer carefully discuss the statistical methods they use, or rather believe that one can use. The main line is – as always with ID – that you try to support ID by primarily criticizing the theory of evolution. But you cannot prove theory A by showing that theory B is bad. The authors are also aware of this. They write in section 6.3:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;However, one may argue that the most suitable approach of science is to compare the best explanations found so far within two competing worldviews. This naturally leads to model selection. … It is possible for some problems to suggest a design model M1 that competes with the currently most promising naturalistic model M2, in terms of which model explains the data the best.
The authors therefore want to compare an evolutionary model with a design model by using statistical methods to determine which of them is more probable. And it is clear that the intention is to make the comparison based on concrete data. But from which models, and from which data?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their critique of evolutionary theory, a number of well-known themes are addressed, primarily “irreducible complexity” on several levels; in individual proteins, in protein complexes and in entire networks. Also the “Cambrian explosion” and the so-called the waiting time problem is addressed. What these have in common is that the authors believe that the structures of life are so complex and thus so improbable that they could never arise naturally. However, this is not a view shared by established science – here the arguments are seen as contrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question now is, in practical terms, these problems could be calculated. A question that has been dealt with extensively - and which is probably the easiest to calculate - concerns the probability that a functioning protein will be able to arise through naturalistic mechanisms. Thorvaldsen and Hössjer mention in section 4.2 two strategies for doing this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is based on the fact that protein consists of one or more chains of amino acids that must be in a certain sequence. Since there are 20 different amino acids to choose from, there are countless combinations. In a small protein consisting of 150 amino acids, the different amino acids can be combined in 10&lt;sup&gt;50&lt;/sup&gt; to 10&lt;sup&gt;74&lt;/sup&gt; different ways. These are astronomically large numbers; the probability that the “right” combination would occur by chance is vanishingly small. The big problem with this strategy, however, is that no sane biologist believes that proteins form in this random way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evolutionary biological view is instead that the first enzymes consisted of short peptide chains with a small number of amino acids – it is known that such chains can have enzymatic activity.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; That such peptide chains could be formed by chance is not unreasonable. They may not have been as efficient as today’s enzymes, but if they had sufficient enzyme activity, they would have been selected and evolved into larger and more efficient molecules. So no one believes that proteins are formed in the way that Thorvaldsen and Hössjer are suggesting. It is a little strange that they mention this bizarre idea at all. It is completely irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other strategy is to set up a hypothetical evolutionary tree for how a certain protein might have evolved, and then calculate the probability of that process. But there is a lot of knowledge that is missing in order to be able to make credible calculations of this kind, not least because we have to reckon with an evolution that extends over billions of years. We would need detailed knowledge of which organisms are involved, mutation frequencies, population sizes, selection pressure and much else that is impossible to know in retrospect. This is not a realistic path. Nor, as far as I know, has anyone attempted to set up any detailed scenario of this kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conclusion is that it is not practically possible to statistically calculate the probability that a protein could evolve via natural mechanisms. The difficulties are so enormous that it will probably never be possible. And yet this was the simplest of the cases discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;***&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thorvaldsen and Hössjer’s strategy for demonstrating fine-tuning is based on a statistical comparison between a naturalistic model M2 and a design model M1. We then need to calculate the probability for both models in order to compare them. We have already seen that it is practically impossible to calculate the probability that a complex biological structure can arise according to a naturalistic model. But how to calculate the likelihood of a design model? It is something the authors wisely do not go into. Here we are in big trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to be able to calculate the probability of how a complex biological structure can arise, we must have a credible and detailed model of the process. This also applies if there is a conscious design behind it. We must therefore have knowledge of the designer in order to assess the probability that he/she/it wanted the design exactly the way we see it. This requires detailed knowledge – we need to understand exactly how the designer thinks, what the intentions, plans and means are. In order to make statistical calculations, we must have actual data, numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design proponents, however, are careful not to say anything about who the designer might be, or what qualities the designer might have. This makes it fundamentally impossible to calculate the statistical probability of a design process. So it’s not just practically impossible, as with the naturalistic model, it’s fundamentally impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statistical model Thorvaldsen and Hössjer have put forward to demonstrate design is misconceived and unworkable – it is based on the unreasonable assumption that it is possible to make a statistical estimate of the probability that an unknown designer would have acted in a certain way. It is a mystery that they chose to publish it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Short peptides can spontaneously form stable complexes that have enzymatic activity. See: Jason Greenwald et. al.: Peptide Amyloids in the Origin of Life. J Mol Biol (2018) vol. 430, pp. 3735–3750 &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29890117/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comment by Ola Hössjer&lt;/strong&gt;
June 29, 2021 3:00 a.m&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 2. About counting on design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to be able to estimate the probability that a biological system should have arisen by chance (so step a) in the fine-tuning argument) a naturalistic model M2 is required that describes how development or evolution took place. The fact that the model is naturalistic means that it contains only natural explanatory mechanisms. When it comes to biological evolution, i.e. the development of complicated life forms from simple single-celled organisms, the five naturalistic mechanisms are usually involved i) mutations, ii) genetic drift, i.e. random variation in how reproductive the individuals in a parental generation are, iii) natural selection, iv) recombinations of genetic material from a pair of parents, and v) the mixing of gene pools caused by geographic migration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erkell claims that it is practically impossible to give a reasonable estimate of the probability that, for example, a protein could have evolved in accordance with a naturalistic model M2. I agree that this is extremely difficult, since such a model must necessarily be complicated, with more or less unknown parameters. Nevertheless, I believe that there is a feasible way to demonstrate the difficulty of naturalistic processes in producing complex structures. If you only focus on certain properties of the protein that according to M2 must have evolved, you get a conservative upper estimate of the probability that a protein was obtained through evolutionary processes. To also take into account the fact that several of the model’s parameters (such as selection pressure, mutation rate, population sizes, generation times, etc.) can be difficult to estimate from the data with good accuracy, a so-called sensitivity analysis can be used to calculate how the upper estimate of the probability for the development of the protein changes when the constituent parameters change. If this upper estimate of the probability is small for all biologically reasonable values of the included parameters, an argument has been given for the difficulty of the proposed naturalistic model M2 to explain the origin of the given protein. I therefore argue, contrary to Erkell, that the first step a) of our method for detecting fine-tuning is highly feasible in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second part b) of our fine-tuning argument consists in finding a measure f(x) of how specified a biological system x is. As mentioned in the introduction, f(x) fastens on some characteristic that the observer recognizes, and which in many cases brings to mind that an intelligent designer is behind the origin of the system. In TH2020 we give several examples of how the system x and its specification f(x) can be chosen. An example is that x corresponds to a protein or a molecular machine, and that the specification indicates how many parts must be in place for x to function. Another example is that f(x) indicates the biological fitness of an organism x, i.e. its reproductive capacity. In connection with the latter example, we argue in TH2020 that evolution will eventually break down the genetic material of a species because most mutations are harmful or neutral. The consequence is then that the fitness of individuals of the species decreases over time. This in turn means that the probability in a) becomes very low for an evolutionary model M2, based on the aforementioned mechanisms i)-v), to be able to explain that the organism in question arose during millions of years of development, because the genetic material during such long time has had time to be depleted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if a naturalistic model M2 has difficulty explaining the emergence of a biological system that contains some form of specification, the question is whether there is any other better explanatory model. At the end of TH2020, we give examples of design- or creationist-inspired models M1 that we believe have greater possibilities than M2 to explain the emergence of the fine-tuned system. To make such reasoning more rigorous, it is necessary to show that the probability of the emergence of the given system is much higher for the design model M1 than for the naturalistic model M2. In the example above, where f(x) corresponds to the biological fitness of an organism x, we refer to various articles where a design model is described, which in addition to the aforementioned (micro)evolutionary mechanisms i)-v) adds a sixth mechanism vi) in the form of genetic variation in a first created pair, from which all individuals in the species descend. According to such a design model M1, the emergence of species can be explained by a combination of created variation (mechanism vi) and a short-term, small-scale microevolution (mechanisms i-v). The problem of genetic depletion then becomes much less, because the created variation makes it possible to assume that the species arose relatively recently, so that the genetic erosion, caused by the harmful mutations, acted for a much shorter time&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erkell is strongly critical of us introducing a design model to explain the emergence of a biological system. He writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In order to be able to calculate the probability of how a complex biological structure can arise, we must therefore have a credible and detailed model of the process. This also applies if there is a conscious design behind it. We must therefore have knowledge of the designer in order to assess the probability that the person concerned wanted his design exactly the way we see it to be. This requires detailed knowledge – we need to understand exactly how the designer thinks, what intentions, plans and means they have. In order to make statistical calculations, we must have concrete data, numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;However, the design movement is very careful not to say anything about who the designer would be, or what qualities the designer would have. This makes it fundamentally impossible to calculate the statistical probability of a design process. It is thus not only practically impossible, as with the naturalistic model, it is fundamentally impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I completely agree with Erkell that it is difficult to determine exactly what plans or intentions a designer has. But this is also not necessary to know. It is enough to let design-inspired thinking generate concrete falsifiable hypotheses. A design-inspired model can therefore be perfectly combined with the hypothetical-deductive method, which forms the basis of empirical science, according to the following three steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Propose a falsifiable hypothesis, which can contain both natural mechanisms and design-inspired parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Evaluate and see if the hypothesis in 1) is consistent with the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) If the agreement in 2) is not good, go back to 1) and propose a better hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erkell makes very far-reaching, not to say unreasonable demands on the design model, because he is not satisfied with falsifiable hypotheses. Instead, he also wants to include characteristics of the designer that can often be difficult to test scientifically. Although it is probably so interesting to have a conversation about what intentions the designers have, this has to do with the interpretation and the reason for the emergence of hypotheses, which is not required for the hypothetico-deductive method. One can thus use more or less intuitive design arguments to formulate testable hypotheses, without having to test the reasoning that led to the formulation of the hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, Erkell’s reasoning backfires like a boomerang on himself. Shouldn’t he make the same rigorous demands on naturalistic models M2, where the interpretation of them is included? How, for example, should chance in an evolutionary model be explained? Is it epistemic chance (as a way of describing lack of knowledge), ontological chance (genuine non-determinism) or should quantum mechanics be used to explain the emergence of chance? Which interpretation of quantum mechanics should be used in that case? If these questions cannot be given an unequivocal answer, Erkell risks sawing off the secular branch of science he himself has set himself up for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) This is usually called Haldane’s dilemma. A historical overview of Fisher’s Fundamental Theorem of Natural selection (which is closely related to Haldane’s Dilemma) is given in Basener W., Cordova S., Hössjer O. and Sanford J. (2021). Dynamical Systems and Fitness Maximization in Evolutionary Biology. In: Sriraman B. (eds) Handbook of the Mathematics of the Arts and Sciences. Running, Cham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reply by Lars Johan Erkell&lt;/strong&gt;
September 8, 2021 6:12 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this section, we get into the core of the work, your statistical model to detect fine-tuning/design. It assumes that you can calculate the probability that a biological structure can evolve via natural mechanisms, an extremely difficult task. You write that you can make meaningful estimates of the probability of a protein being able to evolve by doing a sensitivity analysis of an upper estimate of this probability. If the variation of this estimate is small for all biologically plausible values of the involved parameters, one would have an argument for the difficulty of the proposed naturalistic model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how do you get “all biologically reasonable values”? It is not enough to count on a single gene – genes (and proteins) interact in complex networks, and selection pressure acts on the entire network. The interaction between genes is called epistasis, and it must be included in your model. Ecology is also crucial because the selection pressure is entirely dependent on the organism’s environment. The problem is that there are astronomically many possibilities for epistatic (and ecological) interactions, and you have no clues as to which might be the relevant ones. You cannot count on a certain protein “all else being equal”; because the genome is constantly changing, “all else is not equal”. All of this means that you are nowhere near a realistic model of an evolution that has taken place in countless steps over millions or billions of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from all this, there is also a fundamental flaw in the approach, namely that it assumes the probability of a process with a definite goal in the form of a definite structure (at least that’s how ID advocates tend to calculate). But evolutionary processes have no goal. As far as proteins and protein complexes are concerned, there are a huge number of structures that have the same or similar function, and it is one of these that will be selected. It is thus the probability that the function - not the exact structure - will evolve that is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, you mean that “our method of detecting fine-tuning is highly feasible”. If so, why haven’t you done so? Why don’t you at least have a discussion of which factors would be included in such a calculation, how they should be identified, how they should be estimated, how they should be weighed against each other, etc.? Then—and only then—would this article be interesting. It would be even more interesting if you could succeed with the second part of your method, namely calculating the probability of design. If you are to test the probability that a certain structure is designed, you must know the characteristics of the designer - design is an act of will, and it is the probability of that act of will that you must calculate. And that is of course impossible without in-depth knowledge of the designer. You don’t write anything about how this would work, and that doesn’t surprise me; I suspect you have no idea. At least I don’t have it. But this is necessary if you want to be able to compare M1 and M2. That comparison is the very core of your method. But you comment on it like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Erkell makes very far-reaching, not to say unreasonable, demands on the design model, because he is not satisfied with falsifiable hypotheses. Instead, he also wants to include characteristics of the designer that can often be difficult to test scientifically.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no getting away from this: the probability of a design hypothesis includes the probability that a designer really wants to accomplish a certain thing. Without intention no design. If we imagine an omnipotent designer (which you probably do) it is only an act of will; no practical complications exist. But I get curious; you write “characteristics of the designer that can often be difficult to test scientifically”, which must mean that there are actually characteristics of the designer that can be scientifically tested. What are they? How can you test them? Here we get into really central questions about scientific hypotheses. That discussion is so important and extensive that it hardly fits in the comments section. I have therefore written &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PandasThumb/pandasthumb.github.io/edit/source/_posts/2022/2022-11-09-erkell8.md&quot;&gt;a separate post&lt;/a&gt; on the matter, “Science, hypotheses and Intelligent Design”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In your comment you also touch on completely different things: you talk about “genetic erosion” and refer in a footnote to “Haldane’s dilemma”. Here you are confusing two things. Haldane’s dilemma is not about some kind of erosion 
but about how fast evolution can go, more specifically whether there was enough time for the gene substitutions that must have taken place from the time of the common ancestor of humans and chimpanzees until today. The genetic erosion you talk about is John Sanford’s genetic entropy, a completely different matter. It would consist of a slow and inevitable genetic decay that would lead to our demise. However, neither Sanford nor anyone else has been able to show that this decay actually occur. Sanford builds on an earlier, now dismissed, idea that a genetic “catastrophe” could occur if enough harmful mutations accumulate in a genome. However, it has never been shown that such catastrophes actually take place, but rather that they do not (Springman, R. et al: Evolution at a High Imposed Mutation Rate: Adaptation Obscures the Load in Phage T7. Genetics (2010)184: 221 –232); Summers, J., Litwin, S.: Examining The Theory of Error Catastrophe. J. Virol., (2006) 80, 20–260). So forget about genetic entropy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, you suggest that I should place the same strict demands on my own research as I do on yours. But that’s exactly what I do - I make the same demands on your research that I myself have to live up to. Regarding your question about chance, I (and my colleagues) assume an ontological chance, since chemical reactions are based on the interaction between elementary particles and these are subject to the quantum laws in their Copenhagen interpretation. This is the basis of the molecular orbital theory, and thus of the chemistry and biology, I was once taught.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lars Johan Erkell</name></author><summary type="html">The text is a pun in Swedish: &quot;Logg&quot; means something like a ship´s log or a logbook. A blog is &quot;blogg&quot;. So &quot;Biolog(g)&quot; is a biologist´s log or blog. &amp;nbsp; This is part 2 of a series of 7 posts by Lars Johan Erkell, with comments on each by Ola Hössjer and a reply by Erkell. An eighth post by Erkell is near this one, put here because he refers to it. Part 1 will be found here. Breakthrough for Intelligent design? (Part 2) November 13, 2020 by Lars Johan Erkell How do you calculate design? What stands out about Thorvaldsen and Hössjer’s work, and what makes me write these blog posts, is that they raise the question of how one could demonstrate fine-tuning and design using scientific methods. In any case, how one could imagine doing so; it doesn’t get more concrete than that. Thorvaldsen and Hössjer carefully discuss the statistical methods they use, or rather believe that one can use. The main line is – as always with ID – that you try to support ID by primarily criticizing the theory of evolution. But you cannot prove theory A by showing that theory B is bad. The authors are also aware of this. They write in section 6.3: However, one may argue that the most suitable approach of science is to compare the best explanations found so far within two competing worldviews. This naturally leads to model selection. … It is possible for some problems to suggest a design model M1 that competes with the currently most promising naturalistic model M2, in terms of which model explains the data the best. The authors therefore want to compare an evolutionary model with a design model by using statistical methods to determine which of them is more probable. And it is clear that the intention is to make the comparison based on concrete data. But from which models, and from which data? In their critique of evolutionary theory, a number of well-known themes are addressed, primarily “irreducible complexity” on several levels; in individual proteins, in protein complexes and in entire networks. Also the “Cambrian explosion” and the so-called the waiting time problem is addressed. What these have in common is that the authors believe that the structures of life are so complex and thus so improbable that they could never arise naturally. However, this is not a view shared by established science – here the arguments are seen as contrived.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breakthrough for Intelligent Design? (Part 1)</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breakthrough for Intelligent Design? (Part 1)" /><published>2022-11-09T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-11-09T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/erkell1.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Biologg_Banner_900.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Biolog(g) banner&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;The text is a pun in Swedish: &quot;Logg&quot; means something like a ship´s log or a logbook.&lt;br /&gt; A blog is &quot;blogg&quot;. 
So &quot;Biolog(g)&quot; is a biologist´s log or blog.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This exchange consists of seven posts, each with a comment by Ola Hössjer and a reply by Lars Johan Erkell, plus one other post by Erkell.  It 
is a translation, mostly by Google Translate, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://biologg.wordpress.com/author/larserkell/&quot;&gt;the original 2020 Swedish posts and comments&lt;/a&gt;.  Erkell and Hössjer have kindly corrected the translation.  You and they are welcome to comment at Panda’s Thumb.  Keep in mind that the posts and these appended comments were written two years ago and thus cannot take more recent comments here into account. We hope to publish the sections on seven consecutive Wednesdays (we chose the day of the week without remembering its connection to ancient days in Sweden).  Readers and these authors are invited to contribute further comments in our Disqus comment system.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This week’s post starts with an introduction by Lars Johan Erkell, followed by the first of his posts at Biolog(g) and a comment by Ola Hössjer followed by a rejoinder by Lars Erkell.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Lars Johan Erkell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-breakthrough-for-intelligent-design&quot;&gt;A breakthrough for Intelligent Design?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years ago, Steinar Thorvaldsen and Ola Hössjer, professors of Informatics and Mathematical
Statistics, respectively, published &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519320302071?via%3Dihub&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;an article&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; titled “Using statistical methods to model the fine-tuning
of molecular machines and systems” in “Journal of Theoretical Biology” a regular scientific journal.
Within the Intelligent Design (ID) community the publication was seen as a breakthrough for ID as
science. A close reading of the paper, however, is not convincing. In seven blog posts on “Biolog(g)”
(a blog run by the staff at the Institute for biology and environmental science at the University of
Gothenburg, Sweden) I therefore have detailed my critique on four specific points, and also asked
how this paper could be published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-where-are-the-results&quot;&gt;1) Where are the results?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article title, “Using statistical methods to model …” as well as wordings in the article clearly state
that statistical methods have been used to demonstrate fine-tuning in the cell. However, no results
or calculations are presented to support this claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-how-can-design-be-calculated&quot;&gt;2) How can design be calculated?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors present a statistical model comparing M1, a design model, and M2, a naturalistic model,
in their ability to explain the occurrence of complex cellular structures. However, M1 is
misconceived and M2 is unworkable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-miracles-as-science&quot;&gt;3) Miracles as science?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors also suggest that their statistical model can be used to study human evolution. Here,
they compare M1, a model assuming that humanity arose from a single human couple, and M2,
assuming common ancestry with chimpanzees. However, to explain how present human genetic
diversity could be generated from single couple within a time frame of 6000 to 10 000 years, they
resort to divine intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4-non-physical-information&quot;&gt;4) Non-physical information?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their article, the authors introduce the revolutionary concept of “non-physical information”, but
without discussion or definition. The only reference goes to a text by philosopher Del Ratzsch, who
does not use the term. Instead, the authors have fabricated a hybrid sentence, part of it by Del
Ratzsch and part of it written by themselves, attributing it to Del Ratzsch. That is, they have
presented no evidence whatsoever for the existence of “non-physical information”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;5-why-is-id-not-regarded-as-science&quot;&gt;5) Why is ID not regarded as science?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some reasons ID is not regarded as science are briefly outlined. It is pointed out that ID does not
formulate any concrete theories or predictions and consequently cannot be falsified. ID is a theory
without a theory, without method and without results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;6-why-was-this-article-written&quot;&gt;6) Why was this article written?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may ask why two established professors at respected Scandinavian universities would write an
article like this. The reason is conceivably that they both are connected to Discovery Institute, the
central hub of the ID movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;7-why-was-this-article-published&quot;&gt;7) Why was this article published?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article has been heavily criticized for being pseudoscientific, and the review procedures of the
Journal of Theoretical Biology have been questioned. After the first publication of this post in 2020
(in Swedish) additional information seems to confirm the suspicion that editors and reviewers were
pushing the article through the review process, against the policy of the journal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;breakthrough-for-intelligent-design-part-1&quot;&gt;Breakthrough for Intelligent Design? (Part 1)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;originally posted November 13, 2020&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Lars Johan Erkell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where are the results?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That articles openly arguing for Intelligent Design (ID) are published in the established scientific press is not something one expects. Therefore, it is worth noting that Ola Hössjer, Professor of Mathematical Statistics at Stockholm University, and Steinar Thorvaldsen, professor of Information Science at Norway’s Arctic University in Tromsø, published a paper this summer entitled “Using statistical methods to model the fine-tuning of molecular machines and systems” in the Journal of Theoretical Biology. On July 8, the Swedish Christian newspaper Världen Idag had a report about the publication under the heading “Breakthrough: Research points to intelligent design”. The Swedish creationist association Genesis writes that Norwegian-Swedish research points to intelligent design in our cells. Now is this a scientific breakthrough for ID?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps not the breakthrough one had hoped for. When the article was printed in the September issue, there was a disclaimer from the magazine’s editors-in-chief on the website. They distance themselves from the concept of intelligent design and claim that they were misled by the fact that the authors did not include the keyword “intelligent design” during the review, but added it later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s much to say about this business, so much that I’m devoting seven posts to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of fine-tuning is one of the more common arguments for ID. It is argued that the natural constants that determine the properties of matter and the universe could have been radically different, and that the probability of a universe with properties that allow intelligent life is vanishingly small. Nevertheless, we are here, and that cannot be a coincidence. It shows design – a cosmic mind has created a universe that suits us. That’s the argument in a nutshell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the work is to now go one step further and to show that fine-tuning also exists in the living cell and its components:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This paper describes molecular fine-tuning, how it can be used in biology, and how it challenges conventional Darwinian thinking. We also discuss the statistical methods underpinning fine-tuning and present a framework for such analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fine-tuning means that a number of natural constants have such values that life is possible. But the constants are still not so life-friendly that life could arise and develop through evolutionary processes. Life would therefore not be possible without the intervention of a designer. Thorvaldsen and Hössjer claim to see clear traces of design in the cell’s proteins and in its complex mechanisms. You get the image of a designer who doesn’t quite manage to create a sufficiently life-friendly universe, and is therefore forced to build all living beings together, in the smallest detail. The universe is both life-friendly and life-hostile at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, fine-tuning is a notoriously hard-to-define term, so one is glad to actually get a definition:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We define fine-tuning as an object with two properties: it must (a) be unlikely to have occurred by chance, under the relevant probability distribution (i.e., complex), and (b) conform to an independent or detached specification (i.e., specific).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first condition is therefore that it is unlikely that the object in question could have arisen by pure chance. The second is that it must respond to some sort of independent specification. The question is whether it is possible to detect fine-tuning with advanced statistical methods:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Is it possible to recognize fine-tuning in biological systems at the levels of functional proteins, protein groups and cellular networks? Can fine-tuning in molecular biology be formulated using state of the art statistical methods, or are the arguments just “in the eyes of the beholder”?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That complex biological structures cannot have been formed by pure chance is so obvious that one hardly needs advanced statistical methods to convince oneself of the matter. The real problem is the concept of “specification”; how to define specification in concrete terms is a question the ID movement has wrestled with for decades, without coming to any solution. The article’s discussion of the concept is purely mathematical, and contains no clues as to how specification could be demonstrated in practice. The authors refer to an article by George Montañez, “A unified model of complex specified information”, but this too is completely mathematical and says nothing about how one could determine whether a certain structure or molecule is specified or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the article, section 7, we read:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Functional proteins, molecular machines and cellular networks are both unlikely when viewed as outcomes of a stochastic model, with a relevant probability distribution (having a small P(A)), and at the same time they conform to an independent or detached specification (the set A being defined in terms of specificity). These results are important and deduced from central phenomena of basic science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is therefore not possible to give an account of what specification actually means in practice. Instead, the authors refer to “central phenomena in basic science”, without giving any reference. In the last paragraph they write:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A major conclusion of our work is that fine-tuning is a clear feature of biological systems. Indeed, fine-tuning is even more extreme in biological systems than in inorganic systems. It is detectable within the realm of scientific methodology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is simply not true. Since there is no working method to scientifically detect specificity in actual biological systems, it has &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;  been possible to demonstrate fine-tuning with scientific methods. It has therefore &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; been possible to conclude that fine-tuning is characteristic of biological systems. This is not possible because condition (b) of the definition of fine tuning is not met. It is also impossible for the simple reason that no actual data or any calculations are presented to support the claims. The statistical methods developed are not used to solve any actual problems. All you have is speculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of the article reads “Using statistical methods to model the fine-tuning of molecular machines and systems”. It applies that statistical methods have indeed been applied to model fine-tuning - the word “using” reasonably means that something has really been used. In fact, no methods have been applied at all; nothing has been discussed besides how it might be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to understand that Thorvaldsen and Hössjer in this way make it appear that they have results they clearly do not have. The reader may get the impression that they are bluffing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comment by Ola Hössjer&lt;/strong&gt;
June 29, 2021 2:45 a.m&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Has Intelligent Design made a breakthrough as a science?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction and background&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I published the research article “Using statistical methods to model the fine-tuning of molecular machines and systems” in the Journal of Theoretical Biology together with Steinar Thorvaldsen, who is Professor of Information Science at Tromsø University. In this paper, hereafter referred to as TH2020, we propose a mathematical and statistical framework to test whether biological systems (proteins, protein complexes, cellular networks) can arise by chance or whether fine-tuning is a better explanation. Fine-tuning of a system means that a number of different parameters must be finely calibrated for it to exist. This requires (a) that the probability of the system having arisen by chance is small, and (b) that there is an independent specification of what is fine-tuned. This specification could mean that the system must have all its parts in place in order to function, that it has arisen in a short time despite its complexity, or that it includes codes, instructions, and organized structures that we recognize from intelligent agents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In physics, the concept of fine-tuning has been used for 50 years and today a majority of physicists claim that the universe must be fine-tuned in order to exist and harbor life. On the other hand, fine-tuning has not had the same impact on biology. One may ask why. One explanation is probably that in many examples fine-tuning is associated with an intelligent designer, which in turn brings God to mind. Although the definition of fine-tuning does not involve a designer, this is often the most reasonable interpretation or explanation of specification (b) above. This connection between fine-tuning and design has been central for Intelligent Design (ID), a movement that arose in the United States in the late 1980s with the aim of proposing explanations for the origin and diversity of life, that are alternatives to the secular theories (chemical and biological evolution) that dominate within the academic world. And as a Christian I go one step further and identify the Intelligent Designer with God. With a creationist perspective, I can then use the Bible as inspiration to propose and interpret specified properties of biological structures. Thus, while the ID movement goes “halfway” and identifies fine-tuning with a designer, creationists go “all the way” and interpret fine-tuning as something God created or brought about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my own part, I have both a creationist and an ID perspective. Depending on the research problem and context, I choose to go either half way or all the way in my interpretation of how the fine-tuning may have arisen, or to make no interpretation at all. Sometimes it is appropriate to leave it to the reader to consider how the fine-tuned structures arose, in other contexts it is important to justify that the proposed fine-tuning is inspired by the knowledge we have about intelligent senders, or by texts from the Bible. At the end of the aforementioned article, TH2020, Thorvaldsen and I go halfway and make a connection between fine-tuning and an intelligent source. As this is unusual within a secular academic environment, our publication has received a lot of attention and circulation. Last year, TH2020 was the most downloaded article in the Journal of Theoretical Biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among those who got involved in the debate around TH2020 is Lars Johan Erkell, who is Associate Professor in Zoophysiology at the University of Gothenburg. On Biolog(g), a blog run by the teachers of the Department of Biology and Environmental Science at the University of Gothenburg, Erkell wrote a series of seven articles in November 2020, entitled “Breakthrough for Intelligent Design (?)”. In these articles he analyzes and comments on TH2020. As an academic, I welcome factual criticism where my research results are analyzed and seen at the seams. At best, such debates contribute to the advancement of science. I also want to thank Erkell for actually taking the time to read, not only TH2020, but also several of the articles that Steinar and I refer to. That makes parts of his criticism well-informed. At the same time, Erkell’s series of articles contains a series of claims, for instance that our article is not only pseudo-scientific but also anti-scientific. I therefore would like to take this opportunity to respond to this serious criticism. I have divided my response article into seven parts (corresponding to Erkell’s seven articles) and a concluding summary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 1. The results of the fine-tuning article&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the introduction, the method for detecting fine-tuning in a biological system, which we propose in TH2020, involves two steps. First (a) to show that the probability is small that the system has arisen by chance and second (b) to demonstrate an external specification, which can be recognized by an observer. In part 1, Erkell asks what results are presented in TH2020. According to Erkell, our article contains only mathematical speculations that are not relevant to a biological reality. In other words, Erkell lacks concrete examples where we show how our mathematical theory for detecting fine-tuning should be applied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is true that in TH2020 we do not have concrete examples with numerical calculations in order to illustrate our theory. But this is not the purpose of the article. Our aim is partly to provide an overview of fine-tuning and partly to propose a mathematical framework for establishing fine-tuning, which can then be used in subsequent articles to investigate whether a certain biological system (a protein, a protein complex, a cellular network) is fine-tuned or not. At the same time, TH2020 contains about a hundred references to other articles, and at several places we give concrete suggestions on how the specification in (b) should be chosen, as well as detailed justifications that the probability (a) that the biological system arose by chance is very small. In addition, several of the articles we refer to are based on empirical studies or analyses of such. In other words, our mathematical model is not plucked out of thin air.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, it is important to point out that mathematical models are simplifications of a more complicated biological reality. Whether the model is successful or not depends on how well it is able to describe empirical data. But this does not mean that every research article needs to contain such a connection between mathematics and empiricism, even if this connection is crucial in the long run. There are many examples of science (such as population genetics and theoretical ecology) which were indeed motivated by biological applications, but where initially the theory was developed quite separately from empirical work. Despite this, population genetics later became an important tool for describing small-scale microevolution, when more genetic data became available. Similarly, theoretical ecology has been used to understand the processes that bring about environmental and climate change. My question to Erkell is therefore whether he believes that such developments in the history of science lack value, where theoretical development sometimes precedes applications. Doesn’t this rather indicate a diversity of the scientific project?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;See for example Axe, D.D. (2004). Estimating the prevalence of protein sequences adopting functional enzyme folds. J. Mol. Biol. 341 (5), 1295–1315. and Kozulic, B., and Leisola, M. (2015). Have scientists already been able to surpass the capabilities of evolution? viXra Biochemistry 1504.0130.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reply by Lars Johan Erkell&lt;/strong&gt;
September 8, 2021 5:52 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi Ola,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for commenting on my posts! There is a lot to discuss here, and I hope we can sort things out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me start with your question about whether I think it is OK to publish theoretical articles without empirical data. Yes, of course! It can lead to faster progress. Like when X-ray crystallographic diffraction patterns were first interpreted and the theory of space groups was already in place. So my criticism is not directed at you publishing a model without data, but that TH2020 clearly pretends to show  results, but does not contain any. How can you interpret “A major conclusion of our work is that fine-tuning is a clear feature of biological systems … It is detectable within the realm of scientific methodology” if not that you have concrete results showing that fine-tuning actually does exist in biological systems? I thought I expressed myself clearly here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to the problems with the concept of “specification”. It’s notoriously difficult to define and I can’t find a clear definition or proper discussion of it in TH2020. But you suggest how it should be chosen, like “… a molecular machine, and that the specification states how many parts must be in place for x to work.” Another example is that f(x) indicates the biological fitness of an organism x, i.e. its reproductive capacity”. But one is a structure, the other is a property of a living organism. What does a definition look like that covers these very different cases? And what determines the necessary number of parts in a molecular machine? Furthermore, in the next example, if we move an organism from a favorable environment, where it has high biological fitness, to an unfavorable environment, where it has zero fitness, does it lose its specification? It is still the same organism. And is the specification a quality or a quantity? You mention both options in section 6.2. Which is it? You have to look for a more blurred concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this my first post, I had two points of criticism: (1) that you pretend to have results that do not exist, and (2) that you do not define or sufficiently discuss the term “specification”. In your answer you avoid both points. Do you have any comment on that?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lars Johan Erkell (with comments by Ola Hössjer)</name></author><summary type="html">The text is a pun in Swedish: &quot;Logg&quot; means something like a ship´s log or a logbook. A blog is &quot;blogg&quot;. So &quot;Biolog(g)&quot; is a biologist´s log or blog. &amp;nbsp; This exchange consists of seven posts, each with a comment by Ola Hössjer and a reply by Lars Johan Erkell, plus one other post by Erkell. It is a translation, mostly by Google Translate, from the original 2020 Swedish posts and comments. Erkell and Hössjer have kindly corrected the translation. You and they are welcome to comment at Panda’s Thumb. Keep in mind that the posts and these appended comments were written two years ago and thus cannot take more recent comments here into account. We hope to publish the sections on seven consecutive Wednesdays (we chose the day of the week without remembering its connection to ancient days in Sweden). Readers and these authors are invited to contribute further comments in our Disqus comment system. This week’s post starts with an introduction by Lars Johan Erkell, followed by the first of his posts at Biolog(g) and a comment by Ola Hössjer followed by a rejoinder by Lars Erkell. &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Introduction by Lars Johan Erkell A breakthrough for Intelligent Design? Two years ago, Steinar Thorvaldsen and Ola Hössjer, professors of Informatics and Mathematical Statistics, respectively, published an article titled “Using statistical methods to model the fine-tuning of molecular machines and systems” in “Journal of Theoretical Biology” a regular scientific journal. Within the Intelligent Design (ID) community the publication was seen as a breakthrough for ID as science. A close reading of the paper, however, is not convincing. In seven blog posts on “Biolog(g)” (a blog run by the staff at the Institute for biology and environmental science at the University of Gothenburg, Sweden) I therefore have detailed my critique on four specific points, and also asked how this paper could be published.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This morning's eclipse of the moon</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/this-mornings-eclipse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This morning's eclipse of the moon" /><published>2022-11-08T10:25:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-11-08T10:25:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/this-mornings-eclipse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/this-mornings-eclipse.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/DSC05373_Lunar_Eclipse_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Eclipse photo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeanddate.com/eclipse/map/2022-november-8&quot;&gt;This morning's eclipse of the moon&lt;/a&gt; as seen from Boulder, Colorado, at approximately 4 a.m., near maximum.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">This morning's eclipse of the moon as seen from Boulder, Colorado, at approximately 4 a.m., near maximum.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Comet Neowise</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/comet-neowise.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Comet Neowise" /><published>2022-11-07T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-11-07T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/comet-neowise</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/comet-neowise.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Bob Gitzen&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Gitzen_CometNeowise.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Comet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comet_NEOWISE&quot;&gt;Comet Neowise&lt;/a&gt;, 4:40 a.m., 7/10/20, Lime Ridge Trail, Walnut Creek, California.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Bob Gitzen. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Comet Neowise, 4:40 a.m., 7/10/20, Lime Ridge Trail, Walnut Creek, California.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Science leads to stock photo entertainment</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/stockphotos.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science leads to stock photo entertainment" /><published>2022-11-01T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-11-01T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/stockphotos</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/11/stockphotos.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/chickenspace.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stock science images&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Left: &quot;Talk to us, Dr. Chicken!&quot; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Right: Showing us where outer space is.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent meme widely spread on the internet shows Worst Science Stock Photos.  It seems to have originated with Dr. Kit Chapman of the University of Falmouth, U.K., who posted candidates for worst on his 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ChemistryKit/status/1580308605416325120?cxt=HHwWgICq1biTse4rAAAA&quot;&gt;Twitter account&lt;/a&gt; and conducted a vote.  The two above were among these (the left one was #2 in the voting).  They are 
shown because they are my favorites.  #1 was an image showing a model holding a soldering iron by its hot tip and soldering on the wrong side of a circuit board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also further comments on Reddit, which you can find by searching for “Reddit worst science stock photos”.  To see discussion 
here at PT, click on the title of this post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Left: &quot;Talk to us, Dr. Chicken!&quot; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Right: Showing us where outer space is. &amp;nbsp; A recent meme widely spread on the internet shows Worst Science Stock Photos. It seems to have originated with Dr. Kit Chapman of the University of Falmouth, U.K., who posted candidates for worst on his Twitter account and conducted a vote. The two above were among these (the left one was #2 in the voting). They are shown because they are my favorites. #1 was an image showing a model holding a soldering iron by its hot tip and soldering on the wrong side of a circuit board. There are also further comments on Reddit, which you can find by searching for “Reddit worst science stock photos”. To see discussion here at PT, click on the title of this post.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Phymata pennsylvanica</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/Phymata-pennsylvanica.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Phymata pennsylvanica" /><published>2022-10-24T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-24T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/Phymata-pennsylvanica</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/Phymata-pennsylvanica.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Mark Sturtevant&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Sturtevant.1.Ambush_Bugs.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ambush bug&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insectidentification.org/insect-description.asp?identification=Ambush-Bug&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Phymata pennsylvanica&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; ambush bugs. The photographer writes, &quot;Ambush bugs are well camouflaged insects that lie in wait on flowers. A visiting insect will be grabbed, and the proboscis of this insect will be used to kill and feed upon the prey. In this case, the female of the mating pair has taken a digger bee (&lt;i&gt;Anthophora&lt;/i&gt; sp.). Clearly, ambush bugs are not concerned about taking stinging insects!
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Mark Sturtevant. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Phymata pennsylvanica &amp;ndash; ambush bugs. The photographer writes, &quot;Ambush bugs are well camouflaged insects that lie in wait on flowers. A visiting insect will be grabbed, and the proboscis of this insect will be used to kill and feed upon the prey. In this case, the female of the mating pair has taken a digger bee (Anthophora sp.). Clearly, ambush bugs are not concerned about taking stinging insects!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PBS to rebroadcast “We Believe in Dinosaurs” in December</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/PBS-to-rebroadcast.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PBS to rebroadcast “We Believe in Dinosaurs” in December" /><published>2022-10-19T15:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-19T15:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/PBS-to-rebroadcast</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/PBS-to-rebroadcast.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Allosaurus_SDNHM_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Allosaurus&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Allosaurus at the San Diego Museum of Natural History. &lt;small&gt;Wikimedia. Photograph by user Sheep81. Public domain.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Daniel Phelps was featured in the full-length documentary film &lt;/i&gt;We Believe in Dinosaurs&lt;i&gt;, which we reported on &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/04/reviews-of-documentary.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The film was later slightly shortened to accommodate a 1-hour television program; that version was &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/11/we-believe-on-PBS.html&quot;&gt;broadcast February 17, 2020&lt;/a&gt;. Below is what we received from Mr. Phelps.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was recently forwarded the message below from ITVS Avis, the producer of the documentary. It looks as if PBS will again air the documentary “We Believe in Dinosaurs” on the PBS show “Independent Lens” on December 19 and make the show available for free streaming until mid-January.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is wonderful news. The documentary deserved more local and national coverage than it received when it first aired right before the CoVid pandemic hit in 2020. I hope recipients of this message will publicize the film and review it in appropriate publications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an edited version of the message:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am reaching out to you today to let you know that we are bringing back your film, &lt;i&gt;We Believe in Dinosaurs&lt;/i&gt;, on the Public Television Broadcast &amp;amp; the PBS Video Application. The scheduled TV air date &amp;amp; the Streaming window are as follows.&lt;/p&gt; 
  &lt;p&gt;·  TV Air Date: 10/9C, 12/19/2022&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;·  Free Online streaming: 12/19/2022 - 01/15/2023 (28 days)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Viewing Instructions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the streaming window, to watch &lt;i&gt;We Believe in Dinosaurs&lt;/i&gt; on your computer, go to pbs.org/believeindinosaurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To watch the film on a TV, phone, or tablet, you'll need to download the PBS Video app. On a TV, that means downloading the app in Roku, Apple TV, or your smart TV interface. Once you're in the PBS Video app, look for the &lt;i&gt;Independent Lens&lt;/i&gt; tile (or search for &lt;i&gt;We Believe in Dinosaurs&lt;/i&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
 
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social Media Info&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
·  Independent Lens' handle: @independentlens&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Allosaurus at the San Diego Museum of Natural History. Wikimedia. Photograph by user Sheep81. Public domain. Daniel Phelps was featured in the full-length documentary film We Believe in Dinosaurs, which we reported on here. The film was later slightly shortened to accommodate a 1-hour television program; that version was broadcast February 17, 2020. Below is what we received from Mr. Phelps. I was recently forwarded the message below from ITVS Avis, the producer of the documentary. It looks as if PBS will again air the documentary “We Believe in Dinosaurs” on the PBS show “Independent Lens” on December 19 and make the show available for free streaming until mid-January. This is wonderful news. The documentary deserved more local and national coverage than it received when it first aired right before the CoVid pandemic hit in 2020. I hope recipients of this message will publicize the film and review it in appropriate publications. Here is an edited version of the message:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How jellyfish prove Intelligent Design (according to ID advocates)</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/those-divinely-inspired-jellyfish.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How jellyfish prove Intelligent Design (according to ID advocates)" /><published>2022-10-18T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-18T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/those-divinely-inspired-jellyfish</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/those-divinely-inspired-jellyfish.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Aurelia_aurita.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Moon Jellyfish&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;The Moon Jellyfish, &lt;em&gt;Aurelia aurita&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br /&gt; Photo by Luc Viatour.&lt;br /&gt; From Wikimedia Commons.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On October 6, The Discovery Institute’s ID site “Evolution News and Science Today:” reprised
&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2022/10/secrets-that-give-sea-lions-and-jellyfish-their-edge-as-swimmers/&quot;&gt;(here)&lt;/a&gt;
a 2015 post by David Coppege.  A few days later, at the site Uncommon Descent, their regular
poster “caspian”, whom they identify as physicist Dr. Eric Hedin, noted that post and quoted
much of its content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2015 post was based on two interesting reports in The Conversation.  One, by Megan Leftwich of George Washington University, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/scientists-at-work-cracking-sea-lions-high-thrust-low-wake-swimming-technique-45295&quot;&gt;described her lab’s work on the efficiency with which sea lions swim&lt;/a&gt;.  The other, &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/jellyfish-are-the-most-energy-efficient-swimmers-new-metric-confirms-26729&quot;&gt;by Akshat Rathi, who interviewed Neelesh Patankar of Northwestern University and John Dabiri of Caltech&lt;/a&gt; reports studies that show that jellyfish are unusually efficient in their use of energy in swimming, because they can recover some of the energy they exert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reports in The Conversation are interesting reports on very effective adaptations.  But they do not contain 
any discussion of Intelligent Design.  Here our heroes David Coppege and Dr. Eric Hedin come to the rescue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re used to seeing sites like Evolution News and Uncommon Descent present reports on 
particularly impressive adaptations, with the implication that such a good adaptation
must surely be the result of Design Intervention and could not have been brought about by 
ordinary evolutionary forces such as natural selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This handwaving is not for David Coppege, who has a degree in physics, or Eric Hedin, who
took his doctorate in that field at my own university.  Coppege makes the argument 
more specific:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If the world’s best human designers are attempting to build machines to mimic what these animals “naturally do,” it’s a reasonable inference that sea lions and jellyfish originated from an intelligent cause — one with superior knowledge of propulsion, fluid mechanics, and optimization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Hedin does not add anything to this, but quotes Coppege’s report extensively and approvingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen an Argument From Jellyfish and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/Are-jellyfish-so-dumb.html&quot;&gt;commented on it here before&lt;/a&gt;.  That post reported on one from Uncommon Descent in 
2021, by Dr. Hedin’s colleague Denyse O’Leary, the previous most frequent poster
at that site.  She cited a more recent report of how jellyfish conserve energy while 
swimming.  She had a somewhat different
take on why this supported Intelligent Design:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Either jellyfish are smarter than we think or there is design in nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there we have two fascinating takes on why an excellent adaptation strongly indicates Design Intervention: because natural selection could not do something that works better than what human engineers can design, or because jellyfish are too dumb to know how to design themselves.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">The Moon Jellyfish, Aurelia aurita. Photo by Luc Viatour. From Wikimedia Commons. &amp;nbsp; On October 6, The Discovery Institute’s ID site “Evolution News and Science Today:” reprised (here) a 2015 post by David Coppege. A few days later, at the site Uncommon Descent, their regular poster “caspian”, whom they identify as physicist Dr. Eric Hedin, noted that post and quoted much of its content. The 2015 post was based on two interesting reports in The Conversation. One, by Megan Leftwich of George Washington University, described her lab’s work on the efficiency with which sea lions swim. The other, by Akshat Rathi, who interviewed Neelesh Patankar of Northwestern University and John Dabiri of Caltech reports studies that show that jellyfish are unusually efficient in their use of energy in swimming, because they can recover some of the energy they exert. The reports in The Conversation are interesting reports on very effective adaptations. But they do not contain any discussion of Intelligent Design. Here our heroes David Coppege and Dr. Eric Hedin come to the rescue.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Danaus plexippus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/danaus-plexippus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Danaus plexippus" /><published>2022-10-10T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-10T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/danaus-plexippus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/danaus-plexippus.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Revelle Hamilton&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Revelle_Monarch_Larvae_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Monarch larvae&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monarch_butterfly&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Danaus plexippus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; monarch butterfly larvae.  The photographer writes, &quot;The next generation of monarchs. I saw 5 on the milkweed this AM. I bought plants originally but this spring the seeds from the plants germinated &amp;amp; I have little milkweeds in various places.  I am picking off some of the pods and placing them in places I hope they will come up next year.&quot; We hope so too!
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Revelle Hamilton. Danaus plexippus &amp;ndash; monarch butterfly larvae. The photographer writes, &quot;The next generation of monarchs. I saw 5 on the milkweed this AM. I bought plants originally but this spring the seeds from the plants germinated &amp;amp; I have little milkweeds in various places. I am picking off some of the pods and placing them in places I hope they will come up next year.&quot; We hope so too!</summary></entry></feed>