<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-04-05T11:30:15-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Stromatolitic chert</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/03/stromatolitic-chert.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stromatolitic chert" /><published>2023-03-27T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-03-27T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/03/stromatolitic-chert</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/03/stromatolitic-chert.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;James Kocher&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Kocher_Gunflint_Chert_Translucent_Slice.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Slice of Gunflint Chert&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Digitate &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stromatolite&quot;&gt;stromatolites&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gunflint_chert&quot;&gt;Gunflint formation&lt;/a&gt; (Lower Algal Member), Nolalu, Ontario. Mr. Kocher writes, &quot;Specimen is a vertical section cut on lapidary saw (i.e., perpendicular to bedding). Thin piece (1-2 mm thick) is translucent &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chert&quot;&gt;chert&lt;/a&gt; and shows preserved columnar algal colonies, hematite oolites, and algal pellets (peloids). Specimen is ~4 cm wide. Variously classified as &lt;i&gt;Collenia undosa&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;Stratifera biwabikensis&lt;/i&gt;, among others. Age ~ 1.8 Ga; Mesoproterozoic.&quot; Mr. Kocher explains further, &quot;'Lower Algal Member' is a designation given to a subset of strata within the Gunflint Formation. The Gunflint Formation has been divided up stratigraphically into at least 5 subsets of strata, i.e., 'Members.'&quot; Perhaps it goes without saying, but the specimen is flat, despite the illusion of hills and valleys.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by James Kocher. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Digitate stromatolites in the Gunflint formation (Lower Algal Member), Nolalu, Ontario. Mr. Kocher writes, &quot;Specimen is a vertical section cut on lapidary saw (i.e., perpendicular to bedding). Thin piece (1-2 mm thick) is translucent chert and shows preserved columnar algal colonies, hematite oolites, and algal pellets (peloids). Specimen is ~4 cm wide. Variously classified as Collenia undosa, Stratifera biwabikensis, among others. Age ~ 1.8 Ga; Mesoproterozoic.&quot; Mr. Kocher explains further, &quot;'Lower Algal Member' is a designation given to a subset of strata within the Gunflint Formation. The Gunflint Formation has been divided up stratigraphically into at least 5 subsets of strata, i.e., 'Members.'&quot; Perhaps it goes without saying, but the specimen is flat, despite the illusion of hills and valleys.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AIG owns some, or all, of new hotel adjacent to Ark</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/03/aig-owns-some-hotel.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AIG owns some, or all, of new hotel adjacent to Ark" /><published>2023-03-24T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-03-24T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/03/aig-owns-some-hotel</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/03/aig-owns-some-hotel.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Summary: Ken Ham is being quiet that Answers in Genesis (AIG) owns part, or perhaps all, of the new Hampton Inn that just opened adjacent to the Ark Encounter in Williamstown, Kentucky. Moreover, he is trying to make it look as if the supposed “success” of the Ark Park has brought the new hotel to the region. Information below shows that AIG shares a high-level employee with the new hotel, and the LLC that owns the hotel shares a Post Office box with AIG.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ken Ham is being quiet on who owns the new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hilton.com/en/hotels/cvgarhx-hampton-suites-williamstown-ark-encounter/&quot;&gt; Hampton Inn hotel&lt;/a&gt; next to the Ark. It turns out that AIG is, in all probability, at least a partial owner. AIG has not stated their financial interest publicly.  How long will Ham keep quiet about AIG being a part-owner, or more, of the new hotel?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On March 5, Ken Ham bragged that &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2023/03/05/new-hotel-opens-next-to-ark-encounter/&quot;&gt;a new hotel was being built next to the Ark Park parking lot&lt;/a&gt;. Ken was proud that he and select AIG staff were “offered” and given a tour of a new Hampton Inn hotel. It was not stated, but implied, that a new business, independent from AIG and Ark Encounter, was being brought to the region by the overwhelming success of the Ark. His tour is implied to have been given by an unnamed owner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The address of this new Hampton Inn is 2 Skyway Drive, Williamstown, KY. According to the free portion of the Grant County PVA (Property Valuation Administrator) site, this property is owned by Great Tourism Hospitality, LLC (GTH) of Bellevue, Kentucky (Figure 1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Phelps_Hotel_Fig_1_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Grant County PVA listing&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 1. Screenshot of Grant County PVA description of 2 Skyway Drive. For a higher resolution picture, click &lt;a href=&quot;/uploads/2023/Phelps_Hotel_Fig_1.jpg&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A site called Open Corporates has information on Kentucky Corporations (Figure 2). The Kentucky company address for the “Great Tourism Hospitality, LLC” is PO Box 510, Hebron, KY. Hebron is near the Creation Museum, the headquarters of Answers in Genesis. Lo and behold, &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/about/contact/&quot;&gt; AIG’s mailing address&lt;/a&gt; is &lt;i&gt;also&lt;/i&gt; PO Box 510, Hebron,! I noticed a familiar name on the GTH list of Directors/Officers - a Mr. Scott Fetzer (Figure 3). Mr. Fetzer is the Treasurer for Answers in Genesis as well as the Director of Life Action Ministries. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/scott-fetzer-58ab9938/&quot;&gt; Here&lt;/a&gt; is Mr. Fetzer’s LinkedIn page where he lists himself as being the Chief Financial Officer at Answers in Genesis since 2017.  Thus, the CFO of AIG is also an agent for the hotel’s corporation, GTH. Great Tourism Hospitality, LLC, is incorporated in Ohio, and online information about their owners or Articles of Incorporation were not available. A search of the Kentucky Secretary of State’s general information database showed that &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.sos.ky.gov/ftshow/(S(jc2yera1rbcvj0kiku1rt5dc))/default.aspx?path=ftsearch&amp;amp;id=1170595&amp;amp;ct=06&amp;amp;cs=99999&amp;amp;ce=RCeknMkeMwkfvXIkIqla3qquI9dzfchxO8C20a%2bWpNXWyzYyco6t7fKdE5LWYlHV&quot;&gt;Great Tourism Hospitality is incorporated in Ohio and doing business in Kentucky&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Phelps_Hotel_Fig_2_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Listing for GTH&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 2. Open Corporates listing for Great Tourism Hospitality, LLC. Note that Scott Fetzer is the Kentucky Agent and a Director/Officer for Great Tourism Hospitality and that the company address is PO Box 510, Hebron, KY. For a higher resolution picture, click &lt;a href=&quot;/uploads/2023/Phelps_Hotel_Fig_2.jpg&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Phelps_Hotel_Fig_3_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Listing for Scott Fetzer&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 3. Open Corporates listing for Mr. Scott Fetzer. For a higher resolution picture, click &lt;a href=&quot;/uploads/2023/Phelps_Hotel_Fig_3.jpg&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that a different representative of Great Tourism Hospitality, LLC, appeared before a Williamstown City Council special meeting on September 23, 2021. The City Council unanimously gave permission to Great Tourism Hospitality, LLC, to begin clearing the property for hotel construction. According to the meeting minutes, the Ark &lt;a href=&quot;https://cms5.revize.com/revize/williamstown/Document_Center/Agendas%20&amp;amp;%20Minutes/2021/Minutes/09-23-21_CMS.pdf&quot;&gt; sold part of its parking lot&lt;/a&gt; for the Hampton Inn. This is interesting. Did the for-profit Ark Encounter sell the land to its owner, the non-profit Answers in Genesis? Answers in Genesis, a non-profit, now seems to be a part owner of the Hampton Inn.  What were the complexities of a non-profit selling this small parcel of property to a presumably for-profit hotel business that is at least partly owned by the non-profit? Was the hotel built on part of the nearly 100 acres of land Williamstown originally sold the Ark for $2?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Williamstown already has two rather old and outmoded hotels, the Sunrise Inn and America’s Best Value Inn. Additionally, there are numerous small bed-and-breakfast suites in and around Williamstown. What will the owners of these businesses think of the new competition? Back in 2011, when the Ark was trying to get various perks and incentives from Grant County and Williamstown, a public meeting was held. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2011/08/ark-encounter-l.html&quot;&gt; my account of the meeting&lt;/a&gt;, I noted that AIG representative Mike Zovath discussed how AIG was staying out of the hotel business:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; According Zovath, the area will need many additional hotels and restaurants. According to the Beemer study, there will be enough visitors to justify twenty 100-room hotels in the area. Presently, there are very few hotels and restaurants in this rural area. Zovath said Ark Encounter will have 60 to 70 acres of their 800 acres available to developers to either lease or purchase for hotels and restaurants. Ark Encounter itself is staying out of the hotel and restaurant business. Zovath concluded, &quot;That's my story, I'm sticking to it.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks as if AIG has backed out of the promise not enter the hotel business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since AIG is at least a partial owner of the Williamstown Hampton Inn, will they discriminate in hiring? I cannot find any direct evidence on this. There are &lt;a href=&quot; https://www.google.com/search?q=jobs+at+hampton+inn+williamstown+ky&quot;&gt;jobs available&lt;/a&gt;, but they do not mention any religious requirements as do the Ark and the Creation Museum, both of which require a statement of faith and many more religious requirements for employees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, will they let rooms to unmarried couples or gays? Will this business follow Hilton/Hampton Inn policies or AIG’s? Hilton, the owner of Hampton Inn franchises, has &lt;a href=&quot;https://ir.hilton.com/~/media/Files/H/Hilton-Worldwide-IR-V3/committee-composition/human-rights-policy.pdf&quot;&gt;this policy&lt;/a&gt; . Would the Ark’s Hampton Inn lose their franchise if they discriminate? AIG’s policy concerning non-marital sex and gay sex in summarized in their “&lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/about/faith/&quot;&gt;Statement of Faith&lt;/a&gt;.” Specifically, AIG’s position in part is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; The only legitimate marriage, based on the creation ordinance in Genesis 1 and 2, sanctioned by God is the joining of &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/about/definition-man-and-woman/&quot;&gt;one naturally born man and one naturally born woman&lt;/a&gt; in a single, exclusive union as delineated in Scripture. God intends sexual intimacy to only occur between a man and a woman who are married to each other and has commanded that no sexual activity be engaged in outside of a marriage between a man and a woman. Any form of &quot;sexual immorality,&quot; such as adultery, fornication, prostitution, homosexuality, lesbianism, bisexual conduct, bestiality, incest, pornography, abuse, or any attempt to change one’s gender, or disagreement with one’s biological gender, is sinful and offensive to God (Genesis 1:27–28, 2:24; Matthew 5:27–30, 19:4-5; Mark 10:2–9; 1 Corinthians 6:9–11; 1 Thessalonians 4:3–7; Hebrews 13:4).&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will AIG’s new Hampton Inn refuse guests that they do not approve of? In a controversial decision, the US Supreme Court recently ruled that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/17pdf/16-111_j4el.pdf&quot;&gt;private businesses can discriminate on religious grounds&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, Ken Ham has been quiet on who owns the new hotel. He implies that it is being built because of the supposed grand success of the Ark Encounter. However, attendance at the Ark, as documented by monthly Kentucky Open Records Act requests for the 50 cent/ticket Safety Tax imposed by Williamstown, shows that they have &lt;i&gt;never&lt;/i&gt; come close to attendance projections. Before the Ark opened in 2016, AIG was claiming 1.4 to 2.2 million people would be visiting the Ark every year. There is no available evidence that even one million tickets have sold per year and the data shows a continued downward trend in attendance. Recently, &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2023/02/25/exciting-update-offices-move-incredible-building/&quot;&gt;AIG bought the former headquarters of Toyota, USA&lt;/a&gt; in northern Kentucky for more than $31 million. With Ark and Creation Museum attendance being mediocre, how did they afford this?  AIG is highly likely to be receiving large donations from donors with deep pockets. I recently exposed how AIG has received at least &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/Funder-of-Super-Bowl.html&quot;&gt; $19 million in dark money&lt;/a&gt; from the Servant Foundation via “donor advised funds.” Perhaps AIG has received additional donations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This latest chapter in AIG’s history in Kentucky shows the duplicitous nature of their activities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Summary: Ken Ham is being quiet that Answers in Genesis (AIG) owns part, or perhaps all, of the new Hampton Inn that just opened adjacent to the Ark Encounter in Williamstown, Kentucky. Moreover, he is trying to make it look as if the supposed “success” of the Ark Park has brought the new hotel to the region. Information below shows that AIG shares a high-level employee with the new hotel, and the LLC that owns the hotel shares a Post Office box with AIG. Ken Ham is being quiet on who owns the new Hampton Inn hotel next to the Ark. It turns out that AIG is, in all probability, at least a partial owner. AIG has not stated their financial interest publicly. How long will Ham keep quiet about AIG being a part-owner, or more, of the new hotel? On March 5, Ken Ham bragged that a new hotel was being built next to the Ark Park parking lot. Ken was proud that he and select AIG staff were “offered” and given a tour of a new Hampton Inn hotel. It was not stated, but implied, that a new business, independent from AIG and Ark Encounter, was being brought to the region by the overwhelming success of the Ark. His tour is implied to have been given by an unnamed owner. The address of this new Hampton Inn is 2 Skyway Drive, Williamstown, KY. According to the free portion of the Grant County PVA (Property Valuation Administrator) site, this property is owned by Great Tourism Hospitality, LLC (GTH) of Bellevue, Kentucky (Figure 1). Figure 1. Screenshot of Grant County PVA description of 2 Skyway Drive. For a higher resolution picture, click here.  </summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“P Hacking” and natural selection</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/03/Phacking.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“P Hacking” and natural selection" /><published>2023-03-17T17:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-03-17T17:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/03/Phacking</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/03/Phacking.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Pigeon_peas2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Pigeon Peas, often known by the Filipino Ilocano language word &lt;em&gt;kardis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“P hacking” is a form of cheating, whether inadvertent or advertent.  You test a bunch of chemicals on rats to see whether they cause, say weight loss.  You do a statistical 
test on each, to see whether there is significant evidence for weight loss.  The 
results are judged by the probability &lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; that evidence this strong would arise by 
chance, if there were actually no effect.  You use a small probability, say 0.05, 
as a sign that the effect is real.  But suppose that you have 100 different chemicals, and do 100 separate tests.  If none of these chemicals have any actual effect, what 
is the chance that none of the tests will have &lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; smaller than 0.05?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is easy to compute: it is 0.95&lt;sup&gt;100&lt;/sup&gt;, which is 0.00592.  The chance that at least one of the 100 tests shows a value of &lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; below 0.05 is actually 0.99408.  If what you do is pick that test (or tests) and write a scientific paper reporting the 
effectiveness of that chemical, you will be committing P-hacking.  If none of the 
chemicals actually works, over 99% of the time you will be able to announce that you have found a weight-loss drug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that is relevant to evaluating the meaning of a mathematical paper in the ID journal &lt;em&gt;BIO-Complexity&lt;/em&gt; in 2018.  It is by George Montañez, a computer scientist at Harvey Mudd College in Claremont, California.  It contains mathematical proofs that concepts of Specified Complexity can be considered in a unified way.  The unstated 
implication is that with natural evolutionary processes, high levels of Specified Complexity cannot be expected.  Montañez’s paper can be found 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://bio-complexity.org/ojs/index.php/main/article/view/BIO-C.2018.4/BIO-C.2018.4&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why am I bringing up P-hacking?  Not to accuse Montañez of it.  In fact, the 
opposite.  It is to point out that natural selection acts like P-hacking. 
Let me explain, first what Montañez’s paper does, then what it says about demonstrating Design, 
and finally how natural selection’s “P hacking” makes that difficult:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;montañezs-paper&quot;&gt;Montañez’s paper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Montañez’s paper in &lt;em&gt;BIO-Complexity&lt;/em&gt; is a detailed mathematical treatment of how one can make a unified 
mathematical framework for computing a quantity, Specified Complexity, one which brings together Dembski’s original 
argument, algorithmic specified complexity, and irreducible complexity arguments.  I don’t find any mathematical 
errors in it.  (For those interested: he uses a combination of the Neyman-Pearson Lemma with a distribution 
constructed from a rescaling of the specification function to have unit area under it.  From this he finds a 
rejection region for the null hypothesis.  He covers multiple cases. The likelihood ratio needed in the Neyman-Pearson 
lemma is the ratio of this artificial distribution to the distribution under the null hypothesis.  He calls that 
ratio the “kardis”, for which see the figure caption above.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-he-suggests-demonstrating-design&quot;&gt;How he suggests demonstrating design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Montañez does discuss testing Design, which, like all ID advocates, he equates with rejecting the 
hypothesis that the degree of adaptation, or, more mysteriously, the algorithmic simplicity of something-or-other, 
can be accounted for by natural processes.  (For a lengthy rant by me on why the algorithmic simplicity argument 
seems to make no sense, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/12/Is-Algorithmic-Specified-Complexity-Useless-for-Analyzing-Evolution.html&quot;&gt;an earlier post by me&lt;/a&gt;).  For Montañez, natural processes may be rejected if we do not 
have big enough probabilities of the observed adaptations when natural processes operate.  The burden of proof is on the biologists:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Simply put, &lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt; is the entry fee for a probabilistic mechanism to even enter the tournament of competing explanations (Montañez, 2018, Section 6.1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No similar criterion is proposed for Design explanations to enter this tournament.  In effect, this is simply the 
common taunt of Design advocates: if we do not have a probabilistic argument from a detailed model of natural 
processes, we cannot reject Design Intervention.  When evolutionists ask for a similar calculation for the supposed 
Design processes, this is waved away with the argument that we do not understand that Design is not that kind of 
hypothesis.  In bills recently introduced in U.S. legislatures, they want to allow teaching of how Intelligent Design 
explains biological adaptations.  But Design does not have &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; such explanation, whatever the legislators think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-we-do-not-have-a-detailed-probabilistic-model-of-evolution&quot;&gt;Why we do not have a detailed probabilistic model of evolution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Montañez only requires evolutionary biologists to have a “probabilistic mechanism” stated in sufficient 
detail to actually compute a probability &lt;em&gt;p(x)&lt;/em&gt; that the observed adaptations would occur.  And in addition, able to 
compute the probabilities that adaptations that are as good or better will evolve.  What would we need to know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, we’d need to know all possible relevant features of the environment, including features of organisms that serve 
as predators, prey, or competitors.  And we’d need to know the entire genetics of our organism, including the functions and interactions of all genes.  And we’d need to know the full developmental biology of all relevant phenotypes, the full physiology, and functional ecology.  That’s all.  Obviously we are nowhere near this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what alternative do Montañez and his friends propose?  Nothing.  Not anything involving any of that biology. The classes in which they would teach their actual theory would be pleasantly short, involving just how to say “Poof!”.
Once that is done, it is time for a relaxing recess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;functional-information&quot;&gt;Functional Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the distributions that Montañez points to is the one used by people who compute Functional Information.  This is not a creationist-and-or-ID computation, it is an attempt to quantitate how much biological information is 
involved in an adaptation. We start with a uniform distribution over all possible genomes.  If the genome is, say, 
1,000,000 bases long, there would be 4 possibilities at each of those million sites, for a total of 4&lt;sup&gt;1,000,000&lt;/sup&gt; possible sequences.  That’s 10&lt;sup&gt;602060&lt;/sup&gt;, roughly.  We assume that all these are equally probable.  One needs to know what fraction of those achieve 
higher specification, such as higher fitness, than the observed sequence.  Once we know that fraction &lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt;, we can 
compute functional information as &lt;em&gt;-log&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;(P)&lt;/em&gt; bits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were to take a random one of those sequences and mutate it randomly, you get another random sequence.  If mutation is the only relevant evolutionary process, the distribution of outcomes in the long run is the nearly the same as randomly choosing samples from all possibilities.  If we see in the real organism a reasonble 
fitness, it would have an implausibly high functional information.  Applying 
Montañez’s formulas we would reject random sampling from all sequences as the source of the observed sequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;where-p-hacking-comes-in&quot;&gt;Where P-hacking comes in&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is there some other, biologically plausible, process that could have produced the 
observed sequence?  There is, of course – natural selection.  Instead of meandering mutationally generation after generation, P-hacking occurs.  Among the sequences available, the ones that have higher functionality (in this case, higher fitness) are more likely to be chosen.  If you did this, your teacher would be upset, because the result would be cheating on the exam.  But natural selection does this, not just in each generation, but repeatedly.  And the results accumulate.  Cumulative selection occurs, simply because each generation is the offspring of the previous one.  No elaborate scheme is needed: organisms of higher fitness contribute more genes to the next generation, and future organisms are descended from those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Montañez’s paper he says about the equiprobable distribution used in computing Functional Information that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Claiming that a probabilistic process boosts the 
likelihood of observing some particular result 
remains without force unless one can provide some 
actual numbers for this claim, namely, what 
&lt;em&gt;p(x)&lt;/em&gt; is under the proposed distribution (or some 
reasonable lower bound).  Thus the burden of 
providing such estimates resides with those 
proposing the probabilistic process as an 
explanation in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the observed fitness of organisms is far higher than it would be for genomes typed on 
four-key typewriters by monkeys, Montañez implies that we cannot simply invoke 
cumulative natural selection.  We’ve got to supply a detailed probabilistic model. 
Otherwise he will invoke Design Intervention.  Which always results in a probability 
of 1 for whatever we see.  And that is the biggest P-hack of all.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Pigeon Peas, often known by the Filipino Ilocano language word kardis &amp;nbsp; “P hacking” is a form of cheating, whether inadvertent or advertent. You test a bunch of chemicals on rats to see whether they cause, say weight loss. You do a statistical test on each, to see whether there is significant evidence for weight loss. The results are judged by the probability P that evidence this strong would arise by chance, if there were actually no effect. You use a small probability, say 0.05, as a sign that the effect is real. But suppose that you have 100 different chemicals, and do 100 separate tests. If none of these chemicals have any actual effect, what is the chance that none of the tests will have P smaller than 0.05? That is easy to compute: it is 0.95100, which is 0.00592. The chance that at least one of the 100 tests shows a value of P below 0.05 is actually 0.99408. If what you do is pick that test (or tests) and write a scientific paper reporting the effectiveness of that chemical, you will be committing P-hacking. If none of the chemicals actually works, over 99% of the time you will be able to announce that you have found a weight-loss drug. All that is relevant to evaluating the meaning of a mathematical paper in the ID journal BIO-Complexity in 2018. It is by George Montañez, a computer scientist at Harvey Mudd College in Claremont, California. It contains mathematical proofs that concepts of Specified Complexity can be considered in a unified way. The unstated implication is that with natural evolutionary processes, high levels of Specified Complexity cannot be expected. Montañez’s paper can be found here. Why am I bringing up P-hacking? Not to accuse Montañez of it. In fact, the opposite. It is to point out that natural selection acts like P-hacking. Let me explain, first what Montañez’s paper does, then what it says about demonstrating Design, and finally how natural selection’s “P hacking” makes that difficult:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tenodera sinensis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/03/tenodera-sinensis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tenodera sinensis" /><published>2023-03-13T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-03-13T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/03/tenodera-sinensis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/03/tenodera-sinensis.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Denelsbeck.Tenodera_sinensis.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Chinese mantis emerging from egg sac&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_mantis&quot;&gt;Tenodera_sinensis&lt;/a&gt; – Chinese mantids emerging from egg sac, or ootheca. Mr. Denelsbeck writes, &quot;I have yet to capture the actual emergence, but this is not long afterward. They appear to do an immediate molt, or perhaps partial molt, while still attached to a fine thread, but from what I've been able to observe the legs aren't included in the fragments left behind, so perhaps one of the more entomological readers can clarify. Within the hour, that bulging forehead will shrink, the eyes will swell, and the classic mantis head will become apparent, as the legs begin to gain mobility. Some already-mobile siblings can be made out in the background. There is also a brief video [and additional photographs] to accompany this, found at &lt;a href=&quot;http://wading-in.net/walkabout/2017/04/too-cool-part-35-a-modicum-of-success/&quot;&gt;http://wading-in.net/walkabout/2017/04/too-cool-part-35-a-modicum-of-success/&lt;/a&gt;.&quot; We think you will not be disappointed if you follow the link; the video is near the bottom of the page, following a half-dozen still photos.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Al Denelsbeck. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Tenodera_sinensis – Chinese mantids emerging from egg sac, or ootheca. Mr. Denelsbeck writes, &quot;I have yet to capture the actual emergence, but this is not long afterward. They appear to do an immediate molt, or perhaps partial molt, while still attached to a fine thread, but from what I've been able to observe the legs aren't included in the fragments left behind, so perhaps one of the more entomological readers can clarify. Within the hour, that bulging forehead will shrink, the eyes will swell, and the classic mantis head will become apparent, as the legs begin to gain mobility. Some already-mobile siblings can be made out in the background. There is also a brief video [and additional photographs] to accompany this, found at http://wading-in.net/walkabout/2017/04/too-cool-part-35-a-modicum-of-success/.&quot; We think you will not be disappointed if you follow the link; the video is near the bottom of the page, following a half-dozen still photos.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ailuropoda melanoleuca</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/ailuropoda-melanoleuca.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ailuropoda melanoleuca" /><published>2023-02-27T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-02-27T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/ailuropoda-melanoleuca</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/ailuropoda-melanoleuca.html">&lt;p&gt;Photographs by &lt;strong&gt;Dan Phelps&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Phelps_Panda_Bill_Obverse_900.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Obverse side of bill&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Counterfeit* bill showing image of &lt;i&gt;Ailuropoda melanoleuca&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; giant panda. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giant_panda&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; You may purchase similar bills for less than $2 apiece &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ebay.com/itm/113578496561&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. As Mr. Phelps notes, at least it is not a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/12/aig-counterfeit-money.html&quot;&gt;religious tract&lt;/a&gt;. The panda in the center is, of course, Prof. Steve Steve, who (though we have not heard from him in quite a while) steadfastly maintains that &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2015/07/why-are-giant-p.html&quot;&gt;he is not lazy&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;small&gt;*&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/counterfeit&quot;&gt;Sense 2b&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Phelps_Panda_Bill_Reverse_900.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reverse side of bill&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The reverse side of the bill.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photographs by Dan Phelps. Counterfeit* bill showing image of Ailuropoda melanoleuca &amp;ndash; giant panda. You may purchase similar bills for less than $2 apiece here. As Mr. Phelps notes, at least it is not a religious tract. The panda in the center is, of course, Prof. Steve Steve, who (though we have not heard from him in quite a while) steadfastly maintains that he is not lazy. *Sense 2b.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Science Advocate Frank Lovell: A Remembrance</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/science-advocate-Frank-Lovell.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science Advocate Frank Lovell: A Remembrance" /><published>2023-02-22T13:01:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-02-22T13:01:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/science-advocate-Frank-Lovell</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/science-advocate-Frank-Lovell.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Guest post by Tom Wheeler in remembrance of his friend, Frank Lovell. We extend our sincere condolences to Mr. Wheeler and to Mr. Lovell’s family.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Wheeler_Fig_1_FrankFaceBook_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frank's Facebook photograph&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Frank Lovell's Facebook profile picture.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frank Lovell, an outstanding defender of evolution and promoter of public understanding of science, died on January 26, 2023, from injuries suffered in a fall. He was 79 years old. He is survived by his wife Debbie and children Annie Lovell, Frank Lovell III, Alicia Lovell (Dennis Nalley) and Simon Lovell (Sneha Thapa) (1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Born in Ashland Kentucky, he served four years in the United States Army. He then studied physical organic chemistry at the University of Louisville and University of Kentucky, receiving a bachelor’s degree from the latter. A 30-year career with General Electric in Louisville followed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frank’s anti-creationism efforts began in 1982 with letters to the editor; he estimated that he wrote a couple of dozen letters in the next couple of years (2). In 1983, I had a letter of my own published, critiquing a creationist op-ed. A couple of days later, I received a letter from Frank, praising my letter and including a copy of the letter he had written personally to the creationist. He invited me to join him in fighting creationism. This was the beginning of an extensive collaboration that would continue until I moved away from Louisville in 2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frank and I decided to form a new Committee of Correspondence in the Louisville area, the Kentucky Committee for Science Education. This was to complement the existing Committee for Effective Action in Science Education (CEASE) in Lexington, founded by Drs. Eugenie Scott and Wayne Davis of the University of Kentucky. Unlike the case in Lexington, where proposed teaching of creationism in public schools led to the formation of CEASE, there did not appear to be a similar threat in Louisville. Rather, our focus was on the public presentations (letters to the editor, public talks, media presentations, etc.) of local creationists, particularly ministers of the Church of Christ. (Frank designed a letterhead with a KCSE logo, and issued documents on behalf of the group, but in reality it just consisted of the two of us.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-right-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 40px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Wheeler_Fig_2_FrankPoster_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frank at a poster session&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Poster session, 1986.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frank described our efforts in a presentation at a 1988 AAAS meeting, which can be seen in a YouTube video (2). These included letters to the editor; correspondence with local creationist speakers and other individuals; a poster presentation; handouts distributed at talks related to evolution; and public talks of our own. We engaged extensively with one biology-trained preacher, and even got invited to give a couple of talks at his church. Throughout this we tried to document errors in materials of prominent young-Earth creationists, and hold the locals accountable for not repeating arguments that had been shown to be false. The bulk of this correspondence was Frank’s work; his scholarly output was impressive, especially in light of all his other interests (as noted below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1985, the local pastors challenged us to a public debate. I decided that, given the pitfalls of debating creationists and the amount of time required to debate properly, it was not something I wanted to do. However, Frank accepted the challenge, and a four-night debate was arranged (3). I assisted Frank. The creationists brought in Dr. H.E. “Buddy” Payne from Florida College. Frank made a vigorous attack on the young Earth model as promoted by the Institute for Creation Research. However, Payne refused to take a stand on the age of the Earth, leaving him free to attack standard findings from geology and evolution without having to defend anything. As I noted (3), “Overall, Payne’s superior public speaking ability probably helped make his presentation more persuasive to the audience, which appeared to be mostly sympathetic to creationism.” Frank acknowledged that it was “a very humbling, character building experience” (2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also corresponded with both nationally known creationists and scientific experts in analyzing and responding to creationist claims. These included meteoritic dust on the moon (4) and Grand Canyon lava flows. Frank also assisted me in my detailed rebuttal to D. James Kennedy’s presentations on “The John Ankerberg Show.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another of Frank’s activities was attending creationist conferences, often with Robert Schadewald. They frequently met informally with creationists at lunch. As Schadewald wrote (5), “…our interactions with the creationists invariably were cordial or better…We both felt that these exchanges were the best part of the conference.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have less information about Frank’s activities after I left Louisville in 2006, but I believe that he continued to defend evolution with similar enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Wheeler_Fig_3_FrankShermer_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frank with Michael Shermer&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Frank with Michael Shermer, before Shermer’s debate with William Dembski, 2006.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was also active in combating other forms of pseudoscience besides creationism. When the Committee for the Scientific Investigation of Claims of the Paranormal (CSICOP) issued a call for local groups to coordinate with its goals, we volunteered KCSE to be such a group. Simultaneous, Dr. Robert A. Baker of the University of Kentucky offered to form a group. We decided to defer to Dr. Baker’s leadership and joined his new Kentucky Association of Science Educators and Skeptics (KASES). Later, Frank accepted my invitation to join the Kentucky Council Against Health Fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frank’s activities were not restricted to critiquing bad science; he was an active promoter of scientific knowledge and science education. He was a long-time member of the Louisville Astronomical Society, serving at various times as President, Chairman of the Board, Editor, and Librarian. He served nearly 30 years as a member of the Board of Directors of the Louisville Regional Science Fair, and at different times was Head Judge for physics, Head Judge for team projects, Judging Committee Coordinator, and Fair Co-director.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another major interest of Frank’s was philosophy and religion. I recall that he described himself as “an atheist of the agnostic variety,” meaning he could not disprove the existence of God, but found no compelling reason to believe. He was an active member of the Louisville Freethought Society, participating in weekly meetups and staffing a booth at the Kentucky State Fair each year. As he did with creationists, he carried on extensive correspondence with preachers and lay individuals concerning religious topics, and gave public talks. One of these that I attended was a two-night debate with a local minister. He expressed his views on science and religion as follows: “Where ever objective knowledge is incomplete, there is a place for religious ‘faith’ (for any who feel need for religious ‘faith,’ at any rate); but where ever objective knowledge and religious ‘faith’ conflict, it is religious ‘faith’ (not objective knowledge) which should be modified or abandoned. That is the only rational way that there can be no conflict between science and religion.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Wheeler_Fig_4_FrankAstro_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frank with Deborah Warren and Daniel Phelps&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Frank with Deborah Warren of the Louisville Astronomical Society and guest speaker Daniel Phelps, January 2023.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was a regular participant on FreeThought Channel, including a major interview (6). His fellow panelists have posted a remembrance (7).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frank had a large following on Facebook, where he regularly posted on new scientific developments, philosophical questions, and videos of musical performances that he felt especially enjoyable. The announcement of his death on his Facebook page was met with an outpouring of condolences from around the world. Here is one typical comment: “I deeply appreciated his intelligence, integrity, humanity, warmth and tolerance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Thomas J. Wheeler was a biochemistry professor at the University of Louisville for 25 years, followed by a second career as a high school science teacher in Scranton, PA. He is now retired and living in the Chicago area.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Matt Young will be the moderator of this thread.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ferncreekfuneralhome.com/obituary/frank-lovell&quot;&gt;Frank Lovell obituary&lt;/a&gt; 2023. Fern Creek Funeral Home&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5kp0pTB1yuE&quot;&gt;National Center for Science Education. Do’s and Dont’s Debating Creationists: Part 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wheeler TJ. Lovell-Payne Debate, Aug. 12-16, 1985. Creation/Evolution Newsletter, 1986. 6(1):16-17&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wheeler TJ. More on Creationists and Meteoritic Dust. Creation/Evolution Newsletter, 1987. 7(4):14-15&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Schadewald R. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/1998-international-conference-creationism&quot;&gt;The 1998 International Conference on Creationism&lt;/a&gt;. Reports of the National Center for Science Education, 1998. 18(3)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1xTdvU4Bm-o&quot;&gt;Ask an Atheist with guest Frank Lovell&lt;/a&gt;. FreeThought Channel&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B3MfRTD7EVw&quot;&gt;Eulogy to Frank from the VotN panel&lt;/a&gt;. FreeThought Channel&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Thomas J. Wheeler</name></author><summary type="html">Guest post by Tom Wheeler in remembrance of his friend, Frank Lovell. We extend our sincere condolences to Mr. Wheeler and to Mr. Lovell’s family. Frank Lovell's Facebook profile picture. Frank Lovell, an outstanding defender of evolution and promoter of public understanding of science, died on January 26, 2023, from injuries suffered in a fall. He was 79 years old. He is survived by his wife Debbie and children Annie Lovell, Frank Lovell III, Alicia Lovell (Dennis Nalley) and Simon Lovell (Sneha Thapa) (1). Born in Ashland Kentucky, he served four years in the United States Army. He then studied physical organic chemistry at the University of Louisville and University of Kentucky, receiving a bachelor’s degree from the latter. A 30-year career with General Electric in Louisville followed. Frank’s anti-creationism efforts began in 1982 with letters to the editor; he estimated that he wrote a couple of dozen letters in the next couple of years (2). In 1983, I had a letter of my own published, critiquing a creationist op-ed. A couple of days later, I received a letter from Frank, praising my letter and including a copy of the letter he had written personally to the creationist. He invited me to join him in fighting creationism. This was the beginning of an extensive collaboration that would continue until I moved away from Louisville in 2006.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Funder of Super Bowl &quot;He Gets Us&quot; ad also funds many groups including AIG and the DI via dark money</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/Funder-of-Super-Bowl.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Funder of Super Bowl &quot;He Gets Us&quot; ad also funds many groups including AIG and the DI via dark money" /><published>2023-02-16T09:25:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-02-16T09:25:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/Funder-of-Super-Bowl</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/Funder-of-Super-Bowl.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Phelps_Creation_Museum_DSC03914_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Creation &amp;#34;Museum&amp;#34;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Entrance to the Creation &quot;Museum.&quot; &lt;small&gt;Photograph by Daniel Phelps, used by permission.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funder of the “He Gets Us” ad broadcast during the Super Bowl also funds many groups including Answers in Genesis and the Discovery Institute via dark money techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several investigators have recently looked into The Servant Foundation because they funded the “He Gets Us” Super Bowl advertisements for Jesus (for example &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.au.org/the-latest/articles/christian-nationalist-donors-super-bowl-jesus-ad/&quot;&gt;Americans United&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://skepchick.org/2023/02/whos-behind-those-jesus-ads-youre-gonna-see-during-the-big-game/&quot;&gt;Rebecca Watson&lt;/a&gt;, aka Skepchick). Both AU and Skepchick discovered that, in spite of the liberal-sounding nature of the Super Bowl advertising, the Servant Foundation also has donated to numerous fundamentalist Christian Nationalist hate groups. Apparently, the Servant Foundation is a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.irs.gov/charities-non-profits/charitable-organizations/donor-advised-funds&quot;&gt;donor-advised fund&lt;/a&gt;” and receives donations for a number of worthy causes as well as cringeworthy hateful groups. Because of loopholes in the tax laws, people can donate to the Servant Foundation and see that their money goes to their favorite extremist groups via a “donor-advised fund” without their identity being revealed; this is basically “dark-money.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazingly, The Servant Foundation, doing business as “&lt;a href=&quot;https://thesignatry.com/&quot;&gt;The Signatry&lt;/a&gt;,” presently has assets approaching $1 billion. I looked at their publicly available IRS Form 990’s for 2016 to 2020 and, besides a handful of small donations to worthy organizations, and many organizations of whom I am unaware, there were a number of donations to far-right, generally Christian Nationalist, organizations. I have mentioned below a number of them that are listed in the Form 990 from 4/1/20 to 3/31/21.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Answers in Genesis and the Discovery Institute have received monies from The Servant Foundation, presumably via a “donor-advised fund.” Since 2016, Answers in Genesis has received $19,349,691.00, and the Discovery Institute, $750,600.00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although AIG seems to have difficulty with the shrinking number of paid tickets at the Ark Encounter, they will never go broke because of donations, including these by The Servant Foundation’s donor-advised fund. So who is supplying this dark money to the creationists? Without donor transparency, this question may be impossible to answer. Kentucky media are shrinking and only rarely cover AIG and the Ark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supporting information below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Servant Foundation’s IRS Form 990’s are available via &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instrumentl.com/990-report/servant-foundation&quot;&gt; this website &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Servant Foundation doing business as The Signatry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Form 990, 4/1/20 and ending 3/31/21&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of the year assets $974,727,606.00
Form 990, Schedule I, Part II, Grants and Other Assistance to Domestic Organizations and Domestic Governments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers in Genesis: $10,552,200.00&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other groups that interested me and are listed as receiving donations (this is a far from a comprehensive list) include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Academy for Climate and Energy Analysis, Inc. Shawnee, Kansas, $5,500.00 (a tiny group run by a former TV weatherman that promotes anti-climate change disinformation. Seems mostly to be repeating Heartland Institute disinformation. https://aceanalysis.org/).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alliance Defending Freedom, $16,657,150.00 (far right fundamentalist organization in spite of the Orwellian name, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/alliance_defending_freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;American Center for Law and Justice, $44,636.00 (basically, Pat Robertson’s legal arm, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Center_for_Law_%26_Justice)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;American Family Association, $8,550.00 (a huge fundamentalist Christian Nationalist organization, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Family_Associatio).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creation Instruction Association, Inc., Juanita, Nebraska, $5,500.00 (a creationist organization that has a “Seismosaurus Mobile Museum” in an 18 wheeler truck. Lots of dinosaurs with humans dioramas, and also some real and replica fossils, https://www.creationinstruction.org/). A minor player, but still…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovery Institute, $250,500.00 (the leading “intelligent design” creationist organization https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Discovery_Institute. Yep, they are still out there).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edchoice Kentucky, Inc., Frankfort KY, $10,000.00 (a small organization here in Kentucky that advocates governmental support for charter and “non-public ” schools, https://edchoiceky.com/).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;God’s Not Dead Foundation doing business as Pure Flix, $15,000.00 (Pure Flix is partnered with Answers in Genesis so you can watch Ken Ham videos to your heart’s content if you join).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Institute for Creation Research, Dallas, TX, $11,000.00 (the granddaddy of creationist “science” organizations. Relatively tiny now that AiG is the biggest creationist ministry).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jordan B. Peterson Institute, Witchita, Kansas, $12,500.00 (Peterson has an inexplicable right wing young male anti-feminist following as a psychologist and amateur philosopher).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prager University Foundation, Owings Mills, Maryland, $220,750.00 (a “university.” Note that I use scare-quotes here, as actual universities are not based on a large collection of YouTube videos, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PragerU).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Form 990, 4/1/19 and ending 3/31/20&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of the year assets, $699,516,453.00
Form 990, Schedule I, Part II, Grants and Other Assistance to Domestic Organizations and Domestic Governments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers in Genesis, $7,764,000.00&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovery Institute, $250,000.00&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Form 990, 4/1/18 and ending 3/31/19&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of the year assets, $666,786,525.00
Form 990, Schedule I, Part II, Grants and Other Assistance to Domestic Organizations and Domestic Governments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers in Genesis, $1,025,575.00&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovery Institute, $250,100.00&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Form 990, 4/1/17 and ending 3/31/18&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of the year assets, $3,516,408.00
Form 990, Schedule I, Part II, Grants and Other Assistance to Domestic Organizations and Domestic Governments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers in Genesis, $0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovery Institute, $0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Form 990, 4/1/16 and ending 3/31/17&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of the year assets, $4,471,589.00
Form 990, Schedule I, Part II, Grants and Other Assistance to Domestic Organizations and Domestic Governments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers in Genesis, $7,921.00&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovery Institute, $0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing in older IRS Form 990’s that are available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Matt Young will be the principal moderator of this thread.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Entrance to the Creation &quot;Museum.&quot; Photograph by Daniel Phelps, used by permission. The funder of the “He Gets Us” ad broadcast during the Super Bowl also funds many groups including Answers in Genesis and the Discovery Institute via dark money techniques. Several investigators have recently looked into The Servant Foundation because they funded the “He Gets Us” Super Bowl advertisements for Jesus (for example Americans United and Rebecca Watson, aka Skepchick). Both AU and Skepchick discovered that, in spite of the liberal-sounding nature of the Super Bowl advertising, the Servant Foundation also has donated to numerous fundamentalist Christian Nationalist hate groups. Apparently, the Servant Foundation is a “donor-advised fund” and receives donations for a number of worthy causes as well as cringeworthy hateful groups. Because of loopholes in the tax laws, people can donate to the Servant Foundation and see that their money goes to their favorite extremist groups via a “donor-advised fund” without their identity being revealed; this is basically “dark-money.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Helicoverpa zea</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/helicoverpa-zea.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Helicoverpa zea" /><published>2023-02-13T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-02-13T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/helicoverpa-zea</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/helicoverpa-zea.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/P1000071_Moth_Helicoverpa_zea_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Corn earworm moth&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.butterfliesandmoths.org/species/Helicoverpa-zea?page=6&quot;&gt;Helicoverpa zea&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; corn earworm moth &amp;ndash; enjoying a sip from a &lt;a href=&quot;https://planttalk.colostate.edu/topics/trees-shrubs-vines/1741-rabbitbrush/&quot;&gt;rabbitbrush&lt;/a&gt; flower (&lt;i&gt;Chrysothamnus&lt;/i&gt; sp.), Walden Ponds, Boulder, Colorado, October, 2022.  I saw a zillion of these rather undistinguished looking creatures fluttering all over the rabbitbrush, so naturally I photographed some. They seem to be far more common in the eastern part of the United States, but there is an interesting concentration in Colorado between Fort Collins and Colorado Springs, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.butterfliesandmoths.org/species/Helicoverpa-zea?page=6&quot;&gt;Butterflies and Moths of North America&lt;/a&gt;, presumably because that is where all the people live. Something like 70 years ago, I learned that moths had furry antennas and butterflies had smooth antennas, so I first thought, against all odds, that these were butterflies (is the &quot;furry&quot; simply microscopic?). Fortunately, the Library of Congress asks (and answers), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.loc.gov/everyday-mysteries/zoology/item/how-can-you-tell-the-difference-between-a-butterfly-and-a-moth/&quot;&gt; How can you tell the difference between a butterfly and a moth?&lt;/a&gt; which notes several distinguishing features, not just one.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Helicoverpa zea &amp;ndash; corn earworm moth &amp;ndash; enjoying a sip from a rabbitbrush flower (Chrysothamnus sp.), Walden Ponds, Boulder, Colorado, October, 2022. I saw a zillion of these rather undistinguished looking creatures fluttering all over the rabbitbrush, so naturally I photographed some. They seem to be far more common in the eastern part of the United States, but there is an interesting concentration in Colorado between Fort Collins and Colorado Springs, according to Butterflies and Moths of North America, presumably because that is where all the people live. Something like 70 years ago, I learned that moths had furry antennas and butterflies had smooth antennas, so I first thought, against all odds, that these were butterflies (is the &quot;furry&quot; simply microscopic?). Fortunately, the Library of Congress asks (and answers), How can you tell the difference between a butterfly and a moth? which notes several distinguishing features, not just one.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creationism crawls back out of the woodwork</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/creationism-crawls-back.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creationism crawls back out of the woodwork" /><published>2023-02-10T09:22:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-02-10T09:22:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/creationism-crawls-back</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/creationism-crawls-back.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Creationist_Car_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Creationist car&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/f/f5/Creationist_car.jpg/&quot;&gt; Creationist car spotted on Broad Street in Athens, Georgia.&lt;/a&gt; Image by Amy Watts. &lt;small&gt;Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 2.0 Generic license.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recently learned of an article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edhat.com/news/why-creationism-may-come-back-to-our-schools&quot;&gt;Why Creationism May Come Back to Our Schools&lt;/a&gt;, by Eugenie Scott, the former director of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/&quot;&gt;National Center for Science Education&lt;/a&gt;. The occasion was a talk presented by Dr. Scott to the Humanist Society of Santa Barbara on February 1 and ably reported by Robert Bernstein for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edhat.com/&quot;&gt;Edhat&lt;/a&gt;, an online newspaper that covers Santa Barbara County, California.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may read Mr. Bernstein’s article for yourself; let it suffice to say that Dr. Scott reviews “many decades of cases” regarding the Establishment Clause and discusses why creationism generally fails. Then, she says, we come to the Kennedy case, wherein the Supreme Court overruled lower-court decisions and ruled that an assistant football coach, Joseph Kennedy, will be allowed to pray at the center of the football field with his students. The decision is troubling because the new right-wing Supreme Court has no trouble overruling previously established decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Jerry Coyne tells us, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2023/02/09/montana-considers-bill-that-allows-teaching-of-scientific-fcts-but-not-scientific-theories/&quot;&gt;Montana considers a bill that allows teaching of “scientific facts” but not “scientific theories”&lt;/a&gt;. Prof. Coyne is the proprietor of the popular blog &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com &quot;&gt;Why Evolution Is True&lt;/a&gt; and, as they say, has read the bill so you and I do not have to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bill in question is Montana Senate Bill 235, introduced by freshman Senator Dan Emrich. Prof. Coyne quotes the bill as saying&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHEREAS, [sic] the purpose of K-12 education is to educate children in the facts of our world to better prepare them for their future and further education in their chosen field of study, and to that end children must know the difference between scientific fact and scientific theory; and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WHEREAS, [sic] a scientific fact is observable and repeatable, and if it does not meet these criteria, it is a theory that is defined as speculation and is for higher education to explore, debate, and test to ultimately reach a scientific conclusion of fact or fiction. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prof. Coyne adds, ‘They later clarify: “As used in this section, ‘scientific fact’ means an indisputable and repeatable observation of a natural phenomenon.”’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very little in science can be considered an indisputable fact, so if this bill passes and becomes law, schools will not be allowed to teach, say, the theory of relativity, quantum theory, ideal gas theory, the germ theory of disease, or, for that matter, string theory or the theory of the leisure class. Or, what they are really after, the theory of evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, Sen. Emrich and his cosponsors are a trio of ignoramuses who do not have the foggiest idea what a scientific fact or a scientific theory is. They are very dangerous because, as Dr. Scott shows, they almost certainly have the Supreme Court on their side.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Creationist car spotted on Broad Street in Athens, Georgia. Image by Amy Watts. Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 2.0 Generic license. We recently learned of an article, Why Creationism May Come Back to Our Schools, by Eugenie Scott, the former director of the National Center for Science Education. The occasion was a talk presented by Dr. Scott to the Humanist Society of Santa Barbara on February 1 and ably reported by Robert Bernstein for Edhat, an online newspaper that covers Santa Barbara County, California. You may read Mr. Bernstein’s article for yourself; let it suffice to say that Dr. Scott reviews “many decades of cases” regarding the Establishment Clause and discusses why creationism generally fails. Then, she says, we come to the Kennedy case, wherein the Supreme Court overruled lower-court decisions and ruled that an assistant football coach, Joseph Kennedy, will be allowed to pray at the center of the football field with his students. The decision is troubling because the new right-wing Supreme Court has no trouble overruling previously established decisions. Meanwhile, Jerry Coyne tells us, Montana considers a bill that allows teaching of “scientific facts” but not “scientific theories”. Prof. Coyne is the proprietor of the popular blog Why Evolution Is True and, as they say, has read the bill so you and I do not have to.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ark attendance weak, at best</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/ark-attendance-week.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ark attendance weak, at best" /><published>2023-02-01T16:20:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-02-01T16:20:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/ark-attendance-week</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/02/ark-attendance-week.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Trollinger_Ark_Attendance_900.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Graph&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Actual Ark attendance vs. projected, based on the data of William Trollinger. The actual attendance in Year 1 seems to be an estimate. Actual attendance for the period March 2020 through February 2021 have been omitted owing to Covid. Actual attendance for the period January through June 2023 is an estimate based on the historical ratio of attendance during the first six months of the year to that of the last six months.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Trollinger, on the blog Righting America, presents what he calls a few facts about Ark Encounter attendance and deems that attendance to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/not-even-close-to-what-was-projected-a-few-facts-about-ark-encounter-attendance/&quot;&gt;Not Even Close to What Was Projected&lt;/a&gt;. Dr. Trollinger bases his conclusion on data acquired by the indomitable Dan Phelps, an occasional guest contributor here at PT. Mr. Phelps each month uses the Kentucky Open Records Act to ascertain the monies collected by the city of Williamstown from the safety fee of $0.50 added to each ticket. From these data it is easy to deduce the number of tickets sold and therefore the number of patrons in any given month, apart from a number of possibly fictitious season-pass holders who pass the ticket window without being assessed the safety fee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have graphed Dr. Trollinger’s data and show them as the frontispiece to this article. Two of the years, as noted, are estimates. Year 4 is actually a two-year period from July 2019 to June 2021, but with March 2020 through February 2021 omitted because of the Covid pandemic. The result does not seem out of line. Overall attendance, over the 6 years, is about 40 % of projected attendance and appears to have fallen somewhat since Year 3, as projected attendance rises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For that, as Dr. Trollinger notes, Williamstown issued $62 million in junk bonds and in effect forwent a significant sum in property taxes. For more details, see the original article.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Actual Ark attendance vs. projected, based on the data of William Trollinger. The actual attendance in Year 1 seems to be an estimate. Actual attendance for the period March 2020 through February 2021 have been omitted owing to Covid. Actual attendance for the period January through June 2023 is an estimate based on the historical ratio of attendance during the first six months of the year to that of the last six months. William Trollinger, on the blog Righting America, presents what he calls a few facts about Ark Encounter attendance and deems that attendance to be Not Even Close to What Was Projected. Dr. Trollinger bases his conclusion on data acquired by the indomitable Dan Phelps, an occasional guest contributor here at PT. Mr. Phelps each month uses the Kentucky Open Records Act to ascertain the monies collected by the city of Williamstown from the safety fee of $0.50 added to each ticket. From these data it is easy to deduce the number of tickets sold and therefore the number of patrons in any given month, apart from a number of possibly fictitious season-pass holders who pass the ticket window without being assessed the safety fee. I have graphed Dr. Trollinger’s data and show them as the frontispiece to this article. Two of the years, as noted, are estimates. Year 4 is actually a two-year period from July 2019 to June 2021, but with March 2020 through February 2021 omitted because of the Covid pandemic. The result does not seem out of line. Overall attendance, over the 6 years, is about 40 % of projected attendance and appears to have fallen somewhat since Year 3, as projected attendance rises. For that, as Dr. Trollinger notes, Williamstown issued $62 million in junk bonds and in effect forwent a significant sum in property taxes. For more details, see the original article.</summary></entry></feed>