<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-06-15T03:34:15-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">How to talk to a science denier: Another book by Lee McIntyre</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/how-to-talk-science-denier.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to talk to a science denier: Another book by Lee McIntyre" /><published>2023-06-14T09:39:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-06-14T09:39:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/how-to-talk-science-denier</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/how-to-talk-science-denier.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/McIntyre_Science_Denier.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I more or less accidentally came across a copy of Lee McIntyre's 2021 book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/How-Talk-Science-Denier-Conversations-ebook/dp/B08PCL6NVZ/&quot;&gt;How to Talk to a Science Denier&lt;/a&gt;, subtitled &lt;i&gt;Conversations with Flat Earthers, Climate Deniers, and Others Who Defy Reason&lt;/i&gt;. Having recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/scientific-attitude.html&quot;&gt;reviewed&lt;/a&gt; an earlier book of McIntyre's, &lt;i&gt;The Scientific Attitude&lt;/i&gt;, I naturally snapped up &lt;i&gt; How to Talk&lt;/i&gt;. I was not entirely disappointed in the book, but &lt;i&gt;The Scientific Attitude&lt;/i&gt;, shall we say, was more impressive. &lt;i&gt;How to Talk&lt;/i&gt; was like another New York Times Magazine article stretched into a book and must be 30&amp;nbsp;% notes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And speaking of notes, whereas most of the notes were references, occasionally a note presented important material, but who can reference all those notes, even on an E-reader? If the material was important enough to be included in the book, it should have been in the main text, not in a note.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh well, on to the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will define science denial the way &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Sex-Necessary-Why-You-Feel/dp/0060733144&quot;&gt;James Thurber and E. B. White&lt;/a&gt; may have defined it: when I say &quot;science denial&quot;, I &lt;i&gt;mean&lt;/i&gt; &quot;science denial,&quot; real, hard-core science denial like flat-earthism and climate denial. I will, however, point out that science denial differs from wrong or incorrect science. McIntyre suggests that one way to talk to a science denier is to present them with facts, a technique he calls &lt;i&gt;content rebuttal&lt;/i&gt;; I am not as sanguine as he that mere facts will change the mind of a true science denier. Confirmation bias and motivated reasoning are powerful, and I sometimes think that, when we develop what we consider a &quot;logical&quot; argument for some proposition, we are just giving ourselves a pep talk to convince ourselves that we are right. Although he does not put it this way, McIntyre describes some interesting experiments wherein people deduce the result that they want, not the objectively correct result – but they get the objectively correct result when it is the one they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If content rebuttal fails, you can always try &lt;i&gt;technique rebuttal&lt;/i&gt;. Technique rebuttal &quot;relies on the idea that there are five common reasoning errors made by &lt;i&gt;all&lt;/i&gt; science deniers&quot;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reliance on conspiracy theories, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cherry-picking evidence, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reliance on fake experts, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting impossible expectations for science [but not for the deniers' favored pseudoscience], and &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using illogical reasoning. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You do not have to know any science to apply technique rebuttal, which can be an advantage. McIntyre likes his list so well that he reminds us of it several times, though in fairness he also fleshes it out by showing precisely how various science deniers use such errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McIntyre also notes, correctly, that you must be unfailingly polite, a lesson that some of us commenters here on PT and elsewhere might take to heart. You will never convince somebody by telling them that their argument is &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2017/02/on-bullshit.html&quot;&gt;bullshit&lt;/a&gt;. Similarly, you may have to bite your tongue and call an abortion opponent &quot;pro-life,&quot; rather than &quot;anti-abortion.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the questions McIntyre asks, and it is a good one, is, &quot;What evidence, if it existed, would it take to convince you that you were wrong?&quot; I would say, as Haldane reputedly said, &quot;a rabbit in the Precambrian.&quot; I would even settle for a rabbit in the Cambrian. It is not entirely clear how many of McIntyre's interlocutors might answer that question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, dear reader, is the gist of this short book. The rest, though not uninteresting, consists of a sort of travelog in which the author attends a flat-earth convention in order to learn how to talk to people; visits Maldives, an island nation in the Indian Ocean, in order to learn about climate change; meets with coal miners; and discusses at length genetically modified foods in order to test his hypothesis about convincing people. The author learns a great deal as the book progresses, but sometimes I found myself wishing that he had merely given his conclusions in a much shorter form, rather than subjecting us to the learning process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flat-earth convention was mildly interesting. Flat-earthers think that Antarctica is not a continent but rather a wall surrounding the flat earth. The reaction of one flat-earther when McIntyre offered to fly him over Antarctica was almost worth the price of the book. It helped convince McIntyre that a strong sense of belonging is at least part of the reason that people hold irrationally wrong beliefs. If that is so, and I see no reason to think it is not, then it will be extremely difficult to change a great many minds. Think of the vast number of people who still think Trump won the 2020 election. Still, McIntyre claims to have learned tactics from the flat-earthers: &quot;Remain calm. Be respectful. Engage them ['globalists'] in conversation. Try to build some trust.&quot; They had, as he notes, the conversion tactics just right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visit to the Maldives, by contrast, seemed pointless. It is true that the Maldives are likely to sink and disappear, but I can see no reason to go there to learn about climate change. That part of the book was mostly fill, though one of the people he met noted, &quot;Outside the Maldives, no one cares. &quot; Suddenly, McIntyre realizes that you have to not just believe in climate change, but also &quot;give a damn.&quot; For that he had to shlep to the Maldives?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At any rate, we will certainly not change very many minds one at a time, and McIntyre was not singularly successful with the flat-earthers. Fair enough, because the main reason he went to the flat-earth convention was to learn how to talk to such people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McIntyre talks to coal miners and learns the truth of Upton Sinclair's dictum, &quot;It is difficult to get a man to understand something, when his salary depends upon his not understanding it,&quot; with a twist:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;If a miner was willing to go to work every day and risk their &lt;i&gt;own&lt;/i&gt; life and health, why would they stop just because of a risk to the Earth or to someone else's health, maybe halfway around the world? That wasn't callous; it was reality. There weren't any other jobs, and they had to feed their family. What did anyone expect them to do? &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a fair question and shows not necessarily why denial is so entrenched but rather how difficult the problem truly is. After all, the coal miner he talked to mostly accepted the reality of climate change; he just refused to give up his job. McIntyre later notes a distinction between &lt;i&gt;beliefs&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;values&lt;/i&gt;; the question is, &quot;How do you convince someone to &lt;i&gt;care about&lt;/i&gt; something or someone that they previously did not care about?&quot; And remember: identity influences both your beliefs and your values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McIntyre spends a long time seemingly desperate to find liberal science denial and finally hits on GMO's. Presumably after his education from the flat-earthers and sources in the literature, he describes long, friendly discussions on GMO's with his pseudonymous friend Ted. Ted prefers to &quot;trust in nature,&quot; whereas McIntyre prefers to &quot;trust in reason.&quot; Ted is not unreasonably concerned with unforeseen consequences such as mongooses in Hawaii (not to mention the more well-known rabbits in Australia). Unfortunately, Ted is also prepared to write off countless third-world children by denying them a GMO known as &lt;i&gt;golden rice&lt;/i&gt;, partly because it is a GMO but also partly because the earth is on the road to overpopulation. I do not mean to be catty, but you can tell that Ted's job does not depend on planting GMO's.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last chapter concerns largely the coronavirus pandemic. The book came out during the height of the pandemic, but it was not as dated as you might have expected. In particular he notes that identity has divided people into, for example, maskers and anti-maskers (as well as vaxxers and anti-vaxxers) – and sure enough maskers and anti-maskers broke down largely along party lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the book is well and clearly written, with very few errors (such as effected for affected and quorum for, I think, plurality). I thought, though, that it is somewhat overlong in places, most particularly the Maldives, the conversations, and the text leading up to liberal science denial. And from our Consistency Department, &lt;i&gt;on a single page&lt;/i&gt;, we find: 2 degree Celsius goal, 1.5 degree C increase, 1.5 Celsius target. I think I have made this complaint before: Where, oh where, are the copy editors?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I more or less accidentally came across a copy of Lee McIntyre's 2021 book, How to Talk to a Science Denier, subtitled Conversations with Flat Earthers, Climate Deniers, and Others Who Defy Reason. Having recently reviewed an earlier book of McIntyre's, The Scientific Attitude, I naturally snapped up How to Talk. I was not entirely disappointed in the book, but The Scientific Attitude, shall we say, was more impressive. How to Talk was like another New York Times Magazine article stretched into a book and must be 30&amp;nbsp;% notes. And speaking of notes, whereas most of the notes were references, occasionally a note presented important material, but who can reference all those notes, even on an E-reader? If the material was important enough to be included in the book, it should have been in the main text, not in a note. Oh well, on to the book:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Newly appointed Chief Ministry Officer of Answers in Genesis is cause for concern</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/newly-appointed-chief-ministry.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Newly appointed Chief Ministry Officer of Answers in Genesis is cause for concern" /><published>2023-06-12T14:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-06-12T14:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/newly-appointed-chief-ministry</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/newly-appointed-chief-ministry.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Braterman_Martyn_Iles.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Martyn Iles&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Source: AiG.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;This is a synopsis of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://3quarksdaily.com/3quarksdaily/2023/06/leading-creationist-organisation-appoints-conspiracy-theorist-to-key-position.html&quot;&gt;fuller version&lt;/a&gt; that has appeared in &lt;/i&gt;3 Quarks Daily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Panda's Thumb readers will be familiar with Answers in Genesis, its position as the most vocal and best funded of Young Earth Creationist organisations (assets in excess of $82 million; owner of the Kentucky Creation Museum and Ark Encounter), its links with the Cornwall Alliance &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/the-nature-of-the-beast-fossil-fuel-corporations-the-cornwall-alliance-and-climate-change-denial/&quot;&gt;and hence with the fossil fuel industry&lt;/a&gt;, and its use of biblical arguments to dismiss concerns about the current environmental crisis. In my own reading of AiG materials, I have detected a progressive repetitiveness and loss of vigour. I have also noticed worrying signs of openness to the suggestion that we are living in the Last Days, with all that that implies for the abdication of long-term responsibilities. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These worries are intensified by AiG’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/ministry-news/core-ministry/special-ministry-announcement-ken-ham/&quot;&gt;appointment last month&lt;/a&gt; of the lawyer Martyn Iles, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theage.com.au/politics/victoria/holy-war-breaks-out-at-the-christian-lobby-20230228-p5co3h.html&quot;&gt;until recently&lt;/a&gt; Managing Director of the Australian Christian Lobby, to the newly created post of Chief Ministry Officer. Ministry is after all AiG’s entire reason for existence, and Iles, a skilful orator, also has a track record of effectiveness in political interventions, and in fundraising. Ken Ham is now 71, and we can expect Iles, 34, to become increasingly important in shaping AiG’s direction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iles is an extreme religious conservative, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/martynlloydiles/posts/635836281247343/&quot;&gt;defines reality itself in religious terms&lt;/a&gt;, argues from Genesis that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7AbzGKYl7vM&amp;amp;list=PLFMoODxYYkmeUKy0B6U0im5PKQ_dNk-Xk&amp;amp;index=6&quot;&gt;God approves of population growth&lt;/a&gt;, preaches that Christians &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=N55MT_WpLI4&quot;&gt;must dismiss the findings of climate change science&lt;/a&gt; as “cultural Marxist rubbish,” because “God’s sustaining providence is crucial to our understanding of this world,” and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QSFiiiZ3q0k&quot;&gt;regards&lt;/a&gt; the World Economic Forum as part of a grand conspiracy bent on suppressing individual liberty. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see Iles at his most frightening in his YouTube video, &lt;i&gt;The Truth of It&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8_SBGoi3hzc&amp;amp;list=PLFMoODxYYkmeUKy0B6U0im5PKQ_dNk-Xk&amp;amp;index=4.&quot;&gt;Climate Totalitarianism&lt;/a&gt; (notice the carefully crafted title of the YouTube series, as well as of this particular item). In this, he uses quotations from Genesis to claim that this planet was created for the benefit of mankind. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It follows that environmentalist policies are misguided. And where do such policies come from? From evolutionary thinking, of course. “I understand why they’re getting it wrong, because they basically believe that human beings arose on this planet quite by chance, and in time proceeded to go on a destructive, and a murderous, and exploitative, and a cancerous rampage, which must now be stopped.” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like a judo player, Iles now uses the very force of the environmental argument as a reason for rejecting it. “If I thought we were here by chance, and we were just one of the gazillions of planets and we were just very fortunate to be in the position that we are in, I would think the future was pretty uncertain, and I’d get pretty nervous.” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, “Genesis is quite clear that what we see in the world around us was substantially put there for human use, and enjoyment, and sustenance, including plants, water, minerals, and animals.” The word minerals is the only reference in the piece to fossil fuels, but its significance will not be lost on his then intended Australian primary audience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the logic of this argument. Restraint in resource use is unbiblical, and therefore uncalled for. Unbelievers have cause for anxiety, but for believers this anxiety is unnecessary, because God. I am forced to conclude that he sincerely believes that we are in the End Times, or, if not, that God will somehow intervene to save us from the foreseeable consequences of our actions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To sum up, an eloquent preacher who is also a skilled political operative is rising to the top in the world’s most significant creationist organisation, while objecting in principle to concerns about what we are doing to the planet, because worrying about the planet is God’s job, not ours, and He will look after it all in His own good time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not good news. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman</name></author><summary type="html">Source: AiG. This is a synopsis of a fuller version that has appeared in 3 Quarks Daily. Panda's Thumb readers will be familiar with Answers in Genesis, its position as the most vocal and best funded of Young Earth Creationist organisations (assets in excess of $82 million; owner of the Kentucky Creation Museum and Ark Encounter), its links with the Cornwall Alliance and hence with the fossil fuel industry, and its use of biblical arguments to dismiss concerns about the current environmental crisis. In my own reading of AiG materials, I have detected a progressive repetitiveness and loss of vigour. I have also noticed worrying signs of openness to the suggestion that we are living in the Last Days, with all that that implies for the abdication of long-term responsibilities. These worries are intensified by AiG’s appointment last month of the lawyer Martyn Iles, until recently Managing Director of the Australian Christian Lobby, to the newly created post of Chief Ministry Officer. Ministry is after all AiG’s entire reason for existence, and Iles, a skilful orator, also has a track record of effectiveness in political interventions, and in fundraising. Ken Ham is now 71, and we can expect Iles, 34, to become increasingly important in shaping AiG’s direction.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ken Ham to be Interviewed by Dinosaur Denier and Moon Landing “Skeptic”</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/dinosaurdebate.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ken Ham to be Interviewed by Dinosaur Denier and Moon Landing “Skeptic”" /><published>2023-06-09T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-06-09T10:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/dinosaurdebate</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/dinosaurdebate.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/StuckeyDinosaur.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;StuckeyDinosaurs video&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Can Ken Ham persuade her that dinosaurs are real?&lt;br /&gt;  Screenshot from YouTube.  Fair use claimed.&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On June 7, 2023, Ken Ham tweeted that he was soon going to appear on Allie Beth Stuckey’s podcast “Relatable.” Ms. Stuckey has appeared  at at least one Answers in Genesis‘s “Answers for Women” conference and will be at one scheduled in 2024. Her description at AiG can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/bios/allie-beth-stuckey/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I was previously unfamiliar with Ms. Stuckey, or her popular podcast, so I decided to look closer and await Ken’s future appearance. I glanced at the titles of the more than 800 YouTube videos of the podcast that were available and watched short bits of several. Whew! What a vapid and reactionary show “Relatable” turned out to be! Almost every Christian Nationalist obsession and talking point of the last few years is covered by the podcast; everything from opposition to vaccination mandates to bizarre claims about Antifa being a major part of the January 6 insurrection, to an obsession with gay and transgender people. She could easily be a Tucker Carlson replacement on Fox News.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of her podcast videos in particular got my attention: Relatable, episode #670, from August 31, 2022, titled “I Don’t Know if Dinosaurs Were Real.” (See &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/kIxU5zG-dwg&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). A major portion of this episode is a discussion of the host’s favorite conspiracy “theories” and an insipid discussion of the existence of aliens with her show’s producer and technical staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While discussing whether or not the moon landings were real at 29 minutes 42 seconds into the episode Ms. Stuckey exclaims “I don’t know. Why haven’t we been back?” Then the conversation drifts into her conspiratorial views on dinosaurs. She blathers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Here’s my conspiracy theory and I’ll just drop this and let y’all discuss what you think this is a theory, okay, I’m just gonna say this - Dinosaurs never existed. Thoughts? Discuss.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a bit later:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Okay, so you’ve got these bones. You’ve got these fossils supposedly and supposedly date back millions of years and then I think it’s a bunch of nerds constructing this fantasy world that they think is awesome. Like, how do you know what the, like, skin of a pterodactyl looked like. How do you know what it sounded like? How do you know those things real? And, like, the different color patterns and all of that? How are you picking that up from bones? Now, some people, I don’t think I would go so far as to say this, but some people say it’s a conspiracy against, like, young earth creationism which says the earth is, like, 6,000 years old and you know obviously God created it that they tried to use that as no, the earth is like billions of years old and, like, we’ve evolved over time yada yada. I don’t know about all that, but if I were to pick like a theory. I’m, like, ugh, I could see dinosaurs not being real; I don’t know. And I don’t know about the Moon. I mean I used to say, oh yeah for sure, but then I started thinking about it. I was, like, I don’t know, maybe there is some credence to that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To their credit, her, and her producers, state they aren’t flat earthers. They then discuss the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/False_memory#Mandela_effect&quot;&gt;Mandela Effect&lt;/a&gt;, with Ms. Stuckey stating that “some people” (identities not given) claim it is evidence for an “alternate universe.” Silly me always thought the concept was merely a demonstration of the weakness of human memory (but what do I know?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without irony, the show then delves into a discussion of whether or not a college education is necessary. Examples are given of professions you can learn by watching YouTube, such as tape editing, freeing one from spending a couple of hundred thousand dollars on a useless college degree (such a waste of money and loans!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 35,500 people have viewed this nonsensical episode on YouTube. Before you laugh too hard, have I mentioned that Ms. Stuckey has a degree from Furman University? She is listed as a notable Furman alumnus on Wikipedia. As a part of their general education requirements, a Furman student must take two natural sciences, math, and formal reasoning classes. She also has testified before the US Congress, and appeared on CSPAN and FOX News. She probably has more influence in the world than you or I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to Ken Ham’s upcoming appearance on Relatable! Ken’s scientific knowledge is “incredible” in the most literal definition of the word. Will he be able to persuade Allie Beth Stuckey that dinosaurs were real (and on the Ark)? What about the Apollo program’s moon landings? Or will she convince him to give up dinosaurs (this would free up space on the Ark to sell more stuff)? Inquiring minds want to know! I shall do my best to report on the upcoming podcast when it becomes available. It is sure to be a true meeting of minds!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Can Ken Ham persuade her that dinosaurs are real? Screenshot from YouTube. Fair use claimed. &amp;nbsp; On June 7, 2023, Ken Ham tweeted that he was soon going to appear on Allie Beth Stuckey’s podcast “Relatable.” Ms. Stuckey has appeared at at least one Answers in Genesis‘s “Answers for Women” conference and will be at one scheduled in 2024. Her description at AiG can be found here. I was previously unfamiliar with Ms. Stuckey, or her popular podcast, so I decided to look closer and await Ken’s future appearance. I glanced at the titles of the more than 800 YouTube videos of the podcast that were available and watched short bits of several. Whew! What a vapid and reactionary show “Relatable” turned out to be! Almost every Christian Nationalist obsession and talking point of the last few years is covered by the podcast; everything from opposition to vaccination mandates to bizarre claims about Antifa being a major part of the January 6 insurrection, to an obsession with gay and transgender people. She could easily be a Tucker Carlson replacement on Fox News. One of her podcast videos in particular got my attention: Relatable, episode #670, from August 31, 2022, titled “I Don’t Know if Dinosaurs Were Real.” (See here). A major portion of this episode is a discussion of the host’s favorite conspiracy “theories” and an insipid discussion of the existence of aliens with her show’s producer and technical staff. While discussing whether or not the moon landings were real at 29 minutes 42 seconds into the episode Ms. Stuckey exclaims “I don’t know. Why haven’t we been back?” Then the conversation drifts into her conspiratorial views on dinosaurs. She blathers: Here’s my conspiracy theory and I’ll just drop this and let y’all discuss what you think this is a theory, okay, I’m just gonna say this - Dinosaurs never existed. Thoughts? Discuss.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Discovery Institute experts misunderstand natural selection, Part 1</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/diexperts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Discovery Institute experts misunderstand natural selection, Part 1" /><published>2023-06-06T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-06-06T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/diexperts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/diexperts.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Polar_bear.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Roaring polar bear&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Polar bear on sea ice north of Svalbard. Photo by Andreas Weith. &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Polar_bear_after_unlucky_hunt_for_a_seal.jpg&quot;&gt;From Wikimedia&lt;/a&gt;,
under&lt;br /&gt;the &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.en&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 4.0 International license&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every so often, the Evolution News site run by the Discovery Institute 
brings in an expert to explain why the adaptations in organisms 
cannot be explained by natural evolutionary processes.  I was about 
to discuss the argument of one of these experts, when another,
even-more-impressive expert showed up.  For this post, I’ll 
discuss the arguments of the first one, the medical oncologist Dr. Stephen Iacoboni.
In the next part, I will consider those of
the particle physicist Dr. Eric Hedin, who 
is also Professor and Chair of the Department of Chemistry, Physics 
and Engineering at Biola University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do not doubt that Dr. Iacoboni is an “award-winning cancer 
researcher”.  But somehow these impressive 
credentials do not carry over into a discussion of natural 
selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Iacoboni has written two articles at Evolution News, 
the first &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2023/04/a-new-look-at-natural-selection/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A New Look at Natural Selection&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on 
April 18, and
the second &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2023/05/natural-selection-subtracts-it-doesnt-add-and-that-matters/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Natural selection subtracts, it doesn’t add – and that matters&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on May 16.  The latter 
is decorated with the dramatic image of a constipated Polar Bear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iacoboni argues that all of the natural world, including 
all aspects of each organism’s environment, are designed, and 
it is this design that causes organisms to have adaptations.
So has the ability of natural selection to increase the adaptive 
information in the genomes of living organisms been decisively 
refuted by his argument?  Let’s see … (but no prize for guessing that my 
answer is going to be “no”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;iacobonis-argument&quot;&gt;Iacoboni’s argument&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Iacoboni’s post (&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2023/05/natural-selection-subtracts-it-doesnt-add-and-that-matters/A&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) brings up examples of adaptations that seem to him to have no 
possible antecedent.  Then he hints at his refutation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There really is no reasonable way to believe that all of those trillions and trillions of modifications occurred randomly and without a designer.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;It has been said many times before but it is certainly worth repeating: Natural selection creates nothing. It only subtracts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that, he mentions his alternative explanation for 
the evolution of adaptations: that all of every 
environment is designed, as everything in the universe 
is designed, and that these environments force the 
organisms’ phenotypes to fit them.  He promises more on 
that in future posts.
Leaving the rest of the universe aside, let’s consider 
the point that evolution “only subtracts”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-evolution-adds-as-well-as-subtracts&quot;&gt;Why evolution adds as well as subtracts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Natural selection typically changes the gene frequencies in a 
population.  Can this “create”?  It can change the genotype 
of typical members of a population.  If 1% of the copies 
at a locus are allele &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt;, and the rest allele &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;, then we 
expect 0.0001 (that is, 1/100 of 1%) of the individuals 
in the population to have genotype &lt;em&gt;AA&lt;/em&gt;, and 0.0198 of the 
individuals to have genotype &lt;em&gt;Aa&lt;/em&gt;.  The rest (98.01%) 
are &lt;em&gt;aa&lt;/em&gt;.  Once natural selection 
has changed the frequency of the &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; alele to bring it from 
1% up to 
99%, it is now the &lt;em&gt;AA&lt;/em&gt; homozygote that makes up most of
the population, with &lt;em&gt;Aa&lt;/em&gt; having risen to near 50% and 
then fallen back to 0.0198. &lt;em&gt;aa&lt;/em&gt; will now be the genotype 
that has a frequency of 0.0001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A typical creationist response is that these frequency changes
don’t matter: “new information” comes into the population 
only by mutation.  That is typical Creationist Information Theory. 
No actual specialist in information theory would take that 
seriously. Information theory calculates information using probabilities, not 
just the fact that both 0s and 1s can occur.  A gambler would 
not take the theory seriously either, if you told them that 
it doesn’t matter whether you win 99% of the time or 
1% of the time, all that matters is that sometimes 
you win.  Though they would suddenly get 
&lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; interested in making a few private bets with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, when a detective is trying to discover 
who killed Professor Fudge in the library of the 
manor house, we will not be very satisfied when the 
detective simply presents us with a list of everyone who 
was in the house at the time.  We want him to subtract all the 
ones who didn’t commit the crime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when the differences in fitness are differences in 
viability (survival probability), don’t the deaths of 
members of the less-fit genotypes simply harm the population, 
without helping it?  If you know anything about population 
biology, you know that almost all populations have an 
excess of offspring.  Their numbers rise until they run 
into shortages of resources, such as food or nesting 
places.  And if natural selection kills off members of 
some genotypes, the population tends to recover, though 
now with a changed genetic composition.  So merely 
subtracting can be effective in changing the genetics 
of the population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;genuinely-new-genotypes&quot;&gt;Genuinely new genotypes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at more than one locus in the genome, we 
can see that natural selection really can result in new 
combinations of alleles.  Suppose that we look at 
two loci, one with alleles &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;, and the other 
with alleles &lt;em&gt;B&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;b&lt;/em&gt;.  If &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; is rare, with 
a frequency of 0.001, and if &lt;em&gt;B&lt;/em&gt; is also rare, with
a frequency of 0.0001, then there may be no genotypes 
in the population that contain both &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;B&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If both are favored by natural selection, as each
rises in gene frequency at its locus, sooner or 
later mating and recombination will bring them 
into the same individual, and into the same 
haploid gamete.  Initially, we had no AB gametes; 
now we have them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With more than two loci, the 
effect is even greater.  When the favored alleles 
at many loci are all rare, it is unlikely that 
they can all be found in one individual.  That 
changes dramatically as they all rise in gene 
frequency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frequencies matter, and natural selection can 
change them.  That can result in bringing together 
new combinations of alleles in the genome.  You’d 
never know that from Iacoboni’s dismissal of 
natural selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-ghost-of-edward-blyth&quot;&gt;The ghost of Edward Blyth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, interestingly enough, Iacoboni &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; 
think that natural selection is a real phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Reducing this argument to more tangible physical terms, it seems that Darwin was unwilling to acknowledge that the fix for conscious selection was already embedded in an environment which had the innate ability to nurture creatures with capabilities suited to it. It is actually very important to be able to extract oxygen out of water if you are going to be a fish or a mollusk or a crustacean. It is actually important to have flippers and not fingers if you are going to be a marine mammal or penguin. It is important to have thick fur and to store fat if you are going to live in the snow. If you want to fly above it all you better have hollow bones and extremely strong pectoral muscles. If you want to burrow below the fray, you better have proper claws for digging. And if you are a pine tree, you need to have antifreeze in your needles if you are rooted beyond certain latitudes or elevations.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Yes, indeed, natural selection is true. But that selection is not accomplished in the oxymoronic fashion of the inanimate acting with purpose. It is instead that the environment itself was designed with purpose so that it had the transcendent ability to nurture the arrival and survival of purpose-driven organisms on our glorious blue planet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A somewhat similar argument was made by Edward Blyth, 
in articles in 1835-1837.  Blyth was an English 
ornithologist who worked 
mostly in India.  Charles Darwin corresponded with him 
and valued his expertise on the birds of India.
Blyth did not argue that natural selection brought 
about evolutionary change, but rather that it forced 
organisms to conform to their archetypes, keeping 
them precisely adapted and not allowing them to change 
away from that.  (It has been suggested that Darwin 
got natural selection from Blyth’s articles, but the 
dates of the discussion of it in Darwin’s notebooks 
disprove this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iacoboni goes farther than Blyth – he sees the environment 
as causing the “survival” of “purpose-driven organisms” but 
their “arrival” as well.  So the environment drives the process, 
and the biological process is “survival” of  better-adapted 
organisms.  But he doesn’t call that “natural selection”. 
Thus he has refuted natural selection while invoking it. 
All natural selection can do is “subtract”, but if the 
organism is not well-adapted to its niche, it gets 
subtracted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iacoboni is a teleologist, who sees the whole universe as 
designed.  To him it is that “telos” that brings about 
the change, and natural selection is just a fancy and 
misleading name for the grubby processes doing the 
dirty work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Polar bear on sea ice north of Svalbard. Photo by Andreas Weith. From Wikimedia, underthe Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 4.0 International license. &amp;nbsp; Every so often, the Evolution News site run by the Discovery Institute brings in an expert to explain why the adaptations in organisms cannot be explained by natural evolutionary processes. I was about to discuss the argument of one of these experts, when another, even-more-impressive expert showed up. For this post, I’ll discuss the arguments of the first one, the medical oncologist Dr. Stephen Iacoboni. In the next part, I will consider those of the particle physicist Dr. Eric Hedin, who is also Professor and Chair of the Department of Chemistry, Physics and Engineering at Biola University. I do not doubt that Dr. Iacoboni is an “award-winning cancer researcher”. But somehow these impressive credentials do not carry over into a discussion of natural selection. Dr. Iacoboni has written two articles at Evolution News, the first A New Look at Natural Selection on April 18, and the second Natural selection subtracts, it doesn’t add – and that matters on May 16. The latter is decorated with the dramatic image of a constipated Polar Bear. Iacoboni argues that all of the natural world, including all aspects of each organism’s environment, are designed, and it is this design that causes organisms to have adaptations. So has the ability of natural selection to increase the adaptive information in the genomes of living organisms been decisively refuted by his argument? Let’s see … (but no prize for guessing that my answer is going to be “no”).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ginkgo biloba</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/ginkgo-biloba.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ginkgo biloba" /><published>2023-06-05T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-06-05T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/ginkgo-biloba</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/ginkgo-biloba.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/P1010385_Ginkgo_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ginkgo leaves&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ginkgo_biloba&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Ginkgo biloba&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; ginkgo tree, along Boulder Creek, Boulder, Colorado, June, 2023. An ancient tree, supposedly very similar to its 170 million-year-old ancestors. The tree and its wood are very resistant to insects and diseases, and I remember hearing that it had outlived its enemies, which seems incorrect to me. I came across this specimen while strolling along the Creek near the Boulder Public Library. Though I lived for many years more or less across the street from some ginkgo trees, I have to confess that I never noticed that the leaves grow in bundles like pine needles; the Wikipedia article tentatively classifies them in the division Pinophyta. The leaves themselves show veins, which are somewhat hard to see in this picture, that radiate outward like flattened pine needles.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Ginkgo biloba &amp;ndash; ginkgo tree, along Boulder Creek, Boulder, Colorado, June, 2023. An ancient tree, supposedly very similar to its 170 million-year-old ancestors. The tree and its wood are very resistant to insects and diseases, and I remember hearing that it had outlived its enemies, which seems incorrect to me. I came across this specimen while strolling along the Creek near the Boulder Public Library. Though I lived for many years more or less across the street from some ginkgo trees, I have to confess that I never noticed that the leaves grow in bundles like pine needles; the Wikipedia article tentatively classifies them in the division Pinophyta. The leaves themselves show veins, which are somewhat hard to see in this picture, that radiate outward like flattened pine needles.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fun with IRS Form 990</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/fun-with-irs-form.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fun with IRS Form 990" /><published>2023-06-04T09:45:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-06-04T09:45:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/fun-with-irs-form</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/fun-with-irs-form.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Form_990_Thumbnail.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Form 990 inset&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to learn about the activities of a non-profit organization is to obtain copies of their &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Form_990&quot;&gt;IRS Form 990&lt;/a&gt;. As a critic of young earth creationism in Kentucky, I am always anxious to view the latest Form 990 of Answers in Genesis (AIG), Ark Encounter, and Twelve Stones Christian Academy. These organizations are non-profits that promote creationism in Kentucky and are part of Ken Ham’s Answers in Genesis empire. One can also glean other information from these forms about for-profit shell companies under the AIG umbrella and businesses associated with AIG. Usually, information from IRS Form 990’s is more than a year old and available for free (you need to create an account) from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.guidestar.org/&quot;&gt;Guidestar&lt;/a&gt;, as well as other organizations. For the last year, the most recent Form 990 for AIG, et al. at Guidestar were for the year ending June 2020. Thus, I looked at the forms at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.propublica.org/&quot;&gt;Propublica&lt;/a&gt;. The latest Form 990’s available at Propublica are for the fiscal year ending in June 2021 and were submitted to the IRS in May, 2022. Links to all three forms are given at the end of this document, in case you want to go look for yourself. Presumably, forms concerning the year ending June, 2022 have been submitted this year, but may not be available for quite some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are interesting, frightening, sad, and sometimes humorous items in these forms describing Answers in Genesis’s (and AIG shell companies’) metastasis in Kentucky. Understanding the meaning of the Form 990’s by AIG, Crosswater Canyon, and Twelve Stones Christian Academy is complicated by the odd arrangement of non-profit and for-profit shell companies under the umbrella of Answers in Genesis. I should point out that I am neither a lawyer or an accountant. Someone familiar with non-profit tax law is needed to review these documents in detail (if you are a CPA or otherwise qualified, please volunteer!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; AIG Form 990 for the fiscal year ending 6/21 &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Employees – 1016 (plus 120 volunteers). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assets – almost $82 million, up from ~$67 million for the previous year. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creation Museum brought in $8,127,557.00 (expenses $7,046,399.00), for a $1,081,158.00 profit. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Books, DVDs, CDs, etc. brought in $5,775,844.00 (expenses $4,578,378.00), resulting in a $1,197,466.00 profit. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Answers Magazine brought in $705,839.00 (expenses $806,809.00), for a $100,970.00 loss. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Ark management fees (charged to for-profit Ark Encounter, which AIG owns) brought in $6,240,000 (expenses $10,952,928.00), resulting in a $4,712,928.00 loss. This is interesting and confusing since non-profit Crosswater Canyon oversees for-profit Ark Encounter.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ken Ham’s salary for the period covered by this Form 990 was $230,911.00 plus $60,065.00 in other compensation from AIG and related organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9 other AIG employees earned more than $100K during the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ken has a lot of relatives on the AIG payroll! See:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;David (Bodie) Hodge, Ken Ham’s son-in-law, $70,430.00. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joseph Johnson, Ken Ham’s son-in-law, $50,305.00. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Renee Hodge, Ken Ham’s daughter, $64,957.00. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jeremy Ham, Ken Ham’s son, $69,331.00. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kristel Ham, Ken Ham’s daughter, $42,212.00&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schedule R has some interesting information concerning a business named “Answers Collective.” Earlier this year I found that in late 2022 that “Answers Collective, Inc.” had bought part ownership in a 1995 Cessna 560 Jet. Apparently, Answers Collective is considered an Unrelated Business that pays Income Tax (UBIT). Answers Collective controls something called “Parking Lot Ventures” located at 1 Ark Encounter Drive. It is probable that the $10/vehicle parking at the Ark is going to this side company and thus funds AIG’s corporate jet. The creationists may not have a good grasp of science, but I find this creative funding to own a corporate jet as nothing less than brilliant!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Crosswater Canyon Form 990 for the fiscal year ending 6-21 &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Form 990, Crosswater Canyon (the non-profit portion of Ark Encounter) has 810 employees and 120 volunteers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Net assets for the Ark total more than $143 million, but they had nearly $85 million in liabilities. Thus, the Ark has total assets in excess of $58 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the Ark is claimed to be losing money. In Form, Section 3, Revenue from Ark ticket sales totals $29,538,653.00, while expenses total $30,477,389.00, for a loss of $938,736.00. Revenue from sales at the Ark Encounter totaled $7,145,017.00, while expenses totaled $8,388,526.00, for a loss of $1,243,509.00. Bafflingly, the Ark has lost a total of $2,182,245.00 during the period the Form 990 applies to. This loss could be ascribed to low attendance during Covid, but one wonders where the money could have gone. The Ark apparently makes most of its money via gifts from donors, some of whom appear have deep pockets. Sadly, this means that no matter how few people buy Ark tickets, the Ark will never go out of business because of these donations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the balance sheet listing Crosswater Canyon’s assets, the value of land, buildings, and equipment totals $115,925,334.00. This is interesting because the Grant County PVA (Property Value Administrator) assesses the Ark Park as worth (and taxed for) only a value of $48 million. Thus, Williamstown and Grant County are receiving a low amount of tax revenue from the Ark to support local schools and other government endeavors. Yet, Crosswater Canyon is telling the IRS, and possibly entities lending them money, that the Ark and associated properties are worth at least twice as much as the PVA assesses and taxes them for. I reported on this discrepancy on The Panda’s Thumb &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/02/grant-county-loses.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also interesting is that Crosswater Canyon lists mortgages on the property totaling $47,458,306.00. I am not sure what this mortgage is for, so we can only speculate. In 2014 when the City of Willliamstown issued the $62 million in bonds for the Ark project to proceed, someone bought enough bonds at the end for the project to continue. Did Crosswater Canyon buy these bonds by mortgaging the property they already owned so the project could continue? How much are Ark bonds issued by Williamstown worth now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Twelve Stones Christian Academy (now renamed Answers Academy) Form 990 for the fiscal year ending 6/21. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Form 990 was submitted, AIG’s elementary to junior high school was known as Twelve Stones Christian Academy and had 46 students. The school was located in a building adjacent to a church in Erlanger, Kentucky. Interestingly, the school lost money to the tune of $315,082.00 during the year ending in June, 2021. The Form 990 describes the school’s mission as, “With academic excellence, the Academy partners with Christian parents in their roles of educating and disciplining their children. We stand on the authority of God’s Word in all areas, and train students to think biblically and critically in all subjects.” Apparently, the school features many, many field trips to the Creation Museum and the Ark Encounter (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersacademy.org/student-life&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It is unclear who teaches the classes; the Form 990 in question surprisingly lists zero (0) employees. However, the following people are listed as officers and directors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;John Pinkston, President, no salary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Renee Hodge (Ken Ham’s daughter), Treasurer, $65,295.00.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr. Georgia Purdom, Board Member, $109,622.00 (presumably this includes pay for other AIG activities). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John Pence, Secretary, $125,088.00 (presumably this includes pay for other AIG activities. He is AIG’s attorney). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr. Jennifer Rivera, Board Member, $73,974.00 (presumably this includes pay for other AIG activities).
&lt;li&gt;Eric Thomason, Board Member, no salary. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ken Ham, Board Member, $290,976.00 (presumably this includes pay for other AIG activities).&lt;/li&gt;&amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;

The school, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersacademy.org/curriculum&quot;&gt;their website&lt;/a&gt;, is, as exected, extremely conservative and fundamentalist in nature and emphasizes young earth creationist dogma. They state:


&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The academic program at Answers Academy is grounded in Proverbs 9:10, “The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom.” All subjects must start with the Bible as God is the author of all creation. It is the role of every Christian educator to shape the worldview of their students using the Bible as the authoritative guide. The teachers at Answers Academy teach all subjects from a biblical-worldview perspective and challenge students to think critically and biblically about every academic subject. The curriculum for Answers Academy is carefully chosen by our curriculum committee. They ensure that it is grounded in Scripture, apologetically sound, and academically rigorous so that it will equip the students with skills and knowledge to defend their faith, become good stewards of God’s earth, and be bold witnesses for Christ. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Many of the textbooks used at Answers Academy are published by BJU [Bob Jones University] Press. We appreciate their biblical worldview stance and their consistency to look at each subject based on Creation, the Fall, and Redemption. In other words, these textbooks repeatedly look at subject material like literature, science, history, and so forth from a biblical viewpoint especially in light of the Creation Mandate, the Fall, and Redemption. This is especially important regarding science and history where the world is constantly attacking children with the false humanistic history of big bang, millions of years, and evolution. Answers Academy also supplements with Answers in Genesis and Master Books material which take a strong stance on the authority of Scripture. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As kids learn the true history of what happened according to God's Word, they are better able to spot these common false claims and discern why they are wrong. These textbooks will also give students a chance to understand the nature of God and to have a deeper understanding of the world God designed for us that has been sadly marred by sin. …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Science&lt;/strong&gt; only works because God is upholding all things in a particular way and promises to continue to do so as long as the earth endures (e.g., Genesis 8:22). With God’s Word we can understand geology in light of the Flood, astronomy in light of Genesis 1, biology in light of God’s created kinds, etc. We also use science and the Bible to help us understand evidence. Everyone has the same evidence...the same earth, rocks, stars, DNA, etc., but the difference is the interpretation of that evidence. There are only 2 choices: God or man. A biblical worldview is where you start with God and His Word to understand the evidence (i.e. the worldwide Flood caused most fossils and rock layers). If you reject God, then you are relying on man’s fallible ideas and using that as your basis for looking at the evidence which is trying to explain the world without God - this is also called the religion of humanism which is sadly taught in the public school system today. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;History&lt;/strong&gt; starts in Genesis 1:1, “In the beginning God created the heavens and the earth.” Therefore, there is no such thing as “prehistoric”! The Bible’s record of history is inerrantly revealed to us by a perfect God. It is the absolute truth and when the world’s rewritten history deviates from God’s Word, then it is that alleged history that is in error. We oppose the false views of history that is being articulated in our culture. False history like molecules-to-man evolution, millions of years (geological evolution), evolved from ape-like creatures in an “out-of-Africa” model, and big bang are challenged with the truth of history that uses God’s Word as the foundation. As kids learn the true history of what happened according to God's Word, they are better able to spot these common false claims and discern why they are wrong. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;English&lt;/strong&gt; – where do languages come from? Language was created from God to communicate with Him and each other, but now we have a diversity of languages because of what happened at the Tower of Babel. Language families left Babel with various family groups being put to written script, whether pictorial, alphabetic, etc. Then languages continue to change—adding words, losing words, changing definitions, changing grammar, tonal adjustments, etc., to arrive at the various languages we have today (about 7,000 of them). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, the school emphasizes Answers in Genesis’s dogma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, why is AIG supporting the small school that is losing money? One possible explanation is that they hope to overcome financial losses with state money. There have been many political attempts in Kentucky’s legislature to partially fund non-public schools with public money. So far, attempts to fund private schools with Kentucky government money have been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.courier-journal.com/story/news/education/education/2022/12/15/kentucky-supreme-court-rules-on-school-choice-program/69641057007/&quot;&gt;declared unconstitutional&lt;/a&gt; with respect to Kentucky’s Constitution by the Kentucky Supreme Court. AIG would be thrilled and financially boosted if their private school were to suddenly be eligible for public funding. Thus, they are continuing to support the school with the future prospect of making money and also having a number of well-indoctrinated young followers. Considering the continued ultra-conservative drift of Kentucky politics, the odds are increasing that someday public education money could be given to entities such as Twelve Stones. This is borne out by the announcement in February, 2023 that &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2023/02/25/exciting-update-offices-move-incredible-building/&quot;&gt;AIG has bought Toyota USA’s former headquarters&lt;/a&gt; in northern Kentucky for more than $31 million. AIG has announced that a substantial portion of this new piece of property will house an expanded Twelve Stones Christian Academy (now renamed &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersacademy.org/&quot;&gt;Answers Academy &lt;/a&gt;. The new Answers Academy school will be expanded to include grades K-12 and have first class facilities. Amusingly, AIG recently advertised for a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/04/answers-in-Genesis-seeks.html&quot;&gt;“science” teacher&lt;/a&gt; for Answers Academy; you may find the science teacher’s job description &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.paycomonline.net/v4/ats/web.php/jobs/ViewJobDetails?clientkey=36BAEBCF961EB253FD190A922A7D98D6&amp;amp;job=77715&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. In any case, Answers Academy is scheduled to open for classes this fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers in Genesis continues to expand in Kentucky, apparently with considerable financial backing from unknown sources. No matter how far below projections attendance at the Ark may be, AIG will continue to spread misinformation about science for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix&lt;/strong&gt;. IRS Forms 990 of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://projects.propublica.org/nonprofits/organizations/330596423/202241339349307294/full&quot;&gt;Answers in Genesis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://projects.propublica.org/nonprofits/organizations/274026852/202221339349306477/full&quot;&gt;Crosswater Canyon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://irs-efile-renderer.instrumentl.com/render?object_id=202241369349302589&quot;&gt;Twelve Stones Christian Academy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Posted by Matt Young, who will be principal moderator of the comment thread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">One way to learn about the activities of a non-profit organization is to obtain copies of their IRS Form 990. As a critic of young earth creationism in Kentucky, I am always anxious to view the latest Form 990 of Answers in Genesis (AIG), Ark Encounter, and Twelve Stones Christian Academy. These organizations are non-profits that promote creationism in Kentucky and are part of Ken Ham’s Answers in Genesis empire. One can also glean other information from these forms about for-profit shell companies under the AIG umbrella and businesses associated with AIG. Usually, information from IRS Form 990’s is more than a year old and available for free (you need to create an account) from Guidestar, as well as other organizations. For the last year, the most recent Form 990 for AIG, et al. at Guidestar were for the year ending June 2020. Thus, I looked at the forms at Propublica. The latest Form 990’s available at Propublica are for the fiscal year ending in June 2021 and were submitted to the IRS in May, 2022. Links to all three forms are given at the end of this document, in case you want to go look for yourself. Presumably, forms concerning the year ending June, 2022 have been submitted this year, but may not be available for quite some time. There are interesting, frightening, sad, and sometimes humorous items in these forms describing Answers in Genesis’s (and AIG shell companies’) metastasis in Kentucky. Understanding the meaning of the Form 990’s by AIG, Crosswater Canyon, and Twelve Stones Christian Academy is complicated by the odd arrangement of non-profit and for-profit shell companies under the umbrella of Answers in Genesis. I should point out that I am neither a lawyer or an accountant. Someone familiar with non-profit tax law is needed to review these documents in detail (if you are a CPA or otherwise qualified, please volunteer!).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dan Phelps interviewed on YouTube</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/dan-phelps-interviewed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dan Phelps interviewed on YouTube" /><published>2023-06-03T20:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-06-03T20:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/dan-phelps-interviewed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/dan-phelps-interviewed.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Phelps_YouTube_Interview_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot; Dan Phelps with David Murray&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Dan Phelps interviewed on YouTube yesterday. The background is taken from the movie &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2019/04/reviews-of-documentary.html&quot;&gt;We Believe in Dinosaurs&lt;/a&gt;, to which Mr. Phelps contributed and which we covered extensively here on PT.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan Phelps was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=y1d-DG0N1LU&quot;&gt; interviewed at length&lt;/a&gt; about his opposition to the Ark Park and other Answers in Genesis shenanigans, on a program called Captive Desk by David Murray. The interview lasted nearly an hour and a half, and covered geology, paleontology, and pseudoscience, in addition to AIG. As Mr. Murray details in his introduction, Mr. Phelps has had a remarkably productive career, aside from his day job. Watch the interview!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Dan Phelps interviewed on YouTube yesterday. The background is taken from the movie We Believe in Dinosaurs, to which Mr. Phelps contributed and which we covered extensively here on PT. Dan Phelps was interviewed at length about his opposition to the Ark Park and other Answers in Genesis shenanigans, on a program called Captive Desk by David Murray. The interview lasted nearly an hour and a half, and covered geology, paleontology, and pseudoscience, in addition to AIG. As Mr. Murray details in his introduction, Mr. Phelps has had a remarkably productive career, aside from his day job. Watch the interview!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest XIV coming up</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/05/photography_contest_xiv_coming.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest XIV coming up" /><published>2023-05-26T08:10:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-05-26T08:10:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/05/photography_contest_xiv_coming</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/05/photography_contest_xiv_coming.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/DSC05465_Box_Camera_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Box camera&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;BOX SCOUT/No. 2/&lt;a href=&quot;http://camera-wiki.org/wiki/Seneca&quot;&gt; SENECA CAMERA MANUFACTURING COMPANY&lt;/a&gt;/Rochester New York USA. The camera has what looks like a landscape lens and precisely 2 shutter speeds: 1/30&amp;nbsp;s or thereabouts, and time. It uses Kodak 120 roll film with a 2-1/4 by 3-1/4&amp;nbsp;in format. Roll film, for the uninitiated, is a layer of film and a layer of paper wrapped around a cylinder of wood or metal. The layer of paper is still in the camera and advises the user to use Kodak Velox paper &quot;for quality.&quot; According to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etsy.com/listing/787758589/vintage-camera-seneca-scout-2a-box&quot;&gt; not necessarily reliable source&lt;/a&gt;, model 2A was manufactured between 1913 and 1920. The 2A, to my surprise, had an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pacificrimcamera.com/rl/02396/02396.pdf&quot;&gt;achromatic lens&lt;/a&gt;. I do not know when the model 2 was manufactured.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I had major surgery in early July and elected not to run the XIII-th photography contest. I think we can manage one this year. It will begin Monday, June 19, at noon Mountain Daylight Time. I will post the rules then, but they will be substantially the same as &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/06/photography-contest-xiii.html&quot;&gt;two years ago&lt;/a&gt;, which means we will accept entries until July 5. We will limit you to 3 photos per person, and I think we will have no special themes or categories, unless I get an inspiration in the next couple of weeks. We will display the finalists and open voting for the winner on July 10, close voting on July 21, and announce the winner on July 24. More on June 19!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">BOX SCOUT/No. 2/ SENECA CAMERA MANUFACTURING COMPANY/Rochester New York USA. The camera has what looks like a landscape lens and precisely 2 shutter speeds: 1/30&amp;nbsp;s or thereabouts, and time. It uses Kodak 120 roll film with a 2-1/4 by 3-1/4&amp;nbsp;in format. Roll film, for the uninitiated, is a layer of film and a layer of paper wrapped around a cylinder of wood or metal. The layer of paper is still in the camera and advises the user to use Kodak Velox paper &quot;for quality.&quot; According to a not necessarily reliable source, model 2A was manufactured between 1913 and 1920. The 2A, to my surprise, had an achromatic lens. I do not know when the model 2 was manufactured. Last year, I had major surgery in early July and elected not to run the XIII-th photography contest. I think we can manage one this year. It will begin Monday, June 19, at noon Mountain Daylight Time. I will post the rules then, but they will be substantially the same as two years ago, which means we will accept entries until July 5. We will limit you to 3 photos per person, and I think we will have no special themes or categories, unless I get an inspiration in the next couple of weeks. We will display the finalists and open voting for the winner on July 10, close voting on July 21, and announce the winner on July 24. More on June 19!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Streptopelia decaocto</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/05/Streptopelia-decaocto.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Streptopelia decaocto" /><published>2023-05-22T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-05-22T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/05/Streptopelia-decaocto</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/05/Streptopelia-decaocto.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/P1010189_Doves_600_2.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Eurasian collared dove&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Eurasian_Collared-Dove/overview&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Streptopelia decaocto&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Eurasian collared dove, Elmer's Two-Mile Creek, Boulder, Colorado, 27 April 2023. It seemed kind of late in the season, but these doves were acting kind of, well, lovey-dovey, so I pruriently snapped their picture. The collared doves have colonized the city, and (as I have noted earlier) I no longer see nor hear mourning doves, &lt;i&gt;Zenaida macroura&lt;/i&gt;, within the city limits.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Streptopelia decaocto &amp;ndash; Eurasian collared dove, Elmer's Two-Mile Creek, Boulder, Colorado, 27 April 2023. It seemed kind of late in the season, but these doves were acting kind of, well, lovey-dovey, so I pruriently snapped their picture. The collared doves have colonized the city, and (as I have noted earlier) I no longer see nor hear mourning doves, Zenaida macroura, within the city limits.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creationist Paper on Heat Problems Associated with Genesis Flood</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/05/creationist-paper-heat-problems.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creationist Paper on Heat Problems Associated with Genesis Flood" /><published>2023-05-18T08:02:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-05-18T08:02:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/05/creationist-paper-heat-problems</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/05/creationist-paper-heat-problems.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Phelps_Flood_Stamp_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Noah's Ark&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;And the Ark floated on the face of the waters. &lt;small&gt;Wikimedia Commons, detail from Stamp of Israel &amp;ndash; Festivals 5730, 13 August 1969, http://israelphilately.org.il/he/catalog/stamps/871, Asher Kalderon and Davis Grebu for Israel Post. Public domain.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers in Genesis (AiG) published a &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersresearchjournal.org/noahs-flood/heat-problems-flood-models-4/&quot;&gt;new paper&lt;/a&gt; yesterday in their &lt;i&gt;Answers Research Journal&lt;/i&gt; discussing how life on earth survived the massive amount of heat produced in volcanic eruptions and intrusions during “The Flood.” The paper was authored by Dr. &lt;a href=&quot;https://creation.com/bill-worraker&quot;&gt;William Worraker&lt;/a&gt;, a British creationist with a doctorate in mathematics and a BS in physics. To their credit, the creationists realize having the Paleozoic-to-Recent igneous rock record go from molten to crystallizing in the last few thousand years presents a big problem for Young Earth Creationism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual for &lt;i&gt;Answers Research Journal&lt;/i&gt;, it is difficult to determine who the paper is aimed at or how it was peer reviewed by any competent scientist in the fields the paper discusses. Lots of technical articles from real journals and several mathematical appendices are cited, but then there is a section of definitions taken from &lt;i&gt;Encyclopedia Britannica&lt;/i&gt; that include basic information that an undergraduate chemistry student should be aware of, as well as descriptions of minerals at an undergraduate mineralogy class level. This paper doesn’t appear to be written with the intent of convincing a geophysicist or geoscientist studying tectonics. In reality, it seems written to impress non-scientists, including potential donors to AiG, by being “sciencey.” Much of what is put out by AiG, the Institute for Creation Research, and other creationists that looks technical is really just a parody of science, meant to impress their followers/donors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The abstract mentions supernatural explanations, but most of the paper doesn’t do so until the concluding portion. After paragraphs of rather questionable reasoning, special pleading, attempts at physics, and creation “science,” the author finally comes clean with this total &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2017/02/on-bullshit.html&quot;&gt;bullshit&lt;/a&gt; by claiming the Bible says it and God did it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;However, it is important to appreciate that our inability to identify an acknowledged mechanism for removing the excess heat deposited during and after the Flood, an issue first identified over 35 years ago (Baumgardner 1986), is only a problem in the sense that it represents the limited nature of our human understanding. In a biblical context there is no fundamental problem because God purposely brought about the Flood (Genesis 6:17) as a judgment on the wicked human race of Noah’s day and covenanted with Noah to preserve human and animal life through the cataclysm (Genesis 6:18). He sovereignly accomplished both objectives, implying that environmental temperatures could not have risen beyond biological endurance limits. The only real problem is our current lack of understanding of how this was accomplished; the Flood account in Genesis 6–9 does not tell us directly whether supernatural processes were involved, though it seems very likely that they were. The same basic issue arises in connection with the topics to be covered in Parts 5 (heat due to Accelerated Nuclear Decay) and 6 (heat due to bombardments from space) of this series, and will be considered at greater length in Part 7.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author could have saved a great deal of time if he had just said a miracle occurred rather than subjecting the reader to all of the arm waving and special pleading.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">And the Ark floated on the face of the waters. Wikimedia Commons, detail from Stamp of Israel &amp;ndash; Festivals 5730, 13 August 1969, http://israelphilately.org.il/he/catalog/stamps/871, Asher Kalderon and Davis Grebu for Israel Post. Public domain. Answers in Genesis (AiG) published a new paper yesterday in their Answers Research Journal discussing how life on earth survived the massive amount of heat produced in volcanic eruptions and intrusions during “The Flood.” The paper was authored by Dr. William Worraker, a British creationist with a doctorate in mathematics and a BS in physics. To their credit, the creationists realize having the Paleozoic-to-Recent igneous rock record go from molten to crystallizing in the last few thousand years presents a big problem for Young Earth Creationism. As usual for Answers Research Journal, it is difficult to determine who the paper is aimed at or how it was peer reviewed by any competent scientist in the fields the paper discusses. Lots of technical articles from real journals and several mathematical appendices are cited, but then there is a section of definitions taken from Encyclopedia Britannica that include basic information that an undergraduate chemistry student should be aware of, as well as descriptions of minerals at an undergraduate mineralogy class level. This paper doesn’t appear to be written with the intent of convincing a geophysicist or geoscientist studying tectonics. In reality, it seems written to impress non-scientists, including potential donors to AiG, by being “sciencey.” Much of what is put out by AiG, the Institute for Creation Research, and other creationists that looks technical is really just a parody of science, meant to impress their followers/donors. The abstract mentions supernatural explanations, but most of the paper doesn’t do so until the concluding portion. After paragraphs of rather questionable reasoning, special pleading, attempts at physics, and creation “science,” the author finally comes clean with this total bullshit by claiming the Bible says it and God did it: However, it is important to appreciate that our inability to identify an acknowledged mechanism for removing the excess heat deposited during and after the Flood, an issue first identified over 35 years ago (Baumgardner 1986), is only a problem in the sense that it represents the limited nature of our human understanding. In a biblical context there is no fundamental problem because God purposely brought about the Flood (Genesis 6:17) as a judgment on the wicked human race of Noah’s day and covenanted with Noah to preserve human and animal life through the cataclysm (Genesis 6:18). He sovereignly accomplished both objectives, implying that environmental temperatures could not have risen beyond biological endurance limits. The only real problem is our current lack of understanding of how this was accomplished; the Flood account in Genesis 6–9 does not tell us directly whether supernatural processes were involved, though it seems very likely that they were. The same basic issue arises in connection with the topics to be covered in Parts 5 (heat due to Accelerated Nuclear Decay) and 6 (heat due to bombardments from space) of this series, and will be considered at greater length in Part 7. The author could have saved a great deal of time if he had just said a miracle occurred rather than subjecting the reader to all of the arm waving and special pleading.</summary></entry></feed>