<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-06-06T01:31:38-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Ken Ham may be in trouble for hateful Twitter posts</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/ken-ham-may-be.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ken Ham may be in trouble for hateful Twitter posts" /><published>2022-05-31T16:12:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-31T16:12:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/ken-ham-may-be</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/ken-ham-may-be.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Ham_Disney_Tweet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tweet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mobile.twitter.com/aigkenham/status/1530493331918159872?cxt=HHwWgICwwfLks70qAAAA&quot;&gt;Twitter post that got Ken Ham in trouble with the French and Germans&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at Ken Ham’s daily Twitter posts like I do, you will see that beyond his usual anti-science spiel and promotion of his “Museum” and Ark Park, he is obsessed with complaining about Disney while simultaneously comparing his inane tourist sites to Disney. He also makes lots of posts about LGBTQ issues, especially those concerning transsexuals. Transsexuals are one of Ken’s big bugaboos and his posts indicate he thinks about them often. In any case, a Facebook post by Ken (below the fold) may indicate he is in trouble on Twitter (especially in France and Germany).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that his account says he and Answers in Genesis are on various right-wing sites including &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parler&quot;&gt;Parler&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MeWe&quot;&gt;MeWe&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gettr&quot;&gt;Gettr&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gab_(social_network)&quot;&gt;Gab&lt;/a&gt;. Considering Ham and AiG’s claims to be anti-racist, one of the few things praiseworthy about him and his AiG ministry, this association with these right-wing social media is remarkable. Each of these sites caters to vile, extremist hate groups that have limited access to other social media. Facebook has reprehensible content, but at least Facebook claims to attempt to keep the worst off. Twitter is almost as bad, but seems slightly more responsible in removing the worst posts, at least for the time being. These other sites are replete with racism, Q’Anon, anti-Semitism, anti-vaxx, and numerous other dumbfery. See the Wikipedia links above for further information about these far-right social media organizations Ham and AiG participate in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three tweets below the fold; it appears that Germany did not find the tweet actionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/IMG_9946_Ham_Twitter_1.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Tweet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/IMG_9949_Ham_Twitter_2.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Tweet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/IMG_9950_Ham_Twitter_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tweet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Dan Phelps is a professional geologist and an inveterate Ham watcher. This article is derived with permission from an e-mail he circulated today. Matt Young will be the principal moderator of this post.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Twitter post that got Ken Ham in trouble with the French and Germans. If you look at Ken Ham’s daily Twitter posts like I do, you will see that beyond his usual anti-science spiel and promotion of his “Museum” and Ark Park, he is obsessed with complaining about Disney while simultaneously comparing his inane tourist sites to Disney. He also makes lots of posts about LGBTQ issues, especially those concerning transsexuals. Transsexuals are one of Ken’s big bugaboos and his posts indicate he thinks about them often. In any case, a Facebook post by Ken (below the fold) may indicate he is in trouble on Twitter (especially in France and Germany). Note that his account says he and Answers in Genesis are on various right-wing sites including Parler, MeWe, Gettr, and Gab. Considering Ham and AiG’s claims to be anti-racist, one of the few things praiseworthy about him and his AiG ministry, this association with these right-wing social media is remarkable. Each of these sites caters to vile, extremist hate groups that have limited access to other social media. Facebook has reprehensible content, but at least Facebook claims to attempt to keep the worst off. Twitter is almost as bad, but seems slightly more responsible in removing the worst posts, at least for the time being. These other sites are replete with racism, Q’Anon, anti-Semitism, anti-vaxx, and numerous other dumbfery. See the Wikipedia links above for further information about these far-right social media organizations Ham and AiG participate in. Three tweets below the fold; it appears that Germany did not find the tweet actionable.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Discovery Institute Claims That Science Fueled the Buffalo Shooting</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/discovery-institute-claims.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Discovery Institute Claims That Science Fueled the Buffalo Shooting" /><published>2022-05-30T10:03:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-30T10:03:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/discovery-institute-claims</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/discovery-institute-claims.html">&lt;p&gt;This article is about the mass shooting that took place at the Tops Friendly Market in Buffalo, New York, on May 14, 2022 in which 10 people lost their lives.  While I am going to write about issues peripherally related to this tragedy, rather than on the shooting itself, this is by no means intended to overlook the loss and suffering that the loved ones of the victims and, indeed, the Buffalo community as whole are continuing to deal with at this moment.  I am sure the rest of the Panda’s Thumb team will join me in offering my thoughts and support to the people of Buffalo, as well as those affected by the more recent shooting in Uvalde, Texas, as they attempt to go forward with their lives and repair their shattered communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The horror of the Buffalo shooting was compounded by the fact that it was clearly racially motivated, with the shooter leaving a manifesto in which he expounded at length on the “Great Replacement” conspiracy theory.  This has caused consternation among members of America’s Republican Party and the right wing media with which it is allied.  For some time now, the American Right has been making subtle, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2022/02/28/marjorie-taylor-greene-white-nationalist-conference/&quot;&gt;sometimes not so subtle&lt;/a&gt;, overtures to White Supremacists in order to bring them into their “big tent” as part of their political base.  Nonetheless, it remains a fact that many swing voters will be repelled by associations with such movements.  This likely explains why, immediately after the shooting, the right wing media went into overdrive trying to downplay the killer’s racial motivations and, instead, shift the blame to other less politically inconvenient targets, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://gamerant.com/fox-news-violent-video-games-buffalo-shooting/&quot;&gt;video games&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seattletimes.com/entertainment/tucker-carlson-blames-buffalo-supermarket-shooting-on-biden-mental-illness-ignores-great-replacement-theory-spread-on-fox-news/&quot;&gt;mental illness&lt;/a&gt;.  A question arises:  If the American Right was not courting the support of White Supremacists, then why would it be so important for them to deny the killer’s White Supremacist motivations?  I don’t really have a good answer for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any event, it should come as no surprise that the Discovery Institute is more than willing to lend a helping hand to this effort.  And if it provides them an opportunity to engage in their favorite pastime of Darwin bashing, so much the better.  Which explains the article posted on the Evolution News website May 16, written by the DI’s Senior Fellow, Managing Director and Vice President John G. West and bearing the eye-opening title &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2022/05/how-science-fueled-the-white-supremacist-mass-murderer-in-buffalo-ny/&quot;&gt;How Science Fueled the White Supremacist Mass Murderer in Buffalo, NY.&lt;/a&gt;  While acknowledging the killer’s motivation in White Supremacism and Great Replacement Theory, West goes on to state that this “doesn’t tell us anything about the roots of the shooter’s twisted beliefs. Until we start paying attention to THAT question, we are unlikely to make progress in combatting these kinds of crimes in the future.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reader can probably guess where this is going.  Despite acknowledging the tangled and incoherent mess of ideas the killer drew upon to justify his act, West decides to focus on one aspect of his attempted rationalization (emphasis is West’s):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;(T)he shooter asserts that blacks “are a different subspecies of human.” Why? Because “Whites and Blacks &lt;b&gt;are separated by tens of thousands of years of evolution&lt;/b&gt;, and our genetic material is obviously very different.” (p. 14) Elsewhere he suggests that Europeans and Asians are more recently evolved than blacks (p. 17), which sounds eerily reminiscent of the view of countless racists of the past (including Charles Darwin himself) that blacks are the lowest humans on the evolutionary ladder…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To some degree, the past is coming back to haunt the scientific community. The historical connections between evolutionary biology and racism are undeniable….  To their credit, most supporters of Darwinian evolution largely abandoned their scientific racism after the civil rights era, if not earlier. The problem is that they had little positive to replace it with. Think about it: If humans truly evolved through a blind and accidental process that did not have them in mind, it’s not much of a jump to believe that some human populations must have evolved in ways superior to other human populations. Thus, a tendency toward racism was sort of built-in to evolutionary theory from the get-go.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How ought one respond to such accusations?  One way to &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; respond would be to deny the kernel of truth in West’s article, which is that science, and evolutionary theory in particular, has been used through history to support ideas that we would now consider to be clearly racist, eugenics being but one example.  However, is West justified in laying particular blame on what he calls “Darwinism” for this state of affairs?  I do not believe he is.  If (Tucker Carlson notwithstanding) there now exists a consensus that no significant differences exist in terms of qualities like intelligence or moral worth between people of different ethnicities, this was not the case to nearly the same extent even a few decades ago.  And the idea that people ought to be granted different degrees of rights and privileges based on their ethnic identity, was not one that would be particularly likely to be heard at scientific meetings or conferences.  One would be at least as likely to hear it voiced from the pulpit at a religious gathering, or from the hustings during a political campaign.   That is to say, it would be more accurate to state that science is not immune to corruption by racism, rather than to claim that it holds any particular responsibility for the existence of racism.  Indeed, if one wished to argue that racism was an unavoidable and inherent aspect of religion, this could be done by pointing out how &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/01/arts/from-noah-s-curse-to-slavery-s-rationale.html&quot;&gt;passages from the Old Testament have been used to justify slavery in the US&lt;/a&gt;, as just one example. If such an argument is fallacious, it is surely no more so than the one West tries to make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;West goes on to write “The scientific community’s rejection of scientific racism after the civil rights movement was more sociological than scientific. So when white supremacists come along today and resurrect arguments for Darwinian racism from years gone by, modern evolutionary theory may not have the moral resources to persuade them otherwise.”  Regardless of whether he is correct about evolutionary theory lacking the “moral resources” to counter racist claim, in point of fact it does have the scientific resources to do so.  For instance, the killer’s belief that “Whites and Blacks are separated by tens of thousands of years of evolution” is directly contradicted by scientific evidence that shows, for instance, that most recent common ancestor of all human beings now alive &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/15457259/&quot;&gt;most likely lived no more than a few thousand years ago.&lt;/a&gt; The idea that the human species is polygenic in it origin is one that &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/9781118584538.ieba0579&quot;&gt;has been refuted for some time now&lt;/a&gt;.   And, in fairness to West, he does acknowledge that “obviously, believing in evolution doesn’t compel one to be a racist, let alone predispose a person  to be a killer. Nevertheless, if we want to counteract the influences that shape people like the Buffalo shooter, we need to face the way evolutionary science is being misused to support the new white supremacists.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That seems like a good idea, so it was disappointing to read &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2022/05/weikart-in-his-own-mind-white-supremacist-gunman-was-only-following-the-science/&quot;&gt; an article posted only a few days later on Evolution News&lt;/a&gt; by David Klinghoffer, also about the Buffalo mass shooting, in which he discusses the writings of another DI fellow, Richard Weikart.  Klinghoffer states (as best as I can tell without any irony intended) that the killer believed “he was only following the science — the very best evolutionary science.”  You can read the article in vain for any indication that what the killer believed to be “the very best evolutionary science” was in fact a very poor and inaccurate parody of that science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curious to find how hard the Discovery Institute has tried to correct the misconception, identified by West, that evolutionary theory supports White Supremacism and other forms or racism, I decided to do a search of the EN archives for the term “Hitler”.  And, let me tell you, they talk about Hitler a lot!  I received page after page of hits.  Isn’t that odd?  Why would a website, supposedly devoted to the discussion of evolutionary theory, have so much to say about Hitler?  If you were to look at the index of any textbook on evolution, I highly doubt you would even find a single mention of him.  Many of the most recent articles are by or about the aforementioned Richard Weikart, who seems to have developed something of a cottage industry writing books that blame Darwin for the rise of the Nazis.  In fact, it was through this search that I learned that the ID actually has an entire website devoted to Weikart’s writings, with the catchy title &lt;a href=&quot;https://darwintohitler.com/&quot;&gt;“From Darwin to Hitler”&lt;/a&gt;.  It’s not too difficult to imagine how an angry and confused young man with an arsenal of semiautomatic weapons in his basement might get the idea from this that Darwinism leads to White Supremacism, is it?  And you can search that website in vain for even the slightest indication that such an association would only result from a gross misunderstanding of the facts of evolutionary theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so it goes.  As you read through the many articles the DI has produced on evolution and Hitler, you will repeatedly find remarks like &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2012/05/more_missing_li/&quot;&gt;this from the DI’s Board Chairman Bruce Chapman&lt;/a&gt;:  “The intellectual lineage is obvious and irrefutable. No Darwin, no eugenics.”  (Which is patent nonsense.  Sufficient theoretical grounding for eugenics could be found in the practice of selective breeding, which has been part of agriculture and animal husbandry since pre-history.)  I won’t claim to have read every single article the DI has written about Hitler and “Darwinism”.  That would be next to impossible.  However, I did look thru a good number of them, and other than that single comment by West mentioned earlier, I found no mention of the fact that any attempt to use evolutionary theory to legitimize racism would require a misunderstanding or misrepresentation of the theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s be serious about this.  Any attempt to reduce the causes of a specific mass shooting, or of mass shootings in general, to a single factor is bound to be a gross oversimplification.  But it does not appear to me that the DI is even concerned with trying to help efforts to understand, and hopefully prevent, future tragedies.  From the moment of its founding, an explicit objective of the Intelligent Design movement has been promote the idea that acceptance of the idea that humans evolved from earlier species thru natural processes leads to moral depravity.  One might like to believe the Discovery Institute is above exploiting a tragedy like the Buffalo shooting to promote this agenda. But, no.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Faizal Ali</name></author><summary type="html">This article is about the mass shooting that took place at the Tops Friendly Market in Buffalo, New York, on May 14, 2022 in which 10 people lost their lives. While I am going to write about issues peripherally related to this tragedy, rather than on the shooting itself, this is by no means intended to overlook the loss and suffering that the loved ones of the victims and, indeed, the Buffalo community as whole are continuing to deal with at this moment. I am sure the rest of the Panda’s Thumb team will join me in offering my thoughts and support to the people of Buffalo, as well as those affected by the more recent shooting in Uvalde, Texas, as they attempt to go forward with their lives and repair their shattered communities. The horror of the Buffalo shooting was compounded by the fact that it was clearly racially motivated, with the shooter leaving a manifesto in which he expounded at length on the “Great Replacement” conspiracy theory. This has caused consternation among members of America’s Republican Party and the right wing media with which it is allied. For some time now, the American Right has been making subtle, and sometimes not so subtle, overtures to White Supremacists in order to bring them into their “big tent” as part of their political base. Nonetheless, it remains a fact that many swing voters will be repelled by associations with such movements. This likely explains why, immediately after the shooting, the right wing media went into overdrive trying to downplay the killer’s racial motivations and, instead, shift the blame to other less politically inconvenient targets, like video games and mental illness. A question arises: If the American Right was not courting the support of White Supremacists, then why would it be so important for them to deny the killer’s White Supremacist motivations? I don’t really have a good answer for that.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Weird Earth: capsule review</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/weird-earth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Weird Earth: capsule review" /><published>2022-05-29T09:35:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-29T09:35:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/weird-earth</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/weird-earth.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Prothero_Cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://iupress.org/9781684351794/weird-earth/&quot;&gt;Weird Earth&lt;/a&gt; by Donald Prothero, Red Lightning Press, 2020.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have been reading, for example, &lt;i&gt;Skeptical Inquirer&lt;/i&gt; for 40 years or so, you may think you have little to gain from reading this splendid, newish book by the eminent geologist Donald Prothero. You would not be more wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://iupress.org/9781684351794/weird-earth/&quot;&gt;Weird Earth&lt;/a&gt;, is subtitled “Debunking strange ideas about our planet,” and debunk it does. I thought I knew a lot of the strange ideas about the planet, and indeed I did. But did I know the details? Usually not. Further, I had no idea that the earth is expanding (it is not), that Mount Shasta is riddled with tunnels leading to a secret city (it is not), nor that &lt;i&gt;ley lines&lt;/i&gt; connect various points on a map (they do not).
Professor Prothero devotes 16 chapters to debunking these and other concepts in some detail. Mostly the exposition was clear and I understood it easily; only rarely did I have to grapple with a description or explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book actually contains 18 chapters. The first describes “Science and critical thinking.” This chapter briefly discusses how “[s]cience is a way of thinking about the world.” If I had one criticism, it would regard the common claim that scientists actively attempt to disprove, or falsify, their hypotheses. It is not as simple as that, though surely when good scientists find that their hypotheses have been falsified, they will react accordingly. Nevertheless, when Rutherford traveled to the south seas, he did not intend to falsify general relativity. (See my post and comments &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/scientific-attitude.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last chapter explains &lt;i&gt;why&lt;/i&gt; people believe weird things and introduces such concepts as motivated reasoning, confirmation bias, backfire effect, compartmentalism and cognitive dissonance, and even tribalism. Professor Prothero marvels at the existence of “smart idiots,” who “selectively bias what they learn” in order to defend their (weird) beliefs to their followers. Indeed, he argues that “the root of most of our cognitive biases is tribalism,” a claim that, if true, requires a somewhat broad definition of tribalism. He goes back, convincingly, to the repeal of the Fairness Doctrine during the Reagan administration to explain today’s proliferation of nonsense on formerly reputable television channels. Were I writing the book, I might have combined this chapter with the first or made it the second, so that readers would more readily understand why people believed weird things, but maybe that is just a matter of taste.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Weird Earth by Donald Prothero, Red Lightning Press, 2020. If you have been reading, for example, Skeptical Inquirer for 40 years or so, you may think you have little to gain from reading this splendid, newish book by the eminent geologist Donald Prothero. You would not be more wrong. The book, Weird Earth, is subtitled “Debunking strange ideas about our planet,” and debunk it does. I thought I knew a lot of the strange ideas about the planet, and indeed I did. But did I know the details? Usually not. Further, I had no idea that the earth is expanding (it is not), that Mount Shasta is riddled with tunnels leading to a secret city (it is not), nor that ley lines connect various points on a map (they do not). Professor Prothero devotes 16 chapters to debunking these and other concepts in some detail. Mostly the exposition was clear and I understood it easily; only rarely did I have to grapple with a description or explanation. The book actually contains 18 chapters. The first describes “Science and critical thinking.” This chapter briefly discusses how “[s]cience is a way of thinking about the world.” If I had one criticism, it would regard the common claim that scientists actively attempt to disprove, or falsify, their hypotheses. It is not as simple as that, though surely when good scientists find that their hypotheses have been falsified, they will react accordingly. Nevertheless, when Rutherford traveled to the south seas, he did not intend to falsify general relativity. (See my post and comments here.) The last chapter explains why people believe weird things and introduces such concepts as motivated reasoning, confirmation bias, backfire effect, compartmentalism and cognitive dissonance, and even tribalism. Professor Prothero marvels at the existence of “smart idiots,” who “selectively bias what they learn” in order to defend their (weird) beliefs to their followers. Indeed, he argues that “the root of most of our cognitive biases is tribalism,” a claim that, if true, requires a somewhat broad definition of tribalism. He goes back, convincingly, to the repeal of the Fairness Doctrine during the Reagan administration to explain today’s proliferation of nonsense on formerly reputable television channels. Were I writing the book, I might have combined this chapter with the first or made it the second, so that readers would more readily understand why people believed weird things, but maybe that is just a matter of taste.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">830-million-year-old microorganisms found alive</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/830-million-year-old-microorganisms.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="830-million-year-old microorganisms found alive" /><published>2022-05-23T19:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-23T19:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/830-million-year-old-microorganisms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/830-million-year-old-microorganisms.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Ancient_Microorganisms.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ancient microorganisms&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Microorganisms in individual primary fluid inclusions in Browne Formation (central Australia) halite from the Empress 1A core, at 1520.1 m core depth. (A) Brown algal cell, viewed in plane-transmitted light. (B) Clear prokaryotic cocci (p), orange algal cell (a), and organic compound halo (oc) around air bubble; plane transmitted light. (C) Plane transmitted light (C1) and UV-vis light (C2) images of a chain of yellow algal cells, clear cocci, and an air bubble with a halo of clear organic compound that fluoresce blue. (D) Plane transmitted light (D1) and UV-vis light (D2) images of clear prokaryotes, yellow algae, suspect organic compound halo, air bubble, and clear accidental daughter crystals; organics fluoresce white and gold. &lt;small&gt;Credit: Sara I. Schreder-Gomes, Kathleen C. Benison, and Jeremiah A. Bernau, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1130/G49957.1&quot;&gt;830-million-year-old microorganisms in primary fluid inclusions in halite&lt;/a&gt;, CC BY license.
&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A team of geologists from West Virginia University has discovered what are apparently living cells in halite (rock salt) estimated to be 830 Ma old and more than 1.5 km below the surface. You may read a summary by Michelle Starr in &lt;i&gt;Science Alert&lt;/i&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencealert.com/830-million-year-old-microorganisms-found-trapped-in-australian-rock&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, or you may find the full article in &lt;i&gt;Geology&lt;/i&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1130/G49957.1&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The geologists used optical and ultraviolet fluorescence microscopy and found what they think are algal and prokaryotic cells trapped inside liquid inclusions in the halite. It is at least possible that the cells are alive, judging by the fluorescence spectra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I checked with a biologist, who confirmed my intuition that a seed or a spore, in order to remain alive, must display at least minimal metabolism. It is therefore hard to imagine a spore lasting for so many years, and indeed the &lt;i&gt;Geology&lt;/i&gt; paper notes that the “microorganisms may survive in fluid inclusions by metabolic changes, including starvation survival and cyst stages, and coexistence with organic compounds or dead cells that could serve as nutrient sources,” that is, that they may have been active sometimes and dormant at other times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Years ago, we used some green branches as tomato stakes. At the end of the season, we noticed some green leaves at the top end of one or more of the stakes. “How stubborn life is!” my mother exclaimed. She did not know the half of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Thanks to Vivian Dullien for alerting me to the article and discussing it with me.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Microorganisms in individual primary fluid inclusions in Browne Formation (central Australia) halite from the Empress 1A core, at 1520.1 m core depth. (A) Brown algal cell, viewed in plane-transmitted light. (B) Clear prokaryotic cocci (p), orange algal cell (a), and organic compound halo (oc) around air bubble; plane transmitted light. (C) Plane transmitted light (C1) and UV-vis light (C2) images of a chain of yellow algal cells, clear cocci, and an air bubble with a halo of clear organic compound that fluoresce blue. (D) Plane transmitted light (D1) and UV-vis light (D2) images of clear prokaryotes, yellow algae, suspect organic compound halo, air bubble, and clear accidental daughter crystals; organics fluoresce white and gold. Credit: Sara I. Schreder-Gomes, Kathleen C. Benison, and Jeremiah A. Bernau, 830-million-year-old microorganisms in primary fluid inclusions in halite, CC BY license. A team of geologists from West Virginia University has discovered what are apparently living cells in halite (rock salt) estimated to be 830 Ma old and more than 1.5 km below the surface. You may read a summary by Michelle Starr in Science Alert here, or you may find the full article in Geology here. The geologists used optical and ultraviolet fluorescence microscopy and found what they think are algal and prokaryotic cells trapped inside liquid inclusions in the halite. It is at least possible that the cells are alive, judging by the fluorescence spectra. I checked with a biologist, who confirmed my intuition that a seed or a spore, in order to remain alive, must display at least minimal metabolism. It is therefore hard to imagine a spore lasting for so many years, and indeed the Geology paper notes that the “microorganisms may survive in fluid inclusions by metabolic changes, including starvation survival and cyst stages, and coexistence with organic compounds or dead cells that could serve as nutrient sources,” that is, that they may have been active sometimes and dormant at other times. Years ago, we used some green branches as tomato stakes. At the end of the season, we noticed some green leaves at the top end of one or more of the stakes. “How stubborn life is!” my mother exclaimed. She did not know the half of it. Thanks to Vivian Dullien for alerting me to the article and discussing it with me.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cicada molting</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/cicada-molting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cicada molting" /><published>2022-05-23T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-23T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/cicada-molting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/cicada-molting.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Dan Phelps&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Phelps_Cicada_Crop_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cicada&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cicadamania.com/cicadas/common-cicadas-of-north-america/&quot;&gt;Cicada&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; unknown species, Lexington, Kentucky, July 17, 2015. Mr. Phelps notes, &quot;The cicada was on my back porch. It apparently crawled up a beam after digging itself out of the ground. It split its nymph skin and was in the process of letting its wings dry when I took the photo. They are beautifully colored when they first come out like this. They eventually become darker colors. This is an annual cicada, not one of the 13- or 17-year types. Don’t know which species since this one just molted. Most of the photos available for identification are for ones that are not freshly molted from the nymph stage. This photo is rotated correctly &amp;ndash; the nymph had been crawling up the post before stopping to split its skin and emerge as an adult.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Dan Phelps. Cicada &amp;ndash; unknown species, Lexington, Kentucky, July 17, 2015. Mr. Phelps notes, &quot;The cicada was on my back porch. It apparently crawled up a beam after digging itself out of the ground. It split its nymph skin and was in the process of letting its wings dry when I took the photo. They are beautifully colored when they first come out like this. They eventually become darker colors. This is an annual cicada, not one of the 13- or 17-year types. Don’t know which species since this one just molted. Most of the photos available for identification are for ones that are not freshly molted from the nymph stage. This photo is rotated correctly &amp;ndash; the nymph had been crawling up the post before stopping to split its skin and emerge as an adult.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Futility of Anti-Evolutionary Mathematics</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/futility-anti-evolutionary.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Futility of Anti-Evolutionary Mathematics" /><published>2022-05-22T09:53:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-22T09:53:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/futility-anti-evolutionary</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/futility-anti-evolutionary.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/RosenhouseCover2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book Cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Jason Rosenhouse, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridge.org/us/academic/subjects/life-sciences/evolutionary-biology/failures-mathematical-anti-evolutionism?format=HB&amp;amp;isbn=9781108842303&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Failures of Mathematical Anti-Evolutionism&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Cambridge University Press, 2022.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me thank Joe Felsenstein for &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/rosenhouse-on-mathematical-anti-evolutionism.html&quot;&gt;mentioning my new book&lt;/a&gt; &lt;i&gt;The Failures of Mathematical Anti-Evolutionism&lt;/i&gt;, which is now available from Cambridge University Press.  The original intention was for a book discussing mathematics and evolution more generally, with just one section devoted to anti-evolutionary nonsense.  But when that section ran into the hundreds of pages with no end in sight, we decided just to make the whole book a response to the nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mathematics has considerable propaganda value for anti-evolutionists since it can be used to confuse a lay audience into thinking that something profound has been said.  It also offers the possibility of an in-principle argument.  If the numbers say evolution is impossible then that is the end of the story, regardless of any circumstantial evidence drawn from paleontology, genetics, anatomy, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the book, I analyze all of the main threads of mathematical anti-evolutionism and explain why none of them work at all.  Along the way I explain how to think clearly about probability, information, combinatorial search, and thermodynamics.  However, it is worth noting that even without wading into the technical details, we have a right to be deeply skeptical of the whole project.  After all, the ingredients of the evolutionary process are all just empirical facts.  Genes really do mutate, sometimes leading to new functionalities, and natural selection really can string together these novelties into directional evolutionary change.  If evolution can account for small changes over human timescales, it’s hard to believe that an abstract mathematical argument will fundamentally rule out larger changes over longer time scales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, as soon as you look into the details of their arguments you realize that the mathematics invariably plays only a ceremonial role in their discourse.  The equations and theorems never really contribute anything; it’s always something else that does the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, consider Dembski’s notion of complex, specified information.  Recall that in this context, “complex” means low probability, while “specified” means that there is a recognizable pattern.  In his book &lt;i&gt;No Free Lunch&lt;/i&gt;, Dembski attempted to apply this notion to the bacterial flagellum.  He based his probability calculation on the assumption that an “irreducibly complex” system (meaning, roughly, that the system requires all of its parts to function) cannot evolve gradually.  Interestingly, Michael Behe devoted a whole book to defending this assumption, and he certainly didn’t seem to think that an additional probability calculation was needed to strengthen his argument.  If the assumption is correct, then it’s all by itself a strong argument against evolution, and the probability calculation is irrelevant.  Since the assumption is patently false, any calculation based on its truth is irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behe himself presented some probability calculations in his book &lt;i&gt;The Edge of Evolution&lt;/i&gt;.  This time his argument was that certain evolutionary novelties, such as choloroquine resistance in the malaria parasite, require multiple simultaneous mutations because there is no selectable function until all the mutations are in place.  To bolster this argument, he presented some highly dubious calculations meant to show the probability of such mutational sequences was extremely low.  But here again the calculation was irrelevant.  It was the assumption that whole mutational sequences were required all at once that was doing all the work.  Once again, if that assumption is correct then no probability calculation is needed, but since it is not the calculations were irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the anti-evolutionists invoke a mathematical principle rather than carry out a calculation.  They go on at length about the “No Free Lunch” (NFL) theorems, for example.  These are legitimate mathematical results that establish the non-existence of a universally successful search algorithm.  Dembski, sometimes with various coauthors, has argued that since evolution is in some way analogous to a combinatorial search, these theorems imply that any success that it has can only result from intelligent tailoring of nature’s fitness landscapes to the “algorithm” of natural selection. But once again the theorem plays only a rhetorical role in the argument.  Since nature’s fitness landscapes arise ultimately from the laws of physics, Dembski and his collaborators are really just asking why the universe has just the properties it does.  It’s a reasonable question, but it’s not one biologists need to worry about, and it’s not one to which the NFL theorems make any contribution toward answering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pattern occurs again in their invocations of the second law of thermodynamics.  The second law—the real thing as opposed to the asinine caricatures about randomness and disorder—is a mathematical inequality that precisely quantifies the permissible amount of entropy change that can result from a thermodynamic process.  If you are not using any of the mathematical machinery of thermodynamics, if instead you are just making vague statements to the effect that the second law rules out the possibility of organisms growing more complex over time, then there is no reason to bring up thermodynamics at all.  Everyone agrees that the growth in complexity over time requires a special sort of explanation.  Scientists believe they have such an explanation while the anti-evolutionists demur, but the important point is that the resulting argument has nothing to do with thermodynamics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It requires writing at book length to discuss the myriad conceptual and scientific errors of mathematical anti-evolutionism, and if you are interested in exploring that topic, then I know a good book you can read.  But even without all that effort you can be certain that their arguments amount to nothing.  If someone claims he can refute evolution with a back-of-the-envelope probability calculation or by invoking some abstract principle or theorem, then you can, with total confidence, dismiss the claim out of hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Jason Rosenhouse is a professor of mathematics at James Madison University and the author of &lt;a href=&quot;https://oxford.universitypressscholarship.com/view/10.1093/acprof:osobl/9780199744633.001.0001/acprof-9780199744633&quot;&gt;Among the Creationists: Dispatches From the Anti-Evolutionist Front Line&lt;/a&gt;, as well as books on the mathematics of Sudoku and the Monty Hall problem. His latest book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridge.org/us/academic/subjects/life-sciences/evolutionary-biology/failures-mathematical-anti-evolutionism?format=HB&amp;amp;isbn=9781108842303&quot;&gt;The Failures of Mathematical Anti-Evolutionism&lt;/a&gt;, is available from Cambridge University Press. Matt Young will be the moderator of this thread.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jason Rosenhouse</name></author><summary type="html">Jason Rosenhouse, The Failures of Mathematical Anti-Evolutionism, Cambridge University Press, 2022. Let me thank Joe Felsenstein for mentioning my new book The Failures of Mathematical Anti-Evolutionism, which is now available from Cambridge University Press. The original intention was for a book discussing mathematics and evolution more generally, with just one section devoted to anti-evolutionary nonsense. But when that section ran into the hundreds of pages with no end in sight, we decided just to make the whole book a response to the nonsense. Mathematics has considerable propaganda value for anti-evolutionists since it can be used to confuse a lay audience into thinking that something profound has been said. It also offers the possibility of an in-principle argument. If the numbers say evolution is impossible then that is the end of the story, regardless of any circumstantial evidence drawn from paleontology, genetics, anatomy, and so on.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jason Rosenhouse’s book on mathematical anti-evolutionism is available</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/rosenhouse-on-mathematical-anti-evolutionism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jason Rosenhouse’s book on mathematical anti-evolutionism is available" /><published>2022-05-18T16:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-18T16:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/rosenhouse-on-mathematical-anti-evolutionism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/rosenhouse-on-mathematical-anti-evolutionism.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/RosenhouseCover2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Rosenhouse book cover]&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Jason Rosenhouse, &lt;em&gt;The Failures of Mathematical Anti-Evolutionism&lt;/em&gt;.  Cambridge
University Press, 2022.
&lt;p&gt;

Written by a mathematician who has paid close attention to mathematical arguments
against evolution, this is a beautifully written and careful refutation of
those arguments.  Actually, that sentence I plagiarized from the back cover
of this book.  But I don't have to worry about having done that, since it
comes from a blurb written by me.  I also gave Jason Rosenhouse comments on the
manuscript.
&lt;p&gt;
Jason Rosenhouse is a professor of mathematics at James Madison University
who also writes popularizations of his field, including a book on the
mathematics of Sudoku and one on the Monty Hall Problem (you know:
the one with the doors and the goats).  Is he overreaching by taking on
creationist and ID arguments?  Hardly: he has written extensively
on this, including many posts here in PT starting in its first year. For a while had his own
blog called EvolutionBlog.  He attended creationist and ID conferences
and wrote about that experience in his 2012 book, &lt;em&gt;Among the Creationists. Dispatches from the Anti-Evolutionist Front Line&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;
This is a lovely and fascinating book which covers the most
widely-cited mathematical arguments against evolution, explaining them and
their weaknesses lucidly for a general audience.  If you are not
writing a review for one of the Discovery Institute sites, you
will be impressed.
&lt;p&gt;
Let me outline the chapters, to give you a general picture of what
is covered ...
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here are the chapters and some indication of their contents:
&lt;p&gt;
1. Scientists and Their Hecklers.  Outlines the types of
critics and the way they operate, and explains why
mathematics gets involved.
&lt;p&gt;
2. Evolution Basics.  Outlines evolutionary theory, and
introduces the arguments from complex structures,
unbridgeable gaps, and irreducible complexity.  Plus
a section on &quot;Paying A Price for Being Wrong&quot;.
&lt;p&gt;
3. The Parallel Tracks of Mathematical Reasoning. Explains
how mathematical modeling and logical proof interact
in explaining natural phenomena, and why arguments such
as the rareness of well-adapted organisms in a genotype
space don't work.
&lt;p&gt;
4. The Legacy of the Wistar Conference.  Using the
1966 conference called by some mathematical critics
of evolutionary biology, explains why their critiques
were refuted, and how present-day creationists
misrepresent what was said at that conference.
&lt;p&gt;
5. Probability Theory.  Examples from cards and from
the Hardy-Weinberg calculation in population genetics
lead to a consideration of the argument from
improbability, and its use in William Dembski's
argument from Complex Specified Information and
Michael Behe's argument about the Edge of Evolution.
&lt;p&gt;
6. Information and Combinatorial Search.  Information
theory, claims that random mutations always decrease
the information content of biological systems.
Protein space.  Dawkins' Weasel. The No Free Lunch Theorem.
Artifical life. Dembski and Marks's Conservation
of Information, and fine tuning of the universe.
&lt;p&gt;
7. Thermodynamics. Entropy, thermodynamic laws, and
statistical mechanics. Arguments from entropy and
statistical mechanics.  Henry Morris's Second Law
argument. Granville Sewell's revived Second Law
argument.
&lt;p&gt;
8. Epilogue.  Bad math can be rhetorically
effective.  Can human intelligence build
complex adaptations?
&lt;p&gt;
In addition, each chapter ends with Notes
and Further Reading, typically 2-3 pages
of notes, each with a one or more references
for further reading.
&lt;p&gt;
In short, this is a treasure.  Is it perfect?
Of course not.  As someone who, like most of
us, thinks visually, I would have liked to see
more figures.  The argument fom fine-tuning
is hammered into the ground at a bit more
length than necessary.  The cover design is
lovely, but I don't know what it symbolizes.
And computers have not &quot;been used to
simulate evolution since the late 1960s&quot;, but
actually since the mid-1950s.
&lt;p&gt;
Jason Rosenhouse's book will be cited frequently
in future arguments about mathematical
dismissals of evolution.  And should be.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Jason Rosenhouse, The Failures of Mathematical Anti-Evolutionism. Cambridge University Press, 2022. Written by a mathematician who has paid close attention to mathematical arguments against evolution, this is a beautifully written and careful refutation of those arguments. Actually, that sentence I plagiarized from the back cover of this book. But I don't have to worry about having done that, since it comes from a blurb written by me. I also gave Jason Rosenhouse comments on the manuscript. Jason Rosenhouse is a professor of mathematics at James Madison University who also writes popularizations of his field, including a book on the mathematics of Sudoku and one on the Monty Hall Problem (you know: the one with the doors and the goats). Is he overreaching by taking on creationist and ID arguments? Hardly: he has written extensively on this, including many posts here in PT starting in its first year. For a while had his own blog called EvolutionBlog. He attended creationist and ID conferences and wrote about that experience in his 2012 book, Among the Creationists. Dispatches from the Anti-Evolutionist Front Line. This is a lovely and fascinating book which covers the most widely-cited mathematical arguments against evolution, explaining them and their weaknesses lucidly for a general audience. If you are not writing a review for one of the Discovery Institute sites, you will be impressed. Let me outline the chapters, to give you a general picture of what is covered ...</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Antilocapra americana</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/antilocapra-americana.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Antilocapra americana" /><published>2022-05-09T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-09T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/antilocapra-americana</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/antilocapra-americana.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Vivian Dullien&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Dullien_V.Pronghorn_Antelope_And_Sand_Dunes_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pronghorn&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pronghorn&quot;&gt;Antilocapra americana&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; pronghorn &quot;antelope&quot; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/grsa/learn/nature/sanddunes.htm&quot;&gt;Great Sand Dunes&lt;/a&gt;. Dr. Dullien comments, &quot;Storms, sunsets, and atmospheric conditions can combine in many ways to create amazing effects.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Vivian Dullien. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Antilocapra americana &amp;ndash; pronghorn &quot;antelope&quot; and Great Sand Dunes. Dr. Dullien comments, &quot;Storms, sunsets, and atmospheric conditions can combine in many ways to create amazing effects.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Eric Hedin claims to have been “canceled”</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/eric-hedin-claims.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Eric Hedin claims to have been “canceled”" /><published>2022-05-07T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-07T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/eric-hedin-claims</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/05/eric-hedin-claims.html">&lt;p&gt;Eric Hedin is a physicist who was ordered to stop teaching intelligent-design creationism at Ball State University, as we reported &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2016/05/intelligent-des-1.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; several years ago. Far from being canceled, Prof. Hedin was promoted to Associate Professor and, I assume, granted tenure. He nevertheless left Ball State for Biola “University,” formerly Bible Institute of Los Angeles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Jerry Coyne, &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2022/05/07/eric-hedin-beefs-about-being-canceled-at-ball-state-by-the-ffrf-and-me-but-forgives-me-showing-a-cat-leading-me-to-jesus/&quot;&gt;Eric Hedin beefs about being “canceled” at Ball State by the FFRF and me, but forgives me, showing a cat leading me to Jesus!&lt;/a&gt;. I incline to agree with Prof. Coyne: Prof. Hedin was by no means canceled; he was &lt;i&gt;promoted&lt;/i&gt; for Chrissake! At any rate, Prof. Hedin has now written a book published by the Discovery Institute, presumably because no real publisher would touch it. His video, Canceled Science, may be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/TA4QutvxX88&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I have not watched it yet, but I promise to do so when I return home and comment if I think it is appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I suggest that you enjoy Prof. Coyne’s article.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Eric Hedin is a physicist who was ordered to stop teaching intelligent-design creationism at Ball State University, as we reported here several years ago. Far from being canceled, Prof. Hedin was promoted to Associate Professor and, I assume, granted tenure. He nevertheless left Ball State for Biola “University,” formerly Bible Institute of Los Angeles. According to Jerry Coyne, Eric Hedin beefs about being “canceled” at Ball State by the FFRF and me, but forgives me, showing a cat leading me to Jesus!. I incline to agree with Prof. Coyne: Prof. Hedin was by no means canceled; he was promoted for Chrissake! At any rate, Prof. Hedin has now written a book published by the Discovery Institute, presumably because no real publisher would touch it. His video, Canceled Science, may be found here. I have not watched it yet, but I promise to do so when I return home and comment if I think it is appropriate. Meanwhile, I suggest that you enjoy Prof. Coyne’s article.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Scientific Attitude: book review</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/scientific-attitude.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Scientific Attitude: book review" /><published>2022-04-29T11:10:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-04-29T11:10:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/scientific-attitude</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/04/scientific-attitude.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/McIntyre_Cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://leemcIntyrebooks.com/books/the-scientific-attitude/&quot;&gt;Book cover&lt;/a&gt;. The fourth monkey is known as &quot;Have No Fun,&quot; but it is a misnomer: science can be great fun, especially if it involves optical instrumentation.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chance works in mysterious ways. Shortly after I saw the philosopher Lee McIntyre discussing &lt;a href=&quot;https://centerforinquiry.org/video/how-to-talk-to-a-science-denier/&quot;&gt;How to talk to a science denier&lt;/a&gt; on the Center for Inquiry website, I ran across his splendid little book &lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/scientific-attitude&quot;&gt;The Scientific Attitude: Defending Science from Denial, Fraud, and Pseudoscience&lt;/a&gt;. Naturally, I snapped it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scientific attitude is sort of a technical term to McIntyre. He is not interested in demarcating science from non-science, nor in delineating a scientific method; rather, he considers the scientific attitude necessary for science (not that it is limited to scientists). Specifically, McIntyre writes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scientific attitude can be summed up in a commitment to two principles:&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;(1) We care about empirical evidence. &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;(2) We are willing to change our theories in light of new evidence. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you think that these principles may be “too vague and unrigorous to be helpful,” McIntyre discusses “what it means &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; to care about evidence”: those who do not care about evidence are dogmatic and maintain their beliefs even in defiance of the evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings us to Sir Karl Popper. According to the Introduction, it was Popper who made McIntyre decide to become a philosopher of science. I had known of Popper beforehand, but I was somewhat taken by Popper after I read &lt;i&gt;Conjectures and Refutations: The Growth of Scientific Knowledge&lt;/i&gt;* around 25 years ago. Popper was mistaken if he thought that scientists actively attempt to disprove their own theories experimentally. More likely, we try to confirm our theories. On the other hand, in the face of an apparent disconfirmation, we are willing to discard our theories or at least revise them. We may develop an &lt;i&gt;ad hoc&lt;/i&gt; (auxiliary) hypothesis in order to preserve our theory – but it is not enough to merely state an &lt;i&gt;ad hoc&lt;/i&gt; hypothesis, as many pseudoscientists seem to think; the &lt;i&gt;ad hoc&lt;/i&gt; hypothesis, needless to say, must itself be disprovable (testable, falsifiable).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popper himself notes that some “genuinely testable [falsifiable] theories,” even when found to be false, may be propped up by their “admirers,” who will introduce an &lt;i&gt;ad hoc&lt;/i&gt; hypothesis or otherwise reinterpret their theory in such a way that it cannot be refuted. In other words, judgement is called for, and you have to know when to discard a theory and when to patch it up. If you lack judgement, you lack the scientific attitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you decide whether you have the scientific attitude? You do not just cherry-pick facts but rather&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;act in accordance with a well-vetted set of practices that have been sanctioned by the scientific community because they have historically led to well-justified beliefs&lt;/i&gt; [italics in original]. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to McIntyre’s prescription, Ptolemaic astronomy (epicycles) was science. Phlogiston theory was science. Alchemy was science. Even though these theories were wrong science, they were science, in part because they were discarded and replaced when they were found to be wrong. Astrology, creationism, flat-earth theory are not science because their “admirers” try to prop them up with unprovable or unfalsifiable rationalizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McIntyre goes on to discuss the case of Ignaz Semmelweis, a physician who in the mid-1800’s employed careful observation and experimentation, and deduced that the cause of childbed fever (puerperal fever) was caused by what we would today call insufficient hygiene. Semmelweis had the scientific attitude, but, alas, no one else did, and Semmelweis died a failure. In his case, the “well-vetted set of practices that have been sanctioned by the scientific community” were unfortunately wrong, and it was decades before they were set right, with who knows how many lost lives. Stanley Pons and Martin Fleischmann, the “codiscoverers” of cold fusion, did not have the scientific attitude, and neither did a lot of other people, but eventually their “discovery” was falsified and laid to rest by those who did. McIntyre cites observations by Popper and Einstein to the effect that a critical attitude needs to precede the concept of falsifiability in the sense that, if you do not have a critical attitude, you will not seek to falsify your own theories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will not go into detail, but McIntyre mostly rejects the social constructivist model and insists that evidence is required for a paradigm shift. Science, to my mind, ought to have a privileged position when it comes to questions of fact because its “fads” (and it has fads) may be chosen to some extent by preference, but their direction is generally dictated by evidence, not belief or ideology. Thomas Kuhn was correct about paradigm shifts, but paradigms in science are hard to shift and, indeed, shift only when the evidence warrants a shift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not a philosopher (though a philosopher of science once called me a naïve falsificationist). I will not discuss the portions of the book that worry about demarcation theory, the social sciences, and so on, though I thought that McIntyre might have been just a wee bit supercilious in discussing how many of the social sciences were merely aspiring to be sciences. At least one of his case studies, though, was appalling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McIntyre establishes (or perhaps defines) that fraud has to be deliberate: fabrication or falsification of data. Making mistakes, however, is not fraud. McIntyre inveighs against cherry-picking data, searching data for statistical significance, drawing inferences from too small a data set, and so on, though he does not seem to consider those to be fraud. He reminds me of a colleague who once told me, with a grin, that he had to search high and low for an oscilloscope trace that he could call “typical” but which showed all the features he wanted to emphasize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another chapter details incidents of “fraud and other failures.” Many are probably familiar to readers of PT, but McIntyre provides a degree of detail that may not be so familiar. Among the frauds, I am sorry to report, is the “vaccine-autism debacle,” which features Andrew Wakefield, continues to this day, and contributes to the anti-vaccination movement and its attendant outbreaks of disease, again with the penalty of countless lost lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On what McIntyre deems a happier note, the astronomer Andrew Lyne made an error in a publication, explained it to a scientific conference, and received a standing ovation.  That is how science is supposed to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the head, “denialists, pseudoscientists, and other charlatans,” we meet those who deny well-established theories and those who insist on failed theories. Depressingly, McIntyre notes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;there has always been a human tendency to believe what we want to believe. Superstition and willful ignorance are not new to the human condition. What is new in recent years is the extent to which people can find a ready supply of &quot;evidence&quot; … on the Internet. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He goes on to observe that empirical evidence will not convince people who do not accept empirical evidence. “It is almost as if denialists are making faith-based assertions.” Almost?! He is too kind. Denialists are not skeptics; they are ideologues who refuse to believe conclusions that they do not like but which are based on what everyone else thinks is compelling evidence. Indeed, as he says, the&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;denialist pattern [is] to have impossibly high standards of proof for the things that one does not want to believe and extremely low standards of acceptance for the things that fit one's ideology. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under confirmation bias and motivated reasoning, we meet Senator Ted Cruz, who cherry-picks a particularly hot year to “prove” that climate change is a hoax by liberal politicians out for power. It is worth reading McIntyre’s dissection of an NPR interview with Sen. Cruz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will conclude with a warning. McIntyre discusses the case of Harlen Bretz and the origin of the channeled scablands in the state of Washington. Like Alfred Wegener and continental drift or Galileo and heliocentric theory, Bretz accounted for the scablands by postulating a massive flood and providing significant supporting evidence for such a flood; his theory is accepted today. In the early to mid-twentieth century, however, geologists rejected it vigorously, in part because uniformitarianism was “favored by geologists [because] it was seen as a bulwark against the creationists.” That is, geologists were putting ideology ahead of science – what McIntyre calls “an example of how ideology can infect the scientific process, whether we are on the ‘right’ side of it or not.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McIntyre tackles creationism and intelligent-design creationism, which are familiar to readers of PT, and then Robert Jahn’s study of psychokinesis, which I consider flawed science, not pseudoscience. I will not tackle either of those here.  Read the book!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* Popper, Karl R., 1968, Conjectures and Refutations: The Growth of Scientific Knowledge, Harper Torchbooks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Book cover. The fourth monkey is known as &quot;Have No Fun,&quot; but it is a misnomer: science can be great fun, especially if it involves optical instrumentation. Chance works in mysterious ways. Shortly after I saw the philosopher Lee McIntyre discussing How to talk to a science denier on the Center for Inquiry website, I ran across his splendid little book The Scientific Attitude: Defending Science from Denial, Fraud, and Pseudoscience. Naturally, I snapped it up.</summary></entry></feed>