<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-05-27T22:32:18-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Phidippus audax</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/phidippus-audax.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Phidippus audax" /><published>2024-05-27T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-05-27T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/phidippus-audax</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/phidippus-audax.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/DSC05680_Spider_Phidippus_audax_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jumping spider&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.donerickson.name/spiders/spiders.html&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Phidippus audax&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; jumping spider, often called bold jumper, found in an enclosed, unheated space, Boulder, Colorado, April, 2024. I was interested in the powerful forelegs, if that is the right word (the left foreleg must have been folded under, because a later photograph shows that it is intact). The spider in this photograph was running along the edge of a dish from which it could apparently not get out. Despite the designation jumping spider, it very kindly hung around while I managed a few photographs.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see comments on this post click below: &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Phidippus audax &amp;ndash; jumping spider, often called bold jumper, found in an enclosed, unheated space, Boulder, Colorado, April, 2024. I was interested in the powerful forelegs, if that is the right word (the left foreleg must have been folded under, because a later photograph shows that it is intact). The spider in this photograph was running along the edge of a dish from which it could apparently not get out. Despite the designation jumping spider, it very kindly hung around while I managed a few photographs. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Who Am I?” by Martyn Iles, Executive CEO of Answers in Genesis: Book Review</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/who-am-i.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Who Am I?” by Martyn Iles, Executive CEO of Answers in Genesis: Book Review" /><published>2024-05-22T10:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-05-22T10:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/who-am-i</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/who-am-i.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Braterman_Iles_Book_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Martyn Iles, as many readers will know, was managing Director of the Australian Christian Lobby until sacked by the Board in February 2023, was appointed Chief Ministry Officer of Answers in Genesis in May of that year, and in November was &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/Martyn-Iles-Is-Executive.html&quot;&gt; promoted to Executive CEO&lt;/a&gt;, working alongside Ken Ham, who remains as Founding CEO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While still in Australia, Iles promoted right-wing causes in the name of individual religious freedom, expressed support on his YouTube channel for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/BrBgSjAC7kE 20:15&quot;&gt;claim that the 2020 US presidential election had been stolen&lt;/a&gt;, and in a Facebook post on January 21 2020, just two weeks after the January 6 insurrection, reaffirmed his admiration for Donald Trump. However, since joining Answers in Genesis he has, to the best of my knowledge, refrained from overtly political comment. In a Facebook post on March 17 this year he explicitly rejected the idea of a “Christian nation,” since being a Christian or not is a characteristic of individuals. Thus he has placed a welcome distance between himself and the extremes of US Christian Nationalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one important difference in style between Iles and Ham. Ham, in the tradition of Henry Morris and, before him, George McCready Price, argues that science supports his version of Bible-based Young Earth Creationism. Iles, however, does not even condescend to discuss such mere details. As he &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/martynlloydiles/posts/635836281247343/&quot;&gt; posted on Facebook&lt;/a&gt; in October 2022, “Truth is in the [biblical] word itself. Other things are true insofar as they conform to it.” Moreover, Iles is clear in his own mind that his understanding of the Bible, however far-fetched, is the correct one. So when he tells us what it means, he is speaking for God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On his appointment, &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2023/11/13/aig-appoints-new-executive-ceo-martyn-iles/&quot;&gt;Iles wrote&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Just as evolutionary naturalism has threatened the faith of so many, postmodernism and new critical theories threaten the faith of a new generation. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given his position at the head of the world’s leading Young Earth Creationist organization, we need to know what he has in mind by this laconic statement,and we can gain some insight into this from the book under discussion here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book itself, like others from the same publisher, appears to be directed at young adults. It is an easy read, with large clear print, and the text is liberally illustrated by silhouettes of young people, generating a warm and welcoming impression at odds with the fundamentally dictatorial nature of the content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That content is mass of self-contradictions. We are told that man is made in the image of God, but there are multiple biblical references to human sinfulness and corruption. It is our duty to look after the world, but not to take responsibility for human-caused climate change. And Iles deplores, as do I, the upsurge in young people seeking to mutilate their bodies when their personalities do not fit gender stereotypes, but claims biblical authority for stereotypes of the most constricting kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iles begins by deploring what he sees as the modern emphasis on the self:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Actually, I didn’t realize you could use it [self-] as a prefix quite so much until I started my research. Self-ideation, self-love, self-discovery, self-definition, self-perception, self-determination, self-narrative, self-image, self-concept, self-esteem … All of these I have encountered in contemporary works on identity. This word has brought with it the age of the inward turn — the looking at the self. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably absent from this list: self-knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He goes on to build up an enormous superstructure on a very narrow theological base. He makes extensive use of a handful of verses from the opening chapters of Genesis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Be fruitful and multiply and fill the earth and subdue it, and have dominion over the fish of the sea and over the birds of the heavens and over every living thing that moves on the earth. (Genesis 1:28) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increase greatly on the earth and multiply in it. (Genesis 9:7) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the earth remains, seedtime and harvest, cold and heat, summer and winter, day and night, shall not cease. (Genesis 8:22) &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this he infers that there cannot be an overpopulation problem, that it is a duty of fertile couples to have children, and that concerns about such large-scale matters as climate change are fundamentally misplaced, since these things are in the hands of God and, to use his expression, when we imagine that we can affect them we are “getting too big for our boots.” This is the sin of pride, and pride is a very serious sin indeed. Climate alarmism (his expression) is only one example of such pride, part of a list that includes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;abortion, transgenderism, queer sexuality [sic], critical race theory, feminism, family breakdown, …, childlessness, cultural Marxism, post-modernism, and all that stuff. The common thread is this: all of them seek to usurp God’s authority as Creator by redefining what He has already defined. All of them seek to do His job for Him, only better. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He accepts unquestioningly the interpretation of Genesis 3:15:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;And I will put enmity between you and the woman, and between your offspring and her offspring; he shall bruise your head, and you shall bruise his heel.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;as the very first prophesy of the coming of Jesus. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seed_of_the_woman&quot;&gt;this interpretation&lt;/a&gt;, which goes back to the 2nd Century CE, the serpent is identified with Satan, the woman’s offspring is Jesus, born of a woman, the bruising of his heel is the agony of the crucifixion, and the bruising of Satan’s head is Christ’s triumph over evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this he infers that the highest vocation of woman is motherhood, and that Satan bears special enmity towards pregnant women and babies. Satan is very prominent in Iles’s view of the world, and is mentioned 11 times in this short book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Male and female roles were spelt out at the creation. God decides to create woman because:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;It is not good that the man should be alone; I will make him a helper fit for him. (Genesis 2:18) &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Adam is duly appreciative:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;This at last &lt;sup&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt; is bone of my bones and flesh of my flesh; she shall be called Woman, because she was taken out of Man. (Genesis 2:23). &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, according to Iles,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;woman was made with such care and purpose that she perfectly complemented and completed him [man]. She too was not made to be alone. The two became one. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One, but different:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The LORD God took the man and put him in the garden of Eden to work it and keep it. (Genesis 2:15) &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iles draws our attention to two words, which define a man’s God-given purpose; first, to “work,” and second to “keep.” The reference to “the garden” directs attention to his external responsibilities. And so, he tells us, men are called to industry and must beware the sin of idleness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why, Iles asks, was it Adam that God addressed by name after the Fall:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Adam, where art thou? (Genesis 3:17, KJV) &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This although Eve and the serpent were also present at the scene, the serpent was the primary initiator of the sin, and Eve was the first to eat of the forbidden fruit. The reason for singling out Adam is that, as a man, he had primary responsibility for what had happened in the garden that had been entrusted to his care. Responsibility is a male prerogative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of women, Iles says&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The woman was at her best when making another person their best. That was her commission. And it spills over into her motherhood too. Only women are mothers, and this is a good and beautiful thing indeed — a commission from God, for which she is designed biologically, psychologically, and spiritually. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iles goes on to mentions meekness as part of woman’s special virtue, and uses the word “meek” with reference to women on seven separate occasions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a passage worth quoting in full, he compares the different ways in which men and women go about getting their own way when not entitled to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;While men might prefer to exercise illegitimate control through brutishness, force, and cruelty, women tend to use different methods. They play games. They manipulate circumstances. They might even get their girlfriends involved to “make” things happen or drop ideas, seeds, and prompts through third parties. Their minds are always storyboarding, working out what people are thinking, how they’re feeling, and preempting next moves. They operate in the realm of the emotional, subjective, and interpersonal. To use such powers of discernment to manipulate circumstances and control outcomes is ultimately an abuse of those feminine giftings. They were given to be exercised selflessly and meekly, without the taint of self-will and premeditated outcomes. There is a difference between godly help and controlling “femcraft.” &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when challenged as to what the besetting sin of woman might be, as compared to idleness in men, he answers “Control.” As he put it on Facebook (6 June 2023)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;A word like “independent” is a direct assault on God’s design for women… A woman who prizes strength in independence is a woman rebelling against her nature. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There you have it. You and I may think that our identity is a puzzle, but the book promises in its title to solve it for us, and does so. We may even have imagined that there are many possible solutions, but Iles knows God’s design, and there’s an end of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the book is devoted to theological questions, with heavy emphasis on our sinful nature, but since I have no special insight to offer on such matters, I will leave it there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Who am I? Solving the identity puzzle&lt;/i&gt;, Martyn Iles, with a foreword by Ken Ham, 35,000 words spread out over 208 pages, Master Books, 2024, $19.99 on Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“At last” because in between the two verses cited, we have the creation of the animals, and their being brought to Adam as potential partners and found wanting for that purpose. But if you include this in your materials, you will find yourself with something far more interesting than Iles’s blinkered moralizing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman</name></author><summary type="html">Martyn Iles, as many readers will know, was managing Director of the Australian Christian Lobby until sacked by the Board in February 2023, was appointed Chief Ministry Officer of Answers in Genesis in May of that year, and in November was promoted to Executive CEO, working alongside Ken Ham, who remains as Founding CEO. While still in Australia, Iles promoted right-wing causes in the name of individual religious freedom, expressed support on his YouTube channel for the claim that the 2020 US presidential election had been stolen, and in a Facebook post on January 21 2020, just two weeks after the January 6 insurrection, reaffirmed his admiration for Donald Trump. However, since joining Answers in Genesis he has, to the best of my knowledge, refrained from overtly political comment. In a Facebook post on March 17 this year he explicitly rejected the idea of a “Christian nation,” since being a Christian or not is a characteristic of individuals. Thus he has placed a welcome distance between himself and the extremes of US Christian Nationalism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Prunus americana</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/prunus-americana.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Prunus americana" /><published>2024-05-13T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-05-13T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/prunus-americana</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/05/prunus-americana.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/P1021077_Prunus_Americana_Crop_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wild plum blossoms&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prunus_americana&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Prunus americana&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; wild plum, with erratic honeybee, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Honey_bee&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Apis mellifera&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Bobolink Trail, Boulder, Colorado, May, 2024.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Prunus americana &amp;ndash; wild plum, with erratic honeybee, Apis mellifera, Bobolink Trail, Boulder, Colorado, May, 2024. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Marmota flaviventris</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/marmota-flaviventris.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Marmota flaviventris" /><published>2024-04-29T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-04-29T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/marmota-flaviventris</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/marmota-flaviventris.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photograph by Vivian Dullien&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Vivian_Dullien_Marmot_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Marmot&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/romo/learn/nature/marmot.htm&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Marmota flaviventris&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; young yellow-bellied marmot, preparing for hibernation, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/romo/index.htm&quot;&gt;Rocky Mountain National Park&lt;/a&gt;, fall, 2023.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Vivian Dullien. Marmota flaviventris &amp;ndash; young yellow-bellied marmot, preparing for hibernation, Rocky Mountain National Park, fall, 2023. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Intelligent Design for Dummies, Part 2</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/intelligent-design-dummies-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intelligent Design for Dummies, Part 2" /><published>2024-04-25T08:09:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-04-25T08:09:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/intelligent-design-dummies-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/intelligent-design-dummies-2.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Branch_Part_2_Pandas.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pandas&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Pandas at National Zoo in Washington.&lt;small&gt; Photograph by Asiir. Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 2.5 Generic license.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;This is Part 2 of 2. You may find Part 1 &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/intelligent-design-dummies.html&quot;&gt; here &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Third Problem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Finally, your story has a practical problem,” Questor says: “Is the panda’s thumb a poor design?” — whereupon a panda peeks its head through the panel and confides, “I rather like it, you know” (page 78). In essence, she is attacking premise (4) of Teller’s argument, by a clever appeal to the literature. Questor is presumably a college biology professor, and Wiester, who provided “the science input” for WDGDWI, is a college biology professor. Where do they go to get the information on the panda’s thumb? The &lt;i&gt;Encyclopedia Americana&lt;/i&gt;, which Questor quotes as saying that the panda’s thumb “enables the panda to eat bamboo efficiently” and to “handle stems with great dexterity” (page 78, charmingly illustrated with a panda twirling stalks of bamboo in drum-major fashion). Gould, in contrast, consulted D. Dwight Davis’s monograph &lt;i&gt;The Giant Panda&lt;/i&gt; (1964), which he characterized as “the greatest work of modern evolutionary comparative anatomy” (Gould 1980: 22).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the far-from-authoritative nature of their source, Newman and Wiester’s emphasis on the efficiency of the panda’s thumb reveals that they have again misrepresented Gould’s argument, apparently due to their conflation of two senses in which it is possible for design (or, if you prefer, “design”) to be suboptimal. In the first sense, a biological feature is suboptimally designed if it accomplishes its function not as efficiently as it (or a plausible substitute) might. Thus in the first sense, to say that the panda’s thumb is suboptimally designed is to say that it is not as useful for stripping leaves from bamboo as it (or a plausible substitute) might be. In the second sense, however, a biological feature is suboptimally designed if it is not designed as well as it might have been, that is, if the process whereby it acquired the ability to accomplish its function was not as efficient as it (or a plausible substitute) might have been. That there is such a sense of what it is for design to be suboptimal is testified to by the computer engineer’s word “kludge,” which refers to a clumsy and inelegant, but not necessarily ineffective, solution to a problem. In the second sense, to say that the panda’s thumb is suboptimally designed is to say that the process whereby it acquired the ability to strip leaves from bamboo was a kludge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is obvious that in “The Panda’s Thumb” Gould was thinking about suboptimal design in the second, kludgy, sense: in a passage that Newman and Wiester quote, he explains that “[o]dd arrangements and funny solutions” provide striking evidence for evolution (Gould 1980: 20). Referring to the panda’s thumb, he writes, “An engineer’s best solution is debarred by history … the panda must use parts on hand and settle for … a somewhat clumsy, but quite workable, solution … a contraption, not a lovely contrivance” (Gould 1980: 24). And he acknowledges that the panda’s thumb is not suboptimally designed in the first sense: “I was amazed by their dexterity” (Gould 1980: 21). Thus WDGDWI’s discussion of whether the panda’s thumb is suboptimally designed in the first sense is irrelevant to the question Gould was addressing, whether the panda’s thumb is a kludge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parenthetically, the same conflation is committed by the Discovery Institute’s Paul A. Nelson, in a paper not cited by Newman and Wiester. Nelson quotes the same passages about odd arrangements and funny solutions from Gould (1980: 20–21), glossing the argument as “God is an optimizing creator. This structure, and hence, [&lt;i&gt;sic&lt;/i&gt;] organism, is imperfect. Therefore this organism evolved” (Nelson 2002: 678). Here he is misrepresenting Gould by taking his argument about suboptimal design in the second, kludgy, sense as about suboptimal design in the first sense. Later, considering the panda in particular, Nelson writes, “other observers heap praise on the panda’s use of its forelimbs” (Nelson 2002: 690, emphasis in original), citing such praise from &lt;i&gt;The Giant Pandas of Wolong&lt;/i&gt; (Schaller and others 1986). But, again, whether the panda’s thumb is suboptimally designed in the first sense is irrelevant to Gould’s question of whether the panda’s thumb is a kludge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the third problem is spurious. I conclude that none of the problems that Questor sees in Gould’s and Teller’s argument is at all compelling. And it is hard to avoid reaching the conclusion that she — and hence the authors of WDGDWI — are disingenuous in their purported desire to explore the issues raised by it in a fair and careful manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s Diogenes Got to Do with It?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is surprising that Questor quotes “the Greek philosopher Diogenes” as saying,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The regularity of the season would not have been possible without intelligence, that all things should have their measure: winter and summer and night and day … [which] if one will study them will be found to have the best possible arrangement” (pages 74–75).&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For there were at least five ancient Greek philosophers named Diogenes: Diogenes of Oenoanda (a follower of Epicurus), Diogenes of Smyrna (a Protagorean), Diogenes of Sinope (the Cynic), Diogenes Laertius (the historian of philosophy), and Diogenes of Apollonia. As it happens, it is from the last of these that Questor quotes; the passage is from fragment B3 in the standard collection of Presocratic fragments (Diels and Kranz 1951–2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is Diogenes of Apollonia suddenly the hero of the intelligent design movement? Not due to his philosophical importance: Jonathan Barnes describes him as “essentially second-rate” and “a bore,” and declares that “[b]y common scholarly consent, he was least as well as last” of the Presocratic philosophers (Barnes 1993: 567–568). Edward Hussey says that his “general level of philosophical awareness suggests the age of Anaximenes” (Hussey 1972: 141), implying that he was about a century behind the times. Even his contemporaries were unimpressed by him: the playwrights Euripides and Aristophanes and the poet Philemon all poked fun at his philosophical views (Barnes 1993: 580, 645n3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer, I suggest, is provided by the fact that the passage from B3 is generally considered to be “the first extant exposition of the Teleological Argument for the existence of God, or the Argument from Design” (Barnes 1993: 577).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for the proponents of intelligent design, their hero’s conception of the intelligent designer is not congenial for their purposes. The intelligent designer of which Diogenes speaks in B3 is revealed in B5 to be — believe it or not — &lt;i&gt;air&lt;/i&gt;. “And it seems to me that that which possesses intelligence is what men call air … For it is this which seems to me to be god” (Barnes 1987: 291). To be fair, he adds in B8 that “it is great and strong, eternal and immortal, and knows many things” (Barnes 1987: 292), but it is easy to see why his views were derided by his contemporaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not just the embarrassing airiness of Diogenes’ intelligent designer that disqualifies him as a suitable emblem for the intelligent design movement, however, but the fact that Diogenes embraced the bête noire of intelligent design: methodological naturalism. Like the rest of the Presocratic philosophers, Diogenes was no atheist, but also like them, he believed that the gods do not interfere with the natural world: for these thinkers, the world was orderly arranged without being divinely administered. Reflecting scholarly consensus, Barnes writes that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Presocratic explanations are marked by several characteristics. They are, as I have said, &lt;i&gt;internal&lt;/i&gt;: they explain the universe from within, in terms of its own constituent features, and they do not appeal to arbitrary intervention from without. They are &lt;i&gt;systematic&lt;/i&gt;: they explain the whole sum of natural events in the same terms and by the same methods. Thus the general principles in terms of which they seek to account for the origins of the world are also applied to the explanations of earthquakes or hailstorms or eclipses or diseases or monstrous births. Finally, Presocratic explanations are &lt;i&gt;economical&lt;/i&gt;: they use few terms, invoke few operations, assume few “unknowns.” (Barnes 1987: 17, emphasis in original)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diogenes clearly was working within the naturalistic framework delineated by Barnes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, Newman and Wiester contend that “a &lt;i&gt;preexisting&lt;/i&gt; intelligence created and designed the universe, life and human beings” (page v, emphasis added), violating the internality principle. They contend that although “nobody in their right mind questions that some animals [doubly &lt;i&gt;sic&lt;/i&gt;: they presumably have species, not individuals, in mind, and they presumably do not wish to limit their claim to the animal kingdom] have changed some through the course of their existence on earth” (page 7), it is questionable in other cases, thus violating the systematicity principle. And it would be tedious to detail all the myriad ways in which they violate the economy principle. One example: when Teller remarks that the intelligent designer is “not exactly available for study or experiment,” Questor responds, “That doesn’t prove that an intelligence doesn’t exist, does it?” (pages 14–25). Arguing from ignorance to the existence of the supernatural is a paradigm of the uneconomical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Diogenes of Apollonia is not really the ancient Greek philosopher whom the intelligent design movement should be showcasing. Nor should it be Diogenes of Sinope either — it was he who, according to legend, walked about with a lantern, searching for an honest man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Anonymous]. Report on cartoon book, Darwinism for Skeptics. &lt;i&gt;Newsletter of the American Scientific Affiliation &amp;amp; Canadian Scientific and Christian Affiliation&lt;/i&gt; 1999 May/Jun; 41 (3): 5–6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barnes J. &lt;i&gt;Early Greek Philosophy&lt;/i&gt;. London: Penguin, 1987.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barnes J. &lt;i&gt;The Presocratic Philosophers&lt;/i&gt;, revised ed. London: Routledge, 1993.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behe M. J. &lt;i&gt;Darwin’s Black Box&lt;/i&gt;. New York: The Free Press, 1996.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Davis D. D. &lt;i&gt;The Giant Panda: A Morphological Study of Evolutionary Mechanisms&lt;/i&gt;. Chicago: Chicago Natural History Museum, 1964.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DeHaan R. F., Wiester J. L. The Cambrian explosion: the fossil record &amp;amp; intelligent design. &lt;i&gt;Touchstone&lt;/i&gt; 1999 Jul/Aug; 12 (4): 65–69.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diels H., Kranz W. &lt;i&gt;Die Fragmente der Vorsokratiker&lt;/i&gt;, 6th ed. Dublin and Berlin: Weidmann, 1951–2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forrest B. The wedge at work. In: &lt;i&gt;Intelligent Design Creationism and its Critics&lt;/i&gt;, ed. Pennock R. T. Cambridge MA: The MIT Press, 2002. pp. 3–53.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gould S. J. The panda’s thumb. In: Gould S. J. &lt;i&gt;The Panda’s Thumb: More Reflections in Natural History&lt;/i&gt;. New York: WW Norton &amp;amp; Company, 1980. pp. 19–26.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hussey E. &lt;i&gt;The Presocratics&lt;/i&gt;. New York: Scribners Press, 1972.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nelson P. A. The role of theology in current evolutionary reasoning. &lt;i&gt;Biology &amp;amp; Philosophy&lt;/i&gt; 1996; 11 (4): 493–517. Reprinted in: &lt;i&gt;Intelligent Design Creationism and its Critics&lt;/i&gt;, ed. Pennock R. T. Cambridge MA: The MIT Press, 2002. pp. 677–704.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newman R. C. Progressive creationism. In: &lt;i&gt;Three Views on Creation and Evolution&lt;/i&gt;, ed. Moreland J. P, Reynolds J. M. Grand Rapids MI: Zondervan Publishing House, 1999. pp. 105–133.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newman R. C., Eckelmann H. J. Jr. &lt;i&gt;Genesis One and the Origin of the Earth&lt;/i&gt;. Downers Grove IL: InterVarsity Press, 1977.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newman R. C., Wiester J. L. &lt;i&gt;What’s Darwin Got to Do With it?&lt;/i&gt; Downers Grove IL: InterVarsity Press, 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schaller G., Jinchu H., Wenshi P., Jing Z. &lt;i&gt;The Giant Pandas of Wolong&lt;/i&gt;. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1986.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wiester J. L. &lt;i&gt;The Genesis Connection&lt;/i&gt;. Hatfield PA: Interdisciplinary Biblical Research Institute, 1992.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wiester J. L. Wiester interviewed by BBC. &lt;i&gt;Newsletter of the American Scientific Affiliation &amp;amp; Canadian Scientific &amp;amp; Christian Affiliation&lt;/i&gt; 2000 Jan/Feb; 42 (1): 6–7.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Glenn Branch</name></author><summary type="html">Pandas at National Zoo in Washington. Photograph by Asiir. Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 2.5 Generic license. This is Part 2 of 2. You may find Part 1 here . The Third Problem “Finally, your story has a practical problem,” Questor says: “Is the panda’s thumb a poor design?” — whereupon a panda peeks its head through the panel and confides, “I rather like it, you know” (page 78). In essence, she is attacking premise (4) of Teller’s argument, by a clever appeal to the literature. Questor is presumably a college biology professor, and Wiester, who provided “the science input” for WDGDWI, is a college biology professor. Where do they go to get the information on the panda’s thumb? The Encyclopedia Americana, which Questor quotes as saying that the panda’s thumb “enables the panda to eat bamboo efficiently” and to “handle stems with great dexterity” (page 78, charmingly illustrated with a panda twirling stalks of bamboo in drum-major fashion). Gould, in contrast, consulted D. Dwight Davis’s monograph The Giant Panda (1964), which he characterized as “the greatest work of modern evolutionary comparative anatomy” (Gould 1980: 22). Regardless of the far-from-authoritative nature of their source, Newman and Wiester’s emphasis on the efficiency of the panda’s thumb reveals that they have again misrepresented Gould’s argument, apparently due to their conflation of two senses in which it is possible for design (or, if you prefer, “design”) to be suboptimal. In the first sense, a biological feature is suboptimally designed if it accomplishes its function not as efficiently as it (or a plausible substitute) might. Thus in the first sense, to say that the panda’s thumb is suboptimally designed is to say that it is not as useful for stripping leaves from bamboo as it (or a plausible substitute) might be. In the second sense, however, a biological feature is suboptimally designed if it is not designed as well as it might have been, that is, if the process whereby it acquired the ability to accomplish its function was not as efficient as it (or a plausible substitute) might have been. That there is such a sense of what it is for design to be suboptimal is testified to by the computer engineer’s word “kludge,” which refers to a clumsy and inelegant, but not necessarily ineffective, solution to a problem. In the second sense, to say that the panda’s thumb is suboptimally designed is to say that the process whereby it acquired the ability to strip leaves from bamboo was a kludge.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unlikely Allies: Biology Teachers and Creationists</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/unlikely-allies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unlikely Allies: Biology Teachers and Creationists" /><published>2024-04-22T07:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-04-22T07:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/unlikely-allies</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/unlikely-allies.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Braterman_Unlikely_Allies_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Journal cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am writing in response to the article &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.12775/SetF.2024.010&quot;&gt;Bridging ideological divides: Why Christians still disagree about evolution and what we whould do about it&lt;/a&gt;, by Hans Madueme and Todd Charles Wood, &lt;i&gt;Scientia et Fides&lt;/i&gt; 12(1), 2024, 189–213; open access &lt;a href=&quot;https://apcz.umk.pl/SetF/article/view/45459/38251&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is written by two young earth creationists, who take 25 closely argued pages including 93 references to show complete misunderstanding of the relationship between observation and interpretation in evolution science, in order to claim a false epistemic symmetry between this science and the theological perspective which forces them to reject it; a more sophisticated version of the “two pairs of spectacles” thesis that has been with us since George McCready Price. So why am I bothering to review this article? And why, to my own surprise, do I find myself welcoming its appearance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For three reasons. Firstly, because the authors, unlike “creation science” young earth creationists, accept the validity of the science in its own terms, rather than claiming that it is inferior to their own fantastical offerings. Secondly, because they lay out extremely clearly (and self-revealingly) their own epistemic position. And finally, because their recommendations, made regarding conversations within the evangelical community, are applicable (and indeed to some extent already applied) to the very practical problem of how to teach evolution science in places with a faith-based culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Todd Wood is a name that will be familiar to many readers here. He has a PhD from University of Virginia, conducted postdoctoral work for two years at Clemson, and has published five papers in leading journals on different aspects of molecular phylogeny. He is now applying his skills to baraminology, the attempt to explain the multiplicity of present species in terms of descent from the limited number that could have fitted onto Noah’s Ark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a joke. He describes his book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Understanding-Pattern-Life-Origins-Organization/dp/0805427147&quot;&gt;Understanding the Pattern of Life: Origins and Organization of the Species&lt;/a&gt;, in the preface, as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;an expression of my attempt, however feeble, to allow the truth of God to transform my view of biology. Rather than trying to prove the truth of Scripture, I use it as a starting point. From there, I build what I believe to be a reasonable model of biology that fits both the facts of Scripture and the data of creation.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://henrycenter.tiu.edu/contributor/hans-madueme/&quot;&gt;Hans Madueme&lt;/a&gt;, Associate Professor at Covenant College Georgia, appears to be highly regarded in his field, and has edited a volume, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomsbury.com/us/reading-christian-theology-in-the-protestant-tradition-9780567266149/&quot;&gt;Reading Christian Theology in the Protestant Tradition&lt;/a&gt;, published by Bloomsbury. Despite (or perhaps because of) his own convictions, he has &lt;a href=&quot;https://henrycenter.tiu.edu/2019/06/creationism-embattled-yet-resilient-a-redirect/&quot;&gt;been highly critical&lt;/a&gt; of claims made on behalf of creation science..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the authors are adamant in their own beliefs, they are opposed to polemics, and for this reason, as we shall see, single out for praise Jason Rosenhouse’s Among the Creationists (reviewed in PT &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2012/07/among-the-creat.html&quot;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core of their argument lies in the introduction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The scientific theory of evolution involves higher-level models that are associated with a range of non-scientific factors, including exegetical and theological judgments.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something seems (and indeed is) back to front here. Some scientists work for the greater glory of God, and some to put God out of business, while I expect that most have never given a thought to theological issues. Their conclusions may have implications in “exegetical and theological judgments,” but these are consequences, not components, of the scientific framework. Why do Wood and Madueme (W&amp;amp;M) think otherwise?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors spell out their position, early on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;[W]e argue that the scientific theory of evolution involves higher-level models that are shaped by non-scientific factors. We then show that theological commitments—held not only by Christians but by non-theists as well—affect those higher-level models that influence our epistemic assessment of evolution.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So non-theists ln their attitude to evolution science are influenced in ways that presumably they do not realize by theological commitments. As a non-theist and former theist who has always accepted mainstream evolution science on its merits, I consider this claim both unwarranted and presumptuous, and disconcertingly close to the claim made by many creationists that evolution is itself a form of religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, gradually, we find out what is behind the claim, and why it is crucial to the authors’ entire outlook. They admit the range and strength of the scientific evidence for common ancestry, which is the aspect of evolution science most directly relevant to their own theological concerns, and quote the appraisal by the philosophers McCain and Weslake:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The evidence for common ancestry includes the fossil record, comparative anatomy, embryology, genetics, and geographic species distribution, while natural selection gains support from natural and laboratory work, including computer simulations and mathematical models.&lt;sup&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And later:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Gijsbert van den Brink and his colleagues distinguish three different layers of evolutionary theory, namely, 1) historical evolution, 2) common descent, and 3) natural selection.2 They conclude that multiple, mutually reinforcing lines of evidence for historical evolution render it strongly beyond reasonable doubt. The evidence for common descent, they argue, is also strong though less than the evidence for historical evolution (“weaky beyond reasonable doubt”). They give the lowest evidential score to natural selection, given notable scientific disagreements about its importance in evolution (van den Brink et al. 2017, 466–68).&lt;sup&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt; Most scientists would agree with these conclusions.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I think would most readers here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How, then, could W&amp;amp;M maintain their own rejection of evolution? Easily! They have prepared the ground by saying (p. 198), in response to this classification,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;Common ancestry acts as a higher-level model that coordinates and supports more directly empirical models (like natural selection) within or beneath it.&lt;/i&gt; [Emphasis in original]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The keyword here is “supports.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. Common ancestry does not support the data. It is an outcome, not an input, much as process uniformitarianism is an outcome from looking at ancient rocks. Or, to take an example with which I do not think W&amp;amp;M could possibly disagree, atomic theory is the higher-level model used by chemists since long before they could observe the effects of individual atoms. However, this status is not an overarching presupposition, but the outcome of diverse observations, ranging from the combining ratios of elements to the properties of gases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors give another example of why they regard common ancestry as a higher-level model:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The fact that common ancestry was accepted during the eclipse of Darwinism indicates that scientists could accept this higher-level model independently of any details of how common ancestry came to be.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the contrary. Common ancestry continued to be accepted, even though (in W&amp;amp;M’s version of history) Darwin’s causal mechanism had been rejected, because of the way in which it was supported by the many lines of evidence that they themselves had listed. Bottom-up, not top-down. John Paul II &lt;a href=&quot;https://humanorigins.si.edu/sites/default/files/MESSAGE%20TO%20THE%20PONTIFICAL%20ACADEMY%20OF%20SCIENCES%20(Pope%20John%20Paul%20II).pdf&quot;&gt;got it right&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;It is indeed remarkable that this theory [evolution] has been progressively accepted by researchers, following a series of discoveries in various fields of knowledge. The convergence, neither sought nor fabricated, of the results of work that was conducted independently is in itself a significant argument in favor of this theory.&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If W&amp;amp;M do not see things this way, it is because they are committed to top-down reasoning. As they say, in a section titled “Evolution without theological presuppositions is impossible,”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Dogmatic commitments inevitably shape our overall judgments of the epistemic status of evolution. Theology is the epistemic linchpin.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They impose such dogmatic commitments even when they are absent.&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; Thus they cite Richard Dawkins’s famous remark, “Darwin made it possible to be an intellectually fulfilled atheist,” as evidence that our theology shapes our views on evolution, when Dawkin himself tells us that it was the other way round; learning about evolution led him to reject his former faith. This inverted perspective makes it possible for them to say in all seriousness,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Some epistemic judgments depend on how one evaluates the clarity of nature against the clarity of Scripture. Young-earth creationists tend to foreground the perspicuity of Scripture and the fallibility of science, while theistic evolutionists tend to emphasize the clarity of science and the ambiguity of exegesis.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My translation: Young earth creationists think that their own exegesis of Scripture and commitment to its truth gives them the right to overlook both the scientific evidence and the possibility that their exegesis itself may be in error. This on the basis of a false equivalence between the two epistemic evaluations: on the one side, a priori commitment to a doctrinal position, and on the other, willingness to pay attention to facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later they elaborate on this very point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;We agree with scientific realists that the objective data in creation should inform any assessment of evolution, but the process of interpreting the data should also entail theological oh judgments.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the authors are claiming the right to interpret facts to fit their theological preconceptions. If they do not like the outcome of a scientific enquiry, they will demand that the evidence be tortured until it says what they want to hear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, something interesting happens, that changes the reader’s perspective on everything that has gone before. Having established that for Christians like them, the epistemic status of evolution will depend on theological considerations, they then admit that Christians can reasonably disagree about this theology. Understandably, they deplore the way in which unbelievers and evolution-accepting believers alike regard young earth creationism as absurd. More surprisingly, they deplore the mirror-image attitude of young earth creationists such as Henry Morris and John MacArthur, who describe those who accept evolution as atheistic, irrational, and amoral. They invoke the great commandment to love one another, too often neglected as “we evangelicals find group identity and security in our confessions, doctrinal statements, and ideological consortiums,” and for this reason urge dialogue even when such dialogue seems impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors, I now belatedly realize, are not really talking to me but to those who share their own fundamental outlook. If they have been at great pains to affirm their own epistemic position, that is partly to establish their own credentials, and partly to suggest to their fellows that respectful treatment of a different epistemic position may be possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are practical reasons for the dialogue that they are commending. Evolution-accepting Christians should not be made to feel unwelcome in churches where they are in the minority. Conversely, creationism-accepting students should not be ignored or silenced in the science classroom. Here they cite the philosopher and former biology teacher Douglas Allchin, who discusses how to engage such students, and advocates examining epistemology, building trust, and considering evolution in the context of the moral order.&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; As practical examples of the mutually respectful attitude that they recommend, they quote at some length from Jason Rosenhouse’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Among-Creationists-Dispatches-Anti-Evolutionist-Front/dp/0199744637&quot;&gt;Among the Creationists&lt;/a&gt; (reviewed on PT &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2012/07/among-the-creat.html&quot;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;), with his emphasis on the enriching experience of seeing those we disagree with as real people, not merely defined by stereotypes and the oddity of their beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this also reminded me of James Krupa, award-winning biology professor at the University of Kentucky, who concludes his lectures with explicit discussion of social resistance to evolution.&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; Even more relevant is the approach being developed by Constance Bertka and colleagues.&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt; Here, as a prelude to the discussion of evolution, students consider the range of possible views on the relationship between religion and science, from conflict to integration. Comparing hermeneutics, just as W&amp;amp;M are advocating. A strange alliance, between those dedicated to the effective teaching of evolution science, and those who fundamentally oppose its conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is as different as possible from the attitude that runs through the mainstream creationist literature, from George McCready Price onwards, and that is expressed in the blurb&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt; to Wood’s own book, &lt;i&gt; Understanding the Pattern of Life&lt;/i&gt;, I mentioned earlier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Darwinian evolutionary theory has been largely recognized over the last century to be the most pervasive and damaging influence on modern society. As a frontal assault on the Kingdom, evolution has been Christianity's most notorious detractor and its greatest foe.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What has changed? The times have changed. As W&amp;amp;M put it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;In the North American context, the polarized and fractured political climate illustrates how sinful division can fester in the absence of ideological interaction. Sober reflection on the consequences of ideological segregation should motivate us to cultivate the true discipline of dialogue.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed. And we do not need more riots on the steps of the Capitol, or more pastors forced out of their congregations for showing independence of thought, or more memoirs like Tim Alberta’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Kingdom-Power-Glory-Evangelicals-Extremism/dp/006322688X &quot;&gt;The Kingdom, the Power, and the Glory&lt;/a&gt;, to show us what they mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Notes and References.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;McCain, Kevin and Brad Weslake 2013, “Evolutionary Theory and the Epistemology of Science.” In &lt;i&gt;The Philosophy of Biology: A Companion for Educators&lt;/i&gt;, edited by Kostas Kampourakis, 101–19. Dordrecht: Springer, p 106&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Van den Brink, Gijsbert, Jeroen de Ridder, and René van Woudenberg. 2017. “The Epistemic Status of Evolutionary Theory.” &lt;i&gt;Theology and Science&lt;/i&gt; 15(4): 454–72.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, evolutionary science does not consist of a single theory, but of numerous theories interacting. The Pope was aware of this, and spelled it out later in his message.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As also illustrated by their treatment of Denis Lamoureux’s position in the same Section.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Allchin, Douglas. 2013. “Sacred Bovines.” &lt;i&gt;The American Biology Teacher&lt;/i&gt; 75(2) : 144-147. https://doi.org/10.1525/abt.2013.75.2.16&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Krupa, James. “Defending Darwin.” &lt;i&gt;Orion&lt;/i&gt; March/April 2015:  https://orionmagazine.org/article/defending-darwin/&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Constance M. Bertka, Briana Pobiner, Paul Beardsley and William A. Watson, 2019. “Acknowledging students’ concerns about evolution: a proactive teaching strategy.” &lt;i&gt;Evo Edu Outreach&lt;/i&gt; (2019) 12:3. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12052-019-0095-0&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As shown on the &lt;i&gt;Alibris &lt;/i&gt;website. We do not know if Wood himself wrote this blurb, but it could hardly have been adopted without his approval.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman</name></author><summary type="html">I am writing in response to the article Bridging ideological divides: Why Christians still disagree about evolution and what we whould do about it, by Hans Madueme and Todd Charles Wood, Scientia et Fides 12(1), 2024, 189–213; open access here. This article is written by two young earth creationists, who take 25 closely argued pages including 93 references to show complete misunderstanding of the relationship between observation and interpretation in evolution science, in order to claim a false epistemic symmetry between this science and the theological perspective which forces them to reject it; a more sophisticated version of the “two pairs of spectacles” thesis that has been with us since George McCready Price. So why am I bothering to review this article? And why, to my own surprise, do I find myself welcoming its appearance? For three reasons. Firstly, because the authors, unlike “creation science” young earth creationists, accept the validity of the science in its own terms, rather than claiming that it is inferior to their own fantastical offerings. Secondly, because they lay out extremely clearly (and self-revealingly) their own epistemic position. And finally, because their recommendations, made regarding conversations within the evangelical community, are applicable (and indeed to some extent already applied) to the very practical problem of how to teach evolution science in places with a faith-based culture.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fisher, Fitness, and the Fundamentals of Population Genetics</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/fisher-fitness-fundamentals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fisher, Fitness, and the Fundamentals of Population Genetics" /><published>2024-04-19T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-04-19T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/fisher-fitness-fundamentals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/fisher-fitness-fundamentals.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Hancock_Fig_1_Ronald_Fisher_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;R. A. Fisher.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Figure 1. R.A. Fisher (1890-1962).&lt;small&gt;Credit: Wikimedia Commons, photograph by 2240281ananyapstaiju. Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0).&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Zachary Hancock is a postdoctoral researcher at the University of Michigan and specializes in evolutionary genetics.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evolution by natural selection requires that there exists variation in fitness between individuals. This simple truism goes back to Darwin’s Origin of Species, but where Darwin relied on verbal arguments, the statistician and population geneticist R.A. Fisher sought to codify this basic fact mathematically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1930, Fisher published The Genetical Theory of Natural Selection, and within introduced the fundamental theorem of natural selection (FTNS). The FTNS is, in effect, a restatement of Darwin’s idea on the reliance of natural selection on variation. In words, the FTNS states that the rate of change in a population’s average fitness is equal to the additive genetic variance in fitness at that time. An implication of this is that when there’s a ton of variation in fitness, the population’s average fitness can increase rapidly by natural selection. But if there is very little differences in fitness among individuals, any subsequent fitness increase must be slow or absent entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic idea behind the FTNS is quite simple, even if the derivation mathematically has caused many biologists to scratch their heads over the many decades since Fisher first introduced it. Some, like Warren Ewens (Ewens 1989), have argued that Fisher’s theorem is useless, while others, such as George Price (Price 1972), Alan Grafen (Grafen 2003), and Sean Rice (Rice 2004) have contended it is, indeed, a general theorem properly understood. Point here is that the FTNS has been a source of much debate for decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018, two creationists wandered into this rather esoteric historic dispute. And as is characteristic of creationists, they did so without a clear appreciation of the field they were embarking to critique and with highly suspect motivations. Bill Basener—a mathematician and data scientist at the University of Virginia—and John Sanford—retired Cornell plant geneticist, inventor of the gene gun, and promoter of “genetic entropy”—together (and “BS” hereafter) published a paper in the Journal of Mathematical Biology titled “The fundamental theorem of natural selection with mutations.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They had two goals. First, they wanted to hype the FTNS—they claim that it offered “mathematical proof of Darwinian evolution,” providing what they believed was the much sought after mechanism for perpetual fitness increase. Remember, to BS the definition of fitness is something like “net information” or “net functionality” (Basener et al. 2021). That is, a bacterium is simpler than a catfish, and thus has lower fitness. So, to them, the FTNS was an attempt to show how a bacteria-like organism can “progress” into something fancier and more complex (“from goo to the zoo to you,” as the saying goes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, they wanted to show that actually the FTNS is incomplete because it doesn’t consider where new mutations come from, and what their effect on fitness might be. And now we’ve moved from the enigmatic FTNS to, for readers of Panda’s Thumb, the much more familiar territory of genetic entropy. That’s right: BS add their own distribution of fitness effects (DFE) to the FTNS—one highly skewed towards deleterious alleles with a fraction of beneficial mutations of only 0.001—and then, using numerical simulations, show that fitness is expected to decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The punchline of BS is that the FTNS, while touted as a mathematical proof of Darwinian evolution, was actually derived under questionable assumptions (e.g., no dominance or epistasis) and when “corrected,” actually predicts fitness should decrease. Creationist news agencies had a field day with headlines such as “A Mathematical Proof of Darwinian Evolution Is Falsified” and “Flipping Fisher’s Famous Theorem.” Rob Carter of CMI published a YouTube video titled “Fisher’s failure and the dramatic end of Neo-Darwinism.” Juicy stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While many defenders of evolutionary biology have responded—including &lt;a href=&quot;http://theskepticalzone.com/wp/does-basener-and-sanfords-model-of-mutation-versus-selection-show-that-deleterious-mutations-are-unstoppable/&quot;&gt;Joe Felsenstein and Mike Lynch&lt;/a&gt;—these responses were either in blogs or in video format and tended to focus on the “genetic entropy” part of BS and argue that the FTNS was not foundational in any sense, given that &lt;a href=&quot;http://theskepticalzone.com/wp/does-all-of-evolutionary-theory-rest-on-fishers-fundamental-theorem/&quot;&gt; most of the mathematics of natural selection&lt;/a&gt; had been derived in the preceding decades. Ultimately, the status of the FTNS is immaterial to the “creation-evolution debate.” Fisher could’ve been dead wrong in his derivations and evolution—as understood by biologists—would still be true, and natural selection would still rely on variation in fitness to work. Overturning Fisher’s theorem does nothing to challenge Darwin’s original argument. Genetic entropy, on the other hand, is a critique with more substance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as both a population geneticist and a student of history, sympathetic to the view of Sean Rice and Alan Grafen of the generality of the FTNS, I couldn’t let BS slide. And BS (2018) is the closest Sanford has come to publishing his “genetic entropy” model in the peer-reviewed literature, so it seemed that we could kill two birds with one stone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan Stern Cardinale of Rutgers and I decided to pen a response to BS, which has been published in JMB titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00285-024-02077-w&quot;&gt;Back to the fundamentals: a reply to Basener and Sanford 2018&lt;/a&gt; (the title serves as a play on Fisher’s fundamental theorem and the obvious fact that BS have severely misread The Genetical Theory of Natural Selection, which many consider to be next in line in the great books on evolution to only Darwin’s own magnum opus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we had to clarify the assumptions of the FTNS. While BS contend it’s severely limited in its generality and assumes no dominance, epistasis, environmental effects, etc., we show that none of these are prerequisites for deriving the FTNS. To demonstrate this, we start from the famous Price Equation, which some have called the fundamental theorem of evolution (Queller 2017). We start here because the Price Equation is derived with no simplifying assumptions—it is a true general theorem. In words, it is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[rate of change of the average of some trait] = [covariance between that trait and fitness] + [difference between parent-offspring trait average]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, while fitness can be defined in many ways, in Price’s equation it is simply the number of offspring a parent leaves. Second, a covariance can be thought of as the shared change between two variables; for example, if longer fur is beneficial in a cold environment, then there will be a positive covariance between fur length (the trait) and how many offspring you leave (fitness). In this way, the Price Equation captures natural selection in the covariance term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FTNS is easily derived from this equation by simply letting “trait” be “fitness,” since parental fitness is expected to covary with offspring fitness—that is, fitness is heritable. Rewriting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[rate of change of average population fitness] = [covariance between parent and offspring fitness] + [difference between parent-offspring trait average]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice how this looks much like the definition of the FTNS stated earlier. The “covariance” term can be clarified if we remember a simple mathematical identity. Some might be familiar with the concept of linear regression; this is when you fit a straight line through a plot of points such that the line minimizes the distance between all the points. It turns out, the covariance between two terms (like parent and offspring fitness) is equal to the slope of that line multiplied by the variance in parent fitness. Again, variance here is simply the mean of the squares of the spread of values around the average—high variance means there is high variation around the average value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since linear regression is a straight line, we call the variance that they capture the additive genetic variance. This means that irrespective of the genetic architecture of a trait, selection acts to shift the mean of that trait as if it were simply additive. Consider the simple plot in Figure 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Hancock_Fig_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 2.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Figure 2. Demonstration of the “additive genetic variance.&quot; Here, W is parental fitness and Wo is offspring fitness. The rate that natural selection can shift the mean population fitness in each of these plots, despite the difference in genetic architecture, is equal to the slope of the red line (which is equivalent in both plots).
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice the slope of these is exactly the same, despite the trait clearly not being an additive trait in the second plot. Here, an “additive trait” means one in which every genetic locus contributing to the trait value does so as a simple sum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to remember that we are not performing a linear regression in the statistical sense of fitting a line to some data. Instead, we are relying entirely on mathematical identities: the definition of a covariance is [slope of a straight line as determined by least squares] × [variance of the independent variable].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By replacing the covariance term with this “additive genetic variance” term, we arrive at the classic way of viewing the FTNS: the rate of change in mean population fitness is equal to the additive genetic variance in fitness at that time. No simplifying assumptions were introduced. Fisher’s theorem is, it turns out, a general theorem, contrary to BS. Further, we see that the FTNS does not rely on there being no dominance or epistasis–it’s simply that natural selection acts on the additive variance irrespective of these. As James Crow once remarked, “Nature discovered least squares long before Gauss” (Crow 2008).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we deal with BS’s claim that Fisher thought fitness would perpetually increase and that he viewed the distribution of mutational effects as symmetrical, equal parts beneficial and equal parts deleterious. It’s easy to debunk these ideas with Fisher’s own words. In The Genetical Theory, Fisher writes: “Against the rate of progress in fitness must be set off, if the organism is, properly speaking, highly adapted to its place in nature, deterioration due to undirected changes either in the organism, or in its environment. The former, typified by the pathological mutations observed by geneticists… The latter, due to… changes in the organic environment, including improvement of enemies and competitors… may be in effect either greater or less than the improvement due to Natural Selection” (Fisher 1930). So clearly, Fisher thought that there were other forces in nature that could counterbalance natural selection, and hence the FTNS couldn’t be a “mathematical proof” of perpetual fitness increase. It only serves to illustrate that natural selection, as a single component, acts to increase fitness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then introduce Fisher’s geometric model of adaptation to counter BS’s claim that Fisher thought the effects of mutations were symmetrical. To understand Fisher’s model, imagine a landscape of phenotypes that have valleys of low and peaks of high fitness. Moving across this phenotypic landscape is akin to changing the mean phenotype of the population. If you are far from a fitness peak, then taking a big step through the landscape (that is, a mutation of large effect on the phenotype occurs) is equally likely to move you in the right direction as in the wrong. But if you’re on a peak, large effect mutations almost always take you off the peak. Hence, the effects of mutations are context dependent, and the context is how well adapted the population already is to the environment they’re in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is quite a different picture than how BS present Fisher’s views, and indeed how creationists often view the distribution of fitness effects (DFE). While they tend to present it as some fixed distribution, evolutionary biologists have never seen it that way; the effect of any mutation is dependent on the context in which it arose, both with respect to the environment but also with respect to the optimality of the trait in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, BS fumble Fisher’s views on mutations and fitness increase, and make false claims as to the assumptions necessary to derive the FTNS. The last thing we deal with is their claim that the FTNS, when it incorporates real mutational distributions, predicts fitness decline, not increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those familiar with Sanford’s “genetic entropy” model will already know where this is going. BS rely on a DFE from Kimura (1979) which was used to model effective neutrality and has no beneficial mutations; they add a tiny fraction—0.001—to that distribution and call it “real.” And, as stated above, they find fitness declines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since BS (2018) has been touted as a peer-reviewed paper supporting genetic entropy, we decided to perform our own simulations as a direct response with the (naïve) hope that it puts genetic entropy out to pasture once and for all. We pull distributions from several empirical studies, modelling the deleterious fraction as gamma-distributed and the beneficial as exponential, with 99% of all mutations strictly deleterious. Of the beneficial fraction, the mean effect is only 0.001, and so most merely act to compensate for the loss of fitness from the deleterious. Fitness is absolute in our simulations, so as the population accumulates deleterious mutations, it can slowly go extinct. We run our simulations for 50,000 generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In opposition to BS, not only did our populations not go extinct, but actually grew in size (Figure 3). While the vast majority of mutations were deleterious (and many fixed!), the overwhelming preponderance of mutations that fixed were beneficial due to positive selection. This is because the probability of fixation of beneficial mutations always exceeds that of deleterious, even if they are approximately equal as |s| = 1/(2N), where s is the selection coefficient and N is the population size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creationists often tout studies showing that the vast majority of mutations are deleterious as evidence of genetic entropy. But as many have argued in the past and as our simulations show, this is neither an impediment to evolution nor a hinderance on adaptation. Fitness can still increase despite deleterious mutation pressure because of natural selection. Indeed, this brings us back to the FTNS: since there are differences in the fitness of individuals, and those differences are heritable, natural selection can act to increase the population’s mean fitness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Hancock_Fig_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Figure 3. Observed population growth in our simulations despite the overwhelming preponderance of deleterious mutations and the relatively small advantages of the beneficial mutations (from Fig.3 in Hancock &amp;amp; Cardinale 2024). The different colors represent different replications of the calculation.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, BS misrepresent Fisher’s theorem by claiming it needs to be expanded to include mutations to introduce genetic entropy into a peer-reviewed journal. We argue in the last section of the paper that the “real target” of their assault on the FTNS was actually universal common descent. We expose this by simply letting their other publications speak for themselves, citing numerous examples in which they misrepresent both “fitness” and “Darwinian evolution.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope that this reply to BS serves to undermine the credibility of the original paper. And, in the end, clarify an important and often debated concept in evolutionary biology—the fundamental theorem of natural selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basener, W. F., &amp;amp; Sanford, J. C. (2018). The fundamental theorem of natural selection with mutations. Journal of Mathematical Biology, 76(7), 1589-1622.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hancock, Z. B., &amp;amp; Cardinale, D. S. (2024). Back to the fundamentals: a reply to Basener and Sanford 2018. Journal of Mathematical Biology, 88(5), 1-20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Queller, D. C. (2017). Fundamental theorems of evolution. The American Naturalist, 189(4), 345-353.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basener, W., Cordova, S., Hössjer, O., &amp;amp; Sanford, J. (2021). Dynamical systems and fitness maximization in evolutionary biology. In Handbook of the Mathematics of the Arts and Sciences (pp. 2097-2169). Cham: Springer International Publishing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fisher, R. A. (1930) The genetical theory of natural selection. Clarendon Press, Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ewens, W. J. (1989). An interpretation and proof of the fundamental theorem of natural selection. Theoretical population biology, 36(2), 167-180.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grafen, A. (2003). Fisher the evolutionary biologist. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society Series D: The Statistician, 52(3), 319-329.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rice, S. (2004). Evolutionary theory: mathematical and conceptual foundations. Sinauer Associates, Oxford University Press, Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crow, J. F. (2008). Commentary: Haldane and beanbag genetics. International journal of epidemiology, 37(3), 442-445.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Zach B. Hancock</name></author><summary type="html">Figure 1. R.A. Fisher (1890-1962).Credit: Wikimedia Commons, photograph by 2240281ananyapstaiju. Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 4.0 International license (CC BY-SA 4.0). Zachary Hancock is a postdoctoral researcher at the University of Michigan and specializes in evolutionary genetics. Evolution by natural selection requires that there exists variation in fitness between individuals. This simple truism goes back to Darwin’s Origin of Species, but where Darwin relied on verbal arguments, the statistician and population geneticist R.A. Fisher sought to codify this basic fact mathematically. In 1930, Fisher published The Genetical Theory of Natural Selection, and within introduced the fundamental theorem of natural selection (FTNS). The FTNS is, in effect, a restatement of Darwin’s idea on the reliance of natural selection on variation. In words, the FTNS states that the rate of change in a population’s average fitness is equal to the additive genetic variance in fitness at that time. An implication of this is that when there’s a ton of variation in fitness, the population’s average fitness can increase rapidly by natural selection. But if there is very little differences in fitness among individuals, any subsequent fitness increase must be slow or absent entirely. The basic idea behind the FTNS is quite simple, even if the derivation mathematically has caused many biologists to scratch their heads over the many decades since Fisher first introduced it. Some, like Warren Ewens (Ewens 1989), have argued that Fisher’s theorem is useless, while others, such as George Price (Price 1972), Alan Grafen (Grafen 2003), and Sean Rice (Rice 2004) have contended it is, indeed, a general theorem properly understood. Point here is that the FTNS has been a source of much debate for decades. In 2018, two creationists wandered into this rather esoteric historic dispute. And as is characteristic of creationists, they did so without a clear appreciation of the field they were embarking to critique and with highly suspect motivations. Bill Basener—a mathematician and data scientist at the University of Virginia—and John Sanford—retired Cornell plant geneticist, inventor of the gene gun, and promoter of “genetic entropy”—together (and “BS” hereafter) published a paper in the Journal of Mathematical Biology titled “The fundamental theorem of natural selection with mutations.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Intelligent Design for Dummies, Part 1</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/intelligent-design-dummies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intelligent Design for Dummies, Part 1" /><published>2024-04-18T09:09:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-04-18T09:09:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/intelligent-design-dummies</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/intelligent-design-dummies.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Branch_Part_1_Book_Cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book Cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Glenn Branch is deputy director of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/&quot;&gt;National Center for Science Education&lt;/a&gt;, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as &lt;/i&gt;Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher, &lt;i&gt;and the&lt;/i&gt; Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics&lt;i&gt;, and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of &lt;/i&gt;Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools&lt;i&gt; (2006). He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen Jay Gould’s discussion of the panda’s thumb in his essay of the same name, originally published in 1978, is often misrepresented as describing the false thumb of &lt;i&gt;Ailuropoda melanoleuca&lt;/i&gt; as ineffective in practice rather than as inelegant in origin. A recent incidence of such misrepresentation prompted Glenn Branch of the National Center for Science Education to provide his discussion of a similar misrepresentation in a 2000 cartoon presentation of intelligent design, originally published on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://metanexus.net/&quot;&gt;Metanexus: The Online Forum on Religion and Science&lt;/a&gt; website in two parts on August 15 and 16, 2002. The following appears here in conformity with Metanexus’s republication policy and with Branch’s permission. Minor changes, primarily regarding punctuation, have been made invisibly, and a few updates have been included in square brackets. This is part 1 of 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intelligent design, according to Michael Behe,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;must be ranked as one of the greatest achievements in the history of science. The discovery rivals those of Newton and Einstein, Lavoisier and Schrodinger, Pasteur, and Darwin. The observation of the intelligent design of life is as momentous as the observation that the earth goes around the sun or that disease is caused by bacteria or that radiation is emitted by quanta (Behe 1996: 232–233). &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a great scientific achievement, of course, deserves a careful exposition in a suitably scholarly format. But instead what it received is &lt;i&gt;What’s Darwin Got to Do With It&lt;/i&gt;? (henceforth, for brevity, WDGDWI), Robert C. Newman and John L. Wiester’s cartoon treatment of intelligent design (Newman and Wiester 2000).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WDGDWI is clearly a product of the notorious Wedge strategy for promoting intelligent design creationism, devised by Phillip Johnson (who lauds the book as “deadly accurate — and more fun than a barrel of Australopithecines”) and implemented by the Discovery Institute’s Center for the Renewal of Science and Culture [now &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/evolving-banners-discovery-institute&quot;&gt;Center for Science and Culture&lt;/a&gt;] (Forrest 2002). WDGDWI’s dedication thanks the DI’s CRSC for “its technical, critical and financial support” (page iv), and both Janet and Jonathan Moneymaker, who collaborated with Newman and Wiester on the book, are [as of 2002] Fellows of the CRSC. (According to Newman’s posting on Amazon.com’s page for WDGDWI [no longer available], the cartoons are mainly Janet Moneymaker’s, the story line is mainly due to Newman and Jonathan Moneymaker, and the bulk of the task of providing “the science input” was Wiester’s.) Access Research Network, a “research partner” of the CRSC, is currently [as of 2002] promoting WDGDWI as part of its Teachers’ Origin Resource Kit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be sure, neither Newman nor Wiester is directly associated with the DI’s CRSC. Newman is [now emeritus] professor of New Testament at Biblical Theological Seminary in Hatfield, Pennsylvania [now &lt;a href=&quot;https://missio.edu/&quot;&gt;Missio Seminary&lt;/a&gt; in Philadelphia], and director of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ibri.org/about/&quot;&gt;Interdisciplinary Biblical Research Institute&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;a group of Christians who see a desperate need for men and women convinced of the complete reliability of the Bible who will: (1) get training both in Biblical studies and in some other academic discipline, and (2) use this training to help other Christians deal with the many areas where non-Christian teaching is so dominant today. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IBRI is also thanked in the dedication of WDGDWI for its financial support. Wiester is [as of 2002] a part-time instructor in biology at Westmont College in Santa Barbara, California, and the chairman of the Science Education Commission of the American Scientific Affiliation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WDGDWI purports to be “a friendly conversation about evolution” that “makes sense” of “Darwin, creationism, and intelligent design” for high school students; the conversation takes place between Professor Teller, “an advocate of Darwinism” (page vi), and Professor Questor, who disavows the label “creationist,” preferring instead to be known as a design theorist (page 7); the message implicit in their surnames is too obvious to require comment. It is instructive to compare Questor’s disavowal with what Newman wrote 25 years ago: “We advocate a third, intermediate view usually labeled ‘progressive creationism’” (Newman and Eckelmann 1977: 11). As late as 1999, he declared himself to be an old-earth, or progressive, creationist (Newman 1999: 105). Wiester is cagier about his allegiances, staunchly insisting that the issue is not between creationism and evolution but between Darwinism and intelligent design (Wiester 2000). But his &lt;i&gt;The Genesis Connection&lt;/i&gt; (Wiester 1992) is identified as a work of old-earth creationism by none other than his present collaborator (Newman 1999: 107n1). Still, WDGDWI proclaims, and largely complies with, the thesis that “[d]esign theory is not derived from religious authority nor from appeals to Scripture” (page 136).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before its publication, WDGDWI was heralded in various sectarian publications under several different names: &lt;i&gt;Darwin Ate My Homework&lt;/i&gt; (DeHaan and Wiester 1999: 65); &lt;i&gt;Darwinism for Skeptics&lt;/i&gt; ([Anonymous] 1999). I think that &lt;i&gt;Intelligent Design for Dummies&lt;/i&gt; would have been better (with due apologies to IDG Books Worldwide, the publisher of the “For Dummies” books). A pedant, Bertrand Russell quipped, is a man who likes his statements to be true; pedantry in Russell’s sense was in no way involved in the production of WDGDWI. I propose to remedy the lack by carefully examining Newman and Wiester’s treatment of the panda’s thumb, discussed on pages 72–78 of WDGDWI, which represents the general level of discussion of the book. Even in the limited space of these six pages, it becomes quite clear that, to paraphrase Gibbon’s observation about Augustine, their learning is too often borrowed, and their arguments are too often their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discussion of the panda’s thumb begins when Teller, throwing up his hands, expostulates,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; Well, even if you can raise some questions about whether Darwinism is the only way to explain living things, they certainly weren’t made by an all-wise God. Consider the panda, for example (page 72). &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newman and Wiester then write, “According to Stephen Jay Gould, the panda’s thumb is proof of Darwinism. Imperfect design proves that the creative power at work is not intelligent” (page 73). WDGDWI is of course not a scholarly treatise and contains no footnotes — but remember Chick Publications’ comic book tract &lt;i&gt;Big Daddy?&lt;/i&gt;, which is replete with footnotes from the Institute for Creation Research and Kent Hovind? — but the appendix on background information refers to &lt;i&gt;The Panda’s Thumb&lt;/i&gt;, and presumably the first essay in it (Gould 1980). Newman and Wiester paraphrase Gould’s famous discussion, putting part of it in the mouth of Teller (and managing to reproduce the punctuation incorrectly, if harmlessly, in a verbatim quotation). Questor replies, “I have three problems with your story” (page 73).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The First Problem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questor quotes a passage from the ancient Greek philosopher Diogenes (whose surprising presence here is discussed below) to the effect that the regularity of the seasons is evidence for intelligent design; schematically, Diogenes is arguing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The seasons are arranged in the best possible way. If something is arranged in the best possible way, then it was designed. Therefore, the seasons were designed.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument elicits the following protest from Teller: “You can’t call it design just because it happens to fit your idea of the way it ought to be” (page 75). Questor then pounces: “My point exactly! Just because the thumb doesn’t fit Gould’s idea of what a thumb should be, how can he conclude that it isn’t designed?” Her point presumably is that if Teller objects to Diogenes’ argument, then he is committed to object to Gould’s argument — crudely,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The panda’s thumb is not arranged in the best possible way. If something was designed, then it is arranged in the best possible way. Therefore, the panda’s thumb was not designed.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— on the same grounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teller’s response is ambiguous. To which premise of Diogenes’ argument is he objecting? If he is objecting to the second premise (that if something is arranged in the best possible way, then it was designed), as the wording of his protest suggests, then Questor’s contention that his objection applies to Gould’s argument is false. Gould’s argument uses, not the second premise of Diogenes’ argument, but its converse (that if something was designed, then it is arranged in the best possible way), which is not logically equivalent to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In light of a later description (page 76) of the issue as whether the panda’s thumb is “pleasing to a human observer,” it is perhaps plausible to take Teller as rejecting the first premise on the grounds that judgments about whether or not something is arranged “in the best possible way” are subjective, reflecting only matters of personal preference, and consequently not suitable data for scientific inquiry. But there is no necessity to construe the first premise of Gould’s argument as subjective; it is in principle possible to provide objective biomechanical criteria by which to assess his judgment that “[t]he sesamoid thumb wins no prize in an engineer’s derby” (Gould 1980: 24). (In fairness, if it is possible to provide objective criteria by which to evaluate the first premise of Diogenes’ argument, Teller should retract his objection to it; it is still open to him to reject the argument by rejecting its second premise.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the first problem, whatever it is, is spurious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Second Problem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Secondly,” Questor continues, “your argument has a logical problem” (page 76). Scribbling on a handy blackboard, she represents Teller’s (and Gould’s) argument as follows (pages 76–77, emphasis in original).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;1) If there is a God, He would be ABLE to make organisms with features that are pleasing to a human observer. 2) If he were ABLE to, he WOULD HAVE done so. 3) A practical example is that God would have given the pandas a real thumb. 4) Pandas do not have a real thumb. 5) Hence, God did not make the panda’s thumb. 6) Therefore, Darwinism, the only alternative, produced the thumb.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questor says that (1) is “debatable, moot, and probably irrelevant” (page 76), a charge remarkable for its vacuity. First, the word “moot” is ambiguous between “debatable” and “irrelevant”; either way, then, the charge is redundant. Second, no doubt (1) is debatable, but Questor chooses not to debate it: “debatable, moot, and probably irrelevant” is all she says. Third, if the task at hand is evaluating the soundness of the argument, (1) is hardly irrelevant: the argument is sound only if (1) is true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is just as well, however, that (1) receives no further attention from Questor, for neither Gould nor the hapless Teller asserted it. In both Gould’s argument and Teller’s version of it, what is under consideration is not whether certain biological features please human observers but whether certain biological features are optimally designed to accomplish their functions. The confusion here echoes the confusion about Teller’s objection to the first premise of Diogenes’ argument: the content of the premise is misrepresented, presumably because it is easier to attribute ineradicable subjectivity to our judgments about what is and is not pleasing than to our judgments about what is and is not optimally designed to accomplish its function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On premise (2), Questor comments, “That’s a theological proposition for which you have no evidence.” Leaving aside the oddity of Newman’s using “theological” as a term of objurgation when he teaches at Biblical Theological Seminary, what of it? Neither Gould nor Teller insists that the argument is wholly scientific in nature; hence there is no reason that they should be debarred from invoking theological propositions in their premises. As for whether there is evidence for (2), certainly any evidence for (2), or against (2), is not likely to be scientific, but again there is no reason to require it to be. As it stands, (2) is certainly in need of more support than it is given — the ancient problem of evil is implicated — but the question of its truth cannot simply be sidestepped by relegating it to the realm of theology. (Ironically, Questor argues similarly shortly thereafter: when Teller says, “Darwinism is still the best naturalistic theory we have,” Questor responds, “I want to know if it’s &lt;i&gt;true&lt;/i&gt;” [page 78, emphasis in original].) The same remarks apply, mutatis mutandis, to premise (3), also said by Questor to be theological.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summarizing, Questor says, “Premises 1–3 are purely theological. Statement 6 is not a conclusion. It’s a claim for which you provide no evidence. At best, it’s a faulty premise, and it’s certainly not justified by statements 1–4. Your conclusion might just as well have been, ‘Therefore, you drive a red car’” (page 77). Her judgment is noteworthy because it manifests Newman and Wiester’s failure to accord with their own exposition of argumentation (which, by the way, is itself rife with error). On page 29, they write, “In the study of logic, an ‘argument’ is a series of statements that tries to prove something,” and they add in a note that “the ‘something’ you’re trying to prove is usually called a &lt;i&gt;proposition&lt;/i&gt; or a &lt;i&gt;conclusion&lt;/i&gt;” (emphasis in original); the definition of “conclusion” is repeated on page 43. But clearly (6), by their definition, is a conclusion: it is the proposition that Teller is attempting to prove on the basis of the premises of the argument. Questor may believe that the argument to the conclusion (6) is unsound, but it is ludicrous to deny that it is indeed the conclusion of the argument. She fails to be even minimally consistent here: just two panels after denying that (6) is a conclusion, she refers to it as “your conclusion.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of Questor’s, and presumably Newman and Wiester’s, confusion about whether (6) is a conclusion, is the argument for (6) valid, or is Questor right to detect a logical problem in it? The subconclusion (5), that God did not make the panda’s thumb, in fact follows validly from the premises, interpreted charitably. (For example, it is necessary to supply the implicit premise that real thumbs are, and the panda’s thumb is not, optimally designed.) As for the conclusion (6), that “Darwinism, the only alternative, produced the thumb,” it is laughably misexpressed. For “Darwinism” is defined as “the belief that undirected mechanistic processes (primarily random mutation and natural selection) can account for all the diverse and complex organisms that exist” (page 10); since the panda’s thumb long predates this belief, it could hardly have been produced by it. Of course, Newman and Wiester intended to say that “Darwinian processes, the only alternative, produced the thumb.” Appropriately revised, and adding the implicit premise that Darwinian processes are the only alternative to divine creation, (6) follows validly from (5), belying Questor’s claim that there is a logical problem with the argument. There is not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, however, a serious exegetical problem with the argument. For the premises entail not only that God did not make the panda’s thumb, but also that God does not exist. (Reduced to their essentials, the premises Questor presents are: if God exists, pandas would have real thumbs; pandas do not have real thumbs. It follows that God does not exist.) Needless to say, Gould’s original argument neither proved nor attempted to prove the nonexistence of God. Whether the unwarranted imputation of atheism to Gould’s argument is due to incompetence or malice, it is clearly a blatant misrepresentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second problem thus is also spurious; in addition, Newman and Wiester’s discussion of the argument for which it is supposed to be a problem verges on the incoherent.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Glenn Branch</name></author><summary type="html">Glenn Branch is deputy director of the National Center for Science Education, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher, and the Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics, and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools (2006). He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers. Stephen Jay Gould’s discussion of the panda’s thumb in his essay of the same name, originally published in 1978, is often misrepresented as describing the false thumb of Ailuropoda melanoleuca as ineffective in practice rather than as inelegant in origin. A recent incidence of such misrepresentation prompted Glenn Branch of the National Center for Science Education to provide his discussion of a similar misrepresentation in a 2000 cartoon presentation of intelligent design, originally published on the Metanexus: The Online Forum on Religion and Science website in two parts on August 15 and 16, 2002. The following appears here in conformity with Metanexus’s republication policy and with Branch’s permission. Minor changes, primarily regarding punctuation, have been made invisibly, and a few updates have been included in square brackets. This is part 1 of 2. Intelligent design, according to Michael Behe, must be ranked as one of the greatest achievements in the history of science. The discovery rivals those of Newton and Einstein, Lavoisier and Schrodinger, Pasteur, and Darwin. The observation of the intelligent design of life is as momentous as the observation that the earth goes around the sun or that disease is caused by bacteria or that radiation is emitted by quanta (Behe 1996: 232–233). Such a great scientific achievement, of course, deserves a careful exposition in a suitably scholarly format. But instead what it received is What’s Darwin Got to Do With It? (henceforth, for brevity, WDGDWI), Robert C. Newman and John L. Wiester’s cartoon treatment of intelligent design (Newman and Wiester 2000).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Toxicodendron sp.</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/Toxicodendron-sp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Toxicodendron sp." /><published>2024-04-15T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-04-15T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/Toxicodendron-sp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/Toxicodendron-sp.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/P1021025-Poison_Ivy_Berries_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Poison ivy berries&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poison_ivy&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Toxicodendron&lt;/i&gt; sp.&lt;/a&gt;, judging by a range map &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toxicodendron_radicans&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, probably &lt;i&gt;T. rydbergii&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; poison ivy. As I was taking the picture, someone came by and announced, &quot;Berries white, run in fright,&quot; which is pretty good advice. For a picture of poison ivy leaves with their characteristic mitten shape, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2015/11/toxicodendron-r1.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The leaves may be &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2015/12/toxicodendron-ry.html&quot;&gt;red in the fall&lt;/a&gt;; but they are not always red.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To see comments on this post click below:&lt;/i&gt; &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Toxicodendron sp., judging by a range map here, probably T. rydbergii &amp;ndash; poison ivy. As I was taking the picture, someone came by and announced, &quot;Berries white, run in fright,&quot; which is pretty good advice. For a picture of poison ivy leaves with their characteristic mitten shape, see here. The leaves may be red in the fall; but they are not always red. To see comments on this post click below:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“The song of the cell” by Siddhartha Mukherjee: review</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/song-cell-mukherjee.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“The song of the cell” by Siddhartha Mukherjee: review" /><published>2024-04-03T08:15:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-04-03T08:15:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/song-cell-mukherjee</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/song-cell-mukherjee.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2024/Mukherjee_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Joel Eissenberg is Professor of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology at Saint Louis University School of Medicine. He is the author of the recent PT article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/04/how-humans-lost-tails.html&quot;&gt;How humans lost their tails&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a college junior, I took a course in microbial genetics. The text was Gunter Stent’s &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Molecular-Genetics-Introductory-Gunther-Stent/dp/0716710285&quot;&gt;Molecular Genetics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. I map the beginning of my career as a geneticist to that course. Stent’s book is a history of the origins of molecular biology, and in retrospect, I believe it was the combination of the history and the science that beguiled me. This potent combination is on offer in Siddhartha Mukherjee’s &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Song-Cell-Exploration-Medicine-Human/dp/1982117354/&quot;&gt;The Song of the Cell&lt;/a&gt;: An Exploration of Medicine and the New Human&lt;/i&gt;. I generally avoid popular science books in my field, but this book was a gift from my daughter. I had read and enjoyed Mukherjee’s &lt;i&gt;The Emperor of all Maladies&lt;/i&gt;, so I was hoping for something special. I was not disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The factual information about cells and their roles in tissues and organs, and in disease were well established by the time most of us learned it in school, we mostly learned it by rote. Mukherjee uses the history of scientific discoveries about cells to show us not only each discovery, but also the context in which it was made and the impact it had on thinking at the time. Indeed, the book is chock-a-block with historical anecdotes. Many of these discoveries were controversial at the time, like germ theory as the basis for putrefaction and for disease. The esteemed evolutionary biologist Ernst Mayr mocked Carl Woese’s proposal of Archea as a third kingdom of life; Mayr was wrong and Woese was vindicated. Even today, the origins of eukaryotic cells are still controversial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mukherjee is a marvelous storyteller. For example, he tells the story that when lipids were extracted from a carefully measured number of red blood cells and spread out on a surface, the area was twice that necessary to contain that number of cells, pointing to a lipid bilayer, rather than monolayer. He is very effective at explaining how discoveries emerge at the confluence of scientific disciplines; e.g., the marriage of microscopy and biochemistry to define the functions of various organelles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the evolutionary biologist, Mukherjee discusses the evolution of multicellularity from free-living single cells. As a model, he describes experiments that selected for multicellular clusters of budding yeast. As the clusters grew larger and larger, a subset of cells appeared across the center of the cluster and underwent apoptosis (cellular suicide) to divide the single cluster into two smaller clusters. While certainly artificial, these experiments demonstrate how selection can result in the acquisition of a new property resembling multicellular cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a set-up for a discussion of the community of cells we call embryos. There is a lovingly detailed description of the Spemann-Mangold discovery of the early embryonic “organizer.” The narrative then pivots to describe the infamous case of the anti-anxiety drug thalomide and its teratogenic side effects. The hero of that story was Frances Kelsey, Chief of the Division of New Drugs when Merrell sought to market thalidomide in the US as a sedative. She stood as the lone bulwark against the approval of thalidomide, thus preventing unnumbered birth defects, miscarriages, and stillbirths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mukherjee is a hematologist, so blood cells enjoy pride of place in this book. Blood transfusion was the first cellular therapy. It advanced modern surgery, safe childbirth, and cancer chemotherapy. There is an interesting history of blood clotting and the discovery of its role in heart attacks. The topic of immunology is launched with the ancient history of inoculation for smallpox (a.k.a., variolation) and its western descendant, Jenner’s vaccine. Until I read this book, I didn’t know that the history of antibody discovery began with Paul Ehrlich, who coined the word antibody, and immunity to snake venom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem of how antibody diversity arises was a vexed one for decades, and Mukherjee has an amusing digression on the topic involving Linus Pauling. (A bit of personal history: the problem of antibody diversity was still unsolved when I was a microbiology major in college, and resulted in my aborted infatuation with immunogenetics. Fortunately, the mechanism was worked out by Susumu Tonegawa before I got too far into the weeds, and I went in a different genetics direction.) The complex cell biology of the immune response can be overwhelming, but Mukherjee brings the narrative within grasp using metaphors, engaging anecdotes and lively turns of phrase, while either eliding distracting details or relegating them to footnotes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of César Milstein’s invention of hybridomas—fusions of B-cells (a type of white blood cell) and tumor cells—and the resulting monoclonal antibodies at Cambridge University is a riveting one, intimately bound up with the lethal politics of Argentina at the time. Mukherjee notes that the UK government failed to patent this transformative technology in the belief that it would have no immediate practical application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An aspect of immunology that I’ve always found daunting is T-cell biology. T-cells are another type of white blood cell, and Mukherjee does a superb job of simplifying this branch of immunology without dumbing it down. Key to the cell-cell communication that underpins immunity is distinguishing self from non-self. The puzzle of how this works was solved through a combination of genetics, cell biology, and structural biology, and it makes for engrossing reading. Mukherjee shows how this knowledge is now being harnessed for new anti-cancer therapies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our immune system is in an ongoing arms race with pathogens. How this arms race played out with the SARS-CoV-2 virus in the early stages of COVID-19 pandemic is dramatically narrated. In some patients, the infection triggered a massive cellular over-reaction in the form of a cytokine storm—a hyperactive and dysfunctional inflammatory response that killed patients. As someone who enrolled in the Phase III Moderna trial, I remember hoping I’d be in the vaccine wing of the blinded trial. I was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From blood, the narrative shifts to organs. How the heart muscle contracts and how it coordinates the contractions are designed into its cells. The cellular organization of neurons in the brain was only beginning to be understood at the end of the 19th century, a testament to advances in histological staining and microscopy. That nerves were conduits for electrical impulses became clear by the 1930’s. But detailed histology showed that nerve cells were not physically joined like wires, but separated by small gaps. Mukherjee describes the simple but elegant experiments that led to the discovery of acetylcholine as a chemical neurotransmitter that bridged the gaps between these cells. He speculates on how a system of wires modulated by chemicals might have evolved. In addition to neurons, our brains have glial cells that perform several roles, among them sculpting the connections between neurons. Mukherjee then tells a personal story of his bout of clinical depression to connect us personally with the role of serotonin in regulating mood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The section on the pancreas includes a cinematic description of the original dog experiments by Banting and Best; these led to the discovery of insulin, which is secreted by the pancreatic beta cells. After decades of work, clinical trials using stem cells forced to differentiate into beta cells are proving therapeutic in Type I diabetics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stem cells get their own chapter. Mukherjee begins poignantly by describing the victims of the Hiroshima atom bomb who survived the initial blast and the radiation sickness, only to sicken and die of anemia and loss of immune cells due to death of the stem cells in the bone marrow. Interest in stem cells began in the 19th century, but by the early 20th century it had given way to other aspects of cell biology. It was radiation biology that revived stem cell research in the 1950’s. From studies of bone marrow transplantation in irradiated mice emerged the unexpected finding that all blood cells originated from a single rare—one in ten thousand—precursor cell in the marrow. By 1960, the first successful human bone marrow transplant, and thus the first stem cell therapy, had been performed. In this case, the donor was an identical twin, and it took many years and many patient deaths to work out how to use unrelated donors successfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mukherjee points out that cancer cells have properties shared with stem cells. He discusses evidence that stem cells can become cancer cells, and that some cancers contain “cancer stem cells” that renew the cancer after chemotherapy in analogy to the way that healthy stem cells renew organs and tissue during our lifetimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why are we built from cells? Mukherjee says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Recall that unicellular organisms evolved into multicellular organisms—not just once but many independent times. The driving forces that goaded that evolution, we think, were the capacity to escape predation, the ability to compete more effectively for scarce resources, and to conserve energy by specialization and diversification. Unitary blocks—cells—found mechanisms to achieve this specialization and diversification by combining common programs (metabolism, protein synthesis, waste disposal) with specialized programs (contractility in the case of muscle cells, or insulin-secreting capacity in pancreatic beta cells). Cells coalesced, repurposed, diversified—and conquered.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t do justice in this review to a book that so effectively and seamlessly melds science, history, and philosophy. Science is more than collecting facts. It is a human endeavor of experience and interpretation. While I was well acquainted with most of the factual content in this book, the writing revitalized this familiar territory as a charming and engaging new synthesis, like listening to fresh improvisations on familiar jazz standards. Song of the cell indeed!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joel Eissenberg</name></author><summary type="html">Joel Eissenberg is Professor of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology at Saint Louis University School of Medicine. He is the author of the recent PT article, How humans lost their tails. As a college junior, I took a course in microbial genetics. The text was Gunter Stent’s Molecular Genetics. I map the beginning of my career as a geneticist to that course. Stent’s book is a history of the origins of molecular biology, and in retrospect, I believe it was the combination of the history and the science that beguiled me. This potent combination is on offer in Siddhartha Mukherjee’s The Song of the Cell: An Exploration of Medicine and the New Human. I generally avoid popular science books in my field, but this book was a gift from my daughter. I had read and enjoyed Mukherjee’s The Emperor of all Maladies, so I was hoping for something special. I was not disappointed. The factual information about cells and their roles in tissues and organs, and in disease were well established by the time most of us learned it in school, we mostly learned it by rote. Mukherjee uses the history of scientific discoveries about cells to show us not only each discovery, but also the context in which it was made and the impact it had on thinking at the time. Indeed, the book is chock-a-block with historical anecdotes. Many of these discoveries were controversial at the time, like germ theory as the basis for putrefaction and for disease. The esteemed evolutionary biologist Ernst Mayr mocked Carl Woese’s proposal of Archea as a third kingdom of life; Mayr was wrong and Woese was vindicated. Even today, the origins of eukaryotic cells are still controversial. Mukherjee is a marvelous storyteller. For example, he tells the story that when lipids were extracted from a carefully measured number of red blood cells and spread out on a surface, the area was twice that necessary to contain that number of cells, pointing to a lipid bilayer, rather than monolayer. He is very effective at explaining how discoveries emerge at the confluence of scientific disciplines; e.g., the marriage of microscopy and biochemistry to define the functions of various organelles.</summary></entry></feed>