<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-11-16T15:11:15-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Aurora borealis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/aurora-borealis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aurora borealis" /><published>2025-11-12T09:15:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-11-12T09:15:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/aurora-borealis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/aurora-borealis.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Vivian Dullien&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/IMG_0772_Vivian_Aurora_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aurora borealis&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2025/11/12/nx-s1-5274739/northern-lights-aurora-borealis-solar-storms&quot;&gt;Aurora borealis&lt;/a&gt; seen last night at 10 pm in Boulder, Colorado. 1-s exposure at F/1.8 with a smart phone  at ISO 4000, exposure bias 0.1.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Vivian Dullien. Aurora borealis seen last night at 10 pm in Boulder, Colorado. 1-s exposure at F/1.8 with a smart phone at ISO 4000, exposure bias 0.1.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Anolis carolinensis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/anolis-carolinensis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Anolis carolinensis" /><published>2025-11-10T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-11-10T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/anolis%20carolinensis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/anolis-carolinensis.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Denelsbeck_Anolis_carolinensis2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ring of Brodgar (henge)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://herpsofnc.org/green-anole/&quot;&gt;Anolis carolinensis&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Carolina or green anole. Mr. Denelsbeck writes that this anole &quot;regrew its detached tail, but forked &amp;ndash; I've seen photos but this was the first that I'd found an example of myself, right on the downspout by the front door last November [2023]. Unfortunately, despite keeping a wary eye out, I have not spotted it since. Based on some scarring, this might have been the same one that I found without a tail back in April of that year, which if true, would give a rough time frame of how long it takes to regrow. Canon 7D, Canon 18-135 STM, handheld, cropped.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Al Denelsbeck. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Anolis carolinensis &amp;ndash; Carolina or green anole. Mr. Denelsbeck writes that this anole &quot;regrew its detached tail, but forked &amp;ndash; I've seen photos but this was the first that I'd found an example of myself, right on the downspout by the front door last November [2023]. Unfortunately, despite keeping a wary eye out, I have not spotted it since. Based on some scarring, this might have been the same one that I found without a tail back in April of that year, which if true, would give a rough time frame of how long it takes to regrow. Canon 7D, Canon 18-135 STM, handheld, cropped.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Video: Something Weird Happens When You Simulate Lifeless Molecules</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/video-something-weird.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Video: Something Weird Happens When You Simulate Lifeless Molecules" /><published>2025-11-03T15:04:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-11-03T15:04:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/video-something-weird</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/11/video-something-weird.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Veritasium_Frontis_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A frame from the video, showing differently colored fish&quot; /&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am going to step out of my lane again and tout this video, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XX7PdJIGiCw&quot;&gt;Something Weird Happens When You Simulate Lifeless Molecules&lt;/a&gt;, by Veritasium. What happens is that you get (simulated) life, natural selection, and so on. Professional biologists will no doubt find something to carp about. I did not especially like the term, “survival of the fittest,” when I think he really meant “natural selection.” My first impression was that he may have been conflating origin of life with evolution, though they are certainly closely related. He kind of pushes the selfish gene theory, but also states some criticisms and states flatly that genetic drift can sometimes overcome natural selection. He notes that his model is an oversimplification, but then, as he says, all scientific models are oversimplifications. I will let a real biologist discuss whether evolution takes place at the level of the gene, the individual, or indeed the group. As for me, I thought it was a splendid video which in a half-hour or so gave a clear understanding of how life can develop from non-life and go on to evolve into, well, endless forms most beautiful and most wonderful, several of which make cameo appearances in the video.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I am going to step out of my lane again and tout this video, Something Weird Happens When You Simulate Lifeless Molecules, by Veritasium. What happens is that you get (simulated) life, natural selection, and so on. Professional biologists will no doubt find something to carp about. I did not especially like the term, “survival of the fittest,” when I think he really meant “natural selection.” My first impression was that he may have been conflating origin of life with evolution, though they are certainly closely related. He kind of pushes the selfish gene theory, but also states some criticisms and states flatly that genetic drift can sometimes overcome natural selection. He notes that his model is an oversimplification, but then, as he says, all scientific models are oversimplifications. I will let a real biologist discuss whether evolution takes place at the level of the gene, the individual, or indeed the group. As for me, I thought it was a splendid video which in a half-hour or so gave a clear understanding of how life can develop from non-life and go on to evolve into, well, endless forms most beautiful and most wonderful, several of which make cameo appearances in the video.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Looking Down the Tree – Exploring the Origins of Our Species: book report</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/looking-down-the-tree-report.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Looking Down the Tree – Exploring the Origins of Our Species: book report" /><published>2025-10-31T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-10-31T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/looking-down-the-tree-report</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/looking-down-the-tree-report.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Cruzan_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover.&quot; /&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Looking-Down-Tree-Evolutionary-Biology/dp/0197805167/&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Looking down the Tree – The Evolutionary Biology of Human Origins&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by Mitch Cruzan, Oxford University Press, October, 2025.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;We got news of Mitch Cruzan’s new book on human origins and invited him to write a short introduction, which you may see &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/looking-down-the-tree-preview.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. In the meantime, the publisher graciously sent a review copy, and I report on the book below.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mitch Cruzan is Professor of Biology at Portland State University and has by his reckoning been teaching evolutionary biology for 15 years. I recently read an advance copy of his new book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Looking-Down-Tree-Evolutionary-Biology/dp/0197805167/&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Looking down the Tree – The Evolutionary Biology of Human Origins&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Although I suppose I am a fellow traveler, I am not a biologist, and occasionally something went over my head. I wondered, therefore, who the book’s intended audience was. Not unlike a paleontologist, I searched within the book and immediately found on page 15, “You probably know about DNA from your biology courses.” I frankly thought that he should have aimed higher: it would not have taken much additional explanation to prepare a more popular book and not what I think amounts to a supplementary college text. Indeed, I thought that it would have been useful to have defined terms such as apocrine gland, homologous, and recombination for readers who have never had a biology course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cruzan argues convincingly that to understand our phenotypes, you have to look at our past, not our present. He thus begins each chapter with an anecdote from the daily life of a fictitious hominid he names Launua. Launua belongs to a clan that is barely surviving, having comparatively recently ventured into the savanna. Her clan is inbred (presumably not so much that it is deleterious) and held together by kin selection, or inclusive fitness. Cruzan sometimes seems to conflate inbreeding with kin selection and remarks that inbred populations display kin selection. Each chapter ends with a useful summary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cruzan asks, for example, why we have opposable thumbs. Not, as I understand it, because we need them for grasping, but initially because our upright posture necessitated an elongation of our big toes (not all our toes), and our hands followed along because they use the same regulatory genes. Here he uses the large thumb to introduce the concept of an exaptation, though later he uses the obsolete but more descriptive term preadaptation. Cruzan thinks,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The single most influential event in the history of our lineage was the transition to savannas and selection for bipedalism, which caused correlated changes in the hands of our ancestors.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cruzan argues that we lost our hair in favor of evaporative cooling. He argues further that we have hair on our heads for thermal regulation, which made me wonder why males (European males, anyway) often have heavy beards, not to mention more body hair than females. He does not discuss other animals that live on the savanna and are covered with hair. He uses head and body lice, which live in our hair, to cleverly deduce that we probably wore clothing made of woven fabric about 100,000 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A colleague of mine once remarked that if you want to get students’ attention, just say “testicle.” Cruzan tests this hypothesis in spades and explains in some detail why human males have large penises compared to other apes, and human females have correspondingly long vaginas. &lt;small&gt;(Spoiler alert: it is the other way around and comes about because of our large heads, not sexual selection.)&lt;/small&gt; I was not completely convinced by his claim that the human female breasts and buttocks are primarily for storing fat; anyone who has ever seen a picture of a baboon in estrus might propose a different hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grandmother hypothesis postulates that menopause evolved so that grandmothers would be available to help raise their grandchildren. In discussing this hypothesis, Cruzan claims that human females ovulate about once a month and thus run out of eggs. That seemed to me to be an anachronism; in nature, before contraception, they spent most of their adult lives pregnant or lactating, and possibly ovulated no more than a dozen or two times in their entire lives. Cruzan goes on to note, interestingly, that exclusive homosexuality is almost unique to humans and suggests that it is subject to selection even though homosexual men do not reproduce. Rather, he thinks they were helpers, similarly to the grandmothers. The argument is slightly abstruse and depends on the fact that humans have a constant sex drive, as opposed to the periodic sex drive in other animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final chapter is somewhat depressing, in a way. Cruzan observes that “many millions—probably billions—of individuals had to die [we all die; I think he means die prematurely] as small improvements accumulated generation after generation over the past four to six million years.” He goes on to say that today we “buffer” ourselves against natural selection by extending the lives of those who would otherwise not survive, and a decline in fitness is inevitable: “[D]eleterious mutations will continue to accumulate in populations with access to modern medicine,” and these mutations will become a challenge. Though he does not quite commit himself, he points out, “[S]ome evolutionary biologists have warned that we can expect declines in health and longevity in future generations.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that the file I got was something along the lines of a galley proof, but still I did not find a lot of errors. The figures did not all stand on their own, and I thought that nearly every one would have profited from a detailed caption, as well as more-specific discussions in the text. Phrases such as “You may remember from a previous chapter” would have been more useful had they cited the actual chapter. “Gene genealogy” seems very awkward to me and probably should have been “genetic genealogy”; Google’s search engine agreed by a score of 430,000 to 29,000. The text alternated between “descendent” and the more common “descendant”; I hope that problem was fixed before the book went to press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to know more? Get the book, read it – and, of course, comment below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgement&lt;/strong&gt;. Andrew Petto, Senior Lecturer Emeritus at the University of Wisconsin–Milwaukee, lavished many words commenting on this essay (though he did not read the book) and explained several topics that had been unclear to me. Any errors are my own or may be blamed on my speech-recognition program.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Looking down the Tree – The Evolutionary Biology of Human Origins, by Mitch Cruzan, Oxford University Press, October, 2025. We got news of Mitch Cruzan’s new book on human origins and invited him to write a short introduction, which you may see here. In the meantime, the publisher graciously sent a review copy, and I report on the book below. Mitch Cruzan is Professor of Biology at Portland State University and has by his reckoning been teaching evolutionary biology for 15 years. I recently read an advance copy of his new book, Looking down the Tree – The Evolutionary Biology of Human Origins. Although I suppose I am a fellow traveler, I am not a biologist, and occasionally something went over my head. I wondered, therefore, who the book’s intended audience was. Not unlike a paleontologist, I searched within the book and immediately found on page 15, “You probably know about DNA from your biology courses.” I frankly thought that he should have aimed higher: it would not have taken much additional explanation to prepare a more popular book and not what I think amounts to a supplementary college text. Indeed, I thought that it would have been useful to have defined terms such as apocrine gland, homologous, and recombination for readers who have never had a biology course. Cruzan argues convincingly that to understand our phenotypes, you have to look at our past, not our present. He thus begins each chapter with an anecdote from the daily life of a fictitious hominid he names Launua. Launua belongs to a clan that is barely surviving, having comparatively recently ventured into the savanna. Her clan is inbred (presumably not so much that it is deleterious) and held together by kin selection, or inclusive fitness. Cruzan sometimes seems to conflate inbreeding with kin selection and remarks that inbred populations display kin selection. Each chapter ends with a useful summary. Cruzan asks, for example, why we have opposable thumbs. Not, as I understand it, because we need them for grasping, but initially because our upright posture necessitated an elongation of our big toes (not all our toes), and our hands followed along because they use the same regulatory genes. Here he uses the large thumb to introduce the concept of an exaptation, though later he uses the obsolete but more descriptive term preadaptation. Cruzan thinks,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Looking Down the Tree – Exploring the Origins of Our Species</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/looking-down-the-tree-preview.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Looking Down the Tree – Exploring the Origins of Our Species" /><published>2025-10-29T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-10-29T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/looking-down-the-tree-preview</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/looking-down-the-tree-preview.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Cruzan_Cover_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover.&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Looking-Down-Tree-Evolutionary-Biology/dp/0197805167/&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Looking down the Tree – The Evolutionary Biology of Human Origins&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by Mitch Cruzan, Oxford University Press, October, 2025.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Mitch Cruzan is Professor of Biology at Portland State University. He received his BA and MA in Biology from California State University, Fullerton, and his PhD from Stony Brook University. He is currently an associate editor for Molecular Ecology, a leading journal in the field. He has published more than 80 papers in the primary literature and an advanced textbook, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Evolutionary-Biology-Perspective-Mitchell-Cruzan/dp/0190882670&quot;&gt;Evolutionary Biology: A Plant Perspective&lt;/a&gt;. His latest book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Looking-Down-Tree-Evolutionary-Biology/dp/B0FQYC1Q57&quot;&gt;Looking Down the Tree – Exploring the Origins of Our Species&lt;/a&gt;, is due to be published in a few days, and we have invited him to offer a preview here.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have offered an introductory course on evolution annually over the last 15 years. I always saved in-depth discussions of human evolution to the end for two reasons. First, to discuss human evolution in a meaningful way, we need to have a good understanding of evolutionary principles and processes. Second, I thought it was a good highlight for the course to end on. Each year, I incorporated new information and new ideas about human origins. Much of this content came from the questions that students asked; they weren’t satisfied to look a series of fossil remains or boring details about human genomics. They wanted to know more about the origins of our unique appearance and behaviors, and particularly secondary sexual characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does anyone take on a particular subject for a non-fiction book? You might ask, what could a plant evolutionary biologist such as myself possibly have to say about human evolution? Some reviewers actually said that I had no business writing this book. But evolutionary biology consists of a set of principles and processes that can be applied to any organism. Yes, it helps to have knowledge of the biology of a species, but for humans, that information is readily available. For me, developing the material was a natural process as I explored aspects of human evolution, along with the students in my introductory evolution lectures. By the time the pandemic hit, I had developed what I thought was a unique story of the origin of human traits – one that made sense in the context of the habitats our ancestors inhabited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book is not just a rehash of previous statements and ideas. By integrating information from disparate fields such as paleontology, anthropology, and genomics, I have drawn unique conclusions about the origins of human traits and behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading previous books and sources discussing human evolution on the web was frustrating because of how much misinformation was available. It was also frustrating that many inferences were made from observations of humans in modern societies, which is irrelevant to the origin of human traits. I decided to do something to counteract the wide range of – sometimes crazy – ideas. But I did not want to present information in a dry, dictatorial monograph. I thought that it was important to share what I had learned with as broad an audience as possible and to make it engaging enough to hold the attention of someone with little background in biology. To accomplish this, I made sure to keep things simple while being as accurate as possible. It was a tricky balance, but I managed to keep the writing at the high school level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also strived to provide adequate levels of detail without including too much tangential information, so the end product is relatively short. In addition, I use a conversational writing style to lead the reader through the evidence with logical arguments so they will understand how we come to conclusions – how we do science. To vividly illustrate the challenges and struggles our ancestors experienced, I include a fictional story of someone who lived around 70,000 years ago. I use vignettes from her life to introduce the content of each chapter and to exemplify the evolutionary principles discussed. I expect not all readers will appreciate this approach, but those who don’t can just skip the vignettes without missing the majority of content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that readers will find my discussions of the origins of unique human traits thought provoking and enlightening. I was not involved in collecting the data that I cite, but realize that sometimes you need to step back to see the connections that are not obvious from the perspective of individual research silos. By the end of the book, I hope readers will come to understand the origins of human traits and connections among them. Like those of any other animal, our unique appearance and behaviors are products of natural selection as our ancestors struggled to survive in the harsh and challenging environments they inhabited.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mitch Cruzan</name></author><summary type="html">Looking down the Tree – The Evolutionary Biology of Human Origins, by Mitch Cruzan, Oxford University Press, October, 2025. Mitch Cruzan is Professor of Biology at Portland State University. He received his BA and MA in Biology from California State University, Fullerton, and his PhD from Stony Brook University. He is currently an associate editor for Molecular Ecology, a leading journal in the field. He has published more than 80 papers in the primary literature and an advanced textbook, Evolutionary Biology: A Plant Perspective. His latest book, Looking Down the Tree – Exploring the Origins of Our Species, is due to be published in a few days, and we have invited him to offer a preview here. I have offered an introductory course on evolution annually over the last 15 years. I always saved in-depth discussions of human evolution to the end for two reasons. First, to discuss human evolution in a meaningful way, we need to have a good understanding of evolutionary principles and processes. Second, I thought it was a good highlight for the course to end on. Each year, I incorporated new information and new ideas about human origins. Much of this content came from the questions that students asked; they weren’t satisfied to look a series of fossil remains or boring details about human genomics. They wanted to know more about the origins of our unique appearance and behaviors, and particularly secondary sexual characteristics. Why does anyone take on a particular subject for a non-fiction book? You might ask, what could a plant evolutionary biologist such as myself possibly have to say about human evolution? Some reviewers actually said that I had no business writing this book. But evolutionary biology consists of a set of principles and processes that can be applied to any organism. Yes, it helps to have knowledge of the biology of a species, but for humans, that information is readily available. For me, developing the material was a natural process as I explored aspects of human evolution, along with the students in my introductory evolution lectures. By the time the pandemic hit, I had developed what I thought was a unique story of the origin of human traits – one that made sense in the context of the habitats our ancestors inhabited. This book is not just a rehash of previous statements and ideas. By integrating information from disparate fields such as paleontology, anthropology, and genomics, I have drawn unique conclusions about the origins of human traits and behaviors.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ring of Brodgar</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/ring-of-brodgar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ring of Brodgar" /><published>2025-10-27T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-10-27T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/ring-of-brodgar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/ring-of-brodgar.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Joe Long&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Long_Ring_of_Brodgar.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ring of Brodgar (henge)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ring_of_Brodgar&quot;&gt;Ring of Brodgar&lt;/a&gt;, Mainland Island, Orkney Islands, Scotland, May 21, 2023. Mr. Long writes, &quot;This is part of the Orkney Neolithic Complex recognized as a UNESCO World Heritage site.  It is unusual in having a ring of standing stones (27 at present, of 60 originally) associated with a henge.  Age is estimated as 2000-2500 BCE on poor data.  The fact that it is the northernmost henge and stone circle in Great Britain may be understood by reference to a map; little of Great Britain is farther north.  Technical: Olympus OM-D EM-1 Mark III, Olympus 12-40 mm, f/2.8 at 27 mm, 1/60 s, f/16, ISO 200, handheld.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Joe Long. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Ring of Brodgar, Mainland Island, Orkney Islands, Scotland, May 21, 2023. Mr. Long writes, &quot;This is part of the Orkney Neolithic Complex recognized as a UNESCO World Heritage site. It is unusual in having a ring of standing stones (27 at present, of 60 originally) associated with a henge. Age is estimated as 2000-2500 BCE on poor data. The fact that it is the northernmost henge and stone circle in Great Britain may be understood by reference to a map; little of Great Britain is farther north. Technical: Olympus OM-D EM-1 Mark III, Olympus 12-40 mm, f/2.8 at 27 mm, 1/60 s, f/16, ISO 200, handheld.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jason Rosenhouse and Phil Halper: creationist information theory</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/rosenhouse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jason Rosenhouse and Phil Halper: creationist information theory" /><published>2025-10-15T22:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2025-10-15T22:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/rosenhouse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/rosenhouse.html">&lt;div width=&quot;640px&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;390&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iJe_y4yXM7s&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
.embed-container {
  position: relative;
  padding-bottom: 56.25%;
  height: 0;
  overflow: hidden;
  max-width: 80%;
}
.embed-container iframe,
.embed-container object,
.embed-container embed {
  position: absolute;
  top: 0;
  left: 0;
  width: 100%;
  height: 100%;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Jason Rosenhouse is interviewed by Phil Halper on Halper's Youtube channel.  A demolition
of ID information theory.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;</content><author><name>Jason Rosenhouse</name></author><summary type="html">Jason Rosenhouse is interviewed by Phil Halper on Halper's Youtube channel. A demolition of ID information theory.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Aragonite Frostwork</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/aragonite-frostwork.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aragonite Frostwork" /><published>2025-10-13T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-10-13T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/aragonite-frostwork</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/aragonite-frostwork.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Alan Rice&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Rice-Alan_Aragonite Frostwork.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthodite&quot;&gt;Aragonite frostwork&lt;/a&gt;, taken in a cave in Nevada during field work. Mr. Rice writes, &quot;&lt;i&gt;Anthodites&lt;/i&gt; are speleothems (cave formations) composed of long needle-like crystals situated in clusters which radiate outward from a common base. Most anthodites are made of the mineral aragonite (a variety of calcium carbonate, CaCO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;), although some are composed of gypsum (CaSO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;·2H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O).  The &quot;needles&quot; may be quill-like or feathery.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Alan Rice. Photography Contest, Honorable Mention. Aragonite frostwork, taken in a cave in Nevada during field work. Mr. Rice writes, &quot;Anthodites are speleothems (cave formations) composed of long needle-like crystals situated in clusters which radiate outward from a common base. Most anthodites are made of the mineral aragonite (a variety of calcium carbonate, CaCO3), although some are composed of gypsum (CaSO4·2H2O). The &quot;needles&quot; may be quill-like or feathery.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building Bridges That Can Bear Scientific Scrutiny</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/building-bridges-that-can-bear.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building Bridges That Can Bear Scientific Scrutiny" /><published>2025-10-07T13:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-10-07T13:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/building-bridges-that%20can-bear</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/building-bridges-that-can-bear.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Jensen_Ark_IMG_2686_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Some of Jensen's team at the Ark.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Some of the team visiting the &quot;Ark.&quot; &lt;small&gt;Photograph by author.&lt;/small&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Jamie Jensen is a biologist and discipline-based education researcher at Brigham Young University, where she is a Professor of Biology. She has spent her career researching ways to help students and the public reconcile science with religious worldviews and has done work across the U.S., with the Smithsonian, and in other parts of the world including Qatar, South Africa, and Hungary.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently had the “opportunity” to visit the “Ark Encounter” and “Creation Museum” attractions in Kentucky while visiting Vanderbilt University for the Scopes Centennial Celebration. After participating in the academic meeting, I took a group of undergraduate students with me to these two attractions; these students work in my research lab investigating ways to communicate accurate evolutionary science across religious divides. We have had quite a bit of success in our efforts to increase evolution acceptance in the classroom without damaging students’ religious identities (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution-outreach.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12052-015-0051-6&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution-outreach.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12052-020-00133-9&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://online.ucpress.edu/abt/article-abstract/84/2/75/119835/Exploring-the-Relationship-between-Science?redirectedFrom=fulltext&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). However, with some of my more public-focused programming, I have met with varying levels of resistance (and sometimes hostility), even from members of my own Christian religious “in-group.” (Yes, I do belong to a conservative Christian religion. And I also fully embrace the modern science of evolution, in its entirety.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went to these two attractions seeking to better understand the viewpoints of those who stand in opposition to evolution, and to characterize the misconceptions and logical fallacies that may stand in the way of effective communication across the divide. We were astonished at the extent and sophistication of the attempts made to “create” science that supports alternative worldviews. This is not a case of trying to “sweep under the rug” the inconsistencies between a biblical account of creation and the physical evidence we see around us. It was, rather, an elaborate attempt to build a pseudoscientific “reality” that would satisfy a not unintelligent, but not scientifically well-versed patron of the attraction. But as I walked the halls of this misguided attraction, I got to thinking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;What occurred to me is that people &lt;i&gt;want&lt;/i&gt; a bridge. They &lt;i&gt;want&lt;/i&gt; the science and their faith to make sense. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gone are the days when parents could simply shield their kids from the science and hope they never encounter anything that questions their faith. Gone are the days when you could supply an alternative, completely non–science-based narrative and hope that your children never encounter the “real” story. With the advent of technology, social media, and information literally at our very fingertips, no one runs the risk of never being “exposed” to real science. And I think that those opposing evolution know this. They know that they can’t simply avoid the science. They can’t ask their patrons to rely on biblical writings alone. They can’t ask people to ignore the very real and very compelling evidence. They must invent a new science that is “close enough” to pass muster amongst their audience. They must build a bridge that, if crossed, maintains the integrity of their faith identity, and they understand that this bridge cannot utilize real science. But does this bridge have to be built on false scientific principles? I would argue that it does not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But &lt;strong&gt;first&lt;/strong&gt;: People &lt;i&gt;want&lt;/i&gt; a bridge. How do I know? I have been gathering empirical evidence that suggests it. In our research lab, we have been studying what we call the “Reconciliation Model” for years in various settings with a variety of religious affiliations. The Reconciliation Model involves discussing the nature and limitations of science, offering alternatives to literal biblical interpretations, and presenting evolutionary content in a way that is friendly to faith. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://biology.byu.edu/reconciling-evolution/curricular-materials&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for some example lesson plans, from a variety of faith traditions. We have found that we can increase students’ acceptance of evolutionary theory without reducing their religiosity (e.g., &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lifescied.org/doi/10.1187/cbe.19-04-0080&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution-outreach.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12052-021-00155-x&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. However, in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/jssr.70004&quot;&gt;recent study&lt;/a&gt;, we noticed an enigma that got us thinking about this increase in acceptance a little more. In this study, we measured the relationship between a literal interpretation of the Bible and acceptance of evolution. In a nationwide sample, we see an inverse relationship: the higher your literalism, the lower your acceptance. In our classroom study, utilizing the Reconciliation Model, we found that we could decrease biblical literalism and thereby directly predict increases in acceptance. However, what was puzzling to us was that students’ biblical literalism remained high, even though they were experiencing dramatic upward shifts in evolution acceptance (especially macro- and human evolution). This finding launched us into a second study, which has not yet been published. But I’ll give you a sneak preview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We re-surveyed students from among our highly religious student body and found students who were answering questions in a seemingly contradictory way. For example, they strongly agreed with both “Present animal diversity can be explained by the Great Flood” (a literal biblical interpretation) &lt;i&gt;and&lt;/i&gt; “I think all complex organisms evolved from single celled organisms” (an evolutionarily accurate statement). We wondered how a single student could strongly agree with both statements at the same time. Through thematic analysis using cultural border crossing and collateral learning theories (Aikenhead 1999) as our &lt;i&gt;a priori&lt;/i&gt; framework and then looking for emergent themes, we discovered two different lenses through which students were looking at these statements. Through an epistemological lens (i.e., “how do I know what I know?”), students felt certain that both science and religion are in harmony, that they could reconcile the two, that they could successfully build a bridge spanning the gap. For example, one student stated, “It doesn’t really feel important to me [to figure out how evolution and my religious beliefs fit together]. I just know that they do fit together. In whichever way it may be, I just know that they do.” Clearly, this student wants to believe that bridging the gap is possible – they &lt;i&gt;want&lt;/i&gt; a bridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, from a factual lens (i.e., “how does it actually work?”), students revealed a broad array of misconceptions, mental gymnastics, and uncertainty. When asked how the creation story in the Bible and evolution go together, this same student, who above was confident that both science and religion fit together, offered this explanation: “Just like… a lot of it like first starts off with the creation and all the species that were made and then when species start evolving and adapting to environments, that’s when more diversity happens,” indicating that all the “species” were created, and then they evolved to be more diverse. Another student, who stated from an epistemological standpoint, “I figured all truth is godly—whether it’s scientific or religious—they can be together,” then stated, when asked how the “Noah’s ark” story in the Bible and the evolution of modern diversity fit together, “I would have imagined that all of the land vertebrates that existed before the Ark would have died in the flood. So, the only ones that would survive would have been on the Ark…. But then there’s also that other part where maybe we’ve had some that have since come out of the water and they evolved that way.” Clearly, she holds misconceptions about the amount of modern diversity that exists, and about the time it takes to evolve from a water-dwelling organism to the diversity we see on land today (certainly more than the 4000 years or so since the flood supposedly occurred). We labeled these attempts to mesh a literal biblical interpretation and a scientific explanation together as “mental gymnastics,” which would be a new form of “dependent collateral learning” in collateral learning theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear, from our work, that students can appear to be epistemologically secured (i.e., they &lt;i&gt;want&lt;/i&gt; a bridge to be possible), when in reality, the bridge that they have built is full of factual holes and is likely to crumble as they obtain more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, &lt;strong&gt;second&lt;/strong&gt;: How do we help students build a bridge on a solid scientific foundation? And is it always possible? To answer the second part of the question first: in some cases, with extreme biblical literalist beliefs or specifically contradictory doctrine, a bridge may not be possible. However, in cases where this direct contradiction does not exist, I believe that it &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; possible to fortify their bridge. Here would be my advice: (a) Facilitate an accurate understanding of the nature and limitations of science. Research clearly shows that an understanding of the nature of science is one of the largest predictors of evolution acceptance (Dunk et al. 2019 provides a good overview). We have had large success in our courses when we emphasize the agnostic nature of science. Science can no more provide evidence &lt;i&gt;for&lt;/i&gt; God (a theistic perspective) as it can provide evidence &lt;i&gt;against&lt;/i&gt; the existence of a god (an atheistic perspective). Therefore, science is clearly agnostic and should not be a threat to anyone’s belief system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(b) Do not shy away from the facts. There is an emergingly clear relationship between the knowledge of evolution and its acceptance (again, see Dunk et al., 2019). A lack of the basics of evolution is often a struggle for students trying to build bridges. Some of those big ideas include that evolution is not a quest for perfection, that speciation takes a &lt;i&gt;really&lt;/i&gt; long time (longer than a human lifespan, usually), that organisms do not “choose” to adapt but that random mutations provide the variation upon which natural selection acts, that the process that leads to microevolution is the same process that leads to macroevolution, and that humans did not “come from” monkeys (i.e., an understanding of basic phylogeny principles).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would caution though, to always keep in mind that &lt;i&gt;only&lt;/i&gt; teaching the facts is not likely to overcome ideological barriers. Thus, (c) strive to use culturally competent strategies (or what is often now referred to as “conflict-reducing” strategies [Barnes and Brownell 2018]). Some of these strategies include acknowledging the potential for conflict, emphasizing the agnostic nature of science, providing religious role models who accept evolution, offering ways to reconcile science with religion, and practicing intellectual humility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is certainly a complex issue, and there is no one “silver bullet” way to solve these problems. Much of the conflict that exists today is the fruits of a long and troubled past involving historical events, impassioned publicity, and bad actors on both sides of the aisle. But we are not doomed to perpetuate the conflict. The understanding we have gained through rigorous research on pedagogy and communication can be used to launch us on a better trajectory to greater scientific literacy, more productive conversation, and more fortified bridges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aikenhead, G. S., and Jegede, O. J., 1999. &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/%28SICI%291098-2736%28199903%2936%3A3%3C269%3A%3AAID-TEA3%3E3.0.CO%3B2-T&quot;&gt;Cross-cultural science education: A cognitive explanation of a cultural phenomenon&lt;/a&gt;, Journal of Research in Science Teaching, 36, 269-287.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dunk, R. D. P., et al., 2019. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41559-019-0802-9&quot;&gt;Evolution education is a complex landscape&lt;/a&gt;. Nat. Ecol. Evol. 3(3):327-329. doi: 10.1038/s41559-019-0802-9. PMID: 30718854.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;M. Elizabeth Barnes and Sara E. Brownell, 2018. A Call to Use Cultural Competence When Teaching Evolution to Religious College Students: Introducing Religious Cultural Competence in Evolution Education (ReCCEE). Life sciences education, published online, https://doi.org/10.1187/cbe.17-04-0062&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jamie Jensen</name></author><summary type="html">Some of the team visiting the &quot;Ark.&quot; Photograph by author. Jamie Jensen is a biologist and discipline-based education researcher at Brigham Young University, where she is a Professor of Biology. She has spent her career researching ways to help students and the public reconcile science with religious worldviews and has done work across the U.S., with the Smithsonian, and in other parts of the world including Qatar, South Africa, and Hungary. I recently had the “opportunity” to visit the “Ark Encounter” and “Creation Museum” attractions in Kentucky while visiting Vanderbilt University for the Scopes Centennial Celebration. After participating in the academic meeting, I took a group of undergraduate students with me to these two attractions; these students work in my research lab investigating ways to communicate accurate evolutionary science across religious divides. We have had quite a bit of success in our efforts to increase evolution acceptance in the classroom without damaging students’ religious identities (see here, here, and here). However, with some of my more public-focused programming, I have met with varying levels of resistance (and sometimes hostility), even from members of my own Christian religious “in-group.” (Yes, I do belong to a conservative Christian religion. And I also fully embrace the modern science of evolution, in its entirety.) We went to these two attractions seeking to better understand the viewpoints of those who stand in opposition to evolution, and to characterize the misconceptions and logical fallacies that may stand in the way of effective communication across the divide. We were astonished at the extent and sophistication of the attempts made to “create” science that supports alternative worldviews. This is not a case of trying to “sweep under the rug” the inconsistencies between a biblical account of creation and the physical evidence we see around us. It was, rather, an elaborate attempt to build a pseudoscientific “reality” that would satisfy a not unintelligent, but not scientifically well-versed patron of the attraction. But as I walked the halls of this misguided attraction, I got to thinking:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ID education: coming soon nearby</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/idcourse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ID education: coming soon nearby" /><published>2025-10-04T21:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2025-10-04T21:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/idcourse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/10/idcourse.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;div halign=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/idcourse2a.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[question period at an earlier ID course]&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Students asking questions from the pews at an earlier version of the course in Spokane, Washington.  A speaker (Paul Nelson) seems to have been talking about how development can't anticipate function.&lt;br /&gt;From the announcement at Science &amp;amp; Culture (formerly Evolution News). Fair use claimed.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Discovery Institute’s Center for Science and Culture (formerly the Center for the Renewal of Science and Culture) has announced, at its blog &lt;a href=&quot;https://scienceandculture.com/2025/10/id-education-day-is-coming-to-tacoma-november-6/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; that it will run its ID Education Day for the fourth time, in Tacoma, Washington, on the 6th of November.  The theme will be “Creepy Crawly Complexity”.  I hadn’t been aware of this, but it was run most recently in Spokane, Washington in March, 
with nearly 500 students attending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For the past few years, we’ve held our most popular student event, ID Education Day, in Spokane, WA, and the excitement keeps growing! This past March, nearly 500 students from Central and Eastern Washington and North Idaho joined us, including one school that traveled nearly three hours to attend. To keep the momentum going and to serve the students of Western Washington, we’re excited to host our second “Creepy Crawly Complexity” ID Education Day in Tacoma on Thursday, November 6, from 9:30 am to 2:00 pm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a fantastic field trip opportunity for middle and high school students in homeschool and private school settings to interact directly with scientists and learn about the complexity and diversity of insects, spiders, and worms. Students will get to hear special presentations from philosopher of biology Paul Nelson on the miracle of butterfly metamorphosis and the complexity of the roundworm, biologist Pedro Moura on the phyla Arthropoda, Annelida, and Nematoda, and megadrilologist George Damoff on the elaborate design of the earthworm and its role in ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(A megadrilologist is not a specialist in very large mechanical drills, but in earthworm biology).
As we might expect&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The goal of the event will be to introduce students to the concept of intelligent design, to share updates from the field of zoology, and to think critically about the evidence (or lack thereof) for Darwinian evolution. In the panel Q&amp;amp;A, students will be encouraged to engage with our presenters to discuss the implications of their presentations for culture and worldview, helping them develop critical thinking skills and (in many cases) bolster their faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not know what the admission cost might be, or the requirements for one’s background. The link for the course is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discovery.org/e/idedday-fall-2025/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder whether the presentations and arguments will get beyond “gosh, aren’t these 
beasts amazingly complex? How could that happen except by Design Intervention?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Nelson’s argument apparently goes a bit beyond that, being an argument that 
development of embryos implies that the developmental process has foresight into what 
further-developed forms will need.  His argument is that this foresight could not be 
a property of natural selection, so Design Intervention is implied.  On &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.create.ab.ca/dr-paul-nelson-opened-our-minds/&quot;&gt;a creationist website&lt;/a&gt; he is quoted as saying that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you have a biological system which requires foresight [such as metamorphosis], you can be sure evolution did not do it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a similar argument in May at Evolution News (the previous name of Science &amp;amp; Culture) 
by David Klinghoffer (see my counterargument &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/05/platonic-nonsense.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), who has written a book publicizing the arguments of Richard Sternberg 
that when developmental processes seem to aim at an idealized form, that is impossible by 
normal evolutionary processes and implies that the development refers to a Platonic ideal 
form in an supernatural realm.  It completely ignores the possibility that there is 
genetic variability for developmental processes, and the individuals that succeed in 
achieving function leave more genes to their descendants.  Arguments like Sternberg’s and 
Nelson’s seem to be the new argument-du-jour of the DI.  See also Eric Hedin’s recent 
post at Science &amp;amp; Culture along similar lines (&lt;a href=&quot;https://scienceandculture.com/2025/02/fireweed-an-example-of-intelligent-latent-design/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nelson’s (and Sternberg’s) argument seems to be central to the new wave of “ID Education”.  Do the teachers mention the much simpler and more straightforward explanation using the ordinary processes of evolutionary biology?  Why do I suspect that they don’t?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that the Discovery Institute is working to spread their arguments among 
home school curricula and in private schools that dismiss evolution.  Should we suspect 
that they hope to spread their arguments into public schools?  In the past, when they 
were accused of that, they disclaimed any such intention.  For example, in 2005, they 
took the position, as Casey Luskin (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discovery.org/a/3000/&quot;&gt;posted at their website&lt;/a&gt;), that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s Constitutional But Not Smart to Teach Intelligent Design in Schools&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes since 2005 have largely been in a far-right federal government coming to power, the 
Supreme Court majority allowing many blatant violations of the separation of church and 
state, and states with right-wing governments feeling empowered to plaster public-school 
classrooms with their favorite religious icons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would not be surprised if the Discovery Institute changed its tune.  In which case, we 
will be seeing the new curriculum, coming soon to public-school classrooms near you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Students asking questions from the pews at an earlier version of the course in Spokane, Washington. A speaker (Paul Nelson) seems to have been talking about how development can't anticipate function.From the announcement at Science &amp;amp; Culture (formerly Evolution News). Fair use claimed.    The Discovery Institute’s Center for Science and Culture (formerly the Center for the Renewal of Science and Culture) has announced, at its blog here that it will run its ID Education Day for the fourth time, in Tacoma, Washington, on the 6th of November. The theme will be “Creepy Crawly Complexity”. I hadn’t been aware of this, but it was run most recently in Spokane, Washington in March, with nearly 500 students attending. For the past few years, we’ve held our most popular student event, ID Education Day, in Spokane, WA, and the excitement keeps growing! This past March, nearly 500 students from Central and Eastern Washington and North Idaho joined us, including one school that traveled nearly three hours to attend. To keep the momentum going and to serve the students of Western Washington, we’re excited to host our second “Creepy Crawly Complexity” ID Education Day in Tacoma on Thursday, November 6, from 9:30 am to 2:00 pm. Their description: This is a fantastic field trip opportunity for middle and high school students in homeschool and private school settings to interact directly with scientists and learn about the complexity and diversity of insects, spiders, and worms. Students will get to hear special presentations from philosopher of biology Paul Nelson on the miracle of butterfly metamorphosis and the complexity of the roundworm, biologist Pedro Moura on the phyla Arthropoda, Annelida, and Nematoda, and megadrilologist George Damoff on the elaborate design of the earthworm and its role in ecosystems. (A megadrilologist is not a specialist in very large mechanical drills, but in earthworm biology). As we might expect The goal of the event will be to introduce students to the concept of intelligent design, to share updates from the field of zoology, and to think critically about the evidence (or lack thereof) for Darwinian evolution. In the panel Q&amp;amp;A, students will be encouraged to engage with our presenters to discuss the implications of their presentations for culture and worldview, helping them develop critical thinking skills and (in many cases) bolster their faith. I do not know what the admission cost might be, or the requirements for one’s background. The link for the course is here. I wonder whether the presentations and arguments will get beyond “gosh, aren’t these beasts amazingly complex? How could that happen except by Design Intervention?”</summary></entry></feed>