<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-09-20T07:46:23-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Are Evolutionary Biologists Ignoring Science?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/are-evolutionary-biologists-ignoring-science.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are Evolutionary Biologists Ignoring Science?" /><published>2020-09-17T00:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-17T00:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/are-evolutionary-biologists-ignoring-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/are-evolutionary-biologists-ignoring-science.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/champneysscientists.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;From Champneys' video. Evolutionary biologists ignoring the Second Law
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Uncommon Descent in April, Granville Sewell has called attention to a new video by
Mark Champneys, “The Second Law of Thermodynamics: When Scientists Ignore Science”.
Sewell’s post will be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/when-scientists-ignore-science-by-mark-champney/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
Recall that Sewell’s own videos and books feature a refutation of evolution
by invoking something like the Second Law.  The Discovery Institute often praises Sewell, who is
one of their Fellows, and Sewell and Champneys say nice things about each
other.  So they all think that these arguments are good science, and that
what evolutionary biologists say is most definitely not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Champneys has shown up here once before: in 
2017 &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2017/04/Does-Granville-Sewells-entropy.html&quot;&gt;he made some comments on a 2011 post&lt;/a&gt; by me about Granville Sewell’s
arguments.  He and I had a brief, mild exchange in the comments section.  In those
days we had no Recent Comments widget to allow people to find comments on
older posts like that one, so no one else noticed this.  So I put up &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2017/04/Does-Granville-Sewells-entropy.html&quot;&gt;a new post about Champneys’ arguments&lt;/a&gt;
in the hope that he would join the discussion.  Alas, he did not show up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now Champneys has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/0oOt317kSro&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;new video&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which makes the shocking argument that when
scientists say that evolution occurs by natural selection acting on mutations
over time, they are ignoring the Second Law of Thermodynamics.  The new
video is 35 minutes long.  For a more extensive and discursive version of the
same argument, you could also consult a &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/8wLVBbqOGGA&quot;&gt;video of a lecture by Champneys&lt;/a&gt; where
he also explains how easily he has refuted scientists who fail to take into
account the Second Law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at what the new video says.  I do hope that Champneys will
come by and help us understand why he and Sewell think that we are ignoring
this fundamental law of science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As fodder for our discussion, let me just note some arguments he makes, and indicate
where I disagree with them, with quotes from the new Champneys video.  He says more on each
of these there.  Each quote is accompanied by the time in minutes and seconds
in his video where it will be found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Champneys describes evolutionary biologists as arguing that there are “loopholes”
and “exceptions” preventing the Second Law from working:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
(13:22) Sadly many brilliant scientists seek to dodge the law
with exactly such methods, suggesting that an open system
which lets sunlight in is not subject to this law of
science at all. Nothing can be further from the truth.
Increasing randomness and the principle driving the
law applies everywhere, to every part
of every system, open or isolated -- it just can't be
defined clearly for an open system, but the
principle does not go away just because
biologists want it to -- it is a principle, people, not
a loophole, and the principle driving the law works
everywhere without exception.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
(18:25) Their primary defense is to excuse their theory
by virtue of the fact that the earth is an open system. 
That's it, that's all they have.  Richard Dawkins has
stated that the Second Law can be disregarded simply
because of the sun.  The energy input of sunlight is
supposed to invalidate the application of the laws of
science to biology.  You can almost hear him shout 'loophole!
loophole!' Evolutionists claim that sunlight is the magical
ingredient that makes entropy decrease possible, but
it's simply not true -- sublight is actually very random,
and what's needed is the polar opposite of random,
which is specification. 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as I know that’s not what evolutionary biologists say: all the ones I have
heard say that evolution is completely consistent with the Second Law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Champneys seems to think that natural selection cannot put specified
information into the genome because it only destroys less fit individuals, and
does not preserve fit ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
(22:27) Then comes the evolutionists' last gasp
'but random mutations are not really random -- they
are directed by natural selection', so, they always say.
Oops again. I say, natural
selection is a constraint on random, but random
within constraints is still random.  Natural
selection kills and culls, it does not build
anything.  Killing the weak cannot reduce entropy,
only slow the increase in it.  Random begets random.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He argues that Darwin made a fundamental error in saying in the subtitle of his
book that natural selection “preserves” favored variations.  Actually, that
argument
is that variations of fitness lead to favored variations increasing in frequency
while less favored ones decrease in frequency.  With organisms competing for
limited resources, the one implies the other – culling less-favored variations
implies that more-favored ones are increasing.  They are not separate processes.
In a dense mat of dandelions in my yard, as a less favored genotype becomes
rarer, the more favored genotype is able to become more common and come to contain
more energy drawn from the sun.  This is an increase of specified information,
and affects the entropy calculation for the system.  But to Champneys,
this is not how information comes to be in the genome, he says clearly that
only intelligence can put it there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Champneys seems to miss the role in the thermodynamic bookkeeping
of energy flowing into living systems from
the sun (or from chemosynthesis) in allowing the growth of organisms and increases
in their adaptation and specified information.&lt;br /&gt;
He instead attributes the growth of organisms to “energy transfer mechanisms”,
“ETMs”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
(15:44) Consider photosynthesis. Sunlight alone would
dry up and destroy plants, but the photosynthesis ETM actually
builds them.  Plants use chlorophyll to harness very
random, even damaging sunlight to manufacture carbohydrates
and oxygen from carbon dioxide and water.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His “ETMs” are basically the complicated molecules of life which he thinks of as
basically exporting entropy.  These are simply the molecular
structures that capture energy, use it to maintain cells, retain it
and pass some of it on to offspring.  The proteins and RNAs of the cell.
That the incoming sunlight that arrives is at
a higher &lt;strike&gt;wavelength&lt;/strike&gt; frequency than its ultimate form as outgoing heat radiation seems
important, and affects entropy calculations, but that is
missing from Champneys’ argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Champneys keeps describing biologists as saying that it is mutation that puts
specified information into the genome.  He lampoons the way biologists
say that natural selection makes the mutation nonrandom, and makes
his “culling” argument to say that natural selection cannot add
specified information to the genome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
(21:24) Then after after a while comes the
only answer they can conjure up: 
'Mutations! Randoms mutations generated, and continue
to build the information sequences in DNA.'
Oops, I say, random is not an ETM.  Sorry, but it
is not, and never could be. Random is the
polar opposite of an ETM.  It does not make a
functional genome more probable, it makes it far less
probable.  Random is what ETMs are built to undo,
not to embrace.  Random mutations most certainly
degrade the genome, never sophisticate it. 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He seems not to see that changes in genotype frequencies have the effect
of choosing from among all variations the better-adapted ones.  Choosing a
relevant subset out of a larger set is the fundamental activity in
information theory.  If that subset is the better-adapted genotypes,
the information is also specified information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I hope that’s enough to lead to some discussion.  Watch the
video, and you will see the exact context of these quotes.  Look at
his longer video to get a more extensively and informally explained version.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">From Champneys' video. Evolutionary biologists ignoring the Second Law At Uncommon Descent in April, Granville Sewell has called attention to a new video by Mark Champneys, “The Second Law of Thermodynamics: When Scientists Ignore Science”. Sewell’s post will be found here Recall that Sewell’s own videos and books feature a refutation of evolution by invoking something like the Second Law. The Discovery Institute often praises Sewell, who is one of their Fellows, and Sewell and Champneys say nice things about each other. So they all think that these arguments are good science, and that what evolutionary biologists say is most definitely not. Champneys has shown up here once before: in 2017 he made some comments on a 2011 post by me about Granville Sewell’s arguments. He and I had a brief, mild exchange in the comments section. In those days we had no Recent Comments widget to allow people to find comments on older posts like that one, so no one else noticed this. So I put up a new post about Champneys’ arguments in the hope that he would join the discussion. Alas, he did not show up. Now Champneys has a new video, which makes the shocking argument that when scientists say that evolution occurs by natural selection acting on mutations over time, they are ignoring the Second Law of Thermodynamics. The new video is 35 minutes long. For a more extensive and discursive version of the same argument, you could also consult a video of a lecture by Champneys where he also explains how easily he has refuted scientists who fail to take into account the Second Law. Let’s take a look at what the new video says. I do hope that Champneys will come by and help us understand why he and Sewell think that we are ignoring this fundamental law of science.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The mystery of phosphine gas on Venus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/mystery-phosphine-venus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The mystery of phosphine gas on Venus" /><published>2020-09-15T12:06:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-15T12:06:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/mystery-phosphine-venus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/mystery-phosphine-venus.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Swamidass_Phosphine_Venus_Fig_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Phosphine molecule&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The chemical structure of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phosphine&quot;&gt;phosphine&lt;/a&gt; according to Wikipedia.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is there life on Venus? Yesterday, September 14, 2020, &lt;a href=&quot;an article in Nature Astronomy&quot;&gt;an article in Nature Astronomy&lt;/a&gt; reported careful measurements consistent with trace amounts of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phosphine&quot;&gt;phosphine gas&lt;/a&gt; in the cloud decks of Venus. There is no known geochemical process that can produce phosphine. This phosphine might have come from life. Life on Venus, if this is what we found, might be microbes floating in the clouds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time will tell, but this may become a landmark publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Swamidass_Phosphine_Venus_Fig_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Venus, as seen by synthetic aperture radar&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Venus, the second planet from the Sun, just months away from Earth, as seen by Magellan using synthetic aperture radar. &lt;small&gt;Credit: NASA; reproduced in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rankred.com/facts-about-venus/&quot;&gt;20 Interesting and Weird Facts About Venus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clouds of Venus are temperate, but full of sulfuric acid. Scientists wondered for decades whether or not the clouds could sustain life. We find microbes on Earth in extremely hostile environments. While no human could live unprotected on Venus, maybe a microbe could. Now, with this new finding, we are all wondering if maybe, in fact, there is life on Venus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been an explosion of media coverage in just the last day. &lt;a href=&quot;https://xkcd.com/2359/&quot;&gt;Today’s XKCD&lt;/a&gt; gives us a great filter by which to judge coverage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Not Cautious Enough: They found life on Venus!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Appropriately Cautious: These molecules might be produced by life, or by weird high-heat chemistry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Too Cautious: There is growing evidence that the atmosphere of Venus contains molecules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the study’s authors, Paul B. Rimmer, &lt;a href=&quot;https://discourse.peacefulscience.org/t/phosphine-gas-in-the-cloud-decks-of-venus/11729&quot;&gt;answered some questions&lt;/a&gt; for us at &lt;a href=&quot;https://discourse.peacefulscience.org&quot;&gt;Peaceful Science&lt;/a&gt;, and I look forward to seeing that conversation unfold more. Asked what this means for the origins conversation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Not at all, at present. There’s too much we just don’t know. The first step is to make sure the molecule we see is phosphine and not some unknown molecule that is producing the feature, how much there really is, how it’s distributed through the clouds, and what implications that has for where to look for its source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We then need to find out if there’s actually life in the clouds of Venus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Even when that’s done, there’s still a real possibility that life from Earth hitched a ride to Venus early on, so this may not imply more than one origin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If on Venus, Enceladus, Mars, Europa, any life is found that has a separate origin from life on Earth, that has enormous implications for origins of life and the prevalence of life in the universe. It suggests it’s not all that hard to make life from non-life after all. This is why exoplanets are so compelling. Unless you appeal to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panspermia&quot;&gt;panspermia&lt;/a&gt;, finding life in another stellar system, close enough for us to see evidence of it, strongly implies that origin of life is relatively easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asked, what media coverage is most likely to neglect, he responded,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Two things come to mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;(1) The uncertainty inherent in science. So far, no known explanation except for life can account for the detection, but we don’t know a lot. A lot more investigation needs to be done, especially involving abiotic phosphorus chemistry in sulfuric acid droplets. There’s also huge problems (that you will know more about) with life thriving in 90% sulfuric acid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;(2) That lots of people since &lt;a href=&quot;https://mashable.com/article/venus-life-theory-carl-sagan/&quot;&gt;Carl Sagan&lt;/a&gt; have thought about life in the clouds of Venus and have worked on this question way before our group started looking into this detection and its possible implications. I’d especially highlight David Grinspoon’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://nautil.us/issue/43/heroes/the-romantic-venus-we-never-knew&quot;&gt;research into possible life on Venus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was most exciting about this paper?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The detection of phosphine itself. Whatever its cause, by all rights it just shouldn’t be there, and the mystery is compelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a grand mystery, and that is exciting. The fact that we don’t know what gave rise to this phosphine what makes this finding so compelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was the phosphine, in the end, produced by something other than life? Is there any combination of geological and chemical processes, perhaps with input from meteorites, that could produce phosphine on an ongoing basis?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or is this really life? Did that life first arise when Venus had oceans, and then move to the skies? Was life seeded in Venus by probes in the 1970s and 80s sent from Earth? How much like or unlike life on earth will these microbes be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or was it the most mundane of all options? Could there be an error in the detection? Is there another chemical that absorbs light at the same wavelength? Was there some other technical loophole that misleads us here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions like these are surely going to shape research going forward. Perhaps we have put &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/07/28/science/mars-nasa-science.html&quot;&gt;too much focus on Mars&lt;/a&gt;, to the exclusion of exploring other worlds. What will a mission to Venus tell us about these questions? Would it be possible to return samples of those sulfuric clouds to Earth?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the great mystery that this paper offers. That is what makes it compelling. It is the questions of phosphine gas on Venus that draw us in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://swami.wustl.edu/&quot;&gt;Joshua Swamidass&lt;/a&gt;, a new member of the PT Crew, is Associate Professor, Laboratory and Genomic Medicine, Washington University in St Louis. He is the author of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ivpress.com/the-genealogical-adam-and-eve&quot;&gt;The Genealogical Adam and Eve&lt;/a&gt; and the founding scientist of the blog &lt;a href=&quot;https://peacefulscience.org/mission-and-values/&quot;&gt;Peaceful Science&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>S. Joshua Swamidass</name></author><summary type="html">The chemical structure of phosphine according to Wikipedia. Is there life on Venus? Yesterday, September 14, 2020, an article in Nature Astronomy reported careful measurements consistent with trace amounts of phosphine gas in the cloud decks of Venus. There is no known geochemical process that can produce phosphine. This phosphine might have come from life. Life on Venus, if this is what we found, might be microbes floating in the clouds. Time will tell, but this may become a landmark publication.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Giant ichneumon wasp and mystery visitor</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/giant-ichneumon-wasp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Giant ichneumon wasp and mystery visitor" /><published>2020-09-14T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-14T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/giant-ichneumon-wasp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/giant-ichneumon-wasp.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Mark Sturtevant&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest, &lt;strong&gt;Runner-up&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Sturtevant.Giant_Ichneumon_wasp_and_mystery_visitor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Giant ichneumon wasp&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insectidentification.org/insect-description.asp?identification=Giant-Ichneumon-Wasp-Megarhyssa-Atrata&quot;&gt;Megarhyssa atrata&lt;/a&gt;, giant ichneumon wasp. The photographer writes, &quot;This large female ichneumon wasp is using her long ovipositor to drill into wood in order to lay an egg on a wood-boring sawfly larva. The smaller wasp riding her is probably a male in the genus &lt;i&gt;Rhysella&lt;/i&gt;, and he appears to be mightily confused about his prospects for mating and passing on his genes.&quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Mark Sturtevant. Photography Contest, Runner-up. Megarhyssa atrata, giant ichneumon wasp. The photographer writes, &quot;This large female ichneumon wasp is using her long ovipositor to drill into wood in order to lay an egg on a wood-boring sawfly larva. The smaller wasp riding her is probably a male in the genus Rhysella, and he appears to be mightily confused about his prospects for mating and passing on his genes.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Green hyalite</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/green-hyalite.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Green hyalite" /><published>2020-09-08T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-08T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/green-hyalite</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/green-hyalite.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Alan Rice&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Winner&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Rice_Alan_Green_Hyalite-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hyalite&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyalite&quot;&gt;Hyalite&lt;/a&gt; glowing green, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fluorescence&quot;&gt;fluorescing&lt;/a&gt;, under ultraviolet light (ultraviolet C 100–280&amp;nbsp;nm). The photographer writes, &quot;Hyalite is a form of opal with a glassy and clear appearance. My brother builds ultraviolet lights for mineral exploration and is silhouetted by the abundant hyalite. This sample is deep underground in a tungsten mine in Nevada, USA.&quot; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Alan Rice. Photography contest, Winner. Hyalite glowing green, or fluorescing, under ultraviolet light (ultraviolet C 100–280&amp;nbsp;nm). The photographer writes, &quot;Hyalite is a form of opal with a glassy and clear appearance. My brother builds ultraviolet lights for mineral exploration and is silhouetted by the abundant hyalite. This sample is deep underground in a tungsten mine in Nevada, USA.&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Should you get vaccinated?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/should-you-get.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Should you get vaccinated?" /><published>2020-09-03T17:10:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-03T17:10:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/should-you-get</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/09/should-you-get.html">&lt;p&gt;I can barely believe I have asked that question. It is inspired by an article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@michaelzimmerman_40329/why-ill-not-be-taking-a-covid-19-vaccine-and-i-m-a-scientist-c8e7d7004890&quot;&gt;Why I’ll Not Be Taking a Covid-19 Vaccine — and I’m a Scientist&lt;/a&gt;, that my sometime pen pal, Michael Zimmerman, founder and director of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theclergyletterproject.org/&quot;&gt;Clergy Letter Project&lt;/a&gt;, published in the online magazine &lt;i&gt;Medium&lt;/i&gt;. As you can see, Dr. Zimmerman, who holds a PhD in biology, has pretty well made up his mind, and his answer is “No.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Dr. Zimmerman put it in an e-mail to members of the Clergy Letter Project, his position is “that politics was influencing medical decisions to the detriment of society.” You can read his &lt;i&gt;Medium&lt;/i&gt; article for yourself, but he seems largely influenced by the premature approval of convalescent plasma for Covid-19, slowing down of testing, and “many other recent actions [that] are attacked by virtually all in the scientific community as being scientifically and medically unsound.” Dr. Zimmerman wisely notes that his position could be used to “inflame the passions” of anti-vaxxers and put “a growing number of individuals at risk from diseases that are easily controlled.” For that he blames “permitting previously respected agencies to be subverted for political gain.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His article did not escape the notice of Francis Collins, the director of the National Institutes of Health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Collins wrote what I would call a letter of rebuttal privately to Dr. Zimmerman, but Dr. Zimmerman received permission to post that letter &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theclergyletterproject.org/pdf/mzfccorrespondence.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. In the letter, Dr. Collins asks Dr. Zimmerman to reconsider and argues that “by the end of 2020 we may well have at least one vaccine that is safe and effective – by rigorous standards that I think you would strongly endorse.” He asks, fairly, “Are you allowing your own scientific judgment to be overcome by the current political tumult, and granting a victory to the forces of irrationality?” and adds,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Righteous indignation is one of my favorite emotions too, but sometimes it needs to be scrutinized. Many people depend on you and the Clergy Letter Project to bring a faithful blend of scientific reason and God’s love to a hurting world. Does this stance fit with that? Prayerfully consider what God would expect of you at a time like this. Lives are at stake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Zimmerman’s reply is posted in the same PDF file. He says there that he does not question the dedication nor the ability of government scientists. But he is very frankly afraid, regarding Stephen Hahn, the Commissioner of Food and Drugs (head of the FDA), and Robert Redfield, the director of the CDC, that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[i]f the president were to say “approve this vaccine,” I simply cannot trust them to do anything other than to say “yes, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the e-mail to the Clergy Letter Project, Dr. Zimmerman expresses appreciation for Dr. Collins’s “thoughtful and impassioned note.” Dr. Collins, he says, made him rethink his beliefs, but in the end, “the core of [his] position, that politics was influencing medical decisions to the detriment of society, remained unchanged.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exchange between Drs. Zimmerman and Collins reminded me of a discussion I had recently with a friend, also a scientist. Like Dr. Zimmerman, she is afraid that a harmful or ineffective vaccine may be rushed through and administered to an unsuspecting population. Would she get the vaccine? After some back-and-forth, she averred, “If Fauci said to.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgment.&lt;/strong&gt; Thanks to Michael Zimmerman for allowing me to quote the letters between him and Francis Collins.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">I can barely believe I have asked that question. It is inspired by an article, Why I’ll Not Be Taking a Covid-19 Vaccine — and I’m a Scientist, that my sometime pen pal, Michael Zimmerman, founder and director of the Clergy Letter Project, published in the online magazine Medium. As you can see, Dr. Zimmerman, who holds a PhD in biology, has pretty well made up his mind, and his answer is “No.” As Dr. Zimmerman put it in an e-mail to members of the Clergy Letter Project, his position is “that politics was influencing medical decisions to the detriment of society.” You can read his Medium article for yourself, but he seems largely influenced by the premature approval of convalescent plasma for Covid-19, slowing down of testing, and “many other recent actions [that] are attacked by virtually all in the scientific community as being scientifically and medically unsound.” Dr. Zimmerman wisely notes that his position could be used to “inflame the passions” of anti-vaxxers and put “a growing number of individuals at risk from diseases that are easily controlled.” For that he blames “permitting previously respected agencies to be subverted for political gain.” His article did not escape the notice of Francis Collins, the director of the National Institutes of Health.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A belated happy birthday to Lamarck</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/belated-happy-birhtday-lamarck.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A belated happy birthday to Lamarck" /><published>2020-08-30T08:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-30T08:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/belated-happy-birhtday-lamarck</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/belated-happy-birhtday-lamarck.html">&lt;p&gt;Since 2009 I have posted every year a happy birthday greeting to the first evolutionary biologist, the
Chevalier de Lamarck.  Jean Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet, Chevalier de Lamarck, was born on 1 August 1744,
so now more than 276 years ago.  In my opinion he was the first true evolutionary biologist – he argued for
common ancestry of animals, and he actually had a proposed mechanism that biased change in the direction of
adaptation of a species to its environment.  He was wrong about the mechanism, but right about the need for
one.  He was also a great figure in invertebrate systematics, in which he made great strides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I’ve said all that before, and in addition this year the birthday notice is late.  No apologies for that,
the Pandas Thumb Crew spent his birthday desperately struggling to bring PT back up after a hardware failure of
its server.  We’ve talked about many aspects of his life, good and bad.  Is there anything important spo far
left unsaid?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually yes.  That he invoked an inherent complexifying force, and that it was quietly abandoned by
Lamarckians in subsequent decades.  An interesting story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/380px-Jean-Baptiste_de_Lamarck.jpg&quot; width=&quot;380&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;By Charles Thévenin, 1802 or 1803, Public Domain, https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=19173092
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People today think of Lamarck as a crackpot, which he was not.  They think of him as the great inventor and
advocate of the inheritance of acquired characteristics.  Whenever someone suggest that a phenotypic
modification of a species could be inherited, everyone succumbs to the temptation of calling it “Lamarckian”.
Actually they’re wrong on both scores.  Lamarck was by no means the first to suggest that acquired
characteristics are inherited – it’s an idea that goes back at least to the ancient Greeks, and most likely far beyond them.
No one in Lamarck’s time would be surprised by Lamarck’s use of the phenomenon – they all always knew it was
true.  So they would not think of him as having done anything of interest by using it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, the modifications Lamarck was talking about were not the direct effects of environment, but effects
of use and disuse.  When we use our muscles they tend to get bigger.  To Lamarck, it was that use that had the
effect in modifying the legacy passed on the next generation.  A bird tried to fly faster, so its offspring’s
wings were bigger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s another phenomenon in Lamarck’s theory, one that most people don’t know of.  This is that in
addition to the effects of use and disuse, there a whole other force at work in Lamarck’s theory.  And that is
the inherent complexifying force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, for example, is a summary by Lamarck contrasting the existing theory with his own:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion adopted hitherto:&lt;/em&gt; Nature (or her Author) in creating animals, foresaw all the possible kinds of environment in which they would have to live, and endowed each species with a fixed organisation and with a definite and invariable shape, which compel each species to live in the places and climates where we actually find them, and there to maintain the habits which we know in them.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My individual conclusion:&lt;/em&gt; Nature has produced all the species of animals in succession, beginning with the most imperfect or simplest, and ending her work with the most perfect, so as to create a gradually increasing complexity in their organisation; these animals have spread at large throughout all the habitable regions of the globe, and every species has derived from its environment the habits that we find in it and the structural modifications which observation shows us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note the production of animals “in succession” from simplest to most perfect in a scale of “gradually increasing complexity”.  Although Lamarck drew one of the very first phylogenies, his thought was also dominated by a Great Chain of Being from simplest to most complex.  In fact, he believed that animal species climbed this scale continually, and if one became extinct, this was temporary, because it would arise again from animals further down on the scale of perfection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we not hear of this?  I think that it is simply that, as the 19th century wore on, with dramatic
developments in physics and chemistry, an inherent complexifying force seemed more and more unlikely,  In the aftermath of Darwin’s work, Lamarckian views were still around and advocated by his intellectual descendants.  But the more mystical aspects of the theory were quietly dropped.  Scientists no longer wanted to consider an inherent
complexifying force, or even effects of use and disuse.  The former was dropped, the latter became the direct
effects of the environment on the organism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today any effect of environment on the organism, such as epigenetic modifications, is called “Lamarckian”, usually quite inaccurately.  There is not going to be a true revival of Lamarckian views, as they would involve mystical trends towards complexity, and effects of will power on inheritance.  Neither has much appeal on light of modern physics.  Nevertheless, Happy Birthday to Jean-Baptiste, the first true evolutionary biologist.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Since 2009 I have posted every year a happy birthday greeting to the first evolutionary biologist, the Chevalier de Lamarck. Jean Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet, Chevalier de Lamarck, was born on 1 August 1744, so now more than 276 years ago. In my opinion he was the first true evolutionary biologist – he argued for common ancestry of animals, and he actually had a proposed mechanism that biased change in the direction of adaptation of a species to its environment. He was wrong about the mechanism, but right about the need for one. He was also a great figure in invertebrate systematics, in which he made great strides. Well, I’ve said all that before, and in addition this year the birthday notice is late. No apologies for that, the Pandas Thumb Crew spent his birthday desperately struggling to bring PT back up after a hardware failure of its server. We’ve talked about many aspects of his life, good and bad. Is there anything important spo far left unsaid? Actually yes. That he invoked an inherent complexifying force, and that it was quietly abandoned by Lamarckians in subsequent decades. An interesting story.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography Contest XII: Finalists</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/finalists-xii.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography Contest XII: Finalists" /><published>2020-08-25T07:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-25T07:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/finalists-xii</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/finalists-xii.html">&lt;p&gt;Here are the finalists of the 2020 photography contest. We received 21 photographs, all of which were excellent, as you will no doubt see during the coming months. With assistance from our wife, we chose 6 finalists and then added one rather than bite the bullet and break a tie. We display the &lt;em&gt;7&lt;/em&gt; finalists below the proverbial fold. We chose the photographs more on the basis of their pictorial quality than on their scientific interest. The text, if any, was written by the photographers and lightly edited for consistency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The finalists are presented in alphabetical order of last name. Please look through their photographs before voting for your favorite. Polling will close &lt;em&gt;Tuesday&lt;/em&gt;, September 8, at approximately &lt;em&gt;8&lt;/em&gt; a.m. MDT, and we will display the winner at noon that day. (Monday is Labor Day in the US.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please remember that this is a photography contest, not a popularity contest, and discourage your friends from enlisting others specifically to vote for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Domestic pigeon, by &lt;strong&gt;Muharrem Gorkem&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Gorkem_DomesticPigeon1_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pigeon&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
The photographer writes, &quot;A domestic pigeon, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domestic_pigeon&quot;&gt;Columba livia domestica&lt;/a&gt;, on her evening tour just before my apartment.&quot;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Common gray moth, by &lt;strong&gt;James Kocher&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Kocher_CommonGrayMoth1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Common gray moth&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anavitrinella_pampinaria&quot;&gt;Anavitrinella pampinaria&lt;/a&gt;, common gray moth, resting on block of limestone masonry &amp;ndash; &quot;a nice example of camouflage (cryptic) coloration, St. Louis, Missouri.&quot; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black-headed grosbeak, by &lt;strong&gt;Mark Lee&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Lee_BlackheadedGrosbeak.JPEG&quot; alt=&quot;Grosbeak&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Black-headed_Grosbeak/id&quot;&gt;Pheucticus melanocephalus&lt;/a&gt;, black-headed grosbeak, Palo Duro Canyon State Park, Texas.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roseate spoonbill, by &lt;strong&gt;C. Joseph Long&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Long_roseate_spoonbill.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Roseate spoonbill&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roseate_spoonbill&quot;&gt;Platalea ajaja L.&lt;/a&gt;, with young. The photographer writes, &quot;This shot was taken at the Alligator Farm in St. Augustine, Florida.  This is a popular place (among the birds, as well as humans) because, while nestlings that fall to the surface are lost, the nests are safe from such predators as raccoons, bobcats, and snakes due to the inaccessibility of the trees’ bases.  The color is due, as in flamingos, to carotenoids in the diet.  According to Wikipedia, the roseate’s closest relative is the yellow-billed spoonbill, which is found in southeast Australia.  They do get around.&quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green hyalite, by &lt;strong&gt;Alan Rice&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Rice_Alan_Green_Hyalite-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hyalite&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyalite&quot;&gt;Hyalite&lt;/a&gt; glowing green, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fluorescence&quot;&gt;fluorescing&lt;/a&gt;, under ultraviolet light (ultraviolet C 100–280&amp;nbsp;nm). The photographer writes, &quot;Hyalite is a form of opal with a glassy and clear appearance. My brother builds ultraviolet lights for mineral exploration and is silhouetted by the abundant hyalite. This sample is deep underground in a tungsten mine in Nevada, USA.&quot; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giant ichneumon wasp and mystery visitor, by &lt;strong&gt;Mark Sturtevant&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Sturtevant.Giant_Ichneumon_wasp_and_mystery_visitor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Giant ichneumon wasp&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insectidentification.org/insect-description.asp?identification=Giant-Ichneumon-Wasp-Megarhyssa-Atrata&quot;&gt;Megarhyssa atrata&lt;/a&gt;, giant ichneumon wasp. The photographer writes, &quot;This large female ichneumon wasp is using her long ovipositor to drill into wood in order to lay an egg on a wood-boring sawfly larva. The smaller wasp riding her is probably a male in the genus &lt;i&gt;Rhysella&lt;/i&gt;, and he appears to be mightily confused about his prospects for mating and passing on his genes.&quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gatekeeper butterfly, by &lt;strong&gt;Marilyn Susek&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Susek_Gatekeeper-Butterfly.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Butterfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ukbutterflies.co.uk/species.php?species=tithonus&quot;&gt;Pyronia tithonus&lt;/a&gt;, gatekeeper butterfly. The photographer writes, &quot;This butterfly was taken at my garden in Rotherham, S. Yorkshire, UK. I noticed that the under wing of this Gatekeeper is not the same as other photos of gatekeeper butterflies. It is sitting on an Echinacea.&quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdjFWQnqMJD-8-EhfT8o57nQpuMMGScRSu3K1qqL9ePvmLl-Q/viewform?embedded=true&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;618&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot;&gt;Loading…&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Here are the finalists of the 2020 photography contest. We received 21 photographs, all of which were excellent, as you will no doubt see during the coming months. With assistance from our wife, we chose 6 finalists and then added one rather than bite the bullet and break a tie. We display the 7 finalists below the proverbial fold. We chose the photographs more on the basis of their pictorial quality than on their scientific interest. The text, if any, was written by the photographers and lightly edited for consistency. The finalists are presented in alphabetical order of last name. Please look through their photographs before voting for your favorite. Polling will close Tuesday, September 8, at approximately 8 a.m. MDT, and we will display the winner at noon that day. (Monday is Labor Day in the US.) Please remember that this is a photography contest, not a popularity contest, and discourage your friends from enlisting others specifically to vote for you.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photography contest XII – entries close</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/contest-xii-entries-close.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photography contest XII – entries close" /><published>2020-08-24T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-24T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/contest-xii-entries-close</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/contest-xii-entries-close.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/DSC03492_Close-Up_Lens_Cucumber.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Thorns on cucumber stem&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cucumber&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Cucumis sativus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – cucumber. &lt;small&gt;No, not an entry, but what is a post without a picture?&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The  period for submitting entries to the photography contest ends now, August 24, at noon Mountain Daylight Time (6 h earlier than UTC).  As of this writing, we have received 21 submissions from 9 photographers. We will select finalists and post a poll as soon as possible, but not later than next Monday, August 31. Voting will close the following week, on &lt;i&gt;Tuesday&lt;/i&gt;, September 8 at &lt;i&gt;8&lt;/i&gt; a.m., MDT, and  the winning photograph will be posted at noon that day.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Cucumis sativus – cucumber. No, not an entry, but what is a post without a picture? The period for submitting entries to the photography contest ends now, August 24, at noon Mountain Daylight Time (6 h earlier than UTC). As of this writing, we have received 21 submissions from 9 photographers. We will select finalists and post a poll as soon as possible, but not later than next Monday, August 31. Voting will close the following week, on Tuesday, September 8 at 8 a.m., MDT, and the winning photograph will be posted at noon that day.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ark Sails the Coronavirus Seas</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/ark-sails-coronavirus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ark Sails the Coronavirus Seas" /><published>2020-08-23T11:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-23T11:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/ark-sails-coronavirus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/ark-sails-coronavirus.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2020/Attendance_At_Ark_Park_Graph.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Monthly attendance graph&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Monthly attendance at the Ark Park since its opening in July, 2017, in thousands. The numbers are estimates based on tax payments and may exclude holders of lifetime passes and children.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ark Encounter’s attendance for July, 2020, totals 57,632, according to a recent Kentucky Open Records Act (KORA) request. Of course this figure doesn’t include the hordes (eye roll) of children and lifetime members Ken Ham claims are pouring into the park and need not buy a ticket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest figure is a bit more than a third of some previous years’ July attendance figures (see the graph, above). This low number is understandable considering the current coronavirus pandemic. These numbers do not suggest any massive increase in attendance due to the opening of their new &lt;a href=&quot;https://arkencounter.com/virtual-reality/&quot;&gt;virtual-reality&lt;/a&gt; (virtual unreality?) theater adjacent to the Ark-shaped building. Apparently, in the new VR theater one can climb into a special “Truth Traveller” pod and don the latest high-tech VR glasses, then see Noah herding dinosaurs onto the Ark (ain’t “science“ and technology great?).  The VR show will cost $14.99 at present (supposedly this is an introductory offer; the price is going up soon) on top of the $49.95 adult ticket to see Mr. Ham’s fantasy. I suspect the VR glasses will be a nightmare to clean between showings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to say whether they are hurting due to the coronavirus pandemic; Ken Ham’s fundraiser last spring to “reopen the Ark” netted well over $1.1 million. Moreover, Crosswater Canyon, the non-profit owned by the Answers in Genesis ministry, received between $1 million and 2 million in Paycheck Protection Program (PPP) money. Their gate receipts for 2018 and 2019, however, must have been in the $30-40 million range, and they will not achieve those receipts again for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;––-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Matt Young will be the moderator of this thread. He produced the graph at the top of the page, but the data are entirely the result of persistent effort by Dan Phelps. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Monthly attendance at the Ark Park since its opening in July, 2017, in thousands. The numbers are estimates based on tax payments and may exclude holders of lifetime passes and children. The Ark Encounter’s attendance for July, 2020, totals 57,632, according to a recent Kentucky Open Records Act (KORA) request. Of course this figure doesn’t include the hordes (eye roll) of children and lifetime members Ken Ham claims are pouring into the park and need not buy a ticket. The latest figure is a bit more than a third of some previous years’ July attendance figures (see the graph, above). This low number is understandable considering the current coronavirus pandemic. These numbers do not suggest any massive increase in attendance due to the opening of their new virtual-reality (virtual unreality?) theater adjacent to the Ark-shaped building. Apparently, in the new VR theater one can climb into a special “Truth Traveller” pod and don the latest high-tech VR glasses, then see Noah herding dinosaurs onto the Ark (ain’t “science“ and technology great?). The VR show will cost $14.99 at present (supposedly this is an introductory offer; the price is going up soon) on top of the $49.95 adult ticket to see Mr. Ham’s fantasy. I suspect the VR glasses will be a nightmare to clean between showings. It is hard to say whether they are hurting due to the coronavirus pandemic; Ken Ham’s fundraiser last spring to “reopen the Ark” netted well over $1.1 million. Moreover, Crosswater Canyon, the non-profit owned by the Answers in Genesis ministry, received between $1 million and 2 million in Paycheck Protection Program (PPP) money. Their gate receipts for 2018 and 2019, however, must have been in the $30-40 million range, and they will not achieve those receipts again for some time. ––- Matt Young will be the moderator of this thread. He produced the graph at the top of the page, but the data are entirely the result of persistent effort by Dan Phelps.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Out of Africa</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/out-of-africa.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Out of Africa" /><published>2020-08-18T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-18T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/out-of-africa</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2020/08/out-of-africa.html">&lt;p&gt;We have all become amateur epidemiologists, and I frankly thought there would be hell to pay when the Covid epidemic finally reached Africa. According to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/369/6505/756&quot;&gt;news article&lt;/a&gt; by journalist Linda Nordling of Cape Town South Africa, writing in &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;, Africa&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;seems to have weathered the pandemic relatively well so far, with fewer than one confirmed case for every thousand people and just 23,000 deaths. Yet several antibody surveys suggest far more Africans have been infected with the coronavirus—a discrepancy that is puzzling scientists around the continent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/369/6504/624&quot;&gt;more technical article&lt;/a&gt; by Moustapha Mbow and colleagues, much of which I thought I understood, led to a similar conclusion. Several explanations have been proposed, including the simple fact that Africans are on the whole younger than, say, Europeans and Americans. The explanation may also be genetic. Another hypothesis, however, is that Africans are infected with various parasites, which ramp up their immune systems so that they can effectively fight new pathogens. Mbow and colleagues cite the “hygiene hypothesis” and suggest that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;early and chronic exposure to pathogens leading to relentless immune cell activation in harsh environments induces a strong regulatory immune response to counteract excessive inflammation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I give succor to any anti-vaxxers, let me state that this hypothesis in no way militates against vaccinating for measles, mumps, chickenpox, pertussis (or whooping cough), polio, or all the other deadly childhood diseases that were commonplace when I was in grade school and do not appear every hundred years or so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A day or so after my physician advised me to get a flu shot, I ran across two articles, one by reporter Kelly Servick &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2020/08/how-will-covid-19-affect-coming-flu-season-scientists-struggle-clues&quot;&gt;in Science&lt;/a&gt; and another by reporters Lesley Wroughton and Max Bearak &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/africa/south-africa-coronavirus-flu-season/2020/08/17/bd8aaaca-e084-11ea-82d8-5e55d47e90ca_story.html&quot;&gt;in the Washington Post&lt;/a&gt;. These articles noted that there has been almost no flu season in South Africa this year, and the Post quoted Cheryl Cohen of South Africa’s Institute for Communicable Diseases to the effect that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The main explanation is that measures against coronavirus are having an impact on flu transmission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That explanation, if it holds up, will be good news to those who are concerned about a flu epidemic piggybacked on top of the current Sars epidemic. It would be better news if the United States were taking stronger measures against the coronavirus, but God forbid I should make a political statement like that.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">We have all become amateur epidemiologists, and I frankly thought there would be hell to pay when the Covid epidemic finally reached Africa. According to a news article by journalist Linda Nordling of Cape Town South Africa, writing in Science, Africa seems to have weathered the pandemic relatively well so far, with fewer than one confirmed case for every thousand people and just 23,000 deaths. Yet several antibody surveys suggest far more Africans have been infected with the coronavirus—a discrepancy that is puzzling scientists around the continent. A more technical article by Moustapha Mbow and colleagues, much of which I thought I understood, led to a similar conclusion. Several explanations have been proposed, including the simple fact that Africans are on the whole younger than, say, Europeans and Americans. The explanation may also be genetic. Another hypothesis, however, is that Africans are infected with various parasites, which ramp up their immune systems so that they can effectively fight new pathogens. Mbow and colleagues cite the “hygiene hypothesis” and suggest that early and chronic exposure to pathogens leading to relentless immune cell activation in harsh environments induces a strong regulatory immune response to counteract excessive inflammation. Before I give succor to any anti-vaxxers, let me state that this hypothesis in no way militates against vaccinating for measles, mumps, chickenpox, pertussis (or whooping cough), polio, or all the other deadly childhood diseases that were commonplace when I was in grade school and do not appear every hundred years or so. A day or so after my physician advised me to get a flu shot, I ran across two articles, one by reporter Kelly Servick in Science and another by reporters Lesley Wroughton and Max Bearak in the Washington Post. These articles noted that there has been almost no flu season in South Africa this year, and the Post quoted Cheryl Cohen of South Africa’s Institute for Communicable Diseases to the effect that The main explanation is that measures against coronavirus are having an impact on flu transmission. That explanation, if it holds up, will be good news to those who are concerned about a flu epidemic piggybacked on top of the current Sars epidemic. It would be better news if the United States were taking stronger measures against the coronavirus, but God forbid I should make a political statement like that.</summary></entry></feed>