<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-08-05T01:46:49-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Happy birthday to Jean-Baptiste</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/08/Happy-birthday-Jean-baptiste.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy birthday to Jean-Baptiste" /><published>2023-08-01T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-08-01T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/08/Happy-birthday-Jean-baptiste</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/08/Happy-birthday-Jean-baptiste.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Lamarckat35.png&quot; alt=&quot;[Lamarck at age 35]&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Lamarck at age 35.  From Wikimedia Commons.  Public domain.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, our yearly birthday tribute to Jean-Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet, born on the first day of August.  Who? (“You mean the 
wonderful impressionist painter?”  No, that’s Claude Monet.  “You mean the father of the European Union?” No, that’s Jean Monnet.)  I mean the Chevalier 
de Lamarck, for my money the first real evolutionary biologist.  Some of his accomplishments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clarified systematics of invertebrates greatly (he also coined the term “invertebrate”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drew the first evolutionary tree, of animals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Proposed two mechanisms for evolutionary change:
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;A generalized complexifying force, and&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;An adaptive force, by use and disuse, combined with inheritance of these changes&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Suggested the chimpanzee as humanity’s nearest relative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He would be 279 years old today (he died in 1829).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something he didn’t do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Invent inheritance of acquired characters (everyone already believed it).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He always gets credit for things he didn’t do, such as that.  And his name gets invoked for things like epigenetic molecular modifications, 
which don’t work like his use-and-disuse mechanisms.  And his “complexifying force” has been conveniently forgotten for at least the 
last 125 years.  You can pretty much guarantee that if a biological process is called “Lamarckian”, it really isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His mechanism for adaptation does not work, but he really was the first to propose one.  Not a crank, but a great biologist.
Happy birthday!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Lamarck at age 35. From Wikimedia Commons. Public domain. &amp;nbsp; Once again, our yearly birthday tribute to Jean-Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet, born on the first day of August. Who? (“You mean the wonderful impressionist painter?” No, that’s Claude Monet. “You mean the father of the European Union?” No, that’s Jean Monnet.) I mean the Chevalier de Lamarck, for my money the first real evolutionary biologist. Some of his accomplishments: Clarified systematics of invertebrates greatly (he also coined the term “invertebrate”) Drew the first evolutionary tree, of animals Proposed two mechanisms for evolutionary change: A generalized complexifying force, and An adaptive force, by use and disuse, combined with inheritance of these changes Suggested the chimpanzee as humanity’s nearest relative He would be 279 years old today (he died in 1829). Something he didn’t do:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Did a Panda’s Thumb post nix Ken Ham’s appearance on an ultra-conservative Christian podcast?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/nix-ham-appearance-stuckey-podcast.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Did a Panda’s Thumb post nix Ken Ham’s appearance on an ultra-conservative Christian podcast?" /><published>2023-07-26T12:33:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-26T12:33:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/nix-ham-appearance-stuckey-podcast</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/nix-ham-appearance-stuckey-podcast.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Phelps_Ham_Stuckey_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ham and Stuckey&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Ken Ham, right, with Allie Beth Stuckey on her soundstage.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did a Panda’s Thumb post nix Ken Ham’s appearance on an ultra-conservative Christian podcast?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back on June 7, 2023, Ken Ham &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/aigkenham/status/1666430590130741250&quot;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt; that he had been interviewed for Allie Beth Stuckey’s podcast “Relatable.” Mr. Ham even included a picture of himself with Ms. Stuckey on her soundstage. I looked into this and was amused to find that Ms. Stuckey had done an earlier podcast where she discussed her conspiratorial beliefs that dinosaurs did not exist and that the moon landing was possibly faked. I published an &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/dinosaurdebate.html.&quot;&gt; account&lt;/a&gt; of this on June 9, 2023, on the Panda’s Thumb. To my surprise, Ms. Stuckey’s podcast with Mr. Ham, as of late July, 2023, has never aired as either a podcast or a YouTube video. I have fast forwarded thru all of her numerous podcasts and YouTube videos from early June to July 24, 2023, and she has never even mentioned Ken Ham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Ms. Stuckey has once again mentioned her dinosaur denying conspiracy “theory” on a YouTube video (&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/EPGl7dtBxac&quot;&gt;Episode 826, Why Teens Today Can’t Cope&lt;/a&gt;, dated June 21, 2023). During a bizarre discussion of the implosion of the Titan submersible and space/Mars exploration at 11 minutes 40 seconds into the podcast she states (occasionally speaking for God):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;I don’t know why people want to go to space or go into the ocean. There’s a reason like, okay, there’s a reason why God made us have to stay on Earth – ‘I literally created a force to keep your feet on the ground – Why are you trying? – I didn’t give you gills – I didn’t give you the ability to go to Mars - I put you on Earth – Why do people do this?’ This is gonna be like someone’s gonna clip this and they’re gonna do the same thing they did with the Dinosaur Episode, yeah, which some people are still mad about. Oh well, be mad.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can only speculate as to why the episode of Relatable with Ken Ham as a guest has never aired. Perhaps Ken Ham reads the Panda’s Thumb? Perhaps he actually had the integrity not to be associated with a dinosaur denier? Perhaps Ms. Stuckey was referring to Ken when she stated “be mad”? Could there be a rift between them? NAAAH! Her biography is still on the AiG webpage, &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/bios/allie-beth-stuckey/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There does not seem to be a good reason for Mr. Ham’s interview not to be up yet. Ms. Stuckey has had plenty of time and has covered much more recent events/topics. If she suddenly airs the Ham interview, I will be glad to report the fact in the comments and in an update.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I admit this is all more amusing than meaningful. Ms. Stuckey is a rich seam of stupidity waiting to be mined. Even Ken should be embarrassed to be associated with her.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Ken Ham, right, with Allie Beth Stuckey on her soundstage. Did a Panda’s Thumb post nix Ken Ham’s appearance on an ultra-conservative Christian podcast? Back on June 7, 2023, Ken Ham tweeted that he had been interviewed for Allie Beth Stuckey’s podcast “Relatable.” Mr. Ham even included a picture of himself with Ms. Stuckey on her soundstage. I looked into this and was amused to find that Ms. Stuckey had done an earlier podcast where she discussed her conspiratorial beliefs that dinosaurs did not exist and that the moon landing was possibly faked. I published an account of this on June 9, 2023, on the Panda’s Thumb. To my surprise, Ms. Stuckey’s podcast with Mr. Ham, as of late July, 2023, has never aired as either a podcast or a YouTube video. I have fast forwarded thru all of her numerous podcasts and YouTube videos from early June to July 24, 2023, and she has never even mentioned Ken Ham. However, Ms. Stuckey has once again mentioned her dinosaur denying conspiracy “theory” on a YouTube video (Episode 826, Why Teens Today Can’t Cope, dated June 21, 2023). During a bizarre discussion of the implosion of the Titan submersible and space/Mars exploration at 11 minutes 40 seconds into the podcast she states (occasionally speaking for God):</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Discovery Institute: a change or just a pause?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/dichanged.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Discovery Institute: a change or just a pause?" /><published>2023-07-24T16:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-24T16:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/dichanged</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/dichanged.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Rita_2005-09-21a.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Hurricane Rita]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Hurricane Rita on 21 Sept. 2005 as a&lt;br /&gt;category 5 hurricane in the Gulf of Mexico&lt;br /&gt;NASA satellite image downloaded from Wikimedia. Public domain&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jerry Coyne has published a &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2023/07/23/has-the-discovery-institute-changed-its-mission/&quot;&gt;post at his blog&lt;/a&gt;, Why Evolution Is True asking “Has the Discovery Institute changed its mission?”   After a review of the DI’s mission 
statements, the goals in its 1998 Wedge Document, and information on its funding, he notes that they are still well-funded and active.  Nowadays the activity is making human-exceptionalist arguments about AI, and highlighting “problems of evolution”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous campaigns to “teach the controversy” and introduce ID into the classroom were rejected by the courts, culminating in the 
famous Dover School Board case of 2005.  Here is Jerry’s summary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;This is where creationism in America has gotten to. It started with mandating Biblical creationism in schools, and when that was rejected they tried to get “scientific creationism” taught, but that failed, too, as it was just Biblical creationism gussied up in scientific language. Then it became the “teach the alternatives” (evolution/Biblical creationism), which was declared unconstitutional since the Biblical alternative was just religion pushed into the public schools. Then the strategy became “teach intelligent design (which isn’t creationism),” something that federal judge John Jones deep-sixed in the Kitzmiller case. Now the pathetic institute is reduced to just pointing out problems with evolution, but nobody’s adopting that strategy either.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder whether this isn’t too reassuring.  Here’s why …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;their-ai-initiative&quot;&gt;Their AI initiative&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, an aside on their AI initiative.  This is concentrated in the relatively new Walter Bradley Center of Natural and Artificial Intelligence.  It seeks to present mathematical arguments that artificial intelligence will never be able to achieve true natural intelligence.  This is a human-exceptionalism argument, which implicitly works against human intelligence having evolved by 
unintelligent processes.  But I can’t see how it plays out in the public sphere.  (I suppose that judging whether true natural intelligence has been achieved is to be done by a panel of True Scotsmen).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;is-it-all-over&quot;&gt;Is it all over?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the 2005 Jones decision in the Dover case, there seemed to be no chance that courts would allow the Religious Right to 
teach creationism, even in its ID guise.  The precedents were all clear: &lt;em&gt;Epperson v. Arkansas (1968)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lemon v. Kurtzman (1971)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;McLean v. Arkansas Board of Education (1982)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Edwards v. Aguillard (1987)&lt;/em&gt;, and finally &lt;em&gt;Kitzmiller v. Dover Area School Board (2005)&lt;/em&gt;.  These rulings presented a huge legal barrier for introducing creationist and ID arguments into schools.  It was settled 
precedent, as well established as, well, say &lt;em&gt;Roe v. Wade&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there lies the problem. With a right-wing supermajority on the Supreme Court, and with the Federalist Society shepherding 
hundreds of right-wing federal judges into the lower courts, there is now no guarantee that any of these precedents will be 
effective.  (And yes, I’m aware that &lt;em&gt;Kitzmiller&lt;/em&gt; is not formally precedent at the national level).  It’s not paranoia to 
foresee that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;State legislators will continue to introduce bills allowing 
teachers to introduce creationist and ID material into their 
classes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and bills demanding equal time for this material&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and bills mandating discussion of “problems of evolution”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Local teachers and their school boards will feel uninhibited in 
violating separation of church and state&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Governors and legislatures in Red states will delight in pushing measures 
that reward the Religious Right.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Appeals against these in the courts will fare badly, and no 
one will be able to foresee success at the Supreme Court.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;low-expectations&quot;&gt;Low expectations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s true that right now (or perhaps I should say “Right now”) wars over 
evolution are not very visible.  The Right in general, and the Religious 
Right in particular, are concentrating on demonizing transgender 
people and LGBTQ+ rights more generally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But alongside desperate struggles to defend democracy and human rights more 
generally, we will see gradually increasing efforts to attack 
the teaching of evolutionary biology at all levels.  Waiting for the 
courts to do the right thing will only end with them doing 
the Right thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are in for a long period of war in the trenches, including 
struggles to provide good and accessible resources for studying 
and teaching evolutionary biology, not just for biology 
students but for interested folks in general.  And yes, the DI 
will be there, brewing their usual noxious stew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;optimism&quot;&gt;Optimism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the longer run I’m hopeful, because I think that many 
students will understand that this struggle is going on, and 
where the attacks on evolution are coming from.  And most young 
people won’t buy them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any thoughts?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">Hurricane Rita on 21 Sept. 2005 as acategory 5 hurricane in the Gulf of MexicoNASA satellite image downloaded from Wikimedia. Public domain &amp;nbsp; Jerry Coyne has published a post at his blog, Why Evolution Is True asking “Has the Discovery Institute changed its mission?” After a review of the DI’s mission statements, the goals in its 1998 Wedge Document, and information on its funding, he notes that they are still well-funded and active. Nowadays the activity is making human-exceptionalist arguments about AI, and highlighting “problems of evolution”. Previous campaigns to “teach the controversy” and introduce ID into the classroom were rejected by the courts, culminating in the famous Dover School Board case of 2005. Here is Jerry’s summary: This is where creationism in America has gotten to. It started with mandating Biblical creationism in schools, and when that was rejected they tried to get “scientific creationism” taught, but that failed, too, as it was just Biblical creationism gussied up in scientific language. Then it became the “teach the alternatives” (evolution/Biblical creationism), which was declared unconstitutional since the Biblical alternative was just religion pushed into the public schools. Then the strategy became “teach intelligent design (which isn’t creationism),” something that federal judge John Jones deep-sixed in the Kitzmiller case. Now the pathetic institute is reduced to just pointing out problems with evolution, but nobody’s adopting that strategy either. I wonder whether this isn’t too reassuring. Here’s why …</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lecanospira perplana</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/lecanospira-perplana.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lecanospira perplana" /><published>2023-07-24T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-24T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/lecanospira-perplana</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/lecanospira-perplana.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;James Kocher&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest XIV, &lt;strong&gt;Third Place&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Kocher_Lecanospira_perplana_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fossil gastropods&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Lecanospira_perplana (Heller)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roubidoux_Formation&quot;&gt;Roubidoux Formation&lt;/a&gt;, Lower (Early-Gasconadian/Tremadocian) Ordovician (~480 Ma). Shirley, Missouri. This fossil &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gastropoda&quot;&gt;gastropod&lt;/a&gt; is preserved in chert packstone with chalcedony permineralization and red-orange hydrated iron oxides (limonite-goethite). Sinstral (left-handed/counterclockwise) coiling is seen when looking down from apex of whorls (right-half of fossil).
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Kocher will be offered the book, Dan Levitt, &lt;i&gt;What’s Gotten Into You?&lt;/i&gt;, generously donated by the National Center for Science Education.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by James Kocher. Photography Contest XIV, Third Place. Lecanospira_perplana (Heller) &amp;ndash; Roubidoux Formation, Lower (Early-Gasconadian/Tremadocian) Ordovician (~480 Ma). Shirley, Missouri. This fossil gastropod is preserved in chert packstone with chalcedony permineralization and red-orange hydrated iron oxides (limonite-goethite). Sinstral (left-handed/counterclockwise) coiling is seen when looking down from apex of whorls (right-half of fossil). Mr. Kocher will be offered the book, Dan Levitt, What’s Gotten Into You?, generously donated by the National Center for Science Education.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Egretta thula Ardea alba</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/egretta-thula.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Egretta thula Ardea alba" /><published>2023-07-17T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-17T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/egretta-thula</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/egretta-thula.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Ole Lundin&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest XIV, &lt;strong&gt;Second Place&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Lundin_Snowy_Egret_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Great egret&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.audubon.org/field-guide/bird/snowy-egret&quot;&gt;&lt;strike&gt; &lt;i&gt;Egretta thula&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/strike&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.audubon.org/field-guide/bird/snowy-egret&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Ardea alba&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;strike&gt;snowy egret&lt;/strike&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Great_Egret/id&quot;&gt;great egret&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://veniceaudubon.org/rookery/&quot;&gt;Venice Audubon Rookery Park&lt;/a&gt;, Venice, Florida, March, 2017.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Lundin will be invited to choose from one of these books: Dan Levitt, &lt;i&gt;What’s Gotten Into You?&lt;/i&gt;, generously donated by the National Center for Science Education; or a copy of one of our own books, &lt;i&gt;Why Intelligent Design Fails&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;No Sense of Obligation&lt;/i&gt;, or &lt;i&gt;Why Evolution Works and Creationism Fails&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Ole Lundin. Photography Contest XIV, Second Place. Egretta thula Ardea alba &amp;ndash; snowy egret great egret, Venice Audubon Rookery Park, Venice, Florida, March, 2017. Mr. Lundin will be invited to choose from one of these books: Dan Levitt, What’s Gotten Into You?, generously donated by the National Center for Science Education; or a copy of one of our own books, Why Intelligent Design Fails, No Sense of Obligation, or Why Evolution Works and Creationism Fails.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Roy Spencer's stratospheric levels of denial</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/spencers-stratospheric-denial.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Roy Spencer's stratospheric levels of denial" /><published>2023-07-15T15:41:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-15T15:41:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/spencers-stratospheric-denial</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/spencers-stratospheric-denial.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Braverman_Frontispiece.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frontispiece&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Frontispiece of article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drroyspencer.com/2023/06/climate-fearmongering-reaches-stratospheric-heights/&quot;&gt;Climate fearmongering reaches stratospheric heights&lt;/a&gt;, by Roy Spencer, also published by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cornwallalliance.org/2023/07/climate-fearmongering-reaches-stratospheric-heights/&quot;&gt;Cornwall alliance&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;small&gt;Fair Use.&lt;/small&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Paul Braterman is Professor Emeritus in Chemistry, University of North Texas, and Honorary Research Fellow (formerly Reader) at the University of Glasgow. His research has involved topics related to the early Earth and the origins of life, and received support from NSF, NASA, Sandia National Labs, and Scripps Institution of Oceanography. He is now interested in sharing scientific ideas with the widest possible audience, blogs at &lt;a href=&quot;https://paulbraterman.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;Primate’s Progress&lt;/a&gt;, and is a regular contributor to &lt;a href=&quot;https://3quarksdaily.com&quot;&gt;3 Quarks Daily&lt;/a&gt;, and occasionally to &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/&quot;&gt;The Conversation&lt;/a&gt;, where his articles have received more than a million reads.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a scientist who has won awards for his work in the field disagrees with his colleagues, we must ask how much attention we should give to his opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The image you’re looking at is copied from the website of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drroyspencer.com&quot;&gt;Dr Roy Spencer&lt;/a&gt;, whose piece was also published by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cornwallalliance.org&quot;&gt;Cornwall Alliance&lt;/a&gt;. Spencer is a Principal Research Scientist at the University of Alabama, Huntsville, was involved in the development of satellite-based atmospheric temperature monitoring technology for which in 1996 he was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uah.edu/essc/research/climate&quot;&gt;honoured by the American Meteorological Society&lt;/a&gt;, and has received funding from NASA, NOAA, and DOE. Yet here he is using gutter tactics to assert that a piece of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.2300758120&quot;&gt;significant new work&lt;/a&gt; on the mechanism of climate change is part of an alarmist conspiracy, that the conspiracy is failing to persuade, and that the conspirators are now being forced to invoke arguments based on observations of the stratosphere. Who benefits from this conspiracy and why the overwhelming majority of climate scientists have joined it is not clear
For what it’s worth, acceptance of the reality of the climate crisis is increasing among Americans, as elsewhere, for reasons that are all too obvious, and the smoke of Canadian forest fires is much more persuasive than the scholarly discussion of the stratosphere that has triggered Spencer’s extraordinary reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is going on? I’m doing my best here to make sense of what is happening, in terms of the development of the disagreements between Spencer and his scientific colleagues, and Spencer’s own personal beliefs, to the extent that these are public knowledge. This is not an &lt;i&gt;ad hominem&lt;/i&gt; attack on Spencer’s scientific output, which has been thoroughly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/climate-consensus-97-per-cent/2014/apr/11/climate-change-research-quality-imbalance&quot;&gt;criticised&lt;/a&gt; elsewhere, but a good faith attempt to understand how he came to his present position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1990, Spencer and his colleague John Christy reported that their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.247.4950.1558&quot;&gt; satellite data implied less atmospheric warming&lt;/a&gt; than that suggested by ground-based thermometers. This disagreement with the generally accepted view deepened over the following years, with Spencer claiming that everyone else’s work was hopelessly contaminated by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drroyspencer.com/2008/12/&quot;&gt; failure to account for the effect of clouds &lt;/a&gt; and that the generally agreed temperature record was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drroyspencer.com/2014/12/2014-a-record-warm-year-probably-not/&quot;&gt; distorted by the urban heat island effect&lt;/a&gt;, while downplaying &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/climate-consensus-97-per-cent/2015/apr/06/revealing-interview-with-top-contrarian-climate-scientists&quot;&gt; studies that had shown his work to be in error&lt;/a&gt;. In 2006, he and the corresponding author of the paper he is now attacking collaborated on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Climate_Change_Science_Program&quot;&gt; report by the US Government’s Climate Change Science Program&lt;/a&gt;. This report identified and corrected errors in the satellite temperature record, so that according to its press release, &quot;There is no longer a discrepancy in the rate of global average temperature increase for the surface compared with higher levels in the atmosphere.&quot; The report then drew the inference that &quot;the observed patterns of change over the past 50 years cannot be explained by natural processes alone.&quot; According to an eyewitness account, the putting together of the report involved correcting an error in Spencer’s equations, and Spencer seemed unhappy with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spencer has continued to maintain that the consensus view overestimates the amount of global warming, and is one of a handful of scientists who continues to attribute what is happening to changing cloud cover. This of course is an important factor, and it is perhaps natural for Spencer, a meteorologist, to see it as a driver, rejecting the conventional view that while important, it is not a primary cause.
In 2008, Spencer wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.encounterbooks.com/books/climate-confusion-how-global-warming-hysteria-leads-to-bad-science-pandering-politicians-and-misguided-policies-that-hurt-the-poor-paperback/&quot;&gt;Climate Confusion&lt;/a&gt;, the first of a series of books in which he defends his view that CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; is not an important driver of climate change, describes policies aimed at CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; reduction as “global warming hysteria”, accuses politicians of pandering to special interests, and claims that such policies will harm the poor by restricting economic growth. We should not totally ignore those last two arguments. Biofuel programmes, for example, are beneficial to the US farming lobby but &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Issues_relating_to_biofuels#Energy_efficiency_and_energy_balance&quot;&gt; their value in reducing CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; emissions is hotly contested&lt;/a&gt;. And as I was writing this piece, the United Kingdom seemed at one point close to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2023/jul/04/revealed-uk-plans-to-drop-flagship-climate-pledge-rishi-sunak&quot;&gt;reneging on its commitments to Third World countries&lt;/a&gt;, largely as a result of its own poor economic performance. (On the other hand, it is very much the case that the heaviest direct costs of climate change are falling on the poorest countries, thus contributing to the flow of refugees from such countries towards the UK, Europe as a whole, and the US.) 

&lt;p&gt;Spencer has come to be closely associated with US conservatism. He has self-published a &lt;a href=&quot; https://www.amazon.co.uk/FUNDANOMICS-Market-Simplified-Roy-Spencer-ebook/dp/B005C626NG/&quot;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; on Amazon Kindle in praise of free-market economics, and free-market advocates would rather ignore or deny the damage caused by emissions, since that is an externality built into the true cost, but ignored by the market. He has given testimony to congressional hearings several times, and I should explain to readers outside the US that such hearings are not attempts to discover the truth and influence policy, but political street theatre. In 2010 the right-wing rabble-rouser Rush Limbaugh &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rushlimbaugh.com/daily/2010/04/20/dr_roy_spencer_s_new_book/&quot;&gt;claimed Spencer as his official climatologist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spencer is a member of the advisory board to the Cornwall Alliance for the Stewardship of Creation, where he also has the status of a Senior Scholar. The Cornwall Alliance is a rather unusual organisation, as I have discussed earlier here &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/10/creationclimate.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://3quarksdaily.com/3quarksdaily/2022/10/creationism-in-the-service-of-climate-change-denial.html&quot;&gt;elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;. The Alliance derives its deep motivation from its reading of the Bible, interpreting stewardship in terms of the dominion granted (Genesis 1:28) by God to a newly created literal Adam and Eve; see their &lt;a href=&quot;https://cornwallalliance.org/about/cornwall-alliance-statement-of-faith/&quot;&gt;statement of faith&lt;/a&gt;. Its main activity is arguing on scientific grounds against the consensus view that additional fossil fuel use will cause severe environmental damage, and it has &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/the-nature-of-the-beast-fossil-fuel-corporations-the-cornwall-alliance-and-climate-change-denial/&quot;&gt; direct links to the fossil fuel lobby and its dark funded activities&lt;/a&gt;. 

&lt;p&gt;The Cornwall connection immediately raises the question of Spencer’s own religious beliefs, which he discussed in a 2014 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drroyspencer.com/2014/01/science-and-religion-do-your-own-damn-google-search/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;. There he describes himself as a Bible-believing scientist, but avoids all discussion of evolution and the age of the earth. He tells us that he disagrees on some matters with the position of the Cornwall Alliance, and in particular that he rejects the argument that we are safe from environmental disaster because God is looking after the planet. However, he uses terminology and strawman arguments common in the creationist literature. Thus he attacks the concept of “settled science,” makes the strawman claim that the origin of life is presented as part of settled science, and describes the search by evolutionists (sic) for such a natural origin as “just as religious as the belief in a creator.”

&lt;p&gt;Spencer is being less than open here. In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/roy-spencer-on-intelligent-design/&quot;&gt; more complete statement&lt;/a&gt; preserved in the Discovery Institute’s &lt;i&gt;Uncommon Descent&lt;/i&gt; archive, he addresses evolution directly, and repeats all the standard arguments against it. Macro evolution has never been observed, and “has virtually no observational evidence to support it.” Moths are still moths. Observed similarities can be as well explained by common design, there are no intermediate fossils connecting amphibians to reptiles, reptiles to birds et cetera, and punctuated equilibrium theory is merely an attempt to explain away the absence of the required evidence. Accepting either evolution or intelligent design is a matter of faith, and both should be discussed in schools. “At the very least, school textbooks should acknowledge that evolution is a theory of origins, it has not been proved, and that many scientists do not accept it.” There is no indication of his beliefs about the age of the Universe. However, both here and in the 2014 blog post he denounces attempts to explain its origin by natural means, claiming that this would violate the laws of thermodynamics. The same argument is made in Whitcomb and Morris’s &lt;i&gt;The Genesis Flood&lt;/i&gt;, and repeated in young earth creationist rhetoric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2014 post, he told us that a scientist’s religious beliefs are irrelevant to judging the quality of the science, while at the same time maintaining that scientists are influenced in their work by their presuppositions. These two statements are not always entirely compatible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Climatology is very much a case in point. If, for example, Spencer is a young earth creationist (and his choice of arguments, and self-description as “Bible believing,” suggest that this may well be the case), he will automatically reject all the information on climate change amplification that has emerged from the study of the Ice Ages, and if millions of years of variation are shoehorned in his mind into the last few thousand, then it is certainly possible for him to regard present changes as superficial by comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After so long an introduction, analysis of the scientific development that prompted Spencer’s latest post seems almost anticlimactic. Greenhouse gases, as their name implies, reduce the efficiency by which Earth radiates energy into space by virtue of its infrared emissions. An increase in the temperature of the troposphere, the well-mixed lowest level of the atmosphere, combined with stratospheric cooling, is diagnostic of an increased greenhouse effect, since it directly relates temperature increase at low level to a decrease in upwards energy transfer. (The troposphere is the lowest layer of the atmosphere. It is well mixed, and extends from around 6 km above the surface at the poles to 17 km at the equator. The stratosphere is the 50 km or so above that, and shows relatively little mixing between horizontal layers.) For example, if recent warming were simply due to increased solar activity, the stratosphere would have been warmed along with the troposphere, but it wasn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This much is indeed established science. In 1967, Syukuro Manabe and Richard Wetherall calculated &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.ametsoc.org/view/journals/atsc/24/3/1520-0469_1967_024_0241_teotaw_2_0_co_2.xml&quot;&gt;the specific changes&lt;/a&gt; to be expected with height as the result of increased CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; . Repeated observations using balloons and satellites, for example here &lt;a href=&quot; https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/BF00210339&quot;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;, have confirmed that such changes are indeed taking place, and Manabe’s work on climate modelling was recognised by a share of the 2021 Nobel Prize in physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it’s a bit more complicated than that. The variation of temperature with height, especially in the lower part of the stratosphere, is also affected by changes in the ozone layer and in particulate content. Moreover, other events such as volcanic eruptions and changes in solar illumination can disrupt the temperature profile, and observations of the signal due to this profile are also contaminated by weather-like random fluctuations (technically known as noise). And as if this were not enough, the noise itself is distorted by the slow responses of the oceans to atmospheric temperature changes. The mathematical methods required to sort out signal from noise under these conditions, so as to specify a fingerprint that would be characteristic of human activity, were developed by Klaus Hasselmann, who with Manabe shared in the 2021 Nobel Prize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until recently, unambiguous experimental data were only available for the lower part of the stratosphere. The work described in the paper under discussion, a collaboration involving nine separate investigators and ten different institutions, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.2300758120&quot;&gt;extends our information to the entire stratosphere&lt;/a&gt;. This is important for several reasons. Firstly, the predicted signal of human activity actually increases with height, while the effect of weather-like fluctuations falls away. This leads to an improved signal-to-noise ratio (by a factor of five), greatly enhancing the statistical significance of the findings. Secondly, it is the lower stratosphere that contains the ozone layer, which has of course been changing recently for various reasons, and these changes affect the local temperature profile. This complication is less important at greater heights. Thus the new data enable the most rigorous test to date of Manabe’s predictions, and hence by implication of our intimate understanding of human-caused global warming. There can be few topics more important at present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the conclusion is unavoidable even if unsurprising. The planet is heating up, because of our actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except that, with great intellectual agility, Spencer manages to avoid this conclusion, writing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The authors are taking advantage of the public’s lack of knowledge concerning the temperature effect of increasing CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in the atmosphere, making it sound like stratospheric cooling is part of the fingerprint of global warming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It isn’t. Cooling is not warming.&lt;/strong&gt; [Emphasis in original] &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hardly taking advantage of the public to publish in PNAS, but let that pass.
It gets worse. Spencer claims there is nothing new in the paper, because there have been many earlier accounts of the temperature of the stratosphere. But the whole point of the paper is to extend our earlier knowledge to new heights (ouch! unintended pun, but let it stand.) He refers to Manabe and Wetherall’s seminal theoretical paper (see above), and accepts that its conclusions have been vindicated as regards the stratosphere. Nonetheless, he denies that the work has any real implications for what is happening lower down. But the whole point is that we now have an integrated account of the &lt;i&gt;complete&lt;/i&gt; temperature profile of the atmosphere, from ground level to the top of the stratosphere. And he accepts this account (in view of the data in the paper, he could hardly do otherwise) of what is happening in the stratosphere, which doesn’t directly affect us, while arbitrarily rejecting its implications for climate down at the level where we all live, because it’s cloudy and complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started this piece by asking how much attention we should pay to Spencer’s opinions. I think we have our answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman</name></author><summary type="html">Frontispiece of article, Climate fearmongering reaches stratospheric heights, by Roy Spencer, also published by the Cornwall alliance. Fair Use. Paul Braterman is Professor Emeritus in Chemistry, University of North Texas, and Honorary Research Fellow (formerly Reader) at the University of Glasgow. His research has involved topics related to the early Earth and the origins of life, and received support from NSF, NASA, Sandia National Labs, and Scripps Institution of Oceanography. He is now interested in sharing scientific ideas with the widest possible audience, blogs at Primate’s Progress, and is a regular contributor to 3 Quarks Daily, and occasionally to The Conversation, where his articles have received more than a million reads. When a scientist who has won awards for his work in the field disagrees with his colleagues, we must ask how much attention we should give to his opinion. The image you’re looking at is copied from the website of Dr Roy Spencer, whose piece was also published by the Cornwall Alliance. Spencer is a Principal Research Scientist at the University of Alabama, Huntsville, was involved in the development of satellite-based atmospheric temperature monitoring technology for which in 1996 he was honoured by the American Meteorological Society, and has received funding from NASA, NOAA, and DOE. Yet here he is using gutter tactics to assert that a piece of significant new work on the mechanism of climate change is part of an alarmist conspiracy, that the conspiracy is failing to persuade, and that the conspirators are now being forced to invoke arguments based on observations of the stratosphere. Who benefits from this conspiracy and why the overwhelming majority of climate scientists have joined it is not clear For what it’s worth, acceptance of the reality of the climate crisis is increasing among Americans, as elsewhere, for reasons that are all too obvious, and the smoke of Canadian forest fires is much more persuasive than the scholarly discussion of the stratosphere that has triggered Spencer’s extraordinary reaction. What is going on? I’m doing my best here to make sense of what is happening, in terms of the development of the disagreements between Spencer and his scientific colleagues, and Spencer’s own personal beliefs, to the extent that these are public knowledge. This is not an ad hominem attack on Spencer’s scientific output, which has been thoroughly criticised elsewhere, but a good faith attempt to understand how he came to his present position.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Luana Maroja on the Ernst Mayr Award and 2023 SSB Presidential Address</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/Luana-Maroja-Ernst-Mayr-Award.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Luana Maroja on the Ernst Mayr Award and 2023 SSB Presidential Address" /><published>2023-07-11T12:01:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-11T12:01:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/Luana-Maroja-Ernst-Mayr-Award</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/Luana-Maroja-Ernst-Mayr-Award.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Ernst_Mayr_caricature_by_David_Levine_NYRB.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;[Ernst Mayr in caricature]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Ernst Mayr in caricature. Artist: David Levine, New York Review of Books. Found on Twitter here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/greg_m_priest/status/1676610005834027009&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/greg_m_priest/status/1676610005834027009&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Background:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://biology.williams.edu/profile/lsm1/&quot;&gt;Luana Maroja, a biology professor from Williams College&lt;/a&gt;, wrote a letter to Brian O’Meara, the past president of the Society of Systematic Biologists about his SSB Presidential talk at the June 2023 Evolution meeting (slides can be found here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://brianomeara.info/evol2023.html&quot;&gt;https://brianomeara.info/evol2023.html&lt;/a&gt;; Evolution 2023 talks are going online here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@evolutionmeetings5042&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/@evolutionmeetings5042&lt;/a&gt;).  She decided to publish the letter on the Panda’s Thumb site because she is concerned about some of the directions that evolution societies are taking and wants to highlight that reasonable people might have views different from those expressed in O’Meara’s talk.  Luana hopes her letter will start a general discussion.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luana Maroja writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
Dear Brian,&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

I attended your Presidential talk at the Evolution meeting. I am the person who asked you about selective abortion and embryo selection by polygenic score (“PGS”). I have a few comments, which, I hope, will add a different viewpoint to this discussion.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

In the past, most presidential addresses I attended were motivational – designed to demonstrate and enhance the listeners’ love for evolutionary knowledge and research.  Your talk started this way, too.  But this motivational part was quickly replaced by what seemed to me an attempt to taint Ernst Mayr, setting the stage for a new vote in which his name would finally be removed, replaced by a nameless prize.  Unfortunately, I disagree on several grounds with this idea as well as with other points you made during the talk.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

First, I want to mention your emphasis on “sexual harassment” (keep in mind I am a woman who grew up in South America experiencing lots of serious harassment).  You seemed to ignore, or not know about, some reasons to oppose hiring a “safe evolution” consultant.  The feel of largely performative surveillance in the meeting (which thankfully seems to have decreased since 2019 – the projections of “Safe Evolution” on the wall are now gone!) can actually chill interactions between colleagues, especially interactions between older men and younger women.  Such interactions are often of great benefit to biologists beginning their careers, but older male biologists might now want to avoid them out of fear.  I wrote about this issue &lt;a href=&quot;https://hxstem.substack.com/p/extreme-emphasis-on-sexual-harassment&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and will not repeat myself – but please read it to see other reasons why people like me might be opposed to hiring consultants.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

Further, I think that you seriously misrepresented the views of Ernst Mayr.  I and many others who wish to remain anonymous—such is the climate of today’s academia!—left your talk feeling that you are preparing the Society for a new vote to remove the name from the prize.  For several reasons, some of us are opposed to removing evolutionary history from prizes. When I began my studies in biology, named prizes were a big motivation for me to learn the interesting history of our discipline.  Starting with Will Provine’s biography Sewall Wright, I became an avid student of the history of evolutionary biology.  I believe history should be learned as it really happened, even if today we might not fully agree with all the actions of people from the past.  Erasing names of awards also erases the motivation to learn this rich and amazing history, depriving graduate students of knowing about the accomplishments of those influential in our field. Finally, it is essential that students know why a prize is named after a biologist – it is always due to their contributions to the field and never due to any bad actions. What is being honored are scientific contributions, not the character of human beings.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

What is even more distressing is that you seemed to be deliberately attempting to find bad things about Mayr and his career to justify expunging his name from awards.  For example, you equated “positive eugenics” (an incentive for those with financial/educational capacity to reproduce more) with “negative eugenics” (castration—or worse—of those considered “inferior”).  To me, these actions are as different from each other as a parent’s increasing a child’s allowance versus corporal punishment (e.g., positive vs negative reinforcement in training).  Immediately after stating that “positive eugenics = negative eugenics”), you quoted from a letter in which Mayr asked the National Academy of Sciences to repudiate the arguments of William Shockley (that is, to reject negative eugenics, i.e., sterilizing people with IQs below 100).  In his letter, Mayr explains that he is envisioning a future in which humans are so numerous that governments will have to impose restrictions on reproduction (you will need a license to reproduce!). In this letter, Mayr rightly states that reproduction is important and influences the gene pool (any biologist knows that), but that non-biologists will not understand the importance of reproduction and we should therefore stop using racist arguments.  But read in its full context, Mayr’s letter is not arguing in favor of eugenics—at least not the kind of eugenics we all repudiate.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

To buttress your assertion that eugenics has current support in SSB today, you construct a narrative using nonexistent associations between the SSB and eugenic episodes happening elsewhere. For example, you mentioned sterilization (voluntary or otherwise) in Puerto Rico in the 1970s (if I recall correctly). Yet you showed no connection between this and actions of the SSB; rather, you used the example to bolster the case that eugenics was alive and well in the Society.  The same can be said about the quote from a judge in 2001.  Once again, there is no connection to SSB, but you used the example to imply that SSB scientists were somehow behind this.  I am baffled why you make these connections, and can only guess that somehow you’re trying to indict the Society for things it simply did not do.  And I don’t understand why you did that. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

You also assume that people who published in the Annals of Eugenics (the co-authoring analyses you presented) were all in favor of eugenics.  Yet, if you go back through some issues of Annals of Eugenics in the 1950s you will find that in addition to actual eugenics, there were also non-eugenic papers about matters like statistical genetic and human quantitative genetics—papers lacking any eugenic undertones. The journal was a venue for publishing general genetics research, and it is clear from its content that a lot of what went in there was not actually eugenics. So, your claim appears to be based on the flawed assumption that publishing in a journal with the name “eugenics” implies that the author must be an “eugenicist”. I see no reason to do this unless somehow you want to tar the society for things it did not do, and even that is something I cannot understand. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Finally, you cite a few modern papers to support your argument about modern eugenics (you gave full quotations but no names, though it did not take me long to find that the author is Michael Lynch). Yet, discussions about what civilization should do to prevent and eliminate detrimental mutations leading to disease are important, and now, with embryo and PGS screenings, these actions (via selective abortion or selection of embryos for implantation) are already taking place. You must realize that the main support for eugenics today (whether the name is used or not) takes the form of abortion of “genetically defective” embryos and the new form of embryo selection via PGS, which will soon be available for educational attainment and height, in addition to disease avoidance; indeed, western societies today favor many forms of eugenics.  This is why I asked the question I did at the end. “Do you think aborting Down syndrome fetuses or selecting embryos based on polygenic scores is a form of eugenics?” To which you responded something along the lines “No, if it is the mother’s choice it is ok”.  Notice that “mother’s choice” is also exactly what is behind “positive eugenics”.  My own views on this issue are still evolving, I think that some forms of embryo abortion and selection are ok and others problematic (even when done by parents).  For these reasons as well as others, I welcome discussions in this area without stigmatization of ideas, like those put forth by Michael Lynch.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

Respectfully,&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Luana
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;(Nick Matzke adds: For background on the 2022 attempt to de-name the Ernst Mayr Award, please see &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/Hillis-on-Mayr-Award.html&quot;&gt;David Hills on the SSB vote on the Ernst Mayr Award&lt;/a&gt;, June 13, 2022, and the links therein. As the Ernst Mayr Award is specified in the SSB constitution, changing it required a 2/3 vote of the membership. The vote was 63.4% (according to an SSB email) or 63.2% (91/(91+53); the numbers presented in O’Meara’s presentation; there were also 14 abstentions. In other words, it was a very near thing, with most of the membership not voting; and I gather SSB membership has been as high as 3000 but has declined to about 650. Hopefully this is mostly a pandemic effect, but I’m not sure it helps when there are attempts to cancel famous personalities in the field without a serious scholarly debate informed by thorough and balanced consideration of people and issues within their historical context.)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Also Nick Matzke: For previous comments on the SSB Ernst Mayr Award, please see the below.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255); padding: 30px;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/David-Hillis-on-Ernst-Mayr.html&quot;&gt;David Hillis on the proposal to de-name the Ernst Mayr Award at the Society for Systematic Biology&lt;/a&gt; -- by David Hillis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/David-Hillis-on-Ernst-Mayr.html#comment-5698109834&quot;&gt;Open Letter to the SSB Council&lt;/a&gt; -- by David Hillis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/David-Hillis-on-Ernst-Mayr.html#comment-5681790757&quot;&gt;&quot;As a graduate student myself, I must say that this proposal is outrageous, it deeply offends me.&quot;&lt;/a&gt; -- Comment from Ph.D. student Mario Cupello&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/David-Hillis-on-Ernst-Mayr.html#comment-5681656191&quot;&gt;&quot;[G]iven that the move to remove Ernst Mayr's name from the award is ostensibly being done in service for individuals for which I share many demographic qualities, I thought it worth providing my voice.&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; -- Comment from Ph.D. student Jackie Childers
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/Ernst-Mayr-versus-racism.html&quot;&gt;Ernst Mayr versus racism&lt;/a&gt; -- by Nick Matzke&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/06/Hillis-on-Mayr-Award.html&quot;&gt;David Hills on the SSB vote on the Ernst Mayr Award&lt;/a&gt; -- by David Hillis&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

For more on related issues, please see my old 2012 post: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2012/02/continuous-geog.html&quot;&gt;Continuous geographic structure is real, &quot;discrete races&quot; aren't&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
And my 2021 posts about attempts to can &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/updated-creationists-social-justice-advocates-unite-take-down-huxley.html&quot;&gt;Thomas Henry &quot;Darwin's Bulldog&quot; Huxley&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments.html&quot;&gt;also this post&lt;/a&gt;; Huxley was denamed at Western Washington University, but saved at Imperial College London) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/11/haldane-1938-biology-of-inequality.html&quot;&gt;J.B.S. Haldane&lt;/a&gt; (also saved at Imperial College London).
 &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Luana Maroja</name></author><summary type="html">Ernst Mayr in caricature. Artist: David Levine, New York Review of Books. Found on Twitter here: https://twitter.com/greg_m_priest/status/1676610005834027009 Background: Luana Maroja, a biology professor from Williams College, wrote a letter to Brian O’Meara, the past president of the Society of Systematic Biologists about his SSB Presidential talk at the June 2023 Evolution meeting (slides can be found here: https://brianomeara.info/evol2023.html; Evolution 2023 talks are going online here: https://www.youtube.com/@evolutionmeetings5042). She decided to publish the letter on the Panda’s Thumb site because she is concerned about some of the directions that evolution societies are taking and wants to highlight that reasonable people might have views different from those expressed in O’Meara’s talk. Luana hopes her letter will start a general discussion. Luana Maroja writes: Dear Brian, I attended your Presidential talk at the Evolution meeting. I am the person who asked you about selective abortion and embryo selection by polygenic score (“PGS”). I have a few comments, which, I hope, will add a different viewpoint to this discussion. In the past, most presidential addresses I attended were motivational – designed to demonstrate and enhance the listeners’ love for evolutionary knowledge and research. Your talk started this way, too. But this motivational part was quickly replaced by what seemed to me an attempt to taint Ernst Mayr, setting the stage for a new vote in which his name would finally be removed, replaced by a nameless prize. Unfortunately, I disagree on several grounds with this idea as well as with other points you made during the talk.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cyanerpes cyaneus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/cyanerpes-cyaneus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cyanerpes cyaneus" /><published>2023-07-10T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-10T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/cyanerpes-cyaneus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/cyanerpes-cyaneus.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;John Harshman&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography Contest XIV, &lt;strong&gt;Winner&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/Harshman_Honeycreeper_600_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Honeycreeper&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red-legged_honeycreeper&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt; Cyanerpes cyaneus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Red-legged honeycreeper.  Dr. Harshman writes, &quot;Neotropical honeycreepers belong to the largest bird family, the tanagers, an explosive radiation that includes the Galápagos finches (but none found in the continental USA). Unlike the finches, most tanagers are known for their bright colors. I suspect that the tanager ancestor found its way into South America from the north during or slightly before the Great Faunal Interchange. Hawaiian honeycreepers are a whole separate radiation, descended from some extremely lost flock of fringillid finches.&quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We received relatively few entries this year from only a few photographers (not all of whom observed rules 3 and 7, incidentally). Consistently with rules 8 and 12, not to mention 11, we have decided not to hold a poll this year, but rather with the assistance of our wife and Professor Steve Steve have carefully chosen a winner and two runners-up. The winning photograph by John Harshman is displayed today. We will display the runners-up on consecutive weeks and then most likely display honorable mentions every other week thereafter. Dr. Harshman will be invited to choose from one of these books: Neil Shubin, &lt;i&gt;Some Assembly Required&lt;/i&gt;; Dan Levitt, &lt;i&gt;What’s Gotten Into You?&lt;/i&gt;, both generously donated by the National Center for Science Education; or a copy of one of our own books, &lt;i&gt;Why Intelligent Design Fails&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;No Sense of Obligation&lt;/i&gt;, or &lt;i&gt;Why Evolution Works and Creationism Fails&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by John Harshman. Photography Contest XIV, Winner. Cyanerpes cyaneus &amp;ndash; Red-legged honeycreeper. Dr. Harshman writes, &quot;Neotropical honeycreepers belong to the largest bird family, the tanagers, an explosive radiation that includes the Galápagos finches (but none found in the continental USA). Unlike the finches, most tanagers are known for their bright colors. I suspect that the tanager ancestor found its way into South America from the north during or slightly before the Great Faunal Interchange. Hawaiian honeycreepers are a whole separate radiation, descended from some extremely lost flock of fringillid finches.&quot; We received relatively few entries this year from only a few photographers (not all of whom observed rules 3 and 7, incidentally). Consistently with rules 8 and 12, not to mention 11, we have decided not to hold a poll this year, but rather with the assistance of our wife and Professor Steve Steve have carefully chosen a winner and two runners-up. The winning photograph by John Harshman is displayed today. We will display the runners-up on consecutive weeks and then most likely display honorable mentions every other week thereafter. Dr. Harshman will be invited to choose from one of these books: Neil Shubin, Some Assembly Required; Dan Levitt, What’s Gotten Into You?, both generously donated by the National Center for Science Education; or a copy of one of our own books, Why Intelligent Design Fails, No Sense of Obligation, or Why Evolution Works and Creationism Fails.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Buteo jamaicensis</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/buteo-jamaicensis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buteo jamaicensis" /><published>2023-07-03T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-03T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/buteo-jamaicensis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/07/buteo-jamaicensis.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/P1010532_Hawk_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;red-tailed hawk&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Red-tailed_Hawk/overview&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Buteo jamaicensis&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; red-tailed hawk. I found this juvenile red-tailed hawk sitting on the sidewalk next door and being harassed by a couple of blue jays. While I was out on an errand, my neighbor took her to a rescue place, where they pronounced her to be female, 1.5 months old, and unable to fly yet, but not injured. They will keep her and release her when she can fly. She probably fell out of a nest in a nearby tree, but I saw no sign of parents taking care of her. The blue jays may also have a nest nearby, because they get very agitated when a hawk lands on a telephone pole in the backyard.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only a few days left to enter the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/photography-contest-xiv.html&quot;&gt;XIV-th Photography Contest&lt;/a&gt;! So dust your cameras, polish your lenses (but do not, God forbid, breathe on them), get out your tripods, zoom lenses, macro lenses, microscopes, and whatnot, even buy film, and submit up to Ⅲ entries to ProfessorSteveSteve@gmail.com. Professor Steve Steve has solemnly promised to forward your submissions promptly. Entries close Friday, July 7 at noon, MDT, and we will announce the finalists at noon, Monday, July 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below the fold, just for fun, a portrait of the hawk and a snapshot of one of the unhappy blue jays. The hawk is just below, on the other side of the fence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/P1010540_Hawk_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;red-tailed hawk&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/P1010544_Blue_Jay_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;blue jay&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Buteo jamaicensis &amp;ndash; red-tailed hawk. I found this juvenile red-tailed hawk sitting on the sidewalk next door and being harassed by a couple of blue jays. While I was out on an errand, my neighbor took her to a rescue place, where they pronounced her to be female, 1.5 months old, and unable to fly yet, but not injured. They will keep her and release her when she can fly. She probably fell out of a nest in a nearby tree, but I saw no sign of parents taking care of her. The blue jays may also have a nest nearby, because they get very agitated when a hawk lands on a telephone pole in the backyard. Only a few days left to enter the XIV-th Photography Contest! So dust your cameras, polish your lenses (but do not, God forbid, breathe on them), get out your tripods, zoom lenses, macro lenses, microscopes, and whatnot, even buy film, and submit up to Ⅲ entries to ProfessorSteveSteve@gmail.com. Professor Steve Steve has solemnly promised to forward your submissions promptly. Entries close Friday, July 7 at noon, MDT, and we will announce the finalists at noon, Monday, July 10. Below the fold, just for fun, a portrait of the hawk and a snapshot of one of the unhappy blue jays. The hawk is just below, on the other side of the fence.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Aquilegia chrysantha</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/Aquilegia-chrysantha.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aquilegia chrysantha" /><published>2023-06-26T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-06-26T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/Aquilegia%20chrysantha</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/Aquilegia-chrysantha.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2023/P1010458_Golden_Columbine_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Golden columbine&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fs.usda.gov/wildflowers/beauty/columbines/aquilegia_chrysantha.shtml&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Aquilegia chrysantha&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; golden columbine. A week or so ago, I was, as Feynman might say, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chem.fsu.edu/chemlab/isc3523c/feyn_surely.pdf&quot;&gt;observing the gorgeous garden&lt;/a&gt; of my friend Ron Wittmann (coauthor of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Colorado-Flora-Eastern-Fourth-Vascular/dp/1607321408&quot;&gt;Colorado Flora: Eastern Slope, Fourth Edition: A Field Guide to the Vascular Plants&lt;/a&gt;, as well as a companion volume on the western slope). It was raining and fairly nasty, but I managed this snapshot. This is not the Colorado state flower; that is the blue columbine, &lt;i&gt;A. caerulea&lt;/i&gt;. I have a picture of that too, but unfortunately it lacks the raindrops.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not quite half-time in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/06/photography-contest-xiv.html&quot;&gt;XIV-th Photography Contest&lt;/a&gt;, a bit over a week to go. So dust your cameras, polish your lenses (but not, God forbid, dry), get out your tripods, macro lenses, microscopes, and whatnot, even buy film, and submit up to Ⅲ entries to ProfessorSteveSteve@gmail.com. Professor Steve Steve has solemnly promised to forward your submissions promptly. Entries close July 7 at noon, MDT, and we will announce the finalists at noon, Monday, July 12.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Aquilegia chrysantha &amp;ndash; golden columbine. A week or so ago, I was, as Feynman might say, observing the gorgeous garden of my friend Ron Wittmann (coauthor of Colorado Flora: Eastern Slope, Fourth Edition: A Field Guide to the Vascular Plants, as well as a companion volume on the western slope). It was raining and fairly nasty, but I managed this snapshot. This is not the Colorado state flower; that is the blue columbine, A. caerulea. I have a picture of that too, but unfortunately it lacks the raindrops. Not quite half-time in the XIV-th Photography Contest, a bit over a week to go. So dust your cameras, polish your lenses (but not, God forbid, dry), get out your tripods, macro lenses, microscopes, and whatnot, even buy film, and submit up to Ⅲ entries to ProfessorSteveSteve@gmail.com. Professor Steve Steve has solemnly promised to forward your submissions promptly. Entries close July 7 at noon, MDT, and we will announce the finalists at noon, Monday, July 12.</summary></entry></feed>