<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-03-21T16:32:19-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Safeguarding Sound Science, Climate Change Edition</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/safeguarding-sound-science.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Safeguarding Sound Science, Climate Change Edition" /><published>2025-03-21T13:03:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-21T13:03:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/safeguarding-sound-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/safeguarding-sound-science.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Safeguarding_Sound_Science_600.jpg &quot; alt=&quot;Safeguarding Sound Science logo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safeguarding Sound Science combats misinformation, disinformation, and misconceptions about climate change with actual science. In the 7-episode &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/safeguarding-sound-science&quot;&gt;Season One: Climate Change Edition&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.planetary.org/profiles/mat-kaplan&quot;&gt;Mat Kaplan&lt;/a&gt; (Senior Communications Advisor of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.planetary.org/&quot;&gt;Planetary Society&lt;/a&gt; and former host of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.planetary.org/planetary-radio&quot;&gt;Planetary Radio&lt;/a&gt;) talks to scientists, teachers, and other experts to explore who’s behind some of the more insidious efforts to sow distrust in climate science, how those efforts filter down to schools and classrooms, and what is being done to ensure that everyone — especially students — is exposed to accurate climate science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of this writing, the first two installments have been posted: Episode 1: “What Climate Change? Tackling Climate Denial,” with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Mann&quot;&gt; Michael Mann&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glenn_Branch&quot;&gt;Glenn Branch&lt;/a&gt; of the National Center for Science Education; and Episode 2: “A Century of Disinformation: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naomi_Oreskes&quot;&gt;Naomi Oreskes&lt;/a&gt; and the Merchants of Doubt.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Reprinted with permission from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncse.ngo/catalyzing-action/sign-ncse-monitor&quot;&gt;The NCSE Monitor&lt;/a&gt; for March 21, 2025. You may access the podcasts using the Season One link above, or else use &lt;a href=&quot;https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/safeguarding-sound-science/id1797165552&quot;&gt;Apple Podcasts &lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/show/1VENQjGuH2fMycb2lDsT4Q&quot;&gt;Spotify&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Safeguarding Sound Science combats misinformation, disinformation, and misconceptions about climate change with actual science. In the 7-episode Season One: Climate Change Edition, Mat Kaplan (Senior Communications Advisor of the Planetary Society and former host of Planetary Radio) talks to scientists, teachers, and other experts to explore who’s behind some of the more insidious efforts to sow distrust in climate science, how those efforts filter down to schools and classrooms, and what is being done to ensure that everyone — especially students — is exposed to accurate climate science. As of this writing, the first two installments have been posted: Episode 1: “What Climate Change? Tackling Climate Denial,” with Michael Mann and Glenn Branch of the National Center for Science Education; and Episode 2: “A Century of Disinformation: Naomi Oreskes and the Merchants of Doubt.” Reprinted with permission from The NCSE Monitor for March 21, 2025. You may access the podcasts using the Season One link above, or else use Apple Podcasts or Spotify.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Martyn Iles no longer with AIG</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/martyn-iles-no-longer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Martyn Iles no longer with AIG" /><published>2025-03-19T12:58:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-19T12:58:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/martyn-iles-no-longer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/martyn-iles-no-longer.html">&lt;p&gt;Dan Phelps informs us that Martyn Iles is no longer with Answers in Genesis (AIG). Paul Braterman &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2023/11/Martyn-Iles-Is-Executive.html&quot;&gt;reported earlier&lt;/a&gt; on PT that Mr. Iles had ascended to the position of “Executive CEO” of AIG. I think we had all assumed that he was the heir apparent. Mr. Phelps asks,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;He was apparently [Ken] Ham's chosen successor. I noticed he didn't do much lately. Was there a dispute, or other trouble? Who will Ham pick to succeed him? Will there be a puff of white smoke above the Ark when the decision is made?&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not know the answers to any of those questions, but it is easy to infer from the Facebook post (reproduced below the fold) that Mr. Iles left AIG before he had an alternative in mind. Mr. Phelps notes further that Mr. Iles’s name had been dropped from the AIG speakers’ biography page by March 13, but it was there on February 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If anyone has any further information, please feel free to comment, but please avoid idle speculation and invective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a screenshot taken by Mr. Phelps on March 19:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Iles_No_Longer_1000.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Iles Facebook post&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Dan Phelps informs us that Martyn Iles is no longer with Answers in Genesis (AIG). Paul Braterman reported earlier on PT that Mr. Iles had ascended to the position of “Executive CEO” of AIG. I think we had all assumed that he was the heir apparent. Mr. Phelps asks, He was apparently [Ken] Ham's chosen successor. I noticed he didn't do much lately. Was there a dispute, or other trouble? Who will Ham pick to succeed him? Will there be a puff of white smoke above the Ark when the decision is made? We do not know the answers to any of those questions, but it is easy to infer from the Facebook post (reproduced below the fold) that Mr. Iles left AIG before he had an alternative in mind. Mr. Phelps notes further that Mr. Iles’s name had been dropped from the AIG speakers’ biography page by March 13, but it was there on February 3. If anyone has any further information, please feel free to comment, but please avoid idle speculation and invective.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pantherophis alleghaniensis-quadrivittatus</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/pantherophis-alleghaniensis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pantherophis alleghaniensis-quadrivittatus" /><published>2025-03-17T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-17T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/pantherophis-alleghaniensis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/pantherophis-alleghaniensis.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Al Denelsbeck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Denelsbeck_Pantherophis_alleghaniensis_quadrivittata.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Eastern ratsnake&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern_rat_snake&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Pantherophis alleghaniensis-quadrivittatus&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; eastern rat snake. You may find a discussion of the scientific name &lt;a href=&quot;https://auth1.dpr.ncparks.gov/reptiles/view.php?checklist_number=103.0&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Al Denelsbeck. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Pantherophis alleghaniensis-quadrivittatus &amp;ndash; eastern rat snake. You may find a discussion of the scientific name here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The President and the Paleontologist: Jimmy Carter’s Dalliance with Creationism and Stephen Jay Gould’s Stumble in Rebutting It</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/president-paleontologist.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The President and the Paleontologist: Jimmy Carter’s Dalliance with Creationism and Stephen Jay Gould’s Stumble in Rebutting It" /><published>2025-03-05T10:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-05T10:30:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/president-paleontologist</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/president-paleontologist.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Branch_Carter_Gould.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Left, Jimmy Carter. Right, Stephen Jay Gould.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Left, &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Jimmy_Carter_1971_a.jpg&quot;&gt;Jimmy Carter&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;small&gt;Wikimedia. Public domain. Not subject to copyright in the United States.&lt;/small&gt; Right, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Stephen_Jay_Gould_2015,_portrait_(unknown_date).jpg&quot;&gt;Stephen Jay Gould&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;small&gt;Wikimedia. Photograph posted by Wally McNamee. Fair use: copyright owner unknown.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Glenn Branch is deputy director of the National Center for Science Education, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as &lt;/i&gt;Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher, &lt;i&gt;and the &lt;/i&gt;Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics, &lt;i&gt;and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of &lt;/i&gt;Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools (2006). &lt;i&gt; He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Jimmy Carter &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2024/12/29/us/politics/jimmy-carter-dead.html&quot;&gt;died&lt;/a&gt; on December 29, 2024, the nation lost not only its 39th president but also a prominent born-again Christian who accepted evolution. In chapter 5 of his 2005 book &lt;i&gt;Our Endangered Values &lt;/i&gt;, entitled “No Conflict Between Science and Religion,” Carter insisted, “The existence of millions of distant galaxies, the evolution of species, and the big bang theory cannot be rejected because they are not described in the Bible, and neither does confidence in them cast doubt on the Creator of it all.” Yet in the late 1980s, he proposed a creationist argument to no less a figure than the Harvard paleontologist Stephen Jay Gould — whose rebuttal, surprisingly, was inadequate.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Gould related in a postscript to his 1988 essay “In a Jumbled Drawer” (reprinted in his 1991 book &lt;i&gt;Bully for Brontosaurus&lt;/i&gt;), Carter called him out of the blue one day in the late 1980s, “simply to express his good wishes and his hopes for my continued good health” (Gould was in remission from cancer). In gratitude, he then sent Carter a copy of &lt;i&gt;Wonderful Life&lt;/i&gt; (1989), his new book about the Cambrian fauna of the Burgess Shale. As was typical with Gould, the paleontology served as a springboard to explore a larger theme: “the ‘pageant’ of evolution as a staggeringly improbable series of events, sensible enough in retrospect and subject to rigorous explanation, but utterly unpredictable and quite unrepeatable.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having read &lt;i&gt;Wonderful Life&lt;/i&gt; with pleasure while attempting to defuse armed conflicts in the Horn of Africa, Carter nevertheless offered a counterargument:

&lt;blockquote&gt;You seem to be straining mightily to prove that everything that has happened prior to an evolutionary screening period was just an accident, and that if the tape of life was replayed in countless different ways it is unlikely that cognitive creatures [such as humans] would have been created or evolved. It may be that when you raise “one chance in a million” to the 4th or 5th power there comes a time when pure “chance” can be questioned. I presume that you feel more at ease with the luck of 1 out of 10 to the 30th power than with the concept of a creator who/that has done some orchestrating.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gould described Carter’s argument, a bit fulsomely, as “a brilliant riposte ... a brilliant twentieth-century version of natural theology ... fascinating.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he insisted that Carter’s argument was nevertheless wrong, and wrong for the same reason that a similar argument he discussed in “In a Jumbled Drawer,” due to the 19th-century Harvard paleontologist Nathaniel Shaler, was wrong: “because a probability cannot even be calculated for a singular occurrence known only after the fact.” (It’s because of the similarity of Shaler’s and Carter’s arguments that Gould added the postscript to “In a Jumbled Drawer.”) Gould approvingly quoted the 19th-century Harvard philosopher and psychologist William James, as writing, in a letter to Shaler, “Where only one fact is in question, there is no relation of ‘probability’ at all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gould’s answer to Carter thus presupposed that attributions to probability to individual events are not legitimate: it’s wrong to say that the chance that the next toss of a coin will be heads is 1 in 2, or that there’s a 30 percent chance of rain in Chicago tomorrow, or that the probability that a given atom of cobalt-60 will decay in about 5.27 years is 0.5. Such a view is indeed accepted by a few (such as the mathematician Richard von Mises, who famously declared, “The phrase ‘probability of death,’ when it refers to a single person, has no meaning at all for us”), but it is hard to square with the abundance in ordinary life and scientific practice of attributions to probability to individual events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;i&gt;Wonderful Life&lt;/i&gt; itself abounds in such attributions. Early in the book, Gould explained, “This book is about the nature of history and the overwhelming improbability of human evolution under themes of contingency and the metaphor of replaying life’s tape”; toward the end, he mused, with reference to &lt;i&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/i&gt;, “we are an improbable and fragile entity,” and interpolated a new adjective in a familiar Shakespearean line: “O brave — and improbable — new world, that has such people in it!” In light of these and similar passages, it is hardly fair for Gould to have faulted Carter for wanting to discuss the improbability of human existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What should Gould have said to Carter instead? Carter in effect was arguing that because the probability of human existence is very low on the hypothesis of evolution without divine guidance, and humans yet exist, the hypothesis of evolution without divine guidance is therefore false. But the form of inference is incorrect, as the philosopher Elliott Sober (among others) &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1023/A:1019579220694&quot;&gt;observes&lt;/a&gt;. To see why, take a homely example exactly parallel to Carter’s. Suppose that you buy a single Powerball ticket. If the drawing is conducted properly, it is very improbable (about 1 in 300 million) that you hold a jackpot ticket. But if you turn out to hold a jackpot ticket, are you entitled to infer that the drawing was rigged in your favor? Surely not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Endorsement of the incorrect form of inference is not limited to creationists. The biologist Richard Dawkins, who is about as far from creationism as anyone could be, fell into the trap in his discussion of the origin of life in &lt;i&gt;The Blind Watchmaker&lt;/i&gt; (1986), for example. But it is common among creationists, and Carter’s argument was creationist, at least in a broad sense, for he thought that it showed that it was scientifically necessary to appeal to divine guidance in explaining the facts of life. That was apparently a deviation from his settled views on science and religion, however: in &lt;i&gt;Our Endangered Values&lt;/i&gt;, he relates, “I had always understood that we didn’t need scientific proof of the existence or character of God.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It actually isn’t clear what Carter himself thought of Gould’s rebuttal. In &lt;i&gt;Living Faith&lt;/i&gt; (1996), he wrote that Gould “later contradicted my argument — with good humor.” But in his later book &lt;i&gt;Our Endangered Values&lt;/i&gt;, he seemed a little miffed, writing, “He didn’t respond directly, but subsequently quoted and slyly ridiculed my opinion.” Any rancor evidently subsided by the time of &lt;i&gt;Faith: A Journey for All&lt;/i&gt; (2018), in which Carter listed the influences on his thinking about theology and philosophy, ending with Gould. Although he alluded to their arguments “about facts or principles,” he stressed their agreement about science and described Gould’s &lt;i&gt;Rocks of Ages&lt;/i&gt; (1999) as one of his favorite books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, despite his dalliance with the creationist argument he proposed to Gould, Carter was a stalwart defender of the teaching of evolution. In 1980, as the presidential contest was peaking, his challenger Ronald Reagan declared that evolution “is a scientific theory only” and that “the biblical theory of creation” deserved a place in public schools. Carter &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.210.4465.35&quot;&gt;replied&lt;/a&gt;, through his science adviser, that the scientific evidence for evolution was convincing and that schools ought to respect the constitutional separation of church and state. Since creationism was &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.gallup.com/poll/21814/evolution-creationism-intelligent-design.aspx&quot;&gt;favored&lt;/a&gt; by about 44 percent of the American public at the time, Carter’s reply was — typically for him — both principled and courageous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;i&gt;Reprinted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://rightingamerica.net/the-president-and-the-paleontologist-jimmy-carters-dalliance-with-creationism-and-stephen-jay-goulds-stumble-in-rebutting-it/&quot;&gt; Righting America&lt;/a&gt; with the permission of Glenn Branch and William Trollinger.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Glenn Branch</name></author><summary type="html">Left, Jimmy Carter. Wikimedia. Public domain. Not subject to copyright in the United States. Right, Stephen Jay Gould. Wikimedia. Photograph posted by Wally McNamee. Fair use: copyright owner unknown. Glenn Branch is deputy director of the National Center for Science Education, a nonprofit organization that defends the integrity of American science education against ideological interference. He is the author of numerous articles on evolution education and climate education, and obstacles to them, in such publications as Scientific American, American Educator, The American Biology Teacher, and the Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics, and the co-editor, with Eugenie C. Scott, of Not in Our Classrooms: Why Intelligent Design is Wrong for Our Schools (2006). He received the Evolution Education Award for 2020 from the National Association of Biology Teachers. When Jimmy Carter died on December 29, 2024, the nation lost not only its 39th president but also a prominent born-again Christian who accepted evolution. In chapter 5 of his 2005 book Our Endangered Values , entitled “No Conflict Between Science and Religion,” Carter insisted, “The existence of millions of distant galaxies, the evolution of species, and the big bang theory cannot be rejected because they are not described in the Bible, and neither does confidence in them cast doubt on the Creator of it all.” Yet in the late 1980s, he proposed a creationist argument to no less a figure than the Harvard paleontologist Stephen Jay Gould — whose rebuttal, surprisingly, was inadequate.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Spatula clypeata</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/spatula-clypeata.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spatula clypeata" /><published>2025-03-03T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-03T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/spatula-clypeata</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/spatula-clypeata.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/P1031480_Northern_Shoveler_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Northern shoveler&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Northern_Shoveler/overview&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Spatula clypeata&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; northern shoveler, East Boulder (Colorado) Community Center, February, 2025. It was hard to get a halfway decent picture of this pair, because they kept swimming around in circles with their bills in the water, almost as if they were filter feeding. According to the link, in fact they &lt;i&gt;were&lt;/i&gt; filter feeding: &quot;Shovelers eat tiny crustaceans, other aquatic invertebrates, and seeds which they filter out of the water with comblike projections (called lamellae) along the edge of the bill.&quot; You may see a nice picture of the lamellae &lt;a href=&quot;https://roadsendnaturalist.com/2016/02/24/meandering-at-mattamuskeet/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Spatula clypeata &amp;ndash; northern shoveler, East Boulder (Colorado) Community Center, February, 2025. It was hard to get a halfway decent picture of this pair, because they kept swimming around in circles with their bills in the water, almost as if they were filter feeding. According to the link, in fact they were filter feeding: &quot;Shovelers eat tiny crustaceans, other aquatic invertebrates, and seeds which they filter out of the water with comblike projections (called lamellae) along the edge of the bill.&quot; You may see a nice picture of the lamellae here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">State Police Proselytized during K9 Training at Ark Park; No Word on How Dogs Reacted</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/state-police-proselytized.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="State Police Proselytized during K9 Training at Ark Park; No Word on How Dogs Reacted" /><published>2025-03-01T14:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-01T14:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/state-police-proselytized</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/03/state-police-proselytized.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_KSP_Ark_Fig_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kentucky trooper with dog&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2020, the Kentucky State Police (KSP) were embroiled in a controversy after it was discovered that a &lt;a href=&quot;https://manualredeye.com/90096/news/local/police-training-hitler-presentation/&quot;&gt;training PowerPoint presentation&lt;/a&gt; quoted Adolf Hitler and advocated ruthless violence.  In spite of this horrendous exception, the Kentucky State Police is well-respected and noted for their professionalism and devotion to duty. Imagine my surprise when I learned that the KSP paid Answers in Genesis (AIG) to send an officer on a K9 training class on February 1 to 4, 2025, at the Ark Encounter. Besides K9 training, the class included Fundamentalist Christian and Christian Nationalist propaganda. With the government agencies and politicians increasingly becoming entangled Christian Nationalism, this incident is particularly disturbing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On February 7, 2025, Ken Ham &lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2025/02/07/aig-impacts-law-enforcement-k-9-conference/&quot;&gt;bragged&lt;/a&gt; in his daily blog that the AIG Department of Public Safety had hosted numerous law enforcement organizations in K9 training at the Ark. Photos indicated a Kentucky State Police officer was there with his vehicle, as were several other regional law enforcement agencies. Moreover, an organization known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://tacticaministries.org/&quot;&gt;TACTICA Ministries&lt;/a&gt; (Teaching Authorities Christian Truth in Central America) was also present. My curiosity was immediately piqued by the presence of the KSP trooper. The questions I immediately had were, “Why is a major law enforcement organization being trained by AIG?” and “Why isn’t AIG going to a major organization like the KSP for training instead?” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then wrote a Kentucky Open Records Act (KORA) request. Surprisingly, perhaps as a delaying tactic, my initial request was rejected. The rejection claimed I was not a Kentucky resident, even though I specifically said I was a resident in the KORA request. (I was born here and have owned a house which I have lived in in Lexington for more than 20 years. Many of my ancestors came to the state with Daniel Boone in the late 18th Century.) I resubmitted the request and received a small number of documents. Some of the requested information was not available; no mileage records were kept, and the KSP trooper did not save all of his training materials. Additional withheld information included the redaction of the identities of all third-party instructors “…due to sensitivity of their respective jobs and the need for anonymity.” Were these third-party instructors members of government law enforcement? We may never know. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The open records information showed that Kentucky taxpayers paid approximately $225 for the training of one officer. This doesn’t include money spent by other Kentucky law enforcement agencies. Kentucky law enforcement from Villa Hills Police Department and the Boone County Sheriff’s Office participated. Some out-of-state regional law enforcement that participated included the Genesee County Ohio, Twinsburg (Ohio) Police Department, and the Collier County (Florida) Sheriff’s Department. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event included several breakfasts and lunches, as well as one diner that was sponsored by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nutramaxlabs.com/our-passion&quot;&gt; Nutramax Laboratories&lt;/a&gt; (a company that produces supplements for pets and does a lot of evangelism on the side). Interestingly, the event Welcome Package showed that each lunch included “testimony.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_KSP_Ark_Attachment.pdf&quot;&gt;Welcome Package&lt;/a&gt; for the event also included a message from AIG’s Department of Public Safety’s Sgt. Adam Witherspoon: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also, AIG Dept of Public Safety makes no effort to hide who we are. We care deeply about your working relationship with your dog and want to do everything we can to help you improve as a K9 team. More importantly though we care about you as an individual. God created all of us in His image. Due to our sin, and we are all sinners, Romans 3:23-24. 23. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;...for all have sinned and fall short of the glory of God, 24. being justified as a gift by His grace through the redemption which is in Christ Jesus; we are condemned to spend eternity
separated from God. Jesus Christ however took our punishment on the Cross. Our most sincere prayer is that if you don’t know Jesus Christ as your savior, come and talk to us. We
would love to share with you the Good News of the Gospel, which grants us eternity with God in heaven. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let’s get to some great training, enjoy some great food, fellowship, and learning, and I look forward to meeting and getting to know each one of you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In His Service,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; Sgt Adam Witherspoon &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_KSP_Ark_Fig_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tactica ministries hat&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_KSP_Ark_Fig_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Memorization Card&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt; A presentation at the K9 training (and a major vendor/sponsor) was by a Michigan-based TACTICA Ministries. This ministry apparently gives police/paramilitary training plus substantial religious instruction to police forces in Central and South American countries. Disturbingly, there are numerous YouTube videos available of TACTICA paramilitary training set to high energy Christian music (see: https://youtu.be/x7PKZ7_KA3w?feature=shared, https://youtu.be/SAwjK4QzLUM?si=xvhnvOajsXJ4X53I, and https://youtu.be/ZoHRcZ4SmP0?si=cowgfvsRRT4D-yqi). Figure 2 is a hat that TACTICA Ministries sells. Apparently, part of the TACTICA “training” at the event included memorization of Bible verses on a “Memorization Card.” What do any of these verses have to do with K9 training? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TACTICA Ministries is run by Ryan Rought. At least one presentation was done by Mr. Rought. The training documents give this biography and description of Rought’s work: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ryan is a man fervently committed to his Christian faith, his family, and serving others. His energy is contagious as he is unashamedly committed to investing in the public safety community through high quality training, relationship building, and Gospel centered teaching. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several other participants' biographies mention going on mission trips and long term training in with TACTICA Ministries, including Marty Buffenbarger (2.5 years with TACTICA in Costa Rica), Chris Carpenter of Livingston Security Solutions (several training mission trips), and Bill and Cindy Gruppen (also of Association of Baptists for World Evangelism). The Gruppens' bios indicate that their “mission is to share God's good news through creative and impactful avenues.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the itinerary, a good deal of the first day of training (14:00 to 19:00) involved signing in and “roaming” the Ark. This visitation combined with the speakers' bios and other activities, such as lunchtime “testimonials” show that religious instruction and evangelism of law enforcement officers was a substantial portion of the K9 training. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_KSP_Ark_Fig_4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot; Officer Charity, a K9 dog&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is some evidence that the KSP and other Kentucky law enforcement has participated in similar past events. On July 9, 2024, conservative Republican Kentucky Attorney General Russell Coleman posted pictures of “K9 Officer Charity” in front of the Ark Encounter. Officer Charity is a K9 with the Attorney General’s Office’s Department of Criminal Investigations. This sweet doggie has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/officercharity_k9/&quot;&gt; her own Instagram page&lt;/a&gt;. (The Attorney General’s post mentions that the KSP and the Boone County Sheriff’s Office participated in K9 training at the Ark in early July 2024. The instruction in February 2025 is probably one of several similar events that have used taxpayer money for an odd combination of training and evangelism.) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More disturbing than the use of taxpayer funding to evangelize law enforcement is the likelihood of the officers being indoctrinated in Christian Nationalism. Answers in Genesis is becoming more and more an advocate for far-right politics. On February 25, 2025, Founder CEO of Answers in Genesis, Ken Ham, posted an essay on his blog titled “&lt;a href=&quot;https://answersingenesis.org/blogs/ken-ham/2025/02/25/what-happens-when-your-god-dies/&quot;&gt;What Happens When Your God Dies&lt;/a&gt;.” In this political essay he attacks “wokeness,” “racist” DEI hiring, pronoun use, and transgender ideology while praising the new administration and attacking Democrats. This theme is common throughout AIG’s online publications. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Phelps_KSP_Ark_Fig_5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;God's religion, according to AIG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On July 15, 2023, Bodie Hodge (Ken Ham’s son-in-law) had an essay on AIG’s page called “The Religion of Sexual Humanism” (you may now find it on the Wayback Machine &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20250114135356/https://answersingenesis.org/culture/religion-sexual-humanism/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). In this post, Hodge claims what he and AIG represent is “God’s Religion” while most other people belong to “Not God’s Religion.” Note that “Not God’s Religion” has a sub-section “Counterfeits of Biblical Christianity” that includes Roman Catholics, Seventh Day Adventists, Mormons, Jehovah’s Witnesses, Unitarians, “Moonies,” and even more bizarrely (if possible) Jews, Muslims, Freemasons, and Satanists (isn’t that special?) among many others. Eastern religions and secularism are given separate categories in this incredible (in the literal sense of the word) chart. I almost find this chart comical, but considering the very real possibility of Christian Nationalism becoming an arm of the government, the graphic is simply horrifying. AIG is very well-connected in state politics and apparently is looking to expand their reach. At one point Ken Ham was scheduled to speak at an event on April 24 along with Secretary of Defense Pete Hegseth and Franklin Graham. Recently, Hegseth backed out, presumably because of other duties, but a list of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20250117152827/https://www.dayspringchristian.com/remember-america/speaker-series/&quot;&gt;originally scheduled speakers is available on the Internet Wayback Machine&lt;/a&gt; as recently as January 17, 2025. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every July the Tri-State Freethinkers have a protest near the entrance to Ark Encounter to protest the fake science plus the sales-tax rebate incentives and other handouts that the Ark has received from state, county, and Williamstown governments. I have avoided participating in this event in the past because of concerns about the event’s effectiveness and the possibility of a creationist provocateur causing a disruption. I was recently asked to speak at this event. I am frankly very hesitant. I have to wonder whether law enforcement will look the other way if the protest is attacked, actively disrupt the protest, or find another way of punishing or harassing the participants. In any case the government should not be paying to give their employees religious instruction especially when the employees are in a position where fairness and equanimity should be standard. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dan Phelps</name></author><summary type="html">Back in 2020, the Kentucky State Police (KSP) were embroiled in a controversy after it was discovered that a training PowerPoint presentation quoted Adolf Hitler and advocated ruthless violence. In spite of this horrendous exception, the Kentucky State Police is well-respected and noted for their professionalism and devotion to duty. Imagine my surprise when I learned that the KSP paid Answers in Genesis (AIG) to send an officer on a K9 training class on February 1 to 4, 2025, at the Ark Encounter. Besides K9 training, the class included Fundamentalist Christian and Christian Nationalist propaganda. With the government agencies and politicians increasingly becoming entangled Christian Nationalism, this incident is particularly disturbing. On February 7, 2025, Ken Ham bragged in his daily blog that the AIG Department of Public Safety had hosted numerous law enforcement organizations in K9 training at the Ark. Photos indicated a Kentucky State Police officer was there with his vehicle, as were several other regional law enforcement agencies. Moreover, an organization known as TACTICA Ministries (Teaching Authorities Christian Truth in Central America) was also present. My curiosity was immediately piqued by the presence of the KSP trooper. The questions I immediately had were, “Why is a major law enforcement organization being trained by AIG?” and “Why isn’t AIG going to a major organization like the KSP for training instead?”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fratercula arctica</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/fratercula-arctica.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fratercula arctica" /><published>2025-02-17T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-02-17T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/fratercula-arctica</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/fratercula-arctica.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/IMG_0662_Puffin_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Puffin&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlantic_puffin&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;Fratercula arctica&lt;/i&gt;   &amp;ndash; Atlantic puffin, Iceland, August, 2010.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The eminent physicist R.W. Wood is well remembered for his work &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/physicaloptic00wood/&quot;&gt;Physical Optics&lt;/a&gt;, published in 1911. I always had a paperback handy and used it well into the 1990’s. In 1907, Wood published &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/1593&quot;&gt;How to Tell the Birds from the Flowers&lt;/a&gt;, A Manual of Flornithology for Beginners&lt;/i&gt;, illustrated by the author. His discussion of the puffin follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Upon this cake of ice is perched,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paddle-footed Puffin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find his double we have searched,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But have discovered—Nuffin!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The puffin is the only creature in the book that has no double.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Fratercula arctica &amp;ndash; Atlantic puffin, Iceland, August, 2010. The eminent physicist R.W. Wood is well remembered for his work Physical Optics, published in 1911. I always had a paperback handy and used it well into the 1990’s. In 1907, Wood published How to Tell the Birds from the Flowers, A Manual of Flornithology for Beginners, illustrated by the author. His discussion of the puffin follows: Upon this cake of ice is perched, The paddle-footed Puffin To find his double we have searched, But have discovered—Nuffin! The puffin is the only creature in the book that has no double.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Conservation of arguments</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/Conservation-of-arguments.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Conservation of arguments" /><published>2025-02-06T21:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2025-02-06T21:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/Conservation-of-arguments</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/Conservation-of-arguments.html">&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Peas.png&quot; alt=&quot;[not-too-hard Shell game]&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A shell game in which 
the odds are not too bad,&lt;br /&gt; especially as we can see what's going on.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Dembski has recently made two posts (&lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2025/01/the-displacement-fallacy-evolutions-shell-game/&quot;&gt;on January 10&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2025/01/conservation-of-information-the-history-of-an-idea/&quot;&gt;on January 20&lt;/a&gt;) at
&lt;em&gt;Evolution News&lt;/em&gt;, the advocacy site of the Discovery Institute’s Center for 
Science and Culture.  He describes them as sections of a paper he 
submitted to the DI’s house journal BIO-Complexity.  The paper was not 
immediately accepted, he said, and in the meantime he wanted to post the
sections at EN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Dembski declares in the preface to the first of these posts, their argument in these posts is, in effect, that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Conservation of information is a big result of the intelligent design literature, even if to date it hasn’t gotten the attention it deserves. It quantifies the amount of information needed to increase the probability of finding a needle in a haystack so that the needle can actually be found. The upshot of conservation of information is that the information needed to find a needle in a haystack in turn requires finding another needle in a haystack, implying there is no free lunch in search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Dembski’s account, when evolutionary biologists argue that processes such as natural selection can put 
adaptive information into the genome, they are failing to explain where the information comes from.  They are 
building it into their evolutionary algorithms as a detailed goal, and not informing the reader that they have done that.  The biologists’ argument has thus simply displaced the question, not answered it.  Dembski’s first post is illustrated by an illustration of the Shell Game, to label the argument of evolutionary biologists as a dishonest trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, the two posts leave Dembski’s argument no further than it was 
some years ago.  We can deal with it without going into great detail, 
because we have seen these arguments before.  Let’s ask, and answer, some brief questions as to what 
was accomplished:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;do-these-posts-clarify-how-his-algorithmically-specified-complexity-argument-deals-with-natural-selection&quot;&gt;Do these posts clarify how his Algorithmically Specified Complexity argument deals with natural selection?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, not at all.  That argument, which was the centerpiece of Dembski and Ewert’s recent book: &lt;em&gt;The Design Inference: Eliminating Chance through Small Probabilities, 2nd edition&lt;/em&gt;, which I discussed &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2024/11/dembskiewert2.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; recently, was left hanging by them, with 
the essential questions unanswered.  And Dembski’s recent two EN posts do not discuss ASC at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;have-we-seen-the-arguments-of-the-recent-en-posts-before&quot;&gt;Have we seen the arguments of the recent EN posts before?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes.  Applied to evolution, the conservation of information argument is 
the Active Information argument of Dembski and Marks, which has been 
discussed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.evoinfo.org/papers/2009_ConservationOfInformationInSearch.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://bio-complexity.org/ojs/index.php/main/article/download/BIO-C.2013.4/BIO-C.2013.4&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  It basically says that 
if natural selection can find genotypes of better fitness by climbing 
uphill on a fitness surface, that this &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; an increase of 
information in the genome.  But, they argued, it is not creating new information, 
because the information was already there in the structure of 
the fitness surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;does-the-active-information-argument-rule-out-any-role-for-natural-selection&quot;&gt;Does the Active Information argument rule out any role for natural selection?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not at all, as you can see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-dembski-and-ewert-and-marks-accept-that-natural-selection-explains-adaptations&quot;&gt;So Dembski (and Ewert and Marks) accept that natural selection explains adaptations?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, they are arguing that &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; natural selection can increase 
specfied information in the genome, this is not new 
information.  But they have always been very resistant to 
acknowledging that natural selection does much in 
evolution. In the first of the two EN posts that we 
are discussing, Dembski grapples with Richard Dawkins’s 
book &lt;em&gt;Climbing Mount Improbable&lt;/em&gt;.  Dawkins gives examples of 
natural selection achieving major adaptations by gradual 
small changes.  Dembski calls Dawkins’s argument “displacement”, 
arguing this way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It could be that Mount Improbable is sheer on all sides and getting to the top via baby-steps is effectively impossible. Consequently, it is not enough to presuppose that a fitness-increasing sequence of baby steps always connects biological systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Dembski argues that Dawkins’s examples are a misleading reflection of how 
well (or badly) natural selection will typically be able to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;connection-to-possible-and-likely-fitness-surfaces&quot;&gt;Connection to possible, and likely, fitness surfaces&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dembski argues that fitness surfaces that allow natural selection to work are unlikely, and their existence needs explanation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mountains, after all, do not magically materialize — they have to be formed by some process of mountain formation. Of all the different ways Mount Improbable might have emerged, how many are sheer so that no gradual path to the summit exists? And how many do allow a gradual path to the summit? A Mount Improbable with gradual paths to the top may itself be improbable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improbable in what sense?  We’ll see that only a tiny fraction of all possible fitness surfaces 
will be smooth – but this is true only if all possible fitness surfaces are equally probable.  Which they definitely are not.  Smooth ones are vastly more probable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;connection-to-the-no-free-lunch-argument&quot;&gt;Connection to the No Free Lunch argument&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue has come up before, in Dembski’s 2001 book “No Free Lunch: Why Specified Complexity Cannot Be Purchased without Intelligence”.  There he invokes a mathematical theorem about the success of search algorithms on all possible problems.  This is the No Free Lunch theorem of Wolpert and Macready, which shows that &lt;em&gt;averaged over all possible problems&lt;/em&gt; all search algorithms do equally well, and are no more successful than examining a random set of points and choosing the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolpert and Macready did not prove that all search algorithms will do that badly in finding large values of, say, fitness on all fitness surfaces.  As Dembski’s title says, he cites Wolpert and Macready’s theorem as showing that we need to invoke intelligence, as we cannot expect that natural selection on fitness surfaces to find genomes of better fitness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;was-dembskis-2001-no-free-lunch-argument-refuted&quot;&gt;Was Dembski’s 2001 No Free Lunch argument refuted?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, almost immediately, by many authors, including &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.talkorigins.org/design/faqs/nfl/&quot;&gt;Richard Wein&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://educ.jmu.edu/~rosenhjd/dembski.pdf&quot;&gt;Jason Rosenhouse&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/7429/ef6c62a9cd544df79f0b21985c42dddf138f.pdf?_ga=2.130757519.169921541.1540934691-51823296.1540934691&quot;&gt;the late Mark Perakh&lt;/a&gt;, by Wesley Elsberry and Jeffrey Shallit (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.talkreason.org/articles/eandsdembski.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007%2Fs11229-009-9542-8.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), by &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20071011030112mp_/http://www.talkreason.org/articles/nfl_gavrilets6.pdf&quot;&gt;Erik Tellgren&lt;/a&gt; and by &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007%2Fs10539-006-9040-z.pdf&quot;&gt;Ole Häggström&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nfl-and-smoothness-of-fitness-surface&quot;&gt;NFL and smoothness of fitness surface&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the original Wolpert-MacReady No Free Lunch theorem considers all possible 
problems, it has a space, such as all possible genomes.  Each is assigned a 
value (such as a fitness), and &lt;em&gt;all possible assignments are considered&lt;/em&gt;.  In effect, 
the fitnesses are scrambled among the genotypes in all possible ways, all equally 
probable.  So when we see a fitness of a genotype, what can we say about the 
fitness of a nearby genotype, say one which differs by a single change of a 
single base?  &lt;em&gt;Nothing&lt;/em&gt;.  Every possible DNA sequence has its fitness assigned 
at random, including the nearest neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads to vast numbers of infinitely rough fitness surfaces, of “white noise” 
fitness surfaces. They have no 
smoothness whatsoever.  Dembski’s original NFL argument is that these do not allow for 
much evolution.  If they were typical of fitness surfaces in nature, this would be 
a big obstacle to the effectiveness of natural selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;empirical-evidence-on-mutational-effects&quot;&gt;Empirical evidence on mutational effects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such fitness surfaces are very, very atypical in real biology.  Look at it 
this way: the effect of a single base mutation on such a surface is 
to carry us to a genotype whose fitness is just like that of a 
totally random sequence, one which differs by being mutated at 75 percent 
of the sites!   If this were a human genome, it would be mutated at about 
2,250,000,000 sites simultaneously.  The idea that the effect of one mutation 
is the same as the effect of billions of mutations is bizarre and unreal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when Dembski considers “all the different ways” that a fitness 
surface could have emerged, overwhelmingly those are unreal 
fitness surfaces that would never emerge in real biological cases.
Real ones are much smoother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tight-interaction&quot;&gt;Tight Interaction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only does the equidistribution of all possible fitness 
surfaces imply unreal effects of mutations, it also implies 
incredibly tight interactions between all mutations.  Consider 
the effect of a mutation at one site, and the effect of a 
mutation at another site, millions of sites away.  We’ve 
seen that in the NFL distribution of fitnesses, these two 
mutations are each probably disastrous.  But what about the 
interaction between them?  What if we make both of these 
changes?  Even if each of the two mutations happened to have 
a mild effect on fitness, what would be the effect if both 
mutations occurred?   We cannot predict that the effect would 
also be mild.  Because the fitness would, once again, be drawn 
totally at random, with no predictability from the effects of 
single mutations.  The result is an incredibly strong, and 
unpredictable, interaction between mutations at these two 
sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not just these two sites – at all pairs of sites, and at 
all combinations of sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No biological system works like this.  Mutational changes 
in the genes affecting the production of earwax generally 
have little effect on the development of our kidneys.  And 
for a very simple reason – these are processes separated 
in time and space, and in the real world it is hard for them 
to interact strongly.  In the NFL world, every gene, by default, 
interacts incredibly strongly with everything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-anthropogenetic-principle&quot;&gt;The Anthrop(ogenet)ic Principle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Natural selection could achieve very little if fitness 
surfaces were rough, white-noise surfaces.  We can 
conclude that they aren’t those, because we have in 
fact evolved.  This is, in a sense, like the 
Anthropic Principle in cosmology.  We’re here, so 
we must have been able to evolve.  Perhaps it should 
be called the Anthrop(ogenet)ic Principle.  Of course 
this argument would not convince an “ID theorist” who 
does not believe that natural selection played a 
major role in our evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;choice-of-region-of-the-fitness-surface&quot;&gt;Choice of region of the fitness surface&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When different parts of a fitnes surface have different 
properties, the Anthropogenetic Principle argues that 
life evolved into a region that had sufficient smoothness. 
That is, it sought out evolvability.  Computer simulations 
by Lee Altenberg and Kenneth Kinnear and Günter Wagner 
have shown evolution doing this,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;and-what-about-physics-itself&quot;&gt;And what about physics itself?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if the properties of the fitness surface have 
not evolved, it seems reasonable that physics itself 
predisposes fitness surfaces to be smooth.  After all, 
the forces of physics tend to be local in time and space 
and to lose influence with greater distance.  If I 
gesture with my fingers, there is hardly any effect 
on objects at a distance.  The floor of our room 
does not collapse, nor does the ceiling cave in. Different 
objects are scarcely affected by each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may summarize briefly that William Dembski’s conservation- 
of-information argument is not new, and has been convincingly 
dismissed in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Altenberg L 1994. Kinnear, Kenneth (ed.). “The evolution of evolvability in genetic programming”. &lt;em&gt;Advances in Genetic Programming&lt;/em&gt;, pp. 47–74.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Altenberg L. 1995. “Genome growth and the evolution of the genotype–phenotype map”. &lt;em&gt;Evolution and Biocomputation.&lt;/em&gt; Lecture Notes in Computer Science. Vol. 899. pp. 205–259.  doi:10.1007/3-540-59046-3_11.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wagner G.P., and Altenberg L. 1996. “Perspective: Complex adaptations and the evolution of evolvability”. &lt;em&gt;Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 50 (3): 967–976.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">A shell game in which the odds are not too bad, especially as we can see what's going on. &amp;nbsp; William Dembski has recently made two posts (on January 10 and on January 20) at Evolution News, the advocacy site of the Discovery Institute’s Center for Science and Culture. He describes them as sections of a paper he submitted to the DI’s house journal BIO-Complexity. The paper was not immediately accepted, he said, and in the meantime he wanted to post the sections at EN. As Dembski declares in the preface to the first of these posts, their argument in these posts is, in effect, that Conservation of information is a big result of the intelligent design literature, even if to date it hasn’t gotten the attention it deserves. It quantifies the amount of information needed to increase the probability of finding a needle in a haystack so that the needle can actually be found. The upshot of conservation of information is that the information needed to find a needle in a haystack in turn requires finding another needle in a haystack, implying there is no free lunch in search. In Dembski’s account, when evolutionary biologists argue that processes such as natural selection can put adaptive information into the genome, they are failing to explain where the information comes from. They are building it into their evolutionary algorithms as a detailed goal, and not informing the reader that they have done that. The biologists’ argument has thus simply displaced the question, not answered it. Dembski’s first post is illustrated by an illustration of the Shell Game, to label the argument of evolutionary biologists as a dishonest trick. Actually, the two posts leave Dembski’s argument no further than it was some years ago. We can deal with it without going into great detail, because we have seen these arguments before. Let’s ask, and answer, some brief questions as to what was accomplished:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A plug for The Elements of Marie Curie, by Dava Sobel</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/plug-elements-marie-curie.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A plug for The Elements of Marie Curie, by Dava Sobel" /><published>2025-02-04T13:31:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-02-04T13:31:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/plug-elements-marie-curie</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/plug-elements-marie-curie.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: 10px; margin-right: 40px; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/Sobel_Marie_Curie_Cover_600.jpg &quot; alt=&quot;Book cover&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a plug, not a review. The full title is &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Elements-Marie-Curie-Radium-Science/dp/0802163823/&quot;&gt;The Elements of Marie Curie&lt;/a&gt;: How the Glow of Radium Lit a Path for Women in Science&lt;/i&gt;, by Dava Sobel. The use of “elements” in the title is a pun in more ways than one: besides Mme. Curie’s discovery of radium and polonium, each chapter is related, sometimes very tenuously, to a chemical element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is a scientific biography of Marie Curie and her myriad of protégées. Interestingly, though Madame Curie was sometimes perceived early on as Pierre Curie’s assistant, and as a woman she was not voted into the &lt;i&gt;Académie des sciences&lt;/i&gt;, Ms. Sobel gives no indication of any deliberate prejudice. In North America, by contrast, at least one of her protégées was threatened with losing her job if she married, and another simply gave up science upon her marriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dava_Sobel&quot;&gt;Dava Sobel&lt;/a&gt; is a distinguished science writer with several science biographies to her name. It has been my pleasure to read &lt;i&gt;Longitude&lt;/i&gt;, the story of John Harrison, who invented the naval chronometer and should be a household name; &lt;i&gt;Galileo’s Daughter&lt;/i&gt;; and &lt;i&gt;The Glass Universe&lt;/i&gt;, about how a number of women at Harvard College Observatory revolutionized astronomy, while working essentially for peanuts. In addition, Ms. Sobel has written a play, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davasobel.com/books-by-dava-sobel/and-the-sun-stood-still-book&quot;&gt;And the Sun Stood Still&lt;/a&gt;, about Copernicus; I was indeed privileged to see the premiere of the play by the Boulder Ensemble Theatre Company, as well as an earlier staged reading while the play was being workshopped. All told, depending how you count, Ms. Sobel has written a half-dozen scientific biographies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">This is a plug, not a review. The full title is The Elements of Marie Curie: How the Glow of Radium Lit a Path for Women in Science, by Dava Sobel. The use of “elements” in the title is a pun in more ways than one: besides Mme. Curie’s discovery of radium and polonium, each chapter is related, sometimes very tenuously, to a chemical element. The book is a scientific biography of Marie Curie and her myriad of protégées. Interestingly, though Madame Curie was sometimes perceived early on as Pierre Curie’s assistant, and as a woman she was not voted into the Académie des sciences, Ms. Sobel gives no indication of any deliberate prejudice. In North America, by contrast, at least one of her protégées was threatened with losing her job if she married, and another simply gave up science upon her marriage.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Uria sp.</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/uria-sp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Uria sp." /><published>2025-02-03T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-02-03T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/uria-sp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2025/02/uria-sp.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2025/IMG_0750_Common_Murre_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Murre&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/animal/murre&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;Uria&lt;/i&gt; sp., probably &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Common_Murre/id&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;U. aalge&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; common murre, or guillemot (but what do I know?), Iceland, August, 2010.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Uria sp., probably U. aalge &amp;ndash; common murre, or guillemot (but what do I know?), Iceland, August, 2010.</summary></entry></feed>