<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-03-16T02:06:43-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Panda’s Thumb</title><entry><title type="html">Victoria Mine</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/03/victoria-mine.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Victoria Mine" /><published>2022-03-14T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-03-14T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/03/victoria%20mine</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/03/victoria-mine.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Alan Rice&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Rice_Alan.Copper Ore-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Victoria Mine&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
100 meters underground in the Victoria Mine, Ely, Nevada. The small but extremely high-grade copper ore body is made up of copper minerals:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Azurite&quot;&gt;azurite&lt;/a&gt; [2CuCO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;·Cu(OH)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;] (dark blue),  &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malachite&quot;&gt;malachite&lt;/a&gt; [CuCO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;·Cu(OH)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;] (green),  &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chrysocolla&quot;&gt;chrysocolla&lt;/a&gt; [(Cu,Al)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Si&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;(OH)&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;·n(H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O)] (blue-green), and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chalcopyrite&quot;&gt;chalcopyrite&lt;/a&gt; [CuFeS&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;] (golden yellow), as well as several other non-copper minerals like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pyrite&quot;&gt;iron pyrite&lt;/a&gt; [FeS&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;] (pale brass-yellow).  While spectacular and very high-grade (about 16&amp;nbsp;% Cu),  the ore body is difficult to mine due to its depth, small size and weak structure.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Alan Rice. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. 100 meters underground in the Victoria Mine, Ely, Nevada. The small but extremely high-grade copper ore body is made up of copper minerals: azurite [2CuCO3·Cu(OH)2] (dark blue), malachite [CuCO3·Cu(OH)2] (green), chrysocolla [(Cu,Al)2H2Si2O5(OH)4·n(H2O)] (blue-green), and chalcopyrite [CuFeS2] (golden yellow), as well as several other non-copper minerals like iron pyrite [FeS2] (pale brass-yellow). While spectacular and very high-grade (about 16&amp;nbsp;% Cu), the ore body is difficult to mine due to its depth, small size and weak structure.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is mutation nonrandom? If so, in what sense?</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/03/are-mutations-random.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is mutation nonrandom? If so, in what sense?" /><published>2022-03-06T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-03-06T13:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/03/are-mutations-random</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/03/are-mutations-random.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I was hoping to write this post a week ago, but war intervened,
and I spent much of the time since then watching news about
the invasion of Ukraine by Russia, the incredible courage
of large numbers of Ukrainians who are resisting it, and the
incredible courage of those Russians who are protesting their
government’s aggression. This post takes a short break from
that.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two months ago, an article in &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; argued, from observations
on the plant &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/em&gt; that mutation is not
random.  This was the occasion for loud declarations from
creationists and ID advocates that the foundations of the
Modern Synthesis had been undermined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Here is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-021-04269-6&quot;&gt;the &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; paper, which is open access&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and here are the responses &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolutionnews.org/2022/02/new-study-in-nature-showing-non-random-mutation-spells-trouble-for-neo-darwinism/&quot;&gt;at the Discovery Institute’s site &lt;em&gt;Evolution News and Science Today&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and similar &lt;a href=&quot;https://uncommondescent.com/intelligent-design/are-mutations-really-random/&quot;&gt;commentary from the “peanut gallery”&lt;/a&gt; at Uncommon Descent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and a (short) &lt;a href=&quot;https://discourse.peacefulscience.org/t/mutation-bias-reflects-natural-selection-in-arabidopsis-thaliana/14724&quot;&gt;thread at Josh Swamidass’s site Peaceful Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I would like to ask is, whether modern evolutionary theory,
rests on the assumption that mutation is “random”.  And if so,
in what sense does it need to be random for the theory to be
tenable?  I’ll make some suggestions below, but they are 
tentative, and your thoughts are welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is there evidence that the mixture of mutations that happen
shifts in response to environmental changes, in such a way that
among those mutations that do occur, a larger fraction of them
are adaptive in those environments?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, when one could have mutations that helped the organism
adapt to higher temperatures, do more of those mutations show up?  And when the temperatures are getting colder, do the mutations
that occur become more likely to help adaptation to lower temperatures and less likely to help adaptation to high temperatures?  I
don’t know of any evidence that shifts like this happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does modern evolutionary biology have as a fundamental
tenet that mutation rates in all parts of the genome are equal
and that mutations that change bases are equally
likely to result in each of the other three possible bases?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There, the answer is clearly no, since many models of base
substitutions in neutral mutation have for a long time allowed
for mutation rates to differ in different parts of the genome,
and for the pattern of changes to depart from simple symmetrical
models such as the Jukes-Cantor model.  This includes allowing
models of regional mutation rate variation, such as Hidden
Markov Models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's discuss ...

&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Felsenstein</name></author><summary type="html">I was hoping to write this post a week ago, but war intervened, and I spent much of the time since then watching news about the invasion of Ukraine by Russia, the incredible courage of large numbers of Ukrainians who are resisting it, and the incredible courage of those Russians who are protesting their government’s aggression. This post takes a short break from that. Two months ago, an article in Nature argued, from observations on the plant Arabidopsis thaliana that mutation is not random. This was the occasion for loud declarations from creationists and ID advocates that the foundations of the Modern Synthesis had been undermined. Here is the Nature paper, which is open access and here are the responses at the Discovery Institute’s site Evolution News and Science Today and similar commentary from the “peanut gallery” at Uncommon Descent and a (short) thread at Josh Swamidass’s site Peaceful Science What I would like to ask is, whether modern evolutionary theory, rests on the assumption that mutation is “random”. And if so, in what sense does it need to be random for the theory to be tenable? I’ll make some suggestions below, but they are tentative, and your thoughts are welcome.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On the American Society of Naturalists’ de-naming of its awards</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/03/naturalists-denaming.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the American Society of Naturalists’ de-naming of its awards" /><published>2022-03-05T11:39:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-03-05T11:39:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/03/naturalists-denaming</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/03/naturalists-denaming.html">&lt;p&gt;On Valentine’s Day of this year, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amnat.org/announcements/named-awards.html&quot;&gt;American Society of Naturalists&lt;/a&gt; announced that it was removing individuals’ names from its awards.  Since some of us were concerned about what might lie behind this, I wrote to the Society’s Secretary, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mcglothlin.biol.vt.edu/&quot;&gt;Professor Joel McGlothlin&lt;/a&gt;, asking for clarification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our worst fears were confirmed.  We have witnessed an act of preemptive cowardice by the ASN Executive Council, much of value has been lost, and a valuable educational opportunity has been wasted. However, the changes will not take effect until this year’s awards are made.  In the meantime, I would strongly urge all members of the Society who read this, and in particular all awardees, to contact the Society through the Secretary, Professor Joel McGlothlin, at joelmcg@vt.edu, and make their views known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amnat.org/awards.html&quot;&gt;awards affected&lt;/a&gt; are the Sewall Wright Award, the E.O. Wilson Naturalist Award, the Jasper Loftus-Hills Young Investigator Award, the Ruth Patrick Student Poster Award, the Julia Platt Postdoc Presentation Award, and the Ed Ricketts Student Presentation Award.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of these, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sewall_Wright&quot;&gt;Sewall Wright&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E._O._Wilson&quot;&gt;E.O. Wilson&lt;/a&gt; need no introduction from me. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amnat.org/awards.html#Jasper&quot;&gt;Jasper Loftus-Hills&lt;/a&gt; was an Australian biologist of exceptional promise, killed by a hit and run driver when he was conducting fieldwork, just three years after receiving his PhD. Among numerous other achievements, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruth_Patrick&quot;&gt;Ruth Patrick&lt;/a&gt; established the Department of Limnology at the National Academy of Sciences, and did pioneering work on freshwater biodiversity and how it is impacted by pollution. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julia_Platt&quot;&gt;Julia Platt&lt;/a&gt; was the first to establish the neural crest origin of the cranium, was not able (this was in the 1890s) to obtain a PhD or an academic position in the U.S., went into politics and used her political role to establish one of the earliest marine conservation areas. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ed_Ricketts&quot;&gt;Ed Ricketts&lt;/a&gt; pioneered the study of intertidal ecology, and collaborated with the novelist John Steinbeck.  These are the people whose names the American Society of Naturalists no longer wishes to see prominently attached to their awards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked Professor Joel McGlothlin, Secretary of ASN, the following questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who suggested this change?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the reasons for the change?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did any of the names attached to awards seem to you problematic? If so, which ones, and in what way?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How long has the change been under consideration?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What debate or discussion took place?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What experts were consulted?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why are no reasons given on the website?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When does the change come into effect?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Were the membership consulted? Were current holders of the relevant named awards consulted?&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;li&gt;Were Loftus-Hills' family notified in advance of the announcement? If so, when and how?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will the Society be giving back the Loftus-Hills' endowment money? If not, how do you justify keeping it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His full reply is given below. Here I summarise the main points of his personal reply in the order given. He starts by saying that the decision should be seen in the context of broader discussion of specific names, such as the decision of the Society for the Study of Evolution to rename the Fisher prize, because of Fisher’s role in eugenics, and of the Society of Systematic Biologists to remove the name of Ernst Mayr from their only named award, because, he says, of “the question of whether having named awards could have the effect of excluding some members.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I had suspected, the motivation behind the changes derived from &lt;a href=&quot;https://magazine.scienceforthepeople.org/online/the-last-refuge-of-scoundrels/&quot;&gt;recent discoveries&lt;/a&gt; of the close relationship around 1990 between E. O. Wilson and the evolutionary psychologist J. Philippe Rushton.  When it became clear that the Society would have to decide whether or not to rename the E. O. Wilson Award, council members suggested that all awards be renamed (i.e., de-named), on the grounds that doing so “puts the focus on the accomplishments of the awardee rather than on the prestige of the eponymous scientist.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since award names are not written into ASN’s constitution, the Council itself decided that this was an appropriate matter for the Council itself to decide, without any kind of systematic survey of the membership.  McGothlin further remarks, “We also knew that it would be able to reach a consensus among Society members.” I am not sure what this means, or how they could have known that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes come into effect this year, but previous recipients of an award will be free to use its old name or the new, as they prefer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Society is “in the process of corresponding with relevant parties about the name changes where appropriate,” but regarding the Loftus-Hills prize, there has been no attempt to contact the family because they don’t know the address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the individuals whose names are removed from the awards will have remembrances (unspecified) on the website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many problems here that it is difficult to know where to start.  So I’ll begin with relatively minor matters, and work up towards those that lie at the heart of the matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loftus-Hills is not a common name, but a quick web search brought up two professionally active people, one in New York and one in Chippenham, both of whom hail, like the commemorated researcher, from Australia.  Perhaps the ANS Council was ashamed to contact them.  It is not clear who the other relevant individuals are with whom ANS is corresponding about the other changes, let alone why they are being approached at this stage, rather than before the key decision was taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Council claims consensus, but I suspect that this applies merely to their own echo chamber.  Other members, including honorary life members and previous awardees, did not learn of the matter until the decision was announced on the Society website.  For what it is worth, the one awardee whom I know personally has not written to the council, and is unlikely to do so, but that is out of despair and disgust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the claim that the removal of names “puts the focus on the accomplishments of the awardee rather than on the prestige of the eponymous scientist,” can anyone take this seriously?  Would it add lustre to the accomplishments of this year’s Nobel Prize winner in physics if instead they were named “Physicist of the Year”?  Perhaps Fields Prize mathematicians would prefer to be known instead as “people who did very good work in mathematics before they turned 40”?  And are we really expected to believe that it would put added focus on the work of holders of named Chairs in universities if those Chairs were made anonymous?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the question of how we should regard E. O. Wilson, the question that clearly lies at the heart of the matter.  Wilson is perhaps best known to the general public for his work on applying evolutionary principles to social organisations, but his other accomplishments ranged from understanding the dynamics of insect societies to the theory of island biogeography. This theory plays a key role in strategies for preserving biodiversity, a lifelong preoccupation. He was a two time Pulitzer Prize winner, an honorary member of 30 different learned societies, and a recipient of the Royal Swedish Academy’s Crafoord Prize, awarded to those who work is comparable in stature to that of Nobel Prize winners, but in areas that the Nobel Prizes do not cover. (There is a Nobel Prize in physiology or medicine, but none in biology as such.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem arises, of course, from accusations of racism.  I am not thinking here of ignorant critiques, such as that in the grotesque &lt;i&gt;Scientific American&lt;/i&gt; article, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/the-complicated-legacy-of-e-o-wilson/&quot;&gt;The Complicated Legacy of E. O. Wilson&lt;/a&gt;,” which sees racism in all studies of inheritance and even regards the expression “normal distribution” as showing bias against exceptions (!), but also recently published scholarly work (see, e.g., &lt;a href=&quot;https://magazine.scienceforthepeople.org/online/the-last-refuge-of-scoundrels/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) on the relationship between Wilson and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J._Philippe_Rushton&quot;&gt;J. Philippe Rushton&lt;/a&gt;. Rushton was no marginal character, but a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gf.org/fellows/all-fellows/j-philippe-rushton/&quot;&gt;1988 Guggenheim fellow&lt;/a&gt;.  However, he moved over the course of his career from studies of kinship and altruism to generalisations about the degree of parental altruism in different groups to scientifically untenable claims about race as a determinant of intelligence.  Until at least 1990, Wilson strongly supported Rushton’s right to explore racial differences, but here we must be careful to distinguish between Wilson’s words and Rushton’s, and to avoid assigning guilt by association.  I would also like to know much more about how the relationship between the two men developed after 1990.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my own non-expert reading of the story, it does seem that in 1990 Wilson went beyond simply supporting Rushton’s claim to discuss his work on racial differences on its merits, and crossed the line into helping him support unsound racist claims.  However, before proposing any action on the basis of such a conclusion, I would at the least seek the opinions of those who had closely studied the matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would then have had the opportunity for an important debate.  There are cases like that of Samuel Colston, a Bristol philanthropist whose money came from the slave trade, whose statue was at the height of the Black Lives Matter movement thrown into Bristol Harbour, and not before time.  There are other cases, such as that of T. H. Huxley, where accusations of racism are not only unhistorical but unjust.  Wilson, it seems, lies somewhere in between.  I would like to learn more about his relationship with Rushton, especially as Rushton moved further from the academically defensible after 1990.  We would then need to weigh this association carefully against Wilson’s magnificent accomplishments, remembering that all of us are flawed and complex human beings, but also that by the time under discussion, racism was already scientifically discredited, and that it remained, and remains, a present evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of this happened. No expert opinions were sought.  No new evidence was sought on this fascinating piece of contemporary history.  No E. O. Wilson Award recipients, who might have had a great deal to stay on the matter, were invited to take part in the debate because there was no debate.  Instead, in an unprecedented display of moral cowardice, the Society has made sure that no such debate takes place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes will not come into effect until this year’s awards are made.  In the meantime, I would once again strongly urge all members of the Society who read this, and in particular all awardees, to contact the Society through Professor McGlothlin at joelmcg@vt.edu .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thank numerous colleagues for discussions, including among others Glenn Branch, Joe Felsenstein, and Nick Matzke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt Young will be the principal moderator of the comment thread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is the full text of Joel McGlothlin’s reply to my questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apologies for my delayed response. I have tried to answer your questions to the best of my ability. You are welcome to share my answers, but I do ask that you post the text below in its unabridged form if you do so [I would have done this in any case &amp;ndash; P.B.].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your questions about our recent award policy change at ASN. Although I am currently serving as Secretary of ASN and consulted with some of the other Council members when preparing this response, the following represents my own take on the situation and not an official statement from the Society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to remember that this change happened as part of a broader discussion across a number of scientific societies. Our sister societies, SSE and SSB, have both either renamed awards or considered it in recent years. In 2020, SSE renamed the Fisher Prize, a change that occurred specifically because of Fisher’s role in the eugenics movement. In 2021, SSB introduced a resolution to remove names from all awards, which functionally would only apply to the Mayr Award, their only named award. This had less to do with Mayr himself than the question of whether having named awards could have the effect of excluding some members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, the recent discussion of named awards in ASN Council became more urgent after the revelations about E. O. Wilson’s correspondence with J. Philippe Rushton. Shortly after the first article about this correspondence was published, we began discussing a potential change to ASN’s E. O. Wilson Naturalist Award. Several members of Council suggested that we should rename all awards, not just the Wilson Award. We met by Zoom and a consensus emerged in the discussion that this would be the right course of action. The reason for the change we gave in our statement reflects the consensus of Council. Simply put, removing names puts the focus on the accomplishments of the awardee rather than on the prestige of the eponymous scientist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individual Council members did speak to various members of the Society, some of whom are currently serving on committees (including award committees), and followed discussion surrounding the potential renaming on social media, but the final decision was made by Council. Award names are not written into ASN’s constitution, so this was a change that could be made by Council as the elected representatives of the membership, and we all agreed that it was appropriate to do so. We also knew that it would be able to reach a consensus among Society members. Indeed, we have received a wide range of feedback about the change, but happily, a majority of this has been positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes are in effect as of this year’s awards, the winners of which have not yet been announced. We will be updating the website soon to reflect the awards’ new names and to include some more information about the change. Previous recipients of the awards are free to use the older name or the current name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are currently in the process of corresponding with relevant parties about the name changes where appropriate. You asked specifically about the award named for Jasper Loftus-Hills. We have not contacted members of Loftus-Hills’ family because we do not have any information that would allow us to contact them. We would be happy to speak with any family members about the change. ASN established the Jasper J. Loftus-Hills Prize in 1984 in memory of Loftus-Hills, who had died tragically in 1974. To the best of our knowledge, the establishment of the award was not tied to a gift to the Society from the Loftus-Hills family or from another individual. After the first year, the award was changed to the Young Investigators’ Prize and was not renamed for Loftus-Hills until 2011, when the original name was rediscovered by then managing editor Patricia Morse.&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;As indicated in our announcement, ASN does not intend to relegate the individuals who previously provided names to our awards—including Loftus-Hills—to the dustbin of history. After Council decides on new names for the awards, the website will be updated to include remembrances of those who previously gave their names to awards. In some cases, we hope to significantly expand what is currently on the website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Braterman</name></author><summary type="html">On Valentine’s Day of this year, the American Society of Naturalists announced that it was removing individuals’ names from its awards. Since some of us were concerned about what might lie behind this, I wrote to the Society’s Secretary, Professor Joel McGlothlin, asking for clarification. Our worst fears were confirmed. We have witnessed an act of preemptive cowardice by the ASN Executive Council, much of value has been lost, and a valuable educational opportunity has been wasted. However, the changes will not take effect until this year’s awards are made. In the meantime, I would strongly urge all members of the Society who read this, and in particular all awardees, to contact the Society through the Secretary, Professor Joel McGlothlin, at joelmcg@vt.edu, and make their views known. The awards affected are the Sewall Wright Award, the E.O. Wilson Naturalist Award, the Jasper Loftus-Hills Young Investigator Award, the Ruth Patrick Student Poster Award, the Julia Platt Postdoc Presentation Award, and the Ed Ricketts Student Presentation Award. Of these, Sewall Wright and E.O. Wilson need no introduction from me. Jasper Loftus-Hills was an Australian biologist of exceptional promise, killed by a hit and run driver when he was conducting fieldwork, just three years after receiving his PhD. Among numerous other achievements, Ruth Patrick established the Department of Limnology at the National Academy of Sciences, and did pioneering work on freshwater biodiversity and how it is impacted by pollution. Julia Platt was the first to establish the neural crest origin of the cranium, was not able (this was in the 1890s) to obtain a PhD or an academic position in the U.S., went into politics and used her political role to establish one of the earliest marine conservation areas. Ed Ricketts pioneered the study of intertidal ecology, and collaborated with the novelist John Steinbeck. These are the people whose names the American Society of Naturalists no longer wishes to see prominently attached to their awards.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Trialeurodes vaporariorum</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/Trialeurodes-vaporariorum.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trialeurodes vaporariorum" /><published>2022-02-28T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-02-28T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/Trialeurodes-vaporariorum</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/Trialeurodes-vaporariorum.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/DSC04847_Whiteflies_Crop_1_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;whiteflies&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greenhouse_whitefly&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Trialeurodes vaporariorum&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; greenhouse whiteflies infesting a geranium leaf. F &amp;ndash; female, M &amp;ndash; male, L &amp;ndash; larva, P &amp;ndash; pupa. Thanks to Mark Sturtevant for the annotations. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A geranium plant that I supposedly take care of has a serious infestation with whiteflies. Before dousing the plant with insecticidal soap (a procedure I am supposed to follow every week for a while), I snapped the preceding picture. There is a lot of there there, so I asked Mark Sturtevant exactly what I am looking at. His response:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The spiky things are a weird part of the life cycle of whiteflies. Although they are in the order Hemiptera, which are 'supposed' to have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amentsoc.org/insects/glossary/terms/incomplete-metamorphosis/&quot;&gt;incomplete metamorphosis&lt;/a&gt; (passing thru nymphal stages before molting into adults), whiteflies are hemipterans that essentially have a larval stage and pupal stage of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amentsoc.org/insects/glossary/terms/complete-metamorphosis/&quot;&gt;holometabolous&lt;/a&gt; insects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see quite a bit going on here in this one picture. I have re-attached your picture with some annotations.&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;I don't know if there are eggs in view. The tiny white specks look more like glandular secretions from the leaf. But there are a few larvae along the top border of the picture, and I have marked some with an L.  You see the pupal stage already (one is marked with a P), but technically these are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amentsoc.org/insects/glossary/terms/puparium/&quot;&gt;puparia&lt;/a&gt;. When a larva becomes a pupa, the larva usually sheds its cuticle to show the pupa underneath, with its own cuticle. But in whiteflies (and in some other insects like flies and fleas), the larva does not shed its cuticle. Rather, it puffs it out, hardens it, and the pupal stage stays locked inside the larval cuticle. That outer larval shell is called the puparium. Then there are the adults. The large adults are females, and I have marked one with an F. Males are smaller and much more active. Winged males fly and seek out females. I think the one labelled M is a male.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the day was warm, and there were lots of males on the window trying to get out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked Dr. Sturtevant about the transparent spheres that clutter the frame:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;I don't know what the big spheres are, but it could be like aphids (whiteflies are related to them) which periodically secrete a drop of honeydew. This is excess water from plant sap, and aphids secrete that to concentrate the nutrients. Since whiteflies are always secreting a waxy bloom, a thin wax coating on their honeydew droplets would hold them together. That's a hypothesis, but I don't really know. &lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Trialeurodes vaporariorum &amp;ndash; greenhouse whiteflies infesting a geranium leaf. F &amp;ndash; female, M &amp;ndash; male, L &amp;ndash; larva, P &amp;ndash; pupa. Thanks to Mark Sturtevant for the annotations. A geranium plant that I supposedly take care of has a serious infestation with whiteflies. Before dousing the plant with insecticidal soap (a procedure I am supposed to follow every week for a while), I snapped the preceding picture. There is a lot of there there, so I asked Mark Sturtevant exactly what I am looking at. His response: The spiky things are a weird part of the life cycle of whiteflies. Although they are in the order Hemiptera, which are 'supposed' to have incomplete metamorphosis (passing thru nymphal stages before molting into adults), whiteflies are hemipterans that essentially have a larval stage and pupal stage of holometabolous insects. You can see quite a bit going on here in this one picture. I have re-attached your picture with some annotations. I don't know if there are eggs in view. The tiny white specks look more like glandular secretions from the leaf. But there are a few larvae along the top border of the picture, and I have marked some with an L. You see the pupal stage already (one is marked with a P), but technically these are puparia. When a larva becomes a pupa, the larva usually sheds its cuticle to show the pupa underneath, with its own cuticle. But in whiteflies (and in some other insects like flies and fleas), the larva does not shed its cuticle. Rather, it puffs it out, hardens it, and the pupal stage stays locked inside the larval cuticle. That outer larval shell is called the puparium. Then there are the adults. The large adults are females, and I have marked one with an F. Males are smaller and much more active. Winged males fly and seek out females. I think the one labelled M is a male. Indeed, the day was warm, and there were lots of males on the window trying to get out. I asked Dr. Sturtevant about the transparent spheres that clutter the frame: I don't know what the big spheres are, but it could be like aphids (whiteflies are related to them) which periodically secrete a drop of honeydew. This is excess water from plant sap, and aphids secrete that to concentrate the nutrients. Since whiteflies are always secreting a waxy bloom, a thin wax coating on their honeydew droplets would hold them together. That's a hypothesis, but I don't really know.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Imperial College will not rename Huxley Building</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/imperial-college-will-not-rename.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Imperial College will not rename Huxley Building" /><published>2022-02-28T10:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-02-28T10:40:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/imperial-college-will-not-rename</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/imperial-college-will-not-rename.html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Huxley_Bust_600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bust of Huxley&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The bust of Huxley. &lt;small&gt;Credit: 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2021/10/26/imperial-college-told-remove-bust-slavery-abolitionist-might/&quot;&gt;The Telegraph&lt;/a&gt; (UK). Fair use.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imperial College has decided not to rename the Huxley Building, in a partial victory for those who oppose “canceling” historical figures who held views that today are properly regarded as racist. Instead, according to an article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/news/234096/imperial-commits-ambitious-understanding-history/&quot;&gt;Imperial commits to ‘ambitious understanding’ of history&lt;/a&gt;, by Deborah Evanson, they will add a second, joint name to the building, in addition to that of Thomas H. Huxley. The second name will be that of “a pathbreaking scientist from a Black, Asian or other minority ethnic background.” The College will also retain a bust of Huxley, but will put Huxley and his accomplishments&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;into a fuller context in order to provide everyone with a more complete understanding of Huxley’s complex character and achievements as well as his flaws, including his racially prejudiced writings. Historical context will also be provided for any person whose name is added jointly.  &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huxley, like most of us, was indeed a complex character. He no doubt thought that white, male Englishmen were generally smarter than everyone else. In that respect he was no different from most white, male Englishmen of his time. Nevertheless, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2021/12/Matzke-Huxley-comments.html&quot;&gt;an article by Nick Matzke and others&lt;/a&gt; on Panda’s Thumb last December, Huxley devoted himself to educating women and poor people, and actively opposed slavery; he was thus well in advance of many, if not most, of his contemporaries. It is gratifying that Imperial College recognizes this progressive leader and has decided not to dename the Huxley Building because of a flaw that was widely shared in his era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biologist and blogger Jerry Coyne calls the compromise “&lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2022/02/25/a-small-victory-thomas-henry-huxley-not-cancelled-but-contextualized-at-imperial-college/&quot;&gt;a small victory&lt;/a&gt;,” and I suppose it is. Huxley did not fare so well at Western Washington University, where his name was removed from the Huxley College of the Environment; see the preceding link for more background.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">The bust of Huxley. Credit: The Telegraph (UK). Fair use. Imperial College has decided not to rename the Huxley Building, in a partial victory for those who oppose “canceling” historical figures who held views that today are properly regarded as racist. Instead, according to an article, Imperial commits to ‘ambitious understanding’ of history, by Deborah Evanson, they will add a second, joint name to the building, in addition to that of Thomas H. Huxley. The second name will be that of “a pathbreaking scientist from a Black, Asian or other minority ethnic background.” The College will also retain a bust of Huxley, but will put Huxley and his accomplishments into a fuller context in order to provide everyone with a more complete understanding of Huxley’s complex character and achievements as well as his flaws, including his racially prejudiced writings. Historical context will also be provided for any person whose name is added jointly. Huxley, like most of us, was indeed a complex character. He no doubt thought that white, male Englishmen were generally smarter than everyone else. In that respect he was no different from most white, male Englishmen of his time. Nevertheless, according to an article by Nick Matzke and others on Panda’s Thumb last December, Huxley devoted himself to educating women and poor people, and actively opposed slavery; he was thus well in advance of many, if not most, of his contemporaries. It is gratifying that Imperial College recognizes this progressive leader and has decided not to dename the Huxley Building because of a flaw that was widely shared in his era. The biologist and blogger Jerry Coyne calls the compromise “a small victory,” and I suppose it is. Huxley did not fare so well at Western Washington University, where his name was removed from the Huxley College of the Environment; see the preceding link for more background.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chemistry Professor Paul Kilmartin on “mauri” in the NZ Chemistry/Biology curriculum</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/NZ-mauri-chemistry-kilmartin-seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chemistry Professor Paul Kilmartin on “mauri” in the NZ Chemistry/Biology curriculum" /><published>2022-02-20T17:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-02-20T17:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/NZ-mauri-chemistry-kilmartin-seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/NZ-mauri-chemistry-kilmartin-seminar.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;on-the-left-side&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Paul_Kilmartin.png&quot; alt=&quot;[Prof. Paul Kilmartin university webpage]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Prof. Paul Kilmartin's university webpage. &lt;a href=&quot;https://unidirectory.auckland.ac.nz/profile/p-kilmartin&quot;&gt;Source: UoA webpage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday, February 18, I attended (on Zoom) a fascinating seminar given by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unidirectory.auckland.ac.nz/profile/p-kilmartin&quot;&gt;Paul Kilmartin, Professor of Chemistry&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auckland.ac.nz/en/science/about-the-faculty/school-of-chemical-sciences.html&quot;&gt;School of Chemical Sciences&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auckland.ac.nz/en.html&quot;&gt;University of Auckland&lt;/a&gt;, here in Aotearoa/New Zealand. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://unidirectory.auckland.ac.nz/profile/nmat471&quot;&gt;I work&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auckland.ac.nz/en/science/about-the-faculty/school-of-biological-sciences.html&quot;&gt;School of Biological Sciences&lt;/a&gt; at the same institution.) Prof. Kilmartin specialises in wine chemistry, among other things, and in addition to chemistry, has degrees in theology and philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kilmartin’s talk was entitled &lt;b&gt;“Chemistry and Mātauranga Māori: A Conversation.”&lt;/b&gt; Kilmartin has given me permission to quote this part of his talk, below, which covers science education material of international interest. I will also include the talk summary. Other parts of Kilmartin’s seminar focused on his own background coming to this issue (Scottish and Māori ancestry, member of &lt;a href=&quot;https://ngaitahu.iwi.nz/&quot;&gt;Ngāi Tahu&lt;/a&gt;, deep knowledge of Ngāi Tahu history and land claims), and ideas for Auckland’s chemistry program to explore regarding mātauranga Māori.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Panda’s Thumb blog has an international readership interested in science and science education, and I have been involved with science education controversies for 20 years (and with PT for 18!). But I’m sure the NZ situation is new to many readers. Therefore, I will give some background/introduction to the controversy around the science curriculum, after the quote from Kilmartin’s talk.  For more (much more) on current science education controversies in New Zealand, please search &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.google.com/search?q=science%2C%20M%C4%81tauranga%20M%C4%81ori&amp;amp;hl=en-NZ&amp;amp;gl=NZ&amp;amp;ceid=NZ%3Aen&quot;&gt;Google News&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=science%20%20M%C4%81tauranga%20M%C4%81ori&amp;amp;src=typed_query&amp;amp;f=live&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.com/?s=mauri+zealand&amp;amp;orderby=relevance&amp;amp;order=DESC&amp;amp;post_type=post&quot;&gt;blogs&lt;/a&gt; etc. on the various terms mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;(Please not that all of non-talk material is written by me, and should not necessarily be taken as Kilmartin’s views. And, these are my personal views, not those of current or former employers.)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Quotes from: “Chemistry and Mātauranga Māori: A Conversation”&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Seminar by Professor Paul Kilmartin&lt;br /&gt;
School of Chemical Sciences, University of Auckland&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[Comments/clarifications by Matzke are in square brackets like this.]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[Seminar given on Zoom by Prof. Paul Kilmartin at 2022-02-18 at 11 am.]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[Around 27 minutes in, Kilmartin continues...]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The second Ministry of Education text I would like to comment upon concerns proposals for NCEA science. The courses here involve so-called Big Ideas, and the inclusions of concepts drawn from Mātauranga Māori.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
These were proposed last year for inclusion in the NCEA curriculum, and have been piloted in some schools.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I understand that this year, a further 5 schools will be involved in mini-pilots, with full pilots to take place next year, and full implementation by 2024.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
One of the Big Ideas in the Chemistry area has to do with the properties of matter, as follows:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Kilmartin1.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
But what is mauri? Its definition is important for teachers and students alike. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The following Glossary is provided, where mauri is defined as:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Kilmartin2.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[Then follows several minutes of discussion of various definitions and usages of the mauri concept; Kilmartin states that insofar as mauri is used to refer to a concept like individual or ecosystem health, he can work with it.  Kilmartin also discusses Prof. T.K.K.B. Morgan's &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mauriometer.com/&quot;&gt;mauri-o-meter&lt;/a&gt;, etc.]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[Resume at about minute 33:00]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
But is there more to the concept of mauri than this?  In an earlier publication, within a civil engineers' proceeding, Prof. Morgan provides more background to mauri. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Kilmartin3.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
And there are some new concepts here. Not only do all natural objects possess it, mauri is seen as the binding force between the physical and the spiritual. Indeed, when mauri is impacted and the bond weakened, the physical and the spiritual are separated, leading to death.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
One question is whether using mauri in the sense of life-supporting capacity implies all of this additional meaning.  If it does, then I would want to ask, Who discovered this binding force between the physical and the spiritual?  And what evidence was involved in its discovery? If this binding force is real, then everyone needs to know about it. It needs to be in the chemistry syllabus of every country, not just in New Zealand.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
So how has this new syllabus been received by teachers? We have one publication on this topic from last year [&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.46786/ac21.1591&quot;&gt;Stewart and Tedoldi 2021&lt;/a&gt;], which explains that the inclusion of Māori concepts is an attempt to reflect the principal of equal mana, mana ōrite, for Māori knowledge -- one of the seven principles within the NCEA Change package, announced by the government in May 2019.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Kilmartin4.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
We also learn that these proposals have sparked heated discussions, in which NCEA science teachers have referred to Māori knowledge as &quot;myths and legends,&quot; or &quot;’spiritual concepts’ that do not belong in the science curriculum.&quot; Well, good on the teachers for having their say.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The authors of this article [&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.46786/ac21.1591&quot;&gt;Stewart and Tedoldi 2021&lt;/a&gt;] have other views. The problem with the teachers is seen as a narrow understanding of what is living, as taught under the &quot;MRS GREN&quot; life processes: Movement, Respiration, Sensitivity, Growth, Reproduction, Excretion, and Nutrition, and I remember teaching MRS GREN in my two years as a secondary school teacher in Christchurch in the early 90s.  Instead this should be expanded to consider a river as living. To support this understanding, teachers are recommended to look to the Gaia concept of the Earth as a living thing. I hadn't heard much about Gaia recently, and it was much more popular in the 80s and 90s, and I might be showing my age here.  I had to look up Wikipedia for some recent information. There is every indication that Gaia has little current following in the scientific community, after some years of more active debate.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
One final example of mauri is of interest to myself as an electrochemist, given our use of electricity to interface with chemistry.  And this relates to domestic electrical wiring. In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worksafe.govt.nz/dmsdocument/1580-new-zealand-electrical-code-of-practice-for-homeowneroccupiers-electrical-wiring-work-in-domestic-installations-nzecp-51-2004&quot;&gt;current New Zealand Electrical Code of Practice&lt;/a&gt;, we are encouraged to think of the Green/Yellow=Earth wire as a Papatuanuku or Earth Mother. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Kilmartin5.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
I must admit, I do have trouble taking this seriously, and I doubt the use of tapu and noa in this matter matches their meaning within Mātauranga Māori.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
My own view is that the concept of mauri has no place in the Chemistry curriculum. I would suggest to re-write the Big Idea along these lines:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Kilmartin6.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; class=&quot;centerImage&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[...]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
[References cited above]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Georgina Stewart and Angelo Tedoldi (2021). Bringing Māori concepts into school science: NCEA. Access: Contemporary Issues in Education. 41(1), 77-81. https://pesaagora.com/access-vol-41/bringing-maori-concepts-into-school-science-ncea/ &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Gaia – Wikipedia. Wikimedia Foundation. Accessed 2022-02-18. https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaia &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
T. K. K. B. Morgan (2006). Decision-support tools and the indigenous paradigm. Proceedings of the Institution of Civil Engineers - Engineering Sustainability. 159(4), 169-177. December 2006. https://www.icevirtuallibrary.com/doi/10.1680/ensu.2006.159.4.169 &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
NCEA (2021). Science: Chemistry and Biology. NCEA Level 1 Curriculum.&lt;br /&gt; https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/chemistry-and-biology?view=learning . Accessed 2022-02-18.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
NCEA (2021). Chemistry and Biology Glossary. NCEA Level 1 Curriculum. &lt;br /&gt;
https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/chemistry-and-biology?view=subject-glossary . Accessed 2022-02-18.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;poster&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Poster&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give a fuller summary of the talk, here is the poster advertising and summarising Kilmartin’s seminar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Paul_Kilmartin_talk_poster.png&quot; style=&quot;width:75%&quot; alt=&quot;[Paul Kilmartin poster for Feb. 18 chemistry seminar on mātauranga Māori]&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;Poster for Paul Kilmart's Feb. 18 seminar in the School of Chemical Sciences, University of Auckland on mātauranga Māori and the NCEA Chemistry curriculum&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the text for the same:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;background-color: rgb(235, 235, 235); padding: 15px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Poster and summary of Kilmartin Seminar&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
School of Chemical Sciences - Friday Seminar Series&lt;br /&gt;
Friday 18 February 2022&lt;br /&gt;
11 am&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Chemistry and Mātauranga Māori&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;A Conversation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Professor Paul Kilmartin&lt;br /&gt;
School of Chemical Sciences, University of Auckland&lt;br /&gt;
https://unidirectory.auckland.ac.nz/profile/p-kilmartin &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The NCEA Education web-site provides the following material for the “Big Idea” named “Properties of matter are determined by attractive forces between particles”, prepared for teaching Chemistry and Biology as a consolidated subject at Curriculum level 6 (NCEA 1):&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Mauri is present in all matter. All particles have their own mauri and presence as part of a larger whole, for example within a molecule, polymer, salt, or metal. When matter is broken into smaller particles each particle remains as part of the taiao [environment], for example when a substance is burnt or dissolved the particles remain, with their own mauri.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A glossary definition of mauri is also provided:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The vital essence, life force of everything: be it a physical object, living thing or ecosystem. In Chemistry and Biology, mauri refers to the health and life-sustaining capacity of the taiao, on biological, physical, and chemical levels.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/chemistry-and-biology?view=learning &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
This presentation will provide a personal perspective on several issues related to Chemistry and Mātauranga Māori. These will include selected points from Ngāi Tahu/family history, through to a critique of recent Ministry of Education publications where Mātauranga Māori concepts are being brought into the School curriculum.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The presentation will be organised around the following topics:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Moa bones and the Kemp purchase&lt;br /&gt;
Rowallan land blocks&lt;br /&gt;
The Opihi Taniwha&lt;br /&gt;
Ngā Tautake Pūtaiao me ngā Kōrero o Mua&lt;br /&gt;
Chemistry curriculum&lt;br /&gt;
Legitimate voices&lt;br /&gt;
Future opportunities for the School of Chemical Sciences&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A 45 minute presentation will be followed by ample time for discussion.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In addition to his chemistry background, Paul has degrees in philosophy and theology, and is a Trustee on two blocks of forested land provided to the family under 1906 SILNA act. His research into family history has been deposited with the Ngāi Tahu whakapapa unit.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;background&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quick Backgrounder for international readers (by Matzke)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;i&gt;mātauranga Māori&lt;/i&gt; means Māori knowledge.  (It is often just “mātauranga” when the context is obvious; it is often also abbreviated MM.) Often this primarily refers to traditional indigenous knowledge, but it can also include newer knowledge that was developed or incorporated more recently.  Much more detail is available via google, see for example the Māori dictionary and mātauranga Māori and science, from the NZ Science Learning Hub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was hired in NZ in 2018, and I have gradually learned of a widespread movement to promote MM at all levels. For example, it is an aspect of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mbie.govt.nz/science-and-technology/science-and-innovation/agencies-policies-and-budget-initiatives/vision-matauranga-policy/&quot;&gt;Vision Mātauranga&lt;/a&gt;, the governmental strategy for encouraging scientific research that benefits Māori interests. It is promoted in university strategic plans, and in school systems.  All of this is motivated by many honorable values. I cannot list them all, but motivations include everything from (1) making science education and research more interesting and relevant to Māori students, through to (2) encouraging Māori cultural advancement and renewal (much like government promotion of te reo Māori, the Māori language) – especially important to help repair damaged caused by colonisation, through to (3) economic and conservation benefits that could accrue from deploying traditional knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is well and good, and it is hard to see how anyone could reasonably object to these ideas in general. However, specifics and implementation matter a lot, and controversy has recently arisen over a governmental policy to revise the school curriculum with guideline mandating “parity” between “Western science” and mātauranga Māori. In July 2021, seven professors (full or emeritus) from the University of Auckland wrote a letter to a NZ magazine, &lt;i&gt;The Listener&lt;/i&gt;, objecting to this and other Ministry of Education statements. The initial reaction was swift and harshly negative, as some perceived the letter as denigrating mātauranga.  But over time a more normal public discussion ensued in &lt;i&gt;The Listener&lt;/i&gt; and elsewhere (which is ongoing), and now the Vice Chancellor of the University of Auckland, Dawn Freshwater, has stated “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeshighereducation.com/news/auckland-plans-dialogue-maori-knowledge-and-science&quot;&gt;Nobody is wrong here&lt;/a&gt;,” and promised to host an academic symposium to thoroughly discuss the various issues raised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(The symposium was going to be in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeshighereducation.com/news/auckland-plans-dialogue-maori-knowledge-and-science&quot;&gt;first quarter of 2022&lt;/a&gt;, but now the omicron variant of SARS-CoV-2 has slipped through quarantine, and NZ is experiencing it’s first huge wave of SARS-CoV-2. I say SARS-CoV-2, because NZ is highly vaccinated and omicron is milder, so hopefully we will avoid most of the actual Covid disease. In any case, the University of Auckland is online-only (mostly) for at least the first half of Semester 1, so I imagine the symposium will likely be delayed.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was not involved in &lt;i&gt;The Listener&lt;/i&gt; controversy, except to try to defend the principle of academic freedom of everyone involved. To me, the word “parity” could mean a lot of things, NZ generally seems like a place where common sense prevails (rather than everything going to the nuclear option of litigation or political polarisation, as occurs in the USA), and in any case I’m just a recent immigrant, lucky to be here. It seemed to me that the whole debate needed to happen in long-form (rather than letters, petitions, and tweets) where issues can be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rnz.co.nz/news/on-the-inside/448453/let-s-choose-our-words-more-carefully-when-discussing-matauranga-maori-and-science&quot;&gt;discussed thoroughly&lt;/a&gt;, and perhaps now this will happen in the VC’s Symposium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there has been a new development. The NZ Ministry of Education’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/&quot;&gt;NCEA (“National Certificate of Educational Achievement”)&lt;/a&gt; released its curricula for a &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;variety of classes at NCEA Level 1&lt;/a&gt; (translation: students approximately age 15-16). NCEA Levels 2 and 3 are essentially university preparatory material, and include high-stakes exams run by NZQA, relevant for credits for University admissions. Level 1 is more basic material, and some students choose to skip Level 1 to go straight to higher levels, but the “NCEA Change Process” will move to Levels 2 and 3 when NCEA Level 1 changes are completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NCEA Level 1 includes classes on &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/chemistry-and-biology?view=learning&quot;&gt;Chemistry and Biology&lt;/a&gt; (CB), general &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/science?view=learning&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt; (SC), &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/physics-earth-and-space-science?view=learning&quot;&gt;Physics Earth and Space Science&lt;/a&gt; (PESS), and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/mathematics-and-statistics/mathematics-and-statistics?view=learning&quot;&gt;Mathematics and Statistics&lt;/a&gt; (MS). Reviewing the curricula, some of it, including some of the mātauranga Māori content, seems fine, or at least not something to raise a public ruckus about. (E.g., the curriculum is often pretty vague and general, but NZ deliberately decided to not create hyper-detailed curricula like the 1000+ page curricula used in Australia.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But some of it is…very surprising. The example that leapt out to me is also the section that Kilmartin critiqued: the chemistry discussion of atoms, molecules, chemical bonds, and conservation of mass/energy/the First Law of Thermodynamics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is some quick translations for the international reader. Please see the NCEA glossary or other online resources for more:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;ākonga&lt;/b&gt; = students&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;taiao&lt;/b&gt; = the environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;kaitiakitanga&lt;/b&gt; = guardianship and protection, e.g. of the environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;whakapapa&lt;/b&gt; = genealogy framework used to record relationships (genealogical or otherwise), but more generally, it is often used to refer to heritage, inheritance, cultural and familial connections, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;mauri&lt;/b&gt; (quoting from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/chemistry-and-biology?view=subject-glossary&quot;&gt;NCEA Glossary&lt;/a&gt;) = &quot;The vital essence, life force of everything: be it a physical object, living thing or ecosystem. In Chemistry and Biology, mauri refers to the health and life-sustaining capacity of the taiao, on biological, physical, and chemical levels.&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NCEA Chemistry and Biology curriculum says (or said as of November 2021, if they change it, which they eventually will have to):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;b&gt;Big Idea: Properties of matter are determined by attractive forces between particles&lt;/b&gt;

Mauri is present in all matter. All particles have their own mauri and presence as part of a larger whole, for example within a molecule, polymer, salt, or metal. When matter is broken into smaller particles each particle remains as part of the taiao, for example when a substance is burnt or dissolved the particles remain, with their own mauri. They do not just disappear.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is meant by “mauri” here?  We might avoid conflict by imagining that the term is being used here to refer to individual or ecosystem health, as it is some other places in the curriculum. Elsewhere in his talk, Kilmartin notes that concepts of health are something that he can work with as a scientist, and I agree. For example, a toxin might damage an individual organism, chemical pollution might damage an ecosystem, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that interpretation cannot be applied to this Big Idea. For starters, virtually all matter in the Universe has zero to do with health of living things, because it is outside of our solar system. Even if we stretch the health interpretation to some science fiction scenario where humans and other Earth organisms have escaped our solar system, most of the relevance of various “particles” to organismal/ecosystem health is not due just to the particles’ properties; we must also consider their temperature, arrangement, relative amounts, and the needs of the various organisms. Methane in large amounts is toxic to humans, healthy to certain microorganisms, and deadly to all of them on Titan where the temperature is -179.6 degrees Celsius on a hot day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, in any event, whatever “life-sustaining” capacity of a particle we might imagine, it decidedly does &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; remain upon being burnt. Oxygen (O2) is necessary for human life, but carbon dioxide (CO2), the product of burning carbon-containing compounds like methane in oxygen, is toxic at sufficient levels.  If by “particles”, the NCEA actually meant “atoms”, (a) they should have just said that, and (b) while the “atom” interpretation does refer to something that doesn’t change upon burning, understanding atomic properties is fairly remote from understanding health impacts, which mostly concern how molecules interact with organismal processes, and (c) the term “particles” explicitly refers to “molecule, polymer, salt, or metal” in the standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The passage does not make sense if interpreted as referring to health impacts. What we are left with is the more fundamental definition of mauri, which is closer to its original usage anyway, which is the “vital essence, life force of everything.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the concept of a life force or vital essence is…vitalism!  And vitalism is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/topic/vitalism&quot;&gt;very old&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6208063/&quot;&gt;very very discredited&lt;/a&gt; idea. Wohler’s 1828 synthesis of urea from inorganic compounds, when it was previously thought to be an organic molecule produced only by life, was later recognized as an early episode in the defeat of vitalism, and is cited in virtually all chemistry textbooks and classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note that, as is always the case when the history of science is explored in depth, the history is more complex than the defeat of vitalism in a single experiment. Vitalism was an amorphous doctrine, not refutable by a single experiment, but it died a gradual death by many cuts, as experiments accumulated that synthesized various organic compounds from inorganic sources. See Ramberg 2000.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern chemistry and biology, especially organic chemistry and biochemistry, essentially arose through the examination and experimental defeat of vitalism, including the defeat of many rear-guard attempts to defend some reduced version of the concept of a life force or life essence – something “extra” beyond material matter and forces which gave living things the breath of life. To have some government bureaucrats try to bring it back into chemistry by administrative declaration is not going to fly.  Seeing vitalism in chemistry standards is as surprising as it would be to see a Geology curriculum endorse Noah’s Flood or the idea that the Earth is 6,000 years old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;other_problems&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Other problems&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These problems should have been obvious, and they certainly were to the many science teachers who objected. Unfortunately, science teachers’ objections seem to be being hand-waved away by the educational establishment, for example by &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.46786/ac21.1591&quot;&gt;Stewart &amp;amp; Tedoldi (2021)&lt;/a&gt;, who seem to be closely involved with the science curricula. They note the strong objections that science teachers voiced to bringing mauri into the Chemistry/Biology curriculum in this way, but they reply by bringing up…Gaia. Even if one ignored Kilmartin’s point, namely that the Gaia Hypothesis is itself controversial, Gaia aims to explain how the Earth is a homeostatic system; it doesn’t solve the problems with trying to bring back vitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are other huge problems with the inclusion of mauri in the discussion of particles, chemical bonds, and conservation of mass.  These include: What will be on the exams? Will one question be a chemical formula, and the next a spiritual concept?  Won’t the inclusion of spiritual concepts in amongst basic chemistry concepts create conflict in the classroom between students (or teachers) with differing spiritual views? Is this even authentic mātauranga, or is it actually something hatched in the bowels of the Ministry of Education in mid-2021 in the service of some goal other than science education? And, especially, how did all of this get pushed through over negative reviews that the Ministry must have gotten from scientists and science teachers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Also, where is the “e-word”, evolution? &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=avoiding+the+e-word%2C+evolution&amp;amp;oq=avoiding+the+e-word%2C+evolution&quot;&gt;Avoiding the e-word in Biology curricula is often a warning sign in itself.&lt;/a&gt; Perhaps the idea is that it can be replaced with the concept of whakapapa, but everything I’ve heard suggests it is wildly oversimplified and basically wrong to equate evolution/phylogeny with whakapapa. But perhaps the Ministry of Education thinks it can just declare they are the same.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is a rather profound meta-issue that keeps arising in these discussions, namely, “Who has the authority to speak?”  Professor Kilmartin (in a part of the talk I did not quote) argues strongly that everyone should be allowed to participate in the discussion – scientists, mātauranga Māori experts, and the general public whose children will be educated under these curricula in the schools. I agree, but there is another point worth making. When the subject is a public school curriculum, we should keep in mind the &lt;i&gt;purpose&lt;/i&gt; of such curricula: to get everyone on the same page, to supply the basic concepts and definitions and will be taught. If an introductory curriculum requires a complex hermeneutic to correctly interpret it, or if advanced knowledge is required to understand it, then the curriculum is failing at its basic purpose. Being simple and clear, providing a common baseline for everyone, is the &lt;i&gt;whole point&lt;/i&gt; of a curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this post is long enough as it is, so these other questions will have to wait for future posts. I do encourage others concerned about the situation with science standards in New Zealand to get in touch (nickmatzke@gmail.com); the way that problems like this can get solved is by activism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;refs&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NCEA/Ministry of Education (2021). SCIENCE: Chemistry and Biology Level 1 Curriculum. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/chemistry-and-biology?view=learning&quot;&gt;https://ncea.education.govt.nz/science/chemistry-and-biology?view=learning&lt;/a&gt;. Accessed 2022-02-21.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Ross (2021). Does the teaching of indigenous knowledge need to be examined? New Zealand’s embrace of Māori vocabulary goes hand-in-hand with the incorporation of Māori understandings into curricula. But is a debate about the unintended consequences of this move being stifled by fear of speaking out? &lt;i&gt;Times Higher Education&lt;/i&gt;, November 11, 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeshighereducation.com/depth/does-teaching-indigenous-knowledge-need-be-examined&quot;&gt;https://www.timeshighereducation.com/depth/does-teaching-indigenous-knowledge-need-be-examined&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Ross (2021). Auckland plans dialogue on Māori knowledge and science: Vice-chancellor commits to ‘challenging and confronting debate’ on hot-button issue.   &lt;i&gt;Times Higher Education&lt;/i&gt;, December 15, 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeshighereducation.com/news/auckland-plans-dialogue-maori-knowledge-and-science&quot;&gt;https://www.timeshighereducation.com/news/auckland-plans-dialogue-maori-knowledge-and-science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter J. Ramberg (2000) “The Death of Vitalism and The Birth of Organic
Chemistry: Wohler’s Urea Synthesis and the Disciplinary Identity of Organic Chemistry.” &lt;i&gt;Ambix&lt;/i&gt;,
47:3, 170-195, DOI: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1179/amb.2000.47.3.170&quot;&gt;10.1179/amb.2000.47.3.170&lt;/a&gt;
To link to this article: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1179/amb.2000.47.3.170&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1179/amb.2000.47.3.170&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Georgina Tuari Stewart and Angelo Tedoldi (2021). Bringing Māori concepts into school science: NCEA. Access: Contemporary Issues in Education. 41(1), 77-81. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.46786/ac21.1591&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.46786/ac21.1591&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ian Wilkinson (2002). “History of Clinical Chemistry.” &lt;i&gt;The Journal of the International Federation of Clinical Chemistry and Laboratory Medicine&lt;/i&gt; (EJIFCC). 13(4): 114–118. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6208063/&quot;&gt;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6208063/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Note: I am going to be out of town and off the grid on a trek, so I ask other PT moderators to please eliminate spam and trolling in the comments, if any.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Matzke</name></author><summary type="html">Prof. Paul Kilmartin's university webpage. Source: UoA webpage. On Friday, February 18, I attended (on Zoom) a fascinating seminar given by Paul Kilmartin, Professor of Chemistry in the School of Chemical Sciences at the University of Auckland, here in Aotearoa/New Zealand. (I work in the School of Biological Sciences at the same institution.) Prof. Kilmartin specialises in wine chemistry, among other things, and in addition to chemistry, has degrees in theology and philosophy. Kilmartin’s talk was entitled “Chemistry and Mātauranga Māori: A Conversation.” Kilmartin has given me permission to quote this part of his talk, below, which covers science education material of international interest. I will also include the talk summary. Other parts of Kilmartin’s seminar focused on his own background coming to this issue (Scottish and Māori ancestry, member of Ngāi Tahu, deep knowledge of Ngāi Tahu history and land claims), and ideas for Auckland’s chemistry program to explore regarding mātauranga Māori. The Panda’s Thumb blog has an international readership interested in science and science education, and I have been involved with science education controversies for 20 years (and with PT for 18!). But I’m sure the NZ situation is new to many readers. Therefore, I will give some background/introduction to the controversy around the science curriculum, after the quote from Kilmartin’s talk. For more (much more) on current science education controversies in New Zealand, please search Google News, Twitter, blogs etc. on the various terms mentioned. (Please not that all of non-talk material is written by me, and should not necessarily be taken as Kilmartin’s views. And, these are my personal views, not those of current or former employers.) Quotes from: “Chemistry and Mātauranga Māori: A Conversation” Seminar by Professor Paul Kilmartin School of Chemical Sciences, University of Auckland [Comments/clarifications by Matzke are in square brackets like this.] [Seminar given on Zoom by Prof. Paul Kilmartin at 2022-02-18 at 11 am.] [Around 27 minutes in, Kilmartin continues...] The second Ministry of Education text I would like to comment upon concerns proposals for NCEA science. The courses here involve so-called Big Ideas, and the inclusions of concepts drawn from Mātauranga Māori.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Morpho peleides</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/morpho-peleides.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Morpho peleides" /><published>2022-02-14T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-02-14T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/morpho-peleides</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/morpho-peleides.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;Mark Sturtevant&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/Sturtevant.Morpho.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Morpho butterfly&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morpho&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Morpho peleides&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; an old morpho butterfly sits out its final days in a local butterfly house. The iridescent blue color is not due to pigment, but is rather a structural color caused by wave interference of light that is reflected from the scales on the upper wing surface. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by Mark Sturtevant. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Morpho peleides &amp;ndash; an old morpho butterfly sits out its final days in a local butterfly house. The iridescent blue color is not due to pigment, but is rather a structural color caused by wave interference of light that is reflected from the scales on the upper wing surface.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Neo-Confederate Michael Peroutka to run for Maryland Attorney General</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/neo-confederate-peroutka-to-run.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Neo-Confederate Michael Peroutka to run for Maryland Attorney General" /><published>2022-02-03T16:38:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-02-03T16:38:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/neo-confederate-peroutka-to-run</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/02/neo-confederate-peroutka-to-run.html">&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps slightly off-topic, but we have not heard from the neo-Confederate and one-time secessionist &lt;a href=&quot;http://americanloons.blogspot.com/2014/05/1022-michael-peroutka.html&quot;&gt;Michael Peroutka&lt;/a&gt; in a long time, not since he &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2014/05/dinosaur-fossil.html&quot;&gt;donated a dinosaur fossil to the Creation &quot;Museum&quot;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2014/11/michael-peroutk.html&quot;&gt;was elected to the Anne Arundel County Council in Maryland&lt;/a&gt;. According to an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.baltimoresun.com/politics/bs-md-pol-peroutka-ag-20220202-x6lcsbwfynaordddshodb7tlt4-story.html&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; by Pamela Wood in yesterday’s  &lt;i&gt;Baltimore Sun&lt;/i&gt;, he now plans a run for Attorney General of Maryland. As we noted in 2014,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;… Michael Peroutka until recently was also a board member of the League of the South, a white supremacist, neo-Confederate and pro-secessionist organization that has been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.splcenter.org/fighting-hate/extremist-files/group/league-south&quot;&gt;named a hate group&lt;/a&gt; by the Southern Poverty Law Center. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us hope that the citizens of Maryland show more discernment than the citizens of Anne Arundel County.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">This is perhaps slightly off-topic, but we have not heard from the neo-Confederate and one-time secessionist Michael Peroutka in a long time, not since he donated a dinosaur fossil to the Creation &quot;Museum&quot; or was elected to the Anne Arundel County Council in Maryland. According to an article by Pamela Wood in yesterday’s Baltimore Sun, he now plans a run for Attorney General of Maryland. As we noted in 2014, … Michael Peroutka until recently was also a board member of the League of the South, a white supremacist, neo-Confederate and pro-secessionist organization that has been named a hate group by the Southern Poverty Law Center. Let us hope that the citizens of Maryland show more discernment than the citizens of Anne Arundel County.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">21st Century Left-Handed DNA</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/21st-century-left-handed-DNA.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="21st Century Left-Handed DNA" /><published>2022-01-31T13:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2022-01-31T13:00:01-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/21st-century-left-handed-DNA</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/21st-century-left-handed-DNA.html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt; The left-handed DNA helix model that was displayed in the Seattle World's Fair ended up in storage
in a utility tunnel underneath the Pacific Science Center.  (We'll show the image here as soon as we get
permission to show it on this page.)  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/PacSci/photos/pcb.10152437776723855/10152437771508855/&quot;&gt;This link&lt;/a&gt; shows the image on the PSC Facebook page.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On January 11, Matt Young reported that the Institute for Creation Science announced a new logo that depicted left-handed DNA. Although regularly occurring in vivo in the form of Z-DNA left-handed DNA only represent a very tiny proportion of the world’s DNA which consists predominantly of right-handed B-DNA as Watson and Crick described it in their 1954 paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ICR left-handed DNA logo made it on the pages of &lt;a href=&quot;http://users.fred.net/tds/leftdna/&quot;&gt;Tom Schneider’s Left Handed DNA Hall of Fame&lt;/a&gt; immediately and became the sites first entry in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Institute for Creation Research has created a new logo representing their support for left handed DNA research and the ongoing takeover! First reported on 2022 Jan 11, new as of 2022 Jan 112&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases depicting DNA left-handed will be caused by mirroring a correct picture to better suit design purposes or likely more often by copying publicly available pictures. The same may be true for the ICR logo. Still, the incident reminded me of the likely first ever publicly displayed left-handed DNA model that was part of the Science Exhibition at the Seattle World Fair in 1962 which I came across when I studied the history of a right-handed DNA model Max Delbrück purchased for the Institute of Genetics of the University of Cologne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://spl.contentdm.oclc.org/digital/api/singleitem/image/p15015coll3/523/default.jpg&quot;&gt;There were two DNA models on display in the exhibition&lt;/a&gt;, a right-handed ball and stick model and a left-handed abstract model which depicted the four bases of DNA as poker card suits (diamonds, spades, clubs and hearts) adopting a presentation of nucleotides George Gamow used in a 1955 &lt;em&gt;Scientific American&lt;/em&gt; article (1). Both models can be seen in the promotional film &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/iNMpy2dbEgE&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Century 21 Calling&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; starting at 3:33.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Gamow learned about the double helix structure of DNA he suggested a model by which DNA could encode protein sequences. It turned out later that this model was completely wrong (since the intermediate messenger- and transfer-RNA involved in protein synthesis were unknown back then he assumed a direct interaction between DNA and amino acids during the formation of protein chains), but he suggested that a code of triplets of bases of DNA would be sufficient to encode the 20 proteinogenic amino acids. This idea was adopted by Crick who together with Sydney Brenner, Leslie Barnett and R.J. Watts-Tobin proved the three-letter code in 1961. Actually, by the use of T4 one of the phages Delbrück introduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It remains unclear if Delbrück or Gamow, who both studied in Göttingen, Germany, spent some postdoctoral time in Niels Bohr’s lab in Copenhagen, and stayed in contact later in the US, were involved in the planning of the Seattle World Fair Science Exhibition. But Delbrück was corresponding with Hans Neurath who joined the University of Washington School of Medicine
faculty in 1950 to head the new biochemistry department and later would become &lt;a href=&quot;https://magazine.washington.edu/hans-neurath-1909-2002/&quot;&gt;a member of the
national science planning board of the 1962 Seattle World’s Fair&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, its section on molecular biology, a science still in its infancy in 1962, would not have been possible without the scientific work Delbrück had done since the early 1930s. In a 1935 publication also known as the “Green Pamphlet” he, N. Timofeeff-Ressovky and K. G. Zimmer presented evidence that genes are material and not just abstract entities (2). Delbrück envisioned the gene as a collection of atoms that should be accessible for concrete experimental analyses. Since 1938 Delbrück worked in the US where he introduced bacteriophages, viruses that infect bacteria, into the scientific field that would become molecular genetics. Together with Salvador Luria, Delbrück demonstrated that mutations in microorganisms do occur randomly at a certain rate and are not a reaction to selection by a changing environment thereby proving that Darwin’s evolution theory also applies to bacteria (3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 1945 he established a yearly phage course at the Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory that would run until 1970. He also gathered the so-called phage group around him which beside many others consisted of later to become Nobel laureates Salvador Luria, Alfred Hershey, James D. Watson, Frank Stahl, and Renato Dulbecco. Hershey together with Martha Chase showed in 1952 that DNA is the carrier of genetic information. Watson together with Francis Crick unraveled the structure of DNA in 1953. Stahl together with Matthew Meselson later showed that both strands of a given DNA molecule serve as templates for newly synthesized strands thus, resulting in two daughter molecules that consist of one of the strands of the original double helix and a newly formed one (semiconservative mode of replication).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted though, that the Century 21 exhibit didn’t just display DNA as the newest scientific sensation but presented molecular biology in a much broader context that started out from Darwin’s Beagle voyage and presented genetics as the brainchild of evolution theory (4) that via phage genetics represented by a &lt;a href=&quot;https://cdm16118.contentdm.oclc.org/digital/api/singleitem/image/p15015coll3/322/default.jpg&quot;&gt;huge 3D model of the T2 phage&lt;/a&gt;, one of Delbrück’s T phages, led to the elucidation of the double helix structure of DNA as the molecular basis of inheritance. That the final report (5) summarized the exhibition under the title “Evolution and Heredity – From Darwin to DNA” and the visitors path started with the work of Darwin and ended with the DNA models indicates that Evolution Theory and the Modern Synthesis were central to the exhibition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t find contemporary reactions from creationists. However, this may be not surprising because Morris and Whitcomb published The Genesis Flood just the year before and the ICR would only be established a decade later. Thus, creationism in its today’s highly organized form just didn’t exist or any such critique is hidden in archives not accessible today. On the other hand, religion seems to have been a part of the exhibition which offered rooms for prayer and Billy Graham visited the fair. According to James Gilbert who covered the Seattle World’s Fair and especially the astronomy part of the science exhibition in his book “Redeeming Culture: American Religion in an Age of Science” (6) it turned out that “even in an age of science it would be unthinkable to avoid a major gesture towards religion”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was some back and forth regarding the involvement of religion. While there were suggestions for a Shrine for All Faiths, efforts for a Hall of Religions and a World of Religion display even attempts to depict Christianity with all its facets failed and a committee of local protestant churches, the Christian Witness, became the major religious presence with their own building on the fair ground. However, their idea to compete in the marketplace of ideas has not been too successful although reportedly at some point there were more religious than science events. According to Gilbert even Christian Witness admitted they’ve failed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, how effective was the science exhibition? Gilbert argues that it did not effectively teach the lessons it intended. Gilbert concluded:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“1962 no one could reconcile science and religion to the satisfaction of scientists or religious groups, if neither orientation to the world and its problems could prevail in public discussion, if the federal government, scientists, and the business community believed they needed to bring religion inside this grand American commemoration of scientific achievement, the lesson then and now is that science and religion cannot be reconciled nor can either be conquered or contained. The accommodation at Seattle continued the dialectic, extended a running exchange, and signaled the continuing revision of relationships. Extraordinary changes had occurred in American culture since the Scopes trial of 1925 and the foundation of the Conference on Science, Philosophy, and Religion fifteen years later. But nothing had been settled, and that in itself was the only settlement possible.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irrespective of the correctness of the orientation of the displayed DNA models one should be aware that they presented cutting edge science: Watson and Crick would only be awarded the Nobel Prize at the end of the same year, Jacob and Monod’s published their operon theory just the year before, the genetic code was still not fully deciphered, mRNA was more of a concept than an established fact, DNA sequencing was 15 years ahead and things like PCR or Crispr/Cas gene editing were not even imaginable. In addition, it has to be considered that the form and the shape of DNA haven’t been on public display to often before if at all and that the molecule was far from being the icon everybody nowadays recognizes and its name was likely unfamiliar to the majority of the population. Thus, one may conclude that the exhibit’s aim to explain how science works may have been too ambitious and its content may have been too complex for the general public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a European born in the early 60s the US always appeared to be on the cutting edge of science although I must admit that I was more impressed by things like the atomic car and rockets rather than genetics and evolution back then. I guess the same is true for the majority of visitors. On the other hand, the escalation of the conflict and the power creationism would gain was neither foreseeable at the time and it is sad to see how many people in the US still deny evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There actually was a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/PacSci/photos/a.132354883854/10159386557128855/&quot;&gt;third correctly right-handed DNA model&lt;/a&gt; displayed outside of the exhibition hall which today is still in its original place in one of the pools on the fair ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gamow, G. (1955) “Information Transfer in the Living Cell.” &lt;em&gt;Scientific American&lt;/em&gt;. 193,(4), 70–79
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jstor.org/stable/24943758&quot;&gt;http://www.jstor.org/stable/24943758&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Timofeeff-Ressovsky, N.W. and Zimmer, K.G. and Delbrueck, M. (1935) “Über die Natur der Genmutation und der Genstruktur.“ &lt;em&gt;Nachrichten von der Gesellschaft der Wissenschaften zu Göttingen&lt;/em&gt;. 1935, pp. 190-245
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ini.uzh.ch/~tobi/fun/max/timofeeffZimmerDelbruck1935.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.ini.uzh.ch/~tobi/fun/max/timofeeffZimmerDelbruck1935.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Luria SE, Delbrück M. (1943) “Mutations of Bacteria from Virus Sensitivity to Virus Resistance.” &lt;em&gt;Genetics&lt;/em&gt;. 28(6):491-511 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1209226/pdf/491.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1209226/pdf/491.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;US Department of Commerce (1962) &lt;em&gt;United States science exhibit, World’s Fair in Seattle, 1962 Souvenir Guide Book&lt;/em&gt;](
&lt;a href=&quot;https://spl.contentdm.oclc.org/digital/collection/p15015coll3/id/503&quot;&gt;https://spl.contentdm.oclc.org/digital/collection/p15015coll3/id/503&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;US Department of Commerce: &lt;em&gt;United States Scientific Exhibit Seattle World’s Fair Final Report&lt;/em&gt; (1963) Library of Congress Card No. 63-60022
&lt;a href=&quot;https://cdm16118.contentdm.oclc.org/digital/collection/p15015coll3/id/311&quot;&gt;https://cdm16118.contentdm.oclc.org/digital/collection/p15015coll3/id/311&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gilbert, J. (1997) &lt;em&gt;Redeeming culture: American religion in an age of science.&lt;/em&gt; Chicago: Univ. of Chicago Press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Martin Hafner</name></author><summary type="html">The left-handed DNA helix model that was displayed in the Seattle World's Fair ended up in storage in a utility tunnel underneath the Pacific Science Center. (We'll show the image here as soon as we get permission to show it on this page.) This link shows the image on the PSC Facebook page. On January 11, Matt Young reported that the Institute for Creation Science announced a new logo that depicted left-handed DNA. Although regularly occurring in vivo in the form of Z-DNA left-handed DNA only represent a very tiny proportion of the world’s DNA which consists predominantly of right-handed B-DNA as Watson and Crick described it in their 1954 paper. The ICR left-handed DNA logo made it on the pages of Tom Schneider’s Left Handed DNA Hall of Fame immediately and became the sites first entry in 2022. The Institute for Creation Research has created a new logo representing their support for left handed DNA research and the ongoing takeover! First reported on 2022 Jan 11, new as of 2022 Jan 112 In most cases depicting DNA left-handed will be caused by mirroring a correct picture to better suit design purposes or likely more often by copying publicly available pictures. The same may be true for the ICR logo. Still, the incident reminded me of the likely first ever publicly displayed left-handed DNA model that was part of the Science Exhibition at the Seattle World Fair in 1962 which I came across when I studied the history of a right-handed DNA model Max Delbrück purchased for the Institute of Genetics of the University of Cologne.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rock glacier</title><link href="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/rock-glacier.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rock glacier" /><published>2022-01-31T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-01-31T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/rock-glacier</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pandasthumb.org/archives/2022/01/rock-glacier.html">&lt;p&gt;Photograph by &lt;strong&gt;James Kocher&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography contest, &lt;strong&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/2022/JimKocher_SanJuanMountainRockGlacier.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rock glacier&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rock_glacier&quot;&gt;Rock glacier&lt;/a&gt; on unnamed peak (Mountain 12730 on USGS topo maps) in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Juan_Mountains&quot;&gt;San Juan Mountains&lt;/a&gt;. Viewed from Kendall Mountain (13,338&amp;nbsp;ft) south flank, Silverton, San Juan County, Colorado, July, 1997. (Kodachrome 64 and Olympus OM-10 FC with Toshiba 35-105&amp;nbsp;mm, F/2.8 zoom lens.) 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matt Young</name></author><summary type="html">Photograph by James Kocher. Photography contest, Honorable Mention. Rock glacier on unnamed peak (Mountain 12730 on USGS topo maps) in San Juan Mountains. Viewed from Kendall Mountain (13,338&amp;nbsp;ft) south flank, Silverton, San Juan County, Colorado, July, 1997. (Kodachrome 64 and Olympus OM-10 FC with Toshiba 35-105&amp;nbsp;mm, F/2.8 zoom lens.)</summary></entry></feed>